Hello and welcome.
My name is Stephen Greider, and I'm going to be taking over for Colt for part two on this course.
Congratulations on making it this far.
Hopefully you've had fun so far and you're ready to keep learning a lot more about JavaScript.
Now, right away, I want to tell you that part two of this course is going to be a little bit different
than part one.
In part one, you were learning a lot of different individual topics around JavaScript, and you were
really focused on the basic features of the language.
So understanding things like objects, classes, functions and so on.
And you were in general not building a lot of larger apps.
So in part two, we're really going to change the structure of the course significantly and we're going
to have a very different structure.
So in part two, we're going to be covering fewer topics, but every topic that we do cover is going
to be in way greater detail.
So this is where you're going to really get to apply all of your newfound JavaScript skills.
In addition, we're going to have a lot more focus on design patterns and some more advanced concepts
and features of JavaScript.
So this is a lot more about building larger applications and really giving you some experience and confidence
in building your own apps.
The last thing I want to mention is that as we go through this second part of the course for all these
different apps we build, we're going to be doing a lot of refactoring.
The idea here is that I want to show you for every app several different ways to approach any given
problem.
I don't want to show you just one way and say this is it.
This is the only way to build this application.
Instead, I want to give you a toolbox that you can use and a toolbox of different skills to build your
own apps.
Okay.
So now that we have a better idea of what we're going to be doing inside of part two, let's take a
quick pause right here.
We're going to come back the next video and start to discuss the first application that we're going
to be working on.