In this video, we're going to start working on a new little project based entirely inside the browser.
This is going to be a project focusing on just practicing some of our basic JavaScript skills, particularly
classes and functions.
So let's take a look at a mockup and get a better idea of what we're going to be building.
All right.
Here we go.
So we're going to be making a somewhat simple little timer application.
When a user visits our application inside the browser.
We're going to show them a number like 30 right there, a play button and a pause button.
Whenever the user clicks on play.
We're then going to count this timer down.
So in this case, it starts at 30 seconds.
After 1/2, we'll go down to 29, then 28, 27 and so on, until eventually gets all the way down to
zero.
As that timer is counting down, a user can pause it at any time by clicking on the pause button right
there and then resume it by clicking on play again.
Now, I'm sure this seems like a very simple and straightforward application, kind of basic, kind
of boring.
But there are going to be a couple of elements inside of here that kind of make it a little bit more
challenging and a little bit more interesting overall.
So first thing I want you to notice is that there's this circle around the timer itself.
We're going to have a circle kind of like drawn around the timer element.
And as this timer counts down from 32 to 27, 26 and so on, we're going to essentially revolve the
timer.
So you can imagine this as kind of being like a border, and the border is going to kind of fill up
around the outside all the way until it gets to the very top again.
Now, that's kind of a bad description of what's going on, but as soon as we start writing some code,
you'll get a better idea.
The point is that we're going to have an animated little border around the edge of this element.
The other thing we're going to do to make this just a little bit more interesting is we're going to
make sure that a user can click on that number right there.
And whenever they click on it, we're going to turn that thing into a text input.
So a user can change the timer to say, count down from 10 seconds or 5 seconds or whatever else so
it's not fixed at 30 or anything.
A user can change it to any time that they want.
And of course, once it counts down all the way to zero, the user can then click in there, update
the timer to say 60 seconds and start it all over again.
Okay.
So although it's going to be kind of straightforward in nature, there are these couple of extra things.
So we're definitely going to have to figure out and the border part in particular is going to actually
be kind of challenging.
We're going to have to figure out some interesting stuff in the browser to really make that work.
All right.
So now that we've got a better idea of what we're going to be working on, let's take a pause right
here and start to do some projects set up in the next video.