All right.
Now that we know what we are building, let's flip over to our terminal.
We're going to create a new project directory and start doing a little bit of setup.
So I'm going to go over to my terminal.
I'm inside of a workspace directory of sorts inside of here.
I'm going to make a new project folder that I will call simply timer.
I'll then change into that directory and start up my code editor inside there.
Once my editor is open, I'm going to create an indexed HTML file and in indexed JS file as well.
We're going to put together a little bit of boilerplate inside this HTML document, so let's get to
it right away.
At the very top, I'll put in my dock type of HTML.
I'll put in my HTML element.
I'll put in ahead.
A body.
And finally, a script tag with the source of index dogs.
Okay.
Simple enough.
Then inside of indexes, I'll do a quick console log that says Hi there, just so we can make sure that
we correctly hooked up our indexes file to the HTML file.
Once I've got all this stuff put together, I'm going to make sure that I save both files.
I'll then go back over to my terminal and open up that indexed HTML file.
Once it is open I should see a console log inside of my developer console of simply.
Hi there.
So as long as we see that, that means we are good to go.
All right.
Some pretty straightforward set up.
So now we've got this all put together.
Let's continue in the next video and we're going to start to discuss how we're going to approach this
project and generally architect it out.