In the last video, we did a little bit of project setup and now we're ready to start writing some code.
Before we write any code whatsoever, however, I want to really quickly discuss how we're going to
approach and generally architect this program.
So I want to really take a look at this mockup right here and think about some of the different things
that our program is supposed to do.
So in total, remember, we're going to have the timer and that kind of animated border around it.
I would say that our program really does kind of two different things.
First off, one of the core responsibilities of our program is to display that timer.
So like some element on the screen that displays some number of seconds, the play button underneath
it and the pause button, that is all stuff that is 100% related to running a timer.
Now separate to that is the idea that we want to show that animated border around the timer.
Yes, the border is very tightly coupled with a timer, like we want to update that border animation
every time the timer starts to tick down.
But nonetheless, these really are two different parts of our program.
One is the timer, the other is some result from that timer or some effect that the timer has on our
application.
So as we start to think about what our program does, I want you to imagine how we might write out some
code to implement this thing.
I'm going to show you a little bit of pseudocode or kind of like fake code inside of a diagram to help
you understand one possible way that we might implement this timer with the border around it.
Now, the code that I'm about to show you is not code at all.
It is just a series of steps.
It is not the actual implementation we're going to put together.
It is just for demonstration purposes.
Okay.
So here's one possible implementation.
So we might set up an event listener to watch for a click on that start button.
And the start button, of course, is that little play button right there.
So we could set up a click event listener and watch for a click on it.
And then whenever a click occurs, we'll run this series of steps right here.
So maybe right away we can draw a full border around the timer or like clear out the border or do something
with it.
Some like initialization for that border animation.
Then immediately after that we can start counting down on the timer.
So like 1/2 we'll run some block of code to update our timer and maybe the border as well.
So then each time the timer starts to count down, we can take a look at the border and update the animation
to kind of advance it around the outside of the circle.
In addition, every time the timer counts down, we might also update the text as well.
So this number right here would go from, say, 27 to 26, 25 and so on.
Then we'll take a look at the current timer and we'll say that, okay, if we just cut it down and the
timer reaches zero, we probably have to do some kind of like cleanup stuff.
So maybe we need to reset the border in some style and maybe we need to also reset something around
the internal timer to get it ready for another run.
So again, this is just one kind of guess of a possible implementation.
The reason I'm laying this out here is I want to make a really important point.
I want you to take a look at the ordering of lines of code inside this block right here.
And I want you to notice that between the two things that our program does, just about every other
line of code addresses something very different inside of our application.
So in other words, this first line right here is related to the timer itself.
It is watching for someone to click on that start button.
Then inside of our click event handler, the first thing we do is something about the border.
Then the next line of code is something about the timer.
Then it's something about the border.
Then something about the timer.
Timer.
Border timer.
So as we start to think about the real structure of this block of code right here, we are essentially
alternating what every single line of code does inside of this block.
And that would mean that over time, this would be some really challenging code to understand, because
we're going to essentially change context or change what our brain has to be thinking about as we're
reading every line of code in series.
So rather than taking this kind of approach right here where we have to be considering timer, border
time or border and so on, we should instead try to isolate all the different responsibilities of our
application into different and separate blocs.
So how could we do that?
Because at the end of the day, we still have to say draw the border around the timer and do the update
and so on.
Well, one possible way to address this would be to use a kind of evented style approach.
So this is the same series of actions right here are the same kind of layout.
But rather than having right here something that is specifically related to updating the border, maybe
instead of saying, Hey, border, go update yourself, maybe our timer could instead emit some kind
of event or emit some kind of notification to the rest of our application and say, Hey, if anyone
cares at all, the time are just started.
And then some other part of our application can watch for that event to occur.
Whenever that event occurs, we can run some code to draw the border.
We can then start to count down the timer.
And then every single time that we tick down the timer or kind of count it down, we could once again
emit an event that signals that the timer has ticked in some fashion.
So then we can write some code somewhere else inside of our application that watches for that event
to occur.
And when it does, we can update the border and kind of like advance it or advance that animation around
the outside the circle.
And then same thing down here as well.
Rather than running some code that specifically says, okay, let's take a look at the border and reset
it, instead, we might try to write some code that emits an event or something like that to signal
that the timer is all done.
And so somewhere else inside of our application, we could run some code or watch for that event and
whenever it occurs we could reset the border or do whatever else we want.
So again, the idea here is that rather than try to write some code where we are alternating, what
we are doing step by step and every line of code essentially does something totally different and unrelated
to what occurred before it.
We can instead say, okay, let's have one block of code right here that is 100% focused on one aspect
of our application.
And if some other part of our app like, say, the border needs to know about this stuff rather than
directly saying, Hey, border, please go up to yourself, we can instead emit an event or something
like that.
Maybe run a callback function that says, okay, timer started, timer ticked, timer is done.
And so this kind of approach right here would allow us to write some much more clear code.
We would end up with an implementation of our timer that could possibly use be reused between different
projects or for different purposes beyond just updating the border.
In addition, we would also have some implementation for updating the border that wouldn't really care
about whether we are having it work with a timer or some other kind of thing, like, say, the progress
of making a network request or downloading a file or something like that.
All right.
So if this diagram doesn't make that much sense right now, that's totally fine.
We're going to write some code very quickly.
We're going to start to explore this idea and see how we can kind of really isolate the different responsibilities
inside of our program.
So now we've got a better idea of how we're going to kind of approach this.
Let's take a pause right here and start working on an implementation in the next video.