In the last video, we started to discuss some architecture inside of our application, and we eventually
settled on saying that rather than having a block of code that alternates responsibility of just about
every line, we're going to instead try to create one solid block that is 100% concerned around the
timer, and then that block of code will eventually emit some events or call a callback or otherwise
tell the outside world that something important just occurred.
So in this video, we're going to start to focus on how we're going to actually implement this thing.
How are we going to write out some code that actually does what you see right here?
Well, to implement this, we're going to try to use a JavaScript class.
We do not have to use a class to implement something like this.
But I think that we're going to write out the code and you're going to agree with me that using a class
for this timer is a really good use case.
So we're going to get a good idea of how to use a class around DOM elements and how to actually do it
effectively.
Okay.
So I sat down and thought up of a couple of different ways to design this time or class.
I'm going to share with you one way that seems kind of good to me.
So this is the way that we're going to implement our timer.
So we're going to make a class called timer.
And this class is 100% concerned with these elements right here.
The numbers, the play button and the pause button.
Class timer is not going to know anything about that animated order around the timer.
Instead, class timer just knows about those three things right inside of the border.
So on class timer, we're going to have a couple of different methods.
These different methods are going to be invoked automatically whenever a user interacts with the timer
elements.
So like the numbers and the two buttons.
So whenever a user clicks on the play button, we're going to call the start method.
And so, as you guess, calling the START method is going to start up some internal timer or something
like that.
Whenever a user clicks on the pause button, we're going to run the pause method.
Remember that in order to change the timer right here, a user can click on that thing and whenever
they do, it's going to turn into a text input.
And so we're going to say that whenever a user changes that text right there or changes the duration
of the timer, we will call a method called on duration change.
So that's a sign that, hey, the user just changed the duration of the timer.
And then finally, we might also have a method on here called something like tic.
And tic is essentially going to do what we said.
These steps were right here.
So essentially every single second or so or like half a second or something, we're going to need to
run some code to update the state of the timer.
So like change the actual number on there and all that kind of good stuff.
And so that will be done inside of a tick method.
So Tick is going to be called repeatedly over time, as long as the timer is counting down.
So this is the general idea.
We're going to have a class and certain things we click on or interact with are going to invoke different
methods.
Now, of course, at some point in time, we're going to have to make sure that we set up some event
listeners and say, okay, whenever we click on that play button right there, we want to run the start
method.
So to set up these event listeners, we're going to say that our class timer is going to have a constructor
function.
Remember what a constructor function is.
It's a very special function that gets called immediately whenever we create a new instance of a class.
So we're going to say that whenever we create a class timer or an instance of timer, we're going to
pass in a reference to some dumb element that's going to serve as that little text input right there
as the second argument will pass in some.
DOM element that will serve as the start button.
And finally, it will pass in a third argument that's going to represent the pause button as well.
And when I say duration, input, start button and pause button right there.
All I'm saying is we're going to write a query selector.
We're going to find the text input, the two play buttons, and we're going to pass those into the constructor
so that our class essentially has a handle into the DOM.
And whenever it needs to reach into the DOM and do something, it will have these variables close at
hand.
Okay.
Now, once again, I just want to mention that if this stuff seems a little bit confusing right now,
that is totally fine.
This is really your first taste of seeing how to effectively use a class around dumb elements.
So the first time you see this, it always looks a bit crazy, it always looks challenging.
But I guarantee you, as soon as we start to write some code out, you're going to get a really good
idea of what is going on.
So let's take a pause right here.
We're going to come back the next video and start to implement Class Timer.