All right.
Now that we have a better idea of what we're going to do here at this class of timer, let's go back
over to our code editor and start implementing it again.
I want to repeat that if this seems really confusing right now, no problem.
I fully expect that it does.
As we start to write some code, you're going to very quickly get a better idea of what we're trying
to do.
Okay.
So I'm going to go back over to my index JS file inside of here.
We currently have our console log of hi there.
So I'll just delete that and I'll replace it with class timer.
So inside of here, I'm going to first define our constructor method.
Remember, the constructor is a very special function.
It's going to be called automatically whenever we create a new instance of timer.
So in other words, if I say down here, new timer and pass in an argument of like, hi there.
What actually gets called behind the scenes is the constructor function.
And the first argument to the constructor function will be that message of Hi there.
So if we receive that variable of message and like did a console log of it.
I would expect to see a console log of the string.
Hi there.
Appear inside of our console.
So for us.
We're going to eventually try to pass in references to DOM elements that our timer class are going to
listen into.
So our timer class is going to listen for, say, a click on the start button or click on the pause
button or someone to change the duration input right there as well.
Whenever those events occur, our timer class is going to run some method to find inside of it.
So inside of here, I'm going to look at the constructor and I'm going to receive an argument of duration
input.
So again, this is going to be a reference to a DOM element that is a text input.
So whenever we create a timer, we are going to have to make sure that we pass it as the first argument,
a reference to a text input.
Then our second will be the start button.
And then finally the third is the pause button.
Then inside of here, we're going to immediately take these three different arguments and assign them
to instance variables so we can refer back to these DOM elements from other methods inside of our class
if we so choose.
So I'll say this dot duration input.
Is duration input.
This dot start button is start button.
And this dot pause button.
Is Pause button.
Next thing we're going to do is set up some event handlers on these different elements.
So as I've said many times now, whenever users say clicks on the play button, we're going to want
to call a start method that is defined inside of our class.
So let's just start to worry about that pause or that play button for right now, we will worry about
pause or the text input.
Let's just try to make sure that whenever a user clicks on that play button, we end up calling some
method inside of our class called Start.
So back over here.
I'm going to first define a method called Start.
And inside there I'll do a console log of time to start the timer.
Then to make sure that we call this method.
Any time a user clicks on the start button, we could set up an event listener from directly inside
of our constructor.
So we'll say this start button add event listener.
We're going to watch for a click event.
And any time that occurs, we will call this dot start.
And that's pretty much it.
So that's how we're going to receive some arguments inside of our constructor.
We're going to store a reference to each of them in case we need to work with them at some point in
the future inside of all of our different methods.
And then right away we will bind some event listeners to those elements as well.
And that's how we're going to eventually call some method that is defined inside of our class.
Okay.
So now we've put this together.
Let's try to create a duration input inside of our HTML document.
We're going to create a start button and a pause button.
We will then create an instance of our timer class and pass in references to those three elements.
So I'm going to first go back to my index HTML file.
Over here, I'm going to create an input element.
And I'm going to give it an ID.
Of duration just to make it really easy to select.
I'll also make a button with an ID of start once again just to make it easy to select.
And I'll give that button some text like Start.
And then finally.
Another button with an idea of pause.
I'll give it some text, a pause and close off that tag as well.
So now we can attempt to select each of these three different elements and then create an instance out
of our timer using them.
So back inside of index dogs at the bottom of the file.
I'm going to select those three different elements using some query selectors.
We can either use a query selector or a JIT element by ID.
In this case, I'm just going to use the query selector method because honestly I just personally prefer
to use it.
You could definitely use a JIT element by ID if you so chose.
So I'll say duration input.
Will be document query selector lb duration.
So remember that is how we select an element by ID when we're using query selector.
Ben start button.
The document query selector.
LB start.
And finally pause button.
We document queries.
Cell lector.
Count pause.
And then finally we can create our instance of the timer and pass in those three elements that we just
selected.
So let's say a timer is a new timer and we will pass in duration, input, start button and pause button.
All right.
So now the instant that we create a new instance of the timer and pass in those three elements, our
timer class is going to automatically set up that event listener for us.
And whenever a user clicks on the start button, we're going to run that console log.
So right now this is some very basic interaction, but I'm sure you can start to imagine how over time
we might start to implement different parts of the timer by wiring up events that are occurring to those
different elements to different methods inside of our class.
All right, so let's go back over to our index.html file.
I'm going to refresh the page and I'll see those three elements appear.
I'm going to zoom in my screen.
Just you can see these different elements very easily.
Just remember that as you start to look at my screen, you're going to see these elements very large.
And they're only large on my screen because I'm very far zoomed in.
So now to test this, we'll click on the start button and as soon as we do so, we should see time to
start the timer.
So that's going to be our signal to start to run some code inside of our class.
That's going to start up the timer and start ticking down seconds.
And every time we tick over a second, we're going to update some text representation of the timer at
the same time.
Okay.
So we made some pretty good progress here.
Let's take a pause.
We're going to come back the next video and continue working on our timer class.