We've now got a starting implementation for class timer put together.
Now, unfortunately, in this video and the next one, we're going to have to go into a very quick side
topic.
This side topic is something that's a little bit painful in JavaScript, but that's why we're going
to go over it right now before we get too deep into this application.
So the little issue that we're going to discuss is around the value of this inside of a class.
This is something that was covered earlier on inside this course.
But I'm just going to give you a very quick reminder right here, because it's going to be very relevant
for us as we develop our timer class.
So I want to first begin with a quick demonstration.
I'm going to find my start method.
I'm going to remove the console log inside there and I'm going to replace it with console.log.
This like so.
Now remember, our start method is going to be invoked right now whenever we click on the start button
because we wired it up with an event listener.
So that is one way in which we can invoke the START method.
I'm then going to go down to the bottom of the file right after we create our timer class and I'm going
to call timer start directly as well.
So there are now two ways in which the start method is going to be invoked.
It's going to be called one time automatically when our application first loads up inside the browser,
it's going to be called a second time whenever we click on the start button directly.
Now I want you to recall that in general, we want the value of this inside of a class to be equal to
the instance of the class that we create, because this is how we refer to different instance variables
and methods that are defined inside the class.
So let's save this really quickly.
We're going to go back over to our browser.
I'm going to refresh the page and right away I'll see the first console log.
So that is from the method called.
We added down right here.
So when we call timer start the console log of this that we see is the instance of the timer class we
created.
This is the result that we want in general.
We always want a console log of this to result in the instance of the class because this means that
we can access the different instance variables.
So we defined on the class and the different methods as well.
So this right here is a very good result and that is what we always want to see.
However, if we try to invoke starts using this other way of invoking it by clicking on the button,
we're going to see a very different result.
So I'm going to find the start button and click on it.
And when I do so, I'll see a console log of the button we just clicked on instead.
So that means that the value of this inside of the start function whenever we click on the button is
very different than if we just call start directly through the instance of the class that we created.
This is a very bad thing.
Seeing this console log right here, that is not good at all because it means that whenever a user clicks
on that start button, we will not have access to any of the instance variables inside of our class
or any of the methods as well.
Let me show you a quick demonstration of why this is so important right after the START method.
I'm going to define a new method.
I'm going to delete this very quickly.
This is just a quick demonstration.
I'm going to define a new method called important method to call.
So we're going to imagine that this is a really important method that we have to call whenever start
gets invoked.
So then instead of start, I'm going to try to call that method.
So I'll do important method to call like so.
And then maybe just to make sure that we do successfully call it I'll add in a console log of like important
thing was done.
Okay.
So let's now try to save this.
We're going to go back over and refresh the page once again.
And I made a typo.
There we go.
Important method to call.
My mistake.
I'm going to say that again.
Refresh.
That's better.
So now whenever we call the start method directly through the code that we have right here, we have
access to all the other methods we defined inside of our class.
Once again, this is good.
This is what we want.
However, if we try to click on the start button, we will see an error.
And that is because when we click on the start button, the value of this inside of START is going to
be different than if we just called Start directly.
So again, this comes back to the idea of the value of this inside of a class.
So in order to fix this up and in order to make sure that we can actually use a button like this right
here with an event listener to invoke the different methods inside of our class, we need to make sure
that the value of this inside the start method is what we expect it to be.
And for it to be what we expect it to be, we need to get a better understanding of the value of this
inside of a class.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video.
We're going to get a quick review on how we can determine the value of this inside of a class and how
we can change the value of this if required, because in this case, it definitely is required.
So quick pause right here and we'll continue in just a moment.