In the last video we recapped on why the value of this inside of a method inside of a class is so important.
If we ever want to call some other method inside of a class or reference some instance variable or whatever
else, the value of this must be set equal to the instance of the class.
Right now, when we call this start from our button event listener, the value of this is not what we
expect it to be.
It has been overridden and the value of this inside that method is instead equal to our button that
we are clicking on, which definitely doesn't have a method called important method to call.
So we need to essentially make that error message right there go away.
So to make that go away, we're going to review the three different ways that we can determine the value
of this inside of a method.
So let's get to it.
Let's review those three different ways.
Okay.
So the way that we're going to interpret this diagram right here, whenever we want to determine what
the value of this is going to be inside of a function, we're going to ask ourselves this question first.
We're going to ask ourselves, did we define the function with an arrow function?
If so, that is the answer to what the value of this is.
If this is not true, we're going to move on to question two.
If that is not true, we're going to fall down to the kind of all other cases category here.
So essentially we go down the list and we stop at the first place that we can answer yes to.
So let's first review what it means to use an arrow function and what the value of this inside there
will be if we do use an arrow function.
So if we define a function with an arrow function and then we access this inside that arrow function,
here's what we can determine what the value of this will be.
We can use a little trick.
So right above our arrow function, we're going to find the first valid line and write console.log this
on that first valid line.
Then the value of this inside the arrow function will be equal to whatever was console logged from that
console log that we added in.
Let me give you a very quick demonstration of this, because this rule will actually make a lot of sense
once you see a practical demonstration of it.
Okay.
So back over here.
I'm going to go down to the bottom of the file and we're going to write out a couple of examples really
quickly.
First, I'm going to comment out timer start.
So we don't get any kind of erroneous console.log messages that will kind of throw off this demonstration
we're going to do.
So then down here, I'm going to write out an arrow function called print this.
And inside of here, I bet, as you would guess, we'll do a console.log of this.
So here's the question what is the value of this going to be equal to inside of here whenever we call
it, print this?
Well, if we want to determine what this console log will result in or what the value of this is, we
can take a look at the arrow function.
We're going to find the first valid line of code above the arrow function.
So that would be like this right here.
That's the first valid line.
And right there, we will add in a console log of this.
So now the value of this inside the function is going to be equal to the value of this.
Outside the function, these two console logs will be absolutely identical.
And so we could check that by calling print this.
I'm going to save this file, flip back over, refresh, and we'll see that in both cases we get window,
which is essentially the global context inside of JavaScript when we're executing code inside the browser.
So this definitely means that this first rule worked out correctly.
Let's take a look at a little bit more complex example of how to use this little trick around arrow
functions.
So I'm going to define a new object that I'll call.
How about colors?
Inside of here, I'm going to define a method called print color.
And then we're going to eventually inside of here define a function called this once again.
And inside there I'll do a console.log of this.
And then immediately after it I will run, print this.
So now, once again, in order to determine what the value of this is going to be inside there, we
could add a console.log on the line right above.
So right above the arrow function, I'm going to add in console.log this.
And once again, the value of this is going to be identical between those two console.log statements.
Let's first comment out that little block right there and just run print color by itself and see what
the console.log normally would be.
So down here I'll do colors, print color.
I'm going to save this.
Look back over refresh.
And so normally the value of this inside of that method would be the object itself, like the entire
object that we just created this colors object.
So that means that inside of that arrow function, the value of this.
Is going to be equal to the colors object as well.
So I'll save this now with all that stuff on commented refresh, run it again and we'll see the identical
console.log in both cases.
Okay.
So again, that is the rule for determining the value of this inside of an arrow function.
So let's now take a look at the second way or kind of if we don't define a function with an arrow function,
how then do we decide what the value of this is going to be inside there?
So the second check we're going to do, we're going to see, did we call the function with bind, call
or apply when we invoked it as a quick reminder, bind, call and apply our built in functions that
belong to all functions inside a JavaScript that we create, we can use, bind, call, and apply to
call a function in a very special way.
The first argument to all three of bind, call and apply is going to be the value of this that we want
to execute the function with.
Now, this note right here is really confusing, so let's just write a real quick code example right
away.
I'm going to delete the colors example and I will replace it with a new function that I will call print
this and this time I'm going to define it with a function keyword because if I defined it with an arrow
function, then we would use that rule and set a second one.
So then inside of here, I'll do a console.log of this, as usual.
And now I'm going to invoke this function right here by using call.
So I'm going to call print this.
I'm going to invoke it using call instead of calling it directly.
And now the first argument to call right here is going to be the value of this inside of the function.
So I'm going to put in here.
How about a object with a color of red?
So now in print this gets executed.
The value of this inside of it is going to be equal to that object right there.
So I'll save this.
I'm going to go back over, refresh and sure enough, there we go.
So, again, if we make use of call.
First argument is going to override the value of this inside there.
We can do the same thing with apply as well.
So I'll save this as well.
Refresh.
We get the same exact result.
If we don't call the function with apply.
So if we just call the function directly, the value of this is going to be a little bit more unpredictable.
So let's refresh and we see that in this case it is equal to the window.
So again, it is very clear that if we call the function with bind, call or apply, that is going to
override the value of this inside the function.
So that is the second check that we always do.
So now we fall on to the last case here.
If we don't define the function with an arrow function and if we don't use blind color apply, we fall
into all other cases.
And in order to determine what the value of this is going to be inside the function, we take a look
at where we invoke the function.
We take a look at whatever is to the left of the dot inside of the function call, and that is what
the value of this is going to be equal to.
Now, this is another scenario where the note I have right here is a little confusing.
So let's do a quick example again.
So I'm going to delete this example.
I'm going to create a new object again called Colors.
Inside of here, I'll make a method called print color.
And inside there, I'll do a council log of this.
Now.
How would we run the method print color?
To run that method, we would call colors print color.
So now here's the trick.
We're going to take a look at these rules right here to determine what the value of this is going to
be inside of this function.
When we call it so, we first say, do we have an arrow function?
Nope, definitely don't.
Are we calling the function with bind color apply?
Nope.
Definitely not.
So we fall into this other case right here.
So in order to determine what the value of this is going to be inside of this function, when we call
it, we take a look at the period to the left of the function name, that period right there.
And we look at whatever variable is to the left of it.
In this case, the colors object.
Because the colors object is to the left of that period.
The value of this inside of print color is going to be equal to colors.
So this right here is what this is going to be.
So let's save this and we can verify that really easily.
So I'll refresh again.
And sure enough, I see print color.
We can really abuse this rule right here to really demonstrate how it works very easily.
So let me give you a quick example.
I'm going to create another object right underneath colors, and I'll call this one like random object.
And I'll give it a property of like a is one like so.
I'm then going to assign random object, a new property called print color.
And I'm going to assign to that property right there the print color function from the colors object.
So I'll say colors print.
Color.
Now notice here I am not calling print color, it's not being invoked.
I'm just taking the function and assigning it to the random object on a property called print color.
So this line of code right here is equivalent to if I just copy pasted that function down like so totally
equivalent.
So let's now try to call random object print color.
So random object dot print color.
So now we're going to define a method that is defined inside of the colors object.
But what this method is defined inside of doesn't govern the value of this inside the function.
Instead, the rule that we fall into is this one right here.
And two, to determine the value of this inside the method call.
We take a look at whatever is to the left of the dot when we invoke the method.
So here's we invoke the method.
We're going to take a look at the dot and what is to the left.
It is random object.
So now when we call a print color right here, we're not going to see a value of this being console.log.
That is the color's object.
Instead, we're going to see the random object.
So I'll save this.
Go back over, refresh.
And there we go.
We see a console log of the random object, not the colors one.
Okay.
So that is it.
That is our three big rules right here.
This is how we determine the value of this.
So now the inevitable question is, how does this solve our problem?
Right?
How are we going to fix the issue we have where we need to call starts and have it always give us the
same value of this?
Well, in order to make sure that we can enforce the value of this inside the start function, we're
going to just simply make sure that we fall into case one or two.
So in other words, in order to make sure that the value of this inside of start is always the instance
of timer that we want it to be, we're going to define that function using an arrow function or we're
going to call it using bind, call or apply.
So that's how we're going to fix this problem.
Let's take a quick pause right here, because this is a very long video.
We're going to come back the next section or next video and wrap all this this stuff up rather quickly.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.