Now that we've taken a look at the three different ways to determine the value of this, we're going
to use this knowledge to fix up our scenario.
So we're going to make sure that the value of this inside the start function is always what we expect
it to be.
So the first way that we can solve this is by making sure that we define the start method with an arrow
function.
Right now, the syntax you see right here behind the scenes, this actually gets translated into a normal
keyword function that looks like that right there.
So this is what happens behind the scenes.
So right now we are not making use of an arrow function to define start.
If we wanted to use an arrow function right here, we would put right after starts equals.
And then between the parentheses and the curly brace, we would put in our arrow like so.
So this is going to define an arrow function and assign it to start.
So now we can use our rule back over here to determine what the value of this is going to be inside
this function.
But there's a little caveat this rule does hold.
But if we follow it to a T, the first valid line above our arrow function, this is not a valid line
to put right here.
We can't do a console log of this right here.
That's why I said valid inside this diagram.
So we cannot put a console log right here.
Instead, the first valid line above this arrow function would be outside of the class.
Like up here.
Now normally if we do a council log out here, we're going to get a console log of window because we're
essentially inside the global scope.
So in this case, it would seem like this rule falls apart.
You would think that this rule does not actually hold, but it does because there is a little trick.
When we write out code like this, right here we are using an advanced feature of JavaScript called
Class Properties.
Behind the scenes, JavaScript is going to take this function declaration right here and it's going
to move it out of the class.
We can actually see this in action.
If we take our class definition and run it through a tool, you can find a line called Babel.
Babel takes very modern JavaScript syntax and converts it down to much more basic or simplistic JavaScript
that can be ran or executed inside of older browsers.
It turns out that a lot of the syntax we're using right now relies upon newer features of JavaScript
that are not supported in older browsers.
And so tools like BABBEL just make sure that these very modern features that we're using can still be
executed safely inside of an older browser.
So I'm going to take the code that we just wrote.
I'm going to take this class right here.
I'm going to copy it, and I'm going to throw it into this BABBEL tool.
So I'm going to put my code on the left hand side and I'll see some output come on the right hand side.
So this is what would actually be executed inside of an older browser.
Or put another way, this is how JavaScript kind of interprets our code, adding a more basic or simplistic
level.
So take a look at this.
When we define this start method using this class property syntax, because that's what we're using
right here, it turns out that we're not actually defining an arrow function inside of the class body.
Instead, the browser and this BABBEL tool is going to massage the code that you wrote.
It's going to take that function declaration and move it into the constructor.
So this right here is the code that actually will be executed inside of a browser.
So this is what is really, truly going on behind the scenes.
And once we see this, you'll notice that our rule back over here still holds 100%.
Take a look at the constructor.
Inside the constructor, we define an arrow function.
So now we can take this code right here and apply the original rule to it.
I'm just going to do a quick copy paste back over here just so I can edit it very easily.
So this is what actually executes inside the browser.
And so if you want to figure out what the value of this is going to be inside the arrow function, we're
going to go to the first valid line of code above the function declaration.
So that would be right here.
And we would then do a console log of this.
And whatever comes out of this console log is what the value of this is going to be inside the arrow
function.
And so because we are in the constructor, we are always guaranteed that the value of this is going
to be equal to the instance of the class.
And so the value of this inside the arrow function is going to be equal to the instance of the class.
So that's the secret behind solution number one that we have right here.
If we use an arrow function, this rule back over here still applies.
And that's how we can fix the value of this inside the start function.
Now, just to prove that, I'm going to go back down to the bottom of the file.
I'm going to delete all this extra test code that we put together down here.
And I'm going to delete the timer start line as well.
That was just a quick demonstration.
I'm then going to save this.
I'm going to go back over to my browser.
I'm going to refresh the page, and now I'm going to click on the start button again.
And now we can see that the start button works.
As expected, we were able to call a method defined on the class.
We could also, if we wanted to reference instance variables as well.
So again, this is solution number one right here.
So in order to get the value of this inside the start method to what we want it to be, we just use
the first rule right here.
So now let's take a look at how we would use method number two.
So if you want to do method number two, we could call a bind on our function, which will override
the value of this inside of it when it actually gets called.
This method is a little bit more advanced.
We are not going to use this method just about anywhere inside this course.
I'm only mentioning this way of fixing the value of this because you will see older projects, older
code that uses this style.
So with this approach, we could refactor our start method back to how it was before.
Like so.
And then we will find where we pass our this dot start function off to the event listener.
And then on start, I'm going to call behind this like so.
So when we call dot behind this unlike call and apply which invoke the function right away, bind instead
returns us a new function that we can call at some point in the future.
So calling bind it doesn't run start right away.
We're still passing a function off to the event listener that's going to be executed at some point in
the future when a user actually clicks on the button.
Both bind very similar to call and apply.
We pass in the first argument to bind and that is going to be what the value of this is forced to be
inside of the start function.
So now the value of this inside the start function is going to be forced to the value of this out here
inside the constructor, which is always once again going to be equal to the instance of the class,
which is what we want it to be.
So let's save this.
I'll do a quick test again.
I'll refresh.
Hit start.
And once again, I see.
Important thing was done.
Okay.
So that's it.
Those are the two very easy and most common ways that you're going to see to fix the value of this inside
of a class.
So again, we're going to rely on the first solution right here because it is definitely the more modern
way and it's what you're going to see more frequently moving forward.
So I'll define the start function using the class property syntax like so.
I'm also going to remove the dot bind over here and restore it to just that.
Finally, I'm going to clean up the important method to call.
That was just a very quick demonstration.
Okay.
So again, I apologize for these three videos of going over a topic that was covered earlier.
Maybe this stuff was really challenging, confusing, all that kind of stuff.
The reason I went over it was just to show you a more practical example than what you might have seen
earlier inside the course.
And of course, I'm showing you, because this is going to be very critical to how we put together our
timer class as well.
So now that we've got this this stuff all under wraps, a quick pause right here.
We'll continue working on our timer class in just a moment.