All right.
So now that we've got all this this stuff out of the way, let's get back on track.
We're going to focus on our start method right here.
So the goal of our start method is to start up a timer.
We want to make sure that we run some amount of code every some amount of time that's going to be responsible
for updating the text inside of our timer.
So like count the 19 down to an 18, 17, 16 and so on.
So the code that is going to actually update the timer itself and like count that thing down is going
to be placed inside of this tick method.
The goal, the tick method right here is to update the text inside there and eventually emit a signal
to the rest of our application to say, hey, some amount of time just passed.
So the goal of START is really just to start up the tick method and call it every so many number of
seconds.
So let's take a look at what the implementation will look like.
Right underneath start.
I'm going to also define.
Tick and I'm going to use that same kind of arrow syntax like so.
Inside of Tick.
I'll put a quick console log of tik so we can make sure that we're calling it appropriately.
And then instead of start in order to make sure that we call Tik every so many seconds, like every
second or so, we can use the set interval function that is built into the JavaScript language.
So inside of start we will invoke set interval.
We're going to pass in a reference to a function to invoke which will be this tick.
And then as the second argument, we'll put in how often we want to run this function.
So in this case, I want to run tick every 1/2.
The second argument is expressed in milliseconds.
There are 1000 milliseconds inside of a second.
So this code right here is going to make sure that we run this tick once every second.
So the net result should be seeing a console log every second inside of our console.
All right, so let's save this.
Flip back over and see how we do.
So I'm going to refresh, I'll click on start and then I see tick, tick, tick, tick and so on.
Okay, well, that definitely looks good, but there is a very subtle little issue here.
If we refresh again, I want you to notice that when we click on Start, we have to wait a full second
before we see the first tick.
So it turns out that when you call set interval, it's going to wait 1/2 or whatever that delay is before
calling that function for the first time in our application.
This would be kind of bad because whenever a user clicks on that start button, they really expect to
see the timer start working right away.
We don't want them to be waiting around for a second and then see some kind of update.
Instead, we want that update to occur instantly.
So in order to make sure that occurs, we're going to simply call this dot tick manually right before.
So now this is saying whenever we call start, we're going to immediately run one tick.
Then we're going to set up an interval that's going to be executed 1/2 in the future and then 1/2 after
that, after that, after that, and so on.
So if we save this again, go back over, refresh and click start.
We now instantly see tick and then tick, tick, tick and so on.
Okay.
So it looks pretty good.
Now this is pretty easy, so let's just keep going right now.
The next method that we need to put together is the pause method.
So we need to make sure that when we click on that pause button, we stop the ticking altogether in
order to stop our interval, essentially stop this function from being called.
Whenever we call set interval, we get back something called a timer.
So I'm going to assign it to a variable that I'll call timer.
Like so.
And for right now, let's just do a console.log of that timer and see what exactly it is.
I'll go back over, refresh, click, start again and there's the console log of the timer.
So in this case, it is a simple number of one.
Let me tell you what's going on behind the scenes.
Whenever we call set interval, we get back an integer.
The integer is an ID and it's essentially representing the running timer or the running interval that
is going to continue executing this function again and again.
If we ever need to stop that timer or stop this interval from running, we can call another function
that is built into the browser or into JavaScript called Clear Interval.
When we call clear interval interval, we're going to pass in the ID of the interval that we want to
stop.
And so in this case, it would be the timer variable right there.
So in this scenario right here, we are essentially setting up an interval and then immediately canceling
it.
So I would expect to never see the tick function run except for the first time we call it manually right
there.
So let's save this again.
I'm going to flip back over.
Refresh.
I'll hit start.
And so now I see one tick behind the scenes.
We set up our interval and then on the next line of code we immediately cancelled it.
So I don't see any more ticks up here.
So of course, rather than cancelling the timer right away, well, we probably want to cancel it at
some point in time in the future, specifically in our case, whenever the user clicks on the pause
button, which should run the pause method inside of our class.
Let's define a pause method.
We're going to make sure that the pause method is going to call a clear interval and pass in the relevant
ID.
So underneath starts I'm going to define my pause method like so.
Inside of here, we will call a clear interval.
And now there's just a little issue.
We need to somehow get the timer variable that was created over here into this other method.
In order to share information between different methods, we assign that information to an instance
variable.
So instead of a sunny it directly to a variable right here called timer, we're going to say this timer.
So by assigning the value to this, that's going to make sure that we can refer to this timer over inside
this method and we'll get access to the same information that we just assigned right there.
So in other words, we're going to say clear interval with this timer.
We can also clean up the clear interval that we left inside of Start because we don't need it inside
there anymore.
Now, one other quick thing I want to mention.
We are currently working on a class called Timer referring to a variable inside of here of like this
timer is just a little bit unclear because we now have two words inside of a class that are really,
really similar.
So in order to avoid any confusion whatsoever, I'm just going to change the name of the variable that
we are assigning the ID to to how about interval?
Because that's kind of what it represents.
You could also do something like interval ID that would also be appropriate as well.
But I'm just going to go with interval.
That is what I use personally on projects that I work on.
I'm going to make sure that I update this timer inside of pause as well.
Like so.
So now to test this out, last thing we have to do very quickly.
We need to make sure that back up inside the constructor, we watch for a click event on the pause button
element.
Whenever a click event occurs, we need to run that pause method.
So right after where we set up our click event handler right there, I'm going to do a this dot pause
button add event listener.
I'm going to watch for the click event whenever that occurs.
I want to run the this pause method like so.
Okay.
So it looks pretty good.
So I'm going to save this and we'll do a quick test.
So I'll flip back over refresh I'll hit starts now.
We're going to see a tick once every second and then as soon as we hit the pause button, it stops.
And so I don't see any more ticks occur.
All right.
Well, let's say that this is working out pretty darn well so far.
So let's take a quick pause right here and continue in just a moment.