Okay.
Our class timers looking pretty good.
Believe it or not, our start and pause methods are just about complete.
We're not going to really add any additional code to them, so we're not going to start to focus our
attention on the tick method right here.
Remember, the tick method is going to run once every second because we set up the interval to call
it once every 1000 milliseconds.
So inside of the tick method, we're going to start to want to figure out what we want to do every second.
Well, I think that every second there's probably going be a pretty obvious thing we want to do.
We probably are going to want to reach into the DOM, find whatever the current time is right there
and subtract one from it.
So if we start off with 18 seconds and then the tick method runs, we'll probably want to decrease it
down to 17, then 16, 15, 14, 13 and so on.
I want to remind you really quickly that this input or see this element right here that's going to display
the current time is actually going to be a kind of invisible text input.
The reason we're making it a text input is that a user can very easily reach inside there and change
the current time or the duration of the timer so they could enter in 300 and then hit play and that
would count down our timer from 300 seconds.
So now in this video, I want to focus on a really interesting question.
Well, at least it's interesting to me.
I suppose the question I want to focus on is inside the tick method.
We clearly at some point in time are going to have to write some code that looks like this.
This is going to be pseudocode.
Don't write this.
Just a quick example.
So we're definitely going to have to write out something like time remaining is time remaining minus
one, something like this to count down our timer from whatever the current time is.
Subtract 1/2 and then update the variable or the value of time remaining.
So we're going to write out a line of code that looks like that.
But here's the interesting question, and this is what I want to explore in this video.
Where does the variable time remaining live?
In other words, where is this data actually being stored?
There's two kind of obvious or different ways we can solve that.
Let's take a look at a diagram and understand the two different places that we can store the information
about how much time is remaining on our timer.
So the first way is kind of a slightly more obvious one, I think.
And this is where if I like really grilled you and asked you to figure this out, this is probably what
you might come up with.
So an option number one, in deciding where to store the time left on our timer, we might decide to
create an instance variable on our timer instance called something like time left.
Then every single time the tick method ran, we could subtract one from that value and then take that
value and update our text or our input element with it.
So in other words, when we run, tick will count down 29 to 28, then take the value of 28 and throw
it into the input element.
So some code that looks like that might look like this.
I'm going to very quickly write it.
I'm going to delete this code very quickly so you don't have to write this as well.
So we might write out inside the constructor something like this time left equals 30.
So whenever we create a class or an instance of timer, our default value for time left will be 30,
representing 30 seconds.
That inside of Tik, we could do something like this.
Time left is this.
Time left minus one.
And then we could do something like take our input element.
Remember, we've got a reference to it right there, duration input.
So we could say this duration input.
What value is this time left?
So again, take the current time.
Subtract one from it.
Then take that value and throw it into the duration.
Input.
And that would update the text on the screen.
So this is a definitely way that works.
Without a doubt.
This is a method that works.
I'm going to delete this code really quickly and we're going to take a look at option number two for
where we store this data.
So in option number two, we're going to kind of invert this control flow rather than having our timer
instance have some definition of what the time left is and store it inside the input element or update
the input element.
We're going to instead have the current time live inside of the input element.
So whatever the input elements value is, that is the time remaining.
And then at any time that our timer instance needs to know how much time is remaining, it will reach
into the input element, figure out what the current value is.
So we're going to essentially take the value out of that input element and bring it back over to our
timer instance.
So why would we ever go with this approach right here?
Approach number one seemed like it was kind of obvious.
Of course, we've got a timer instance.
It's got some time left.
It's an instance variable.
Really easy to get at that value right away.
So why would we ever use this approach right here?
Well, the reason that we might use this approach is that it makes some UCS or some actual interactions
with the user a little bit easier to handle.
Remember, at some point in time, we want the user to be able to type in a new text value inside this
input right here.
So we want them to be able to click in there and type in like give me a timer.
That countdown counts down from ten.
If we were storing all of our data inside of our class, we would want to set up an event handler and
watch for any time.
A user changes that value.
So if a user changes that from 300 down to ten, we would have to have an event listener that watches
for a change event on that input.
When that occurs, we would have to take that change value and go and update our time left.
But with this approach, we don't have to worry about any event handlers at all on that input element
because any time you want to figure out what the current time remaining is, we can just reach directly
in, get that value, pull it back out and make use of it inside of our timer instance.
Now that's sounds like a very small and simple thing, but I just want to suggest that's maybe one reason
that we would want to just have our timer instance stored the value or the time remaining inside of
that input element.
There are going to be some other interactions that get a little bit easier as well when we start to
take this approach in this approach.
But they're not going to be quite as obvious until we get a little bit further along with this application.
Now just at a higher level.
I want to mention that option number two, we refer to this as storing our data inside of our DOM.
So our application has some critical data that is required to make it work correctly.
And we are storing that data inside of different DOM elements with option number one.
We're storing all of our data inside of our JavaScript code.
So we've got a JavaScript class right here.
That class or that instance of the class has the data that is critical to making our application work.
Now option number one is a little bit more popular these days, right, to be totally honest with you.
Option number one is definitely more popular these days.
Option number two used to be really popular.
So like years ago, this used to be the way that we wrote JavaScript applications, but it's definitely
pivoted towards option number one more recently.
Having said that, we're going to use option number two inside this application.
And the reason for that is I want you to see what this approach looks like.
I want you to see some of the downsides.
I want you to understand why we used to write code like this as JavaScript engineers years ago and why
we now instead use option number one and store data inside of our JavaScript code instead.
So I'm sorry to kind of show you not the most modern or like technically correct way to do this stuff
or what's really popular right now.
But again, it is important for you to understand why we take one approach over the other.
And the easiest way to do that is to write out the code in that older approach so you can see some of
the problems that start to arise.
Okay.
So with all this in mind, let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to start to update our class and make sure that it
can very easily read some data out of that input element to figure out how many seconds are left on
our timer and then make sure that whenever our tick method gets called, we're going to update the value
of that input element and subtract one from it.
So quick pause right here, and I'll see you in just a minute.