Okay.
So in the last video, we had a long discussion about where we're going to store data inside of our
application.
So again, we're going to store the current time inside of that input element.
That is going to be our source of truth.
That is really going to be the only place that has any information about what our current timer is.
So in order to actually get some value inside there in updated over time, I'm going to first go over
to my index.html file inside of here.
I'm going to find that input element.
And I'm going to give it a value property.
And I'll start it off as 30.
Now, whenever we assign an HTML attribute, it always has to be a string.
So notice how this is a string that says 30.
So we just need to keep that in mind.
As soon as we start to read a value out of this text input to figure out how much time is left on our
timer.
We're going to get a string and we're going to have to convert it into a number.
I'll then go back over to my index file.
So over here, I'm then going to go down to my tick method.
I'm going to delete that console log of tick.
And inside of here, I'm going to add in some code to reach into the text input.
I'm going to get the current value out of it.
We're going to subtract one from it and then throw that updated value back inside the input.
So to do so, we're going to first get a reference to the text input.
Remember, we already have a reference to it inside of our class as this duration input.
That was one of the arguments to our constructor.
So inside of here, I'll say time remaining is going to be this duration, input, value.
Now the value right here, once again, that is going to be a string.
So we have to take that string and turn it into a number to do so.
We're going to wrap that thing inside of Parse Float.
The parts float function is built into the JavaScript language, so we can just freely reference it
at any point in time.
This function is going to take a string that contains a number and it's going to pull out just the number
part of that string and give it back to us.
There are two functions that do this kind of operation.
There's Parse, int and parse float, parse int is short for parse integer parse int will give us a
number that does not have a decimal, whereas parse float will give us a number that has decimal.
So just as a quick example, if we have some string that has like 10.1 inside of it and we ran it through
parse int that would give us ten.
If we ran it through past float, that would give us 10.1.
So we're going to use Parse Float because we're going to eventually support decimals inside of our timer.
Okay.
So after we get our time remaining.
We can then do.
A update to the value of time remaining and give the new value or throw the new value back into the
input element so we can say.
This duration, input value is going to be time remaining.
Minus one.
And that should pretty much be it.
So let's now go back over to our browser and to save both these files and test this out.
So I'm going to refresh over here.
I can now see the default value of 30, which I set inside the HTML file.
I'll then click on start and I'll see the timers start to count down.
Now, the very good thing about this approach or kind of the nice thing, if I click on pause right
here and I update that value to say 300 and then click on Start, my timer is just going to work right
away the way I expect.
We did not have to add in any additional event handlers to watch for a change event and change some
internal representation of that timer inside of our timer instance.
That's what we would have had to do to get a change to work correctly.
You and I would have had to set up that event listener watch for a change to the input element and then
throw that updated value back inside the timer instance.
So again, nice thing about this approach, a little bit less work from the get go.
Okay.
So it's definitely works.
But let's take a quick pause right here.
And I want to point out something about the current state of our code inside the tick method.
We're going to figure out some way to kind of condense the code we have inside of here just a little
bit.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a moment.