Our method definitely works, but I want to point out something kind of awkward about it right now.
Right now, in order to figure out what the current value of our time remaining is, we're going to
always have to run that chunk of code right there at present inside of our tick class or assuming our
timer class.
This is the only location where we really need to figure out what the current time remaining is.
However, in the future, we might have many different methods inside of our class.
In each of those, different methods might need to access the current time.
And so they would all have that little repeated piece of code right there.
The same thing is true of updating the value inside the input as well.
Every single time we want to update the value, we have to reference this dot duration input value which
again starts to get just a little bit old pretty quickly.
So in this video, I want you to try to extract that little expression right there where we get a value
out of our text input and parse it with the parse float method.
And I want to extract out that part right there where we set the value of our duration input as well.
So to do this, we could define two helper methods inside of our class.
We could say something like Get time.
Or get time remaining or something like that.
I'll go with get time.
And we could also define set time as well.
So instead of get time, we could do something like return.
Our float this duration input value.
And on set time, we could receive some new time.
And then set that inside of the duration input like so.
So this is definitely an approach that would work.
Anytime we want to get our time, call that method.
Anytime we want to set it, call that method.
And we no longer have to worry or remember at all about how we actually get a value out of there.
But rather than using these two functions, there's a little bit better way of handling this by using
a feature inside of our JavaScript classes.
So the better way of handling this is to use a getter and a setter method.
Let's figure out how those work.
It's going to delete those two methods, and I'm going to set up a getter and a setter for a new property
that I'm going to call time remaining.
So I'm going to say get time remaining.
So notice how I've got a keyword in front of the method name.
So inside of here, we're going to write out the code that's going to get the time remaining out of
our duration input.
So I will return.
Hearse float.
This dot duration input value.
So now because we have to get keyword right here in order to run this method, rather than saying something
like back up inside of TTIC, we're going to eventually replace that right there.
So I'm just going to delete it right away.
So rather than saying this time remaining and calling it like a method because the JIT keyword is right
here, we can instead treat this as though it were an instance variable so we can just say this time
remaining that is going to automatically invoke this function right here, even though we don't have
the parentheses on the end.
The reason it gets invoked is because of that JIT keyword.
We set up a jitter.
This is how we add in some logic that's going to essentially retrieve a variable inside of our class
and we don't have to call a method or anything like that.
So this might seem like a very small difference.
Like at the end of the day, what is the difference between putting on time remaining with the parentheses
and not?
Well, the difference is that when we are able to write out just this time remaining, it makes it kind
of a little bit more clear to other engineers or we kind of trick other engineers.
Another way of putting it and to thinking that we are just retrieving a instance variable or like a
property of the class.
And we are essentially hiding away all the confusion about what is really going on with trying to get
some value out of that input inside the Skitter so we could even like collapse this thing right here
and we could forget about the implementation entirely.
And as far as another engineer is concerned as they read this, they're just going to look at this and
think, okay, there's like a time remaining instance variable and they won't have to worry about the
fact that this actually technically is a function or anything like that.
Now we can use a very similar approach.
We can set up a setter to change the value inside the input, and once again, we can essentially hide
away all the complexity around actually setting the value as well.
So I can say set time remaining.
So we're going to call this with the updated time.
And inside of here, we'll have the same implementation we had before.
So we'll say this dot duration, input value.
Equals time.
Start to make use of the setter, we can just attempt to set a value to the variable time remaining.
So back up here, rather than saying this dot duration input value, we could instead just say this
dot time remaining equals time remaining, minus one.
So in this case, we are attempting to set a value or essentially assign a value to the value or to
the property.
Time remaining time remaining is actually technically a function, but again, because we put the set
keyword inside of here, when we assign a value to it, whatever this value is right here is going to
be automatically provided as the argument right here of time.
And so again, we're essentially going to hide away all the complexity around how we actually update
the variable time remaining inside of our class.
So now in total, this entire tick method can be condensed down to just this time remaining.
Equals.
This time remaining minus one.
So again, behind the scenes, we are calling the Gitter right there to retrieve that value.
And we're calling the center right here whenever we want to update the value.
And I can't say enough.
I'm going to say it for like the fourth time inside this video, we have hidden away all the complexity
on how we get at that value and how we set it.
So I would definitely say this is a big improvement and this is another good reason in this particular
case.
Again, this is not super popular approach these days, but it's a good reason to go with option number
two, because one of the reasons that in the past we as JavaScript developers kind of moved away from
option number two is that we always had to write out some really confusing code like this right here
and this right here in order to update values inside the DOM whenever we are storing values on DOM elements.
But because we now have access to getters and setters, which are a newer feature inside of JavaScript,
we can write out methods that look like this that makes storing this data a lot easier than it had been
in the past.
Okay.
So let's save this.
We're going to do another quick test.
So I'll flip back over.
I'll refresh.
Hit start and we are still counting down successfully.
I can pause again, update the value hit start and it still works correctly.
Okay.
So this is definitely looking pretty good.
Let's take a quick pause right here and continue in just a moment.