There's really just one last thing we have to do to implement our timer.
So back inside of our browser.
I'm going to change the timer down to just 3 seconds and then start it up.
So I'll see that it's going to count down to zero, but then continue into the negatives.
So to finish up the timer aspect of this application, all we have to do is add in a check to stop the
timer automatically whenever it hits zero.
So I'm going to implement that inside my tick method.
So inside of here.
I'm going to say if this time remaining is less than or equal to zero.
Then let's call this dot pause.
To stop.
Our tick method from continuing to be invoked once every second.
Then inside the case.
So if this time remaining is greater than zero.
Then we're going to run the original.
Let's subtract 1/2.
So I'm going to cut that and put it into the case like so.
Yeah, it's.
I'm going to save this.
I'm going to go back over.
We'll do a quick test.
So I'm going to just change this to down to 3 seconds.
So go.
Three, two, one, zero, stop.
Okay.
So that definitely looks pretty good.
All right.
Well, that's pretty much it for the timer aspect of this thing.
So now you need to start to pivot our focus a little bit and figure out how we're going to get that
animated border to display around this.
So, remember, we want to have some kind of like border that's going to either fill up over time or
count down over time.
We want that thing to update with every tick of a second.
The other thing I want you to remember is that we still have to do a little bit of work on our timer
class because we want to make sure that during these very critical stages, like whenever we are starting
up the timer, whenever a second counts down or whenever the timer ends, we're going to make sure that
we watch or emit an event or call a callback or something like that.
So stuff outside of our timer class can kind of hook into or watch for that to occur and then update
the actual border animation.
Now, one thing I want to focus on right now or just mention really quickly is that our current implementation
of the timer class is like really simple and pretty darn straightforward.
So you can take a look at this thing and really very quickly understand what is going on.
If we started to add in all that border updating code into this class right now, well, our time or
class would start to get really confusing really quickly, much harder to understand than it currently
is.
Okay.
So quick pause.
We're going to come back the next video and start to implement the ability to watch for these different
things occurring.