Our timer class is now mostly complete.
The last thing we need to do is make sure that we can somehow emit these events or otherwise tell the
outside world that something important just happened inside of our timer class.
So we're going to add in the ability to detect whenever the timer starts, whenever we tick down a second
and whenever the timer is complete as well.
So in other words, our time remaining hits zero.
There are many different ways that we can actually implement these things.
So we could actually emit an event from our class.
But we're going to take a little bit more straightforward approach.
We're going to say that every single time that one of these things occurs, we're going to call a callback
function that can be provided to our timer class.
So that's how we're going to essentially notify the outside world.
Let's write out a little bit of test code really quickly.
And as soon as we do, I think you're going to get a better sense of what we're going for with this.
So back inside, my editor.
I'm going to go down to the bottom where we create our instants of the timer class.
So right now our timer class takes three arguments duration, input, start button and pause button.
We're now going to pass in a fourth argument to this thing as well.
The fourth argument is going to be totally optional so we can use our timer with or without the fourth
argument.
And we're going to need to make sure that we write our code out to accommodate that.
And inside this object, we're going to pass in a series of different callbacks that we're going to
make sure get invoked at very specific times during our timers life cycle.
So the three different callbacks that we're going to pass in and again we're going to make sure that
these are all optional, are going to be on start.
On tick.
And on complete.
So if we provide these callback functions, we're going to make sure that our timer calls each of them
at some appropriate time.
And so this is how we're going to essentially hook up our timer to the outside world and allow us to
kind of react to the timer starting to a second ticking down or to our timer completing as well.
This right here is what is going to allow us to really kind of segment or isolate the different parts
of our code base.
So isolate the timer from the logic that actually updates the border animation.
And remember, that was the entire idea that we spoke about over here where we had said, Oh yeah,
the timer would be really messy if we mixed in all the border stuff.
So this is how we're going to emit these little events or essentially signal to the outside world that,
Hey, timer just started, timer just tick down and timer is complete.
And so eventually in these different callback methods, we'll add in some code to update that border
animation, and we could potentially add in some other code inside of each of these to do other stuff
as well.
Like maybe you play a sound when the timer is all complete or play a ticking sound whenever an tick
gets called and so on.
So in order to demonstrate how each of these are going to work, let's first just focus on on start.
So we're just going to think about on Start right now.
So I'm going to say that whenever our timer starts, I want to do a console log of timer started.
So we need to make sure that this OnStar callback that we are providing to our timer is going to be
invoked the instant that we start up our timer.
So in order to do so, we need to first go into our timer implementation.
We're going to first update our constructor function and have it receive this object that has all these
callbacks inside of it.
So let's do that right away.
So I'm going to go up to my constructor.
So our constructor is now going to receive a fourth argument.
So we're going to receive that as callbacks.
Now I want to make sure that my timer class is still going to work, even if that object is not provided.
So the base implementation of our timer like just to get a basic timer that works, we're going to make
sure or require that we get the duration, input, start button and pause button.
But we're going to say that you do not have to pass in a set of callbacks at all in order to get the
timer to work.
Now, for the purposes of this application, there's not a good reason for that.
I just want to show you how we would write out this code to say, Oh, yeah, the callbacks are optional.
So to make sure that we have some optional fourth argument here, we're going to check and see if callbacks
was provided.
So if we call our timer with only three arguments now just those three.
We would fail this if statement.
Because callbacks would be undefined.
But if we did pass in an object representing our set of callbacks, then we will enter this if statement.
So inside the if statement, we'll put a little bit of code to process the callbacks that were just
passed in.
So I'm going to say this on start.
Is callbacks on start.
So we're going to essentially just save a reference to the callback that was passed in.
So now any time that we start up our timer, we're going to call this on start function that we just
save the reference to.
Now we are going to eventually come back to this little statement and handle the other two callbacks
as well.
But like I said, right now we're just focused on on start.
So we've now got a reference to the on start method.
Now we need to make sure that we call it at some very specific point in time.
So inside of the start function, this is where we should probably call that callback and signal to
the outside world.
Hey, timer, starting right now.
So right before tick, I'm going to first check and see if this dot.
On start is defined because remember, it is entirely possible that it won't be defined.
If we didn't pass in any callbacks, then we never assigned anything like that, never occurred right
there.
And so if we tried to just directly call this on start, we would get an error.
Saying something like undefined is not a function.
So we do have to see and just do a quick check to see if we were given an OnStar callback.
If we do have it, then we're going to go ahead and invoke it inside of here.
So I'll say this dot on start.
Okay.
That's pretty much it.
So that's just on start.
Let's do a save right here.
We're going to go back over to our browser and test this out.
So I should be able to click on start in the instant.
I do.
I should see timer started.
Well, that's pretty much it.
So that's how we're going to communicate to the outside world that something just occurred or something
important just occurred inside of our timer.
Now that we've got the on start wired up, we'll take a quick pause, come back in just a moment and
we will wire up the other two callbacks as well.
So on, tick and on, complete.