Our OnStar callback is all done.
Let's do the same for authentic and on complete.
So inside of Pontiac I'm going to put in a quick console.log and say timer just ticked down.
And then inside of on complete I'll do a console.log and say timer is completed.
So now we need to receive these inside of our constructor as well.
We're going to assign them to an instance variable and eventually invoke them during some very specific
point in time of our timer's lifecycle.
Well, first, go back up to the constructor once again inside of this callbacks.
Check.
We'll do this dot on tic will be callbacks on tic.
We'll also do this on complete in-store reference to callbacks on complete as well.
Okay.
So we've now stored a reference to both of those callbacks.
So now we need to make sure that we call both them at some very specific points in time.
So we would need to take a look at our code and figure out where the most appropriate time is to invoke
those callbacks.
Well, I think that in the case of on tick where we want to call this thing, every time we tick down
our timer, chances are the most appropriate time for that would be like right here inside the case
of our tick function.
So inside the case, that means that we are going to like tick down the timer.
So for that right after subtracting, I'll say if this dot on tick.
So if we were given that callback, let's go ahead and call it.
So now we can repeat the same process for on complete as well.
Where would be the most appropriate time to call this?
We want to call that function any time that the timer is done.
So in other words, when it has reached zero.
So for that, we might go down to tick once again.
And right after calling this pause, we could do a quick check, see if this dot on complete was provided
and if it was once again, we will call it.
Okay.
So this is looking pretty good.
So let's now save this.
We're going to do another quick test inside the browser and we're going to take a look at our console
and make sure that these console logs show up at all the appropriate times.
So we should see a console log occur when our timer starts.
We should see some tick messages as the timer counts down and we should see one on complete when the
timer is all done.
Yes.
I'll go back over.
Well, refresh.
I'm going to change this down to just 3 seconds again.
I'll hit start and I see timer started.
Tick down.
Completed.
Excellent.
That is exactly what we want.
So once again, these little console logs right here, these are proof that we can essentially tell
the outside world all the code outside of our class that something important just occurred.
And so, again, we're going to eventually take a look at those callbacks and we're going to add in
some code to draw the border, to update the border and eventually reset it as well.
So that's pretty much it for our timer implementation for right now.
We are going to have to come back to this once again in just a little bit and add in one little more
piece of code, but we'll get to that in just a little bit.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
We're going to start working on all this animated border stuff in the next video.