Well, our timer is all done for right now.
I said at the end of the last video that we're going to start working on the border.
There actually is one last very quick thing I want to do right now.
Our index file has a lot of different code inside of it, so it has our timer implementation at the
top, then has some query selectors and then where we actually create the timer as well.
Just to clean up our project a little bit, I would like to extract the class definition for the timer
into a separate file, just so that our index file is a little bit easier to read.
So to do so inside of my root project directory, I'm going to make a new JavaScript file called Timer
JS.
I'll then go back over to my index case file.
I'm going to select the entire timer class, so I'm going to highlight the entire thing.
There we go.
All the way to the bottom of the class definition.
I'm going to cut it.
I'm going to go over to timer DJs and paste.
And we'll go ahead and save it.
And then finally, finally, I'll go back over to index dogs.
Just do a little bit reformatting just to make it look nice.
The last thing we need to do is open up our indexed HTML file.
We're going to make sure that we get a script tag for the timer JS file that we just created.
So inside of index HTML, I'll find my script tag.
We're going to copy it, paste a duplicate, and I'll make sure that the top script tag is going to
get our timer JS file because we need to run timer dogs before we can safely run index dogs.
So the first one right here, I'll make sure it says timer dogs like so.
All right, let's save all these files, save all the changes we just made.
We'll just do another quick test just to make sure everything still works.
Yep.
No errors.
That means everything is good to go.
Okay.
Well, this looks pretty good.
So another quick pause right here and we'll actually start working on that border in just a moment.