All right.
Time to start working on the animated border that is going to go around the timer.
Now, at this point, I've really just showed you this circle and said, oh, yeah, like the border
is going to fill up or something like that.
That's not really a really good explanation.
So I'm going to show you the finished product of what we're trying to actually build here.
So here's what we're going for.
I want to show a full border around our timer.
And then whenever we click on that play button, we're going to essentially kind of empty the thing
out until it gets all the way down to zero like so.
That's the goal.
I'll refresh and do it one more time.
Yeah, there we go.
So that's what we're trying to build.
Now I've got some good news and bad news for you.
The good news is that, well, we could definitely do this.
Like that is within the realm of possibility.
We can figure out how without any library or anything like that, we can show that kind of animation.
The bad news, there's always bad news.
The bad news is we cannot make this kind of animation right here using just CSS borders alone.
So if you're used to using borders with CSS and normal styling, unfortunately, we cannot use that
to do an animation like the one you just saw.
So to do the animation, we're going to instead have to learn about a little side topic called SVG elements.
SVG stands for Scalable Vector Graphics.
This is going to be a set of HTML elements that we can use to draw kind of arbitrary shapes on the screen.
In this video, I'm going to give you a quick demonstration of an SVG element, and then we're going
to take a look and understand some of the rules governing them and eventually understand how we're going
to use an SVG to make that kind of animation that we just saw.
Okay.
So here we go.
We're going to flip over to our indexed HTML file.
SVG elements are HTML elements.
And so for this demonstration, we're going to write out some HTML inside of here.
Right above my input element.
I'm going to add in an SVG with a height of 200 and a width of 200.
Then inside there, I'm going to place a circle.
Now, of course, I'm going to tell you what all this stuff is in just a moment.
But right now, just a quick demonstration.
My circle element is going to have a property of R equals 20, C X equals 30, and C Y equals 30.
Okay.
So there's the HTML markup that we just added in.
Let's then save this.
We're going to go back over to our browser refresh.
And then, lo and behold, we see a circle up here on the screen.
So kind of humble beginnings here, so to speak.
But this is essentially the technique or strategy that we're going to use to get that fancy border to
show up.
All right.
So now that we can plainly see that there is some kind of circle and we can draw kind of like arbitrary
shapes here.
Let's pause.
We'll come back in a moment.
And I'm going to give you a lot more details on how SVG is work and how we're going to eventually use
them to do that animation.