We got an SVG to show up.
Let's now take a look at a couple of diagrams and understand how we work with them in general.
Okay.
Here we go.
Right here.
So first things first.
Whenever we want to show a SVG or essentially some set of random shapes that we want to draw onto the
screen, we're going to place an SVG element.
When we create an SVG element, we're going to assign it a height and a width.
So you can see that we did back that back inside the markup that we just put together right here.
So when we wrote that out, it essentially created a big square inside of our HTML document that was
200 pixels tall, 200 pixels wide.
This SVG element is kind of like a canvas of sorts, and on this canvas we can draw different shapes.
We can very easily see the SVG element in action.
If we go back over to our index.html file, use our element inspector and then hover over the SVG so
we can very easily see the full span of the SVG.
Now, so again, this is kind of like a canvas of sorts or kind of like an area.
We can draw as much stuff as we want to.
The SVG element has a couple of interesting properties around it.
One of the most important things we need to understand is the axes that it has or those dimensions.
So the top left corner of the SVG SVG element is what we refer to as the origin.
We're going to be working with a lot of coordinate pairs, so like x y values in order to place in size
different shapes inside the SVG element.
All the coordinate pairs that we are going to work with.
Use the origin of the top left hand side.
The x axis.
Then increases from left to right, and the y axis increases from top to bottom.
So if we were to try to show some different points on here, a point right here might be at about 175
pixels along the X direction.
So that means we go over 175 pixels from left to right and then 20 pixels in the Y direction.
So that means we go down from 0 to 20 in the vertical direction.
Then down here, this would be 190 pixels over to the right in 190 pixels down.
So again, origin is always at the top left and we have our x axis running from left to right, and
the y axis goes from top down to the bottom.
So we're going to very rarely for our application anyways have negative x or y values because negative
x or y would mean that we are trying to place a point outside of our available area of the SVG.
So like out over here and that would not display inside the SVG for something to display it must have
an x and y coordinate within the bounds of our SVG.
Right now we've got 200 pixels wide and tall.
So in other words, anything that we want to show up must be placed within 0 to 200 on the x axis and
0 to 200 on the Y axis.
So that's a bit more about SVG elements in general.
Now inside of an SVG element, we can place a variety of different other elements, such as a circle,
and as you would guess, this is going to draw a circle out onto the screen.
There are several other shapes we can place as well.
So we can do a polygon, which is essentially a shape with an arbitrary number of sides.
We can do a circle, which is what we just did.
We can draw any lips or a square or otherwise a rectangle.
We could also draw a path, which is essentially a line that has some arbitrary kind of direction to
it.
So we can draw out a path that kind of like curves and twists around as much as we please.
For our application.
As you probably guess, we're going to end up drawing a circle.
So we're going to draw a really big circle like so and we're going to place our timer text.
So like the countdown thing, that text input, all that kind of stuff is going to be placed inside
of this circle.
Now the circle itself.
There are a couple of different properties we need to understand.
These are pretty basic properties.
So are is the radius of the circle.
Remember, a radius is from the center point out to a edge that is separate from the diameter, which
is the full distance from one edge to the opposite edge.
So in this case, we created a circle with the radius of 20.
The C, X and C values are the center point of the circle or where to place the circle on the SVG.
So in our case, because we said C and C of 30, that meant that we could go back over to like this
diagram right here.
So we went over 30 units and then down 30 units and then we placed our circle, the center point of
it at that location.
So you can imagine 30, 30 might be like right there or so we can see that as plainly what happened
inside of our drawing over here.
Okay.
So that's some more about drawing a circle.
So now if we want to, we could easily play around with some of these R values and see and see.
So, for example, I can move my circle to the right by increasing the C value that is going to increase
the X value or the center point of the X value for the circle.
So go to like 130 and I'll expect to see this thing shift over by a hundred pixels.
Yep.
There we go.
I'm going to revert the C to 30 and I'll try increasing C Y to 130 as well.
So that should move our circle downwards by about 100 pixels.
Yep.
Definitely happen.
And then, of course, we can start to increase the R value.
So it could go up to say 120.
And now the radius of our circle is going to be significantly larger.
So now the circle is so large that it actually flows off the SVG.
If something is outside the SVG, it means that we just plain can't see it.
So even though the circle is technically off the edge, well, we can't really see it because the SVG
itself is going to clip that.
Okay.
So that is the SVG and the circle.
Now, last thing I'm going to do, I'm going to revert the circle back to an R of 20, a C of 30 and
a C of 30.
And then I'm going to copy paste this circle down twice.
Then on the second one, I'll change the course to 130.
And on the third one, I'll change the CI to 130 as well.
And so now I can see very easily three circles on the screen.
So for us, we're just going to show one circle, but I just want you to know that we could show as
many shapes inside of an SVG as we wish.
Within reason, of course.
So I'm going to reduce this back down to just one circle like so.
All right.
So we now understand some of the basics around drawing a shape inside of an SVG and some properties
around SVG as well.
But now we need to understand how we can actually draw something like, well, what we were going for
before this thing over here where we only see the outline of a circle.
In addition, we want to make sure that we can kind of like have a line of sorts that goes around at
the same time.
So we still need to understand a little bit more about how we're going to achieve that.
So quick pause right here and I'll see you in just a minute.