You now have a bit better idea of how an SVG element works along with circle elements.
So now in this video, I want to tell you a little bit more about circles and some special properties
around them.
And this is going to start to help us understand how we're going to finally implement that animation.
Okay.
So a couple of things I want you to understand about circles.
When we draw out a circle using an SVG element, there are really two parts to the circle.
The inside of the circle are kind of like the content inside we refer to as the fill the border, going
around the outside the circle, rather than calling it simply a border.
We instead call it a stroke.
We can change the colour of the fill and the stroke by adding in some additional HTML properties to
our circle element.
We can also change the width of the stroke or the border as well at the same time.
So let's go back over to our HTML file.
We're going to start to play around with these different properties a little bit and see what effect
it actually has on our circle.
Okay.
So I'm going to go back to my HTML file.
I'm going to first change the dimensions of the circle just slightly so we can see these changes to
the fill and stroke a little bit more easily.
So I'm going to increase the radius to 90.
I'm going to take my C to 100 and see Y to 100 as well.
Let's save this and refresh our app just to see the effect it has.
Okay.
So that's what it looks like now.
Now, quick reminder, just really quickly.
Remember, I run my browser very far, zoomed in.
So you probably see something a little bit closer to that right there.
Okay.
So let's try changing the fill and the stroke.
I'm going to first give myself a little bit of space to work with because we're going to eventually
add in several different properties here.
So I'm going to put in a fill of red and a stroke of blue.
I'm also going to set the stroke with property as well.
So stroke, dash width and I'll pass in ten for that.
So this means make the center of the circle blue or something.
Make the center of the circle red, make the border blue.
And the border should be about ten pixels wide or ten pixels thick.
So let's save this.
Go back over and see what happens.
Well, yep, that's pretty much it.
So now we've got the red interior, the blue exterior.
If we start to increase the stroke width here to say like 50, the borders can get that much larger.
I'm going to stick with ten for now because it's a little bit easier on the eyes.
There's another very interesting value for Phil that we can use for our application, and it's really
relevant to what we are trying to do.
For the Phil, we could specify a color of transparent, which means make the center of the circle see
through.
So if we use a fill of transparent, that means we could very easily start to see some timer elements
behind this thing or something like that.
So I'll set Phil to Transparent and now the center totally gone and I can see directly through it.
Okay.
So that's some basic additional properties around a circle.
Now there's a couple more that are going to help us modify or play around with that stroke.
So let's take a look at a couple more diagrams and understand what these other properties are that are
going to allow us to modify the border around the exterior.
So the first additional property I want you to understand is stroke, dash, dash array.
We're going to give this a number of value and it's going to specify the length of a dash around the
perimeter or essentially for the border of the circle.
Let's try adding in this property and playing around with it just a little bit.
So I'll go back over to my HTML file and I'm going to add in a stroke.
Dash, dash array.
And I'll start out with ten.
So that means give me a dashboard order and I want each segment of the dash to be ten pixels long and
then a ten pixel gap before the next dash segment.
So I'll save this.
Go back over and refresh.
So this means or I can see very easily now I've got about ten pixels of dash and then a ten pixel gap,
then ten pixels dash, ten pixels gap and so on around the exterior.
The statutory property technically accepts two different values.
If we only pass in one, then ten will be used for two.
For both the different values.
The first value we pass in is going to be the length of the dash, and if we pass in a second, it is
totally optional.
It will be used as the spacing in between each dash segment.
So for example, if I put in a ten and then a five, that means give me dash lengths of ten and then
spacing in between each of those dashes of five.
So we can save this, go back over and now we'll see.
We've got about ten units of dash and five units of spacing in between.
But again, if we just put in the one number, that means give us give us identical dash lengths and
gaps as well.
So I'm going to leave it at ten for right now.
Okay.
So this looks good.
I want to remind you of something about properties of circles in general.
So if we take a circle and we measure its radius, so that's going to be from the very center point
to the outside edge.
We can calculate the entire perimeter of the circle.
So the total length of the outside edge by using the formula two times pi times the radius.
Now the radius that we just changed our circle to is 90.
So if we do two times PI times 90, we end up with 565.
So that means that the total length of the outside edge of the circle is about 565 pixels.
So with that calculation in mind, we can start to draw like a quarter or like a half segment of border
around the circle.
Let me show you in my terminal.
I'm going to calculate two times math pi times 90 and then divide that by two.
So that gives me about 282.
So if we enter in a dash array of 282, that means that we want to have about half the circle, have
a dash, and then have the half the circle not have a dash.
Yes.
I'm going to go back over and try updating the dash array to about 282.
So if I now save that and then refresh.
There we go.
So I've now got half the circle with a dash, half without it.
We can do something very similar.
So two times pi times 90.
And then this time I will.
How about multiply?
By one quarter SOE 0.25.
So now I would have just a quarter segment if I use that 141.
So now I get a quarter, half a quarter of no dash, half a quarter a dash, half a quarter of no dash.
And then, of course, last thing I want to show you.
Around this perimeter is that if we do the full five, 65 or just slightly less than it, that should
give us just about the entire length of the thing and then leave us just a little bit of a gap.
So I'll do right around 560 and just leave a little bit of a gap.
So now I can see I get a whole bunch of border and then just a tiny little gap at the very edge.
So the next thing I want to tell you about this circle is that the border is always started, started
drawn from the right hand side, and then it draws around clockwise.
And we can see that very easily with the border dash array or the stroke dash array that we just added
on.
So it's very clear that the border starts right there and then travels around clockwise until it decides
to hit an empty spot.
We can start to play around with that value of dash array.
It's not going to change it really quickly here.
Several times it's going to start to decrease it to say 550.
And I can see that the gap is a little bit larger.
I can go to 520 little larger.
I go to 480 a little larger yet.
Okay.
So that's how we can get like a just about full border but have a gap at the very end.
So now there's just one last thing I want to show you.
I'm going to change the dash array back to the full about 560 or so.
The last property I want to show you is called the Dash Offset.
Now, the dash offset is a really tricky property to understand.
Suffice it to say, if we have a border that goes just about around the entire outside edge.
Dash Offset will introduce an extra little spacing right there.
Let's play around with Dash Offset just to get a sense of what's going on with it.
So back on my circle element, I'm going to add on stroke dash, dash offset and I'll start it off at
ten.
So this means in addition to that little space we have right there, give us another extra ten units
of spacing as well.
So that's going to give us a little ten extra units of a white space right there.
So I'll save this refresh and I can clearly see ten extra units or about ten extra units.
I don't actually know what ten units looks like, but hey, there's ten right there.
So now if I start to increase that value to, say, 20.
Some more.
If I go to say 40, I get more.
Yet if I go to 100 140, that should be about a quarter.
And then if I go to about to what was it, 80 or so to 82, that's going to be about half.
And I can eventually essentially unravel the entire thing by specifying about 560.
And so that's going to give me extra white space all the way around that outside edge back to around
right there.
Okay.
So the dash array and the dash offset properties are how we're going to actually pull off this animation.
So let's take a pause right here in the next video.
We're going to take another look at these properties and I'll explain exactly how we're going to use
them to actually show the animation on the screen.