Now that we understand the dash ray and dash offset properties, let's understand how we're going to
use them to actually implement this animation.
I want to first begin by taking a look at the finished product one more time.
So this is what we are going after.
We want to have the entire stroke starting off as covered.
So that would imply that we're going to begin with a dash array with whatever our perimeter value is.
So for us, it's right around 565.
And we should also have a dash offset starting at zero.
So that's how we're going to get that full arrow or that full border excuse me, starting up when we
first start our application.
Now, here's where things get challenging.
Take note of how this animation plays out.
We're starting from the very top edge and we're going to show white space going in the clockwise direction.
That's kind of counter to what we were just discussing, remember?
The default behavior is to draw the border starting from right here as opposed to anything up at the
top.
And then the dash offset is going to add in additional white space going in the counter-clockwise direction.
So this final product has the spacing or the white space going in clockwise.
What I just showed you around Dash Offset is going to add space in the counterclockwise.
So in other words, if we use dash offset as we know it right now and we start off at zero and let's
say 1/2 goes by and we change that to 20.
We're going to get that gap.
Then if we go to 40, we're going to get that gap and so on.
So again, it is playing in the opposite direction of what we really want.
So how are we going to fix this?
Well, as usual, it's just a little trick dash offset.
We're just going to make it negative.
Yep, that's pretty much it.
Providing a negative value of dash offset is going to add in that white space in the opposite direction.
So it's going to start to go in the clockwise direction instead of the counterclockwise that we saw
in the last video.
So if I change dash offset to -40, we're going to get the white space right there.
And then as we start to take that number more negative, it's going to start to go in the clockwise
direction.
We're going to see more and more white space like so.
So you can imagine that for every second that goes by, we're going to change dash offset to be slightly
more and more negative.
And that's what's going to give us white space going all the way around the outside edge until it eventually
comes back to the same right hand side.
It's now the last big question is how are we going to actually get.
The animation to start at the top like up there, as opposed to the default behavior, which is to have
the entire border being drawn right there on the right hand side.
Well, once again, a little trick.
It's usually how it works out.
So the little trick we're going to use, we're just going to rotate this entire circle, -90 degrees.
So we're going to take the entire circle, rotate it -90.
So we're going to take it 90 degrees in the counterclockwise direction.
Counterclockwise.
To do that rotation, we can add on an additional property to our circle element.
We're going to provide transform.
Is rotate -90.
And then this will also take two other arguments.
When we call rotate, we're going to pass in 100 oops, 101 hundred.
Let me expand this.
Just we can see it more easily.
So as you would guess, the first argument to rotate is going to be the amount we want to rotate and
the direction that we are rotating in a negative value means that we're going to rotate in the counterclockwise
direction.
The second two values right here define the origin point of the transform.
So by default, usually a transform is done against the top left corner of our SVG element.
By passing in at 101 hundred, we are saying that we want to rotate this circle around what happens
to also be the center point of the circle.
So we're going to rotate around that point right there.
So let's save this refresh.
And now if we start off with a data or a dash offset of zero.
We start up right there, everything is matching up on the top.
And then as we start to make this number more and more negative, so we'll go to negative ten, it's
going to start to give us that white space.
As I go to -50, give us more as we go to -100, and we can start to see how as we start to make dash
offset more and more negative, we're going to get that white space around that outside edge going into
the clockwise direction, just like we saw on our finished product over here.
So that's pretty much it.
That is the secret.
The secret is to use the negative value of dash offset.
We're going to use a dash array value equal to the entire perimeter of the circle.
And then finally, we're going to transform the circle as well to implement a rotation, -90 degrees.
Okay.
So now that we see like the general idea, essentially what we're trying to do here, the last thing
we have to do is essentially take this entire strategy.
We need to make sure that every single time we tick our timer.
So like over here with on tick, every single time that happens, we need to make sure that we start
to make dash offset right here more and more negative.
We're also going to add in a little bit of code to kind of adjust these values of dash array and calculate
that value on the fly.
Because obviously putting in the parameter or assuming the parameter right here, that is a calculated
value we have to do two times pi times the radius.
So rather than encoding the dash array right here, we'll instead set that programmatically.
So we'll read the value of the radius of the circle, calculate the perimeter, stick it in, and then
every single time we get a tick, we will update dash offset.
So now that we've got the full story, quick pause right here and we'll work on our implementation in
the next video.