Now that we've got the entire story, let's start to work on the actual implementation of this animation.
The first thing we're going to do is change some of the dimensions of the SVG and the circle element.
Right now, if I zoom all the way out to 100%, that timer that we have right here is really small.
So I want to basically double the size of the timer, just sort of fills up the screen a little bit
more nicely.
So to get started, I'm going to find my SVG element.
I'm going to change the height to 400, the width to 400.
I'm going to change the radius as well.
We're going to use a radius of 190.
We're going to leave the C or C at 202 hundred, but we are going to have to come back and adjust those
in just a little bit.
You'll see why very shortly.
We will leave the fill of Transparent.
The stroke.
I'm going to leave as blue.
I'm going to do a slightly adjust the stroke width, make it just a little bit thicker at 15.
And then finally I'm going to take out the dash array and the dash offset.
We're going to calculate both those values on the fly using the radius, because otherwise, like I
just mentioned, if we ever decide to change the radius again, chances are we might not remember how
dash array is calculated.
Remember, it's supposed to be the parameter value, so we're going to calculate that value on the fly
using the radius just so we don't have to remember.
Oh yeah, two times pi times the radius to figure this out.
So in total, we're going to double check here.
We should have our CSI fill stroke, stroke with and transform.
One last thing.
I apologize here on rotate.
We need to adjust that to 200 200 to specify the new center point.
Okay.
So let's save this now and see how we're doing.
Well, that looks pretty good.
Definitely a little bit better sized.
We're going to make sure that the text input and the start and pause buttons eventually show up inside
there.
But let's just work on the animation to get started.
So now I want to go back over to our index dogs file.
And down by our timer.
We're going to eventually write a bunch of different code inside of here to work with the timer and
make sure that every time we get a tick, we kind of clean up a little bit or really kind of change
some of the different properties of that circle element.
So to get started at the very top with all these other query selectors, I'm going to add in a selector
to find that circle element.
So I'll say const circle.
Is document query selector circle.
And after that we will immediately read off the value of R or the radius and we'll use it to calculate
the parameter.
To find the radius of the circle, we can use circle, dot, get attribute, and then we put in the
name of the attribute that we want to find in this case are.
So to calculate the perimeter, it will be the radius times two times math pi.
And notice how pi right here is all capitals.
So I'm going to assign that to a variable that I will call perimeter.
Then immediately after that, we're going to set the dash array value on the circle equal to the perimeter.
Remember, that is what is going to get us the full big circle like you see right here.
So I'll say circle set attribute, and we're going to try to set stroke, dash, dash array and we're
going to set it equal to the perimeter.
Okay.
So it looks pretty good.
So now the next thing we're going to do is to make sure that every single time our timer ticks, we're
going to once again set an attribute.
But this time we're going to set our stroke offset property, which is what's going to give us that
white space up here on the starting on the top edge and then go around in the clockwise direction.
So inside of authentic, I'm going to delete that console log.
And I'll replace it with circle.
Set attribute.
We're going to set the stroke.
Dash, dash, offset property.
And we need to provide a value right here that's going to start off as zero and go more and more negative
over time, ideally by the time our entire loop finishes.
So by the time the timer like ticks down to zero set or the stroke dash offset right here should be
equal to the perimeter.
That would be ideal.
So to make that happen.
For right now, we're going to declare a little variable right above our timer.
That will call current offset.
And I'll initialize it at zero.
Then inside of the set attribute are inside the on tick right here I'm going to say current offset.
And during every tick will update the value of current offset.
So we'll say current offset will be current offset.
-50 and I apologize.
I actually want that line to be underneath these set attributes like so.
So we'll set the attribute and then subtract a little bit off the current offset.
Okay.
So let's say this and see how we're doing right now.
So I'm going to flip back over.
I'm going to refresh.
I'm going to hit start.
And now we can see the things starting to tick down.
Well, look at that.
It actually works.
Okay.
Well, that's definitely not bad at all.
The only problem right now is that it is a very kind of like blocky animation because remember, we
are only taking once every second and then every second we are counting off by exactly 50.
So that's what's resulting in this really blocky looking animation.
The other issue is that as soon as we start to get down to right there, well, unfortunately, because
we are just subtracting 50 units every time we're going to eventually roll around that entire property
or that entire value of stroke dash offset.
So it's going to eventually get greater than the perimeter.
So definitely what we have right now works.
But there are a couple of things about it.
We need to improve, so we need to make sure that the animation is a lot smoother.
We also need to make sure that rather than using this just -50 right here, we should adjust by a very
even increment.
So essentially the number of ticks or really our perimeter divided by the number of ticks, so that
by the time it gets down to zero or the timer gets down to zero, we should end up right there and not
go over to the next edge.
So definitely still a little bit of work.
So let's get started on that in the next video.