Well, we've got our animation working, but there are two big issues with it right now.
Whenever we run the animation, it's occurring in this real kind of like block segment second by second.
So it'd be really nice to have a much smoother animation.
The other big issue is that because we are always subtracting by 50 units for our offset value, we're
always going to end up either overshooting or undershooting, having the animation finished at the very
top point right there.
Let's take a look at this.
I'm going down to nine, eight, seven.
Ideally, the animation would stop right there and even not even really right there because we still
had that little segment visible.
For the animation to be really correct, the entire border should disappear right when it hit zero.
So again, we need to make sure that we somehow get a better subtraction, subtraction right here than
the -50.
Let's first focus on the animation, however.
So let's make sure that we can show a really smooth animation as opposed to the big blocky thing.
To make the animation a lot smoother, we can just choose to run our timer much more frequently.
So let's take a look at our timer implementation once again back inside of our timer JS file.
If you take a look at start right here, you'll recall that we are running the tick method once every
1/2 or 1000 milliseconds.
So what we could do to make our animation a lot smoother is run the tick method way more frequently
in every single time we run the tick method.
Rather than doing the 50 unit update right here, we could do a really small update like one pixel.
So if we only do one pixel update at a time, it will make the animation a lot smoother.
So to make this happen, let's go back to timer DJs.
We're going to find where we set up our interval and rather than running tick every 1/2, we'll instead
run it every 50 milliseconds.
So that's going to be way more frequent.
Let's make sure.
Down inside of our tick method as well.
Right here where we update the value of time remaining rather than subtracting 1/2 because we're going
to run tick so much more frequently, we should instead only subtract .05 now.
So that's 50 milliseconds.
It matches up perfectly with the interval timer that we have right there.
Okay.
So let's now save this.
I'm going to go back over to my index file.
I'm going to find where we've got the 50, and I'm going to change that to one instead.
So now every single time we have a tick, I'm going to update the current offset by just one unit or
one pixel.
So I'm going to save this.
I'm going to go back over, refresh and hit, start again.
And so now we can very easily see that the animation is a lot smoother.
But there's another little issue that's cropped up.
Take a look at the text input right here that shows the current value of the timer.
It definitely has the like 17 point, whatever it looks like it's counting down.
But you'll notice that there are a ton of extra nines inside of here.
So how could that be?
We are only ever adjusting the timer by.
Over here, 0.05 units.
But for some reason, we're getting all these extra nines inside there.
Well, the reason we're seeing this is because mathematics in JavaScript is a very imprecise science.
All this subtraction, addition, multiplication, all the stuff that we do uses a system in JavaScript
called floating point operations and math inside of JavaScript sometimes gets subject to these really
strange rounding errors.
Well, let me show you a really common it very easy to reproduce rounding error inside my council right
now.
I'll say 1.9 minus one.
Yeah.
Didn't really see that coming.
So of course the result of that should be just 0.9.
But because the way JavaScript handles math and actually to be honest, most programming languages handle
math, we end up with this really weird result.
And so because of this floating point error, that is the same reason that we're seeing something really
funky inside of our input right there as well.
So we can fix this up pretty easily.
We're just going to do a little kind of a rounding operation when we set the value inside that input.
I'm going to go back over to my editor, find the timer JS file.
And I'll find our setter method for time remaining at the bottom.
So here's the setter.
So we take the current time that has been passed into time remaining and throw that into the value or
the input value property.
So it's this time variable right here that has all those extra decimal points inside of it.
So it makes everything work out nicely.
We can just call two fixed on this that's going to essentially round the decimal on there to just two
decimal places.
So we're going to drop off all those extra little values that we see inside all the actual decimals.
So I'm going to save the update.
Go back over.
Refresh.
Hit start again.
That's definitely better.
So now we just see the first two numbers and the first two decimals.
Okay.
So overall, I'd say that this was a good fix.
It's not the last big thing we have to do inside of our index dogs file subtracting by one right here.
Still not appropriate.
We need to make sure that we adjust the current offset by some appropriate value so that no matter what
our timer is running for, we will always end the animation at 0 seconds perfectly at the very top of
the circle.
So we'll have to figure out some way of handling that.
Let's take a pause right now and discuss how to do it in the next video.