The next thing we have to do is to make sure that we adjust our dash offset value by something more
precise than negative one.
So let's take a look at a couple of diagrams and really understand the math that we have to do.
Okay.
So here's the general idea.
When everything first starts are in our side of our animation, we want our dash array value of our
circle element to be equal to perimeter.
That is what is going to give us that big round circle when everything first starts out.
When the animation ends, we still want the dash array to be equal to perimeter.
But what's really going to change over time is the dash offset.
The dash offset will start out off at zero.
So that's what's going to give us the kind of nice circle right here.
And then over time, we want to make it more and more negative as the dash offset gets more negative.
We're going to get additional white space from the top going around the clockwise direction.
So by the end, we want to have a dash offset equal to negative one times perimeter.
So the real question here becomes how do we start with a dash offset of zero and then effectively over
the span of our entire timer and in very equal increments go from a value of zero to negative perimeter.
We make that happen, we're essentially going to say if our perimeter is, say, a circle of 100 units.
And we have total 50 different TIC events.
Then each individual tic would need to adjust that offset by negative one times 100 divided by 50.
That gives us negative two.
Let me show you a better diagram to really illustrate how this formula works.
So here's the formula that we need.
So we're going to calculate offset.
This is going to be how much we're going to change that stroke dash offset property for every tic.
So that's the general formula.
We can start to plug in the start and end values inside of it to figure out or make sure that actually
makes sense.
So our offset at the very start would be p times, the time remaining, which would for us be 30 seconds
divided by the total duration, which would also be 30 seconds.
And then we would subtract by the perimeter.
The 30 divided by 30 would turn into one, so we'd end up with P minus P, and so offset at the very
start would be equal to zero.
And so that matches up with our initial requirement over here.
Then at the very end our dash offset is equal to zero, or that's our dash offset.
We want to be equal to a negative perimeter.
So at the very end, we're going to have a time remaining of zero divided by 30.
So we get zero divided by 30.
That's going to end up zeroing out and we are left with just negative P and that once again matches
up with what we just discussed over here.
So this is pretty much the formula that we have to increment or implement inside of our on tick function.
There's just one problem with it.
Our intake function doesn't really have any idea of how much time is remaining or the total duration.
That's not a big problem.
Kind of let me show you a real small change that we can make to our code to make sure that the authentic
function that we have.
So this function right here can get access to the time remaining.
If you want to do that, we could go back over to time or JS.
I'm going to find my tic function here is right here.
Inside there.
I'll find where we call on tick and inside of it.
When we call on tick, I will simply pass in this time remaining.
So now back inside of our index dogs file on tick is going to receive the time remaining.
So that's not bad.
So we now have one of the values inside of our formula that we need to determine what the offset should
be at each tick.
Now, there is a second problem here, and that is the total duration value.
We need to know the entire duration of the timer.
So if we set it for 30 seconds and hit start, we need to know that starting time right now, there
is absolutely nothing inside of our application to track that value.
In other words, there is no input.
There is no value inside of our timer class, nothing that tracks the total duration of the timer.
But by using one of the callbacks we implemented, we can start to track it ourselves.
So we're going to say that whenever we call on start, we're going to pass in an argument that represents
how much time is going to take for this entire timer to run.
Well, then receive that argument right here and store it.
So then later on inside of on tick, we can use that value to figure out what the total duration is
going to be.
So let's write out some code, because I know this is confusing.
Let's write out some code.
You're going to see where we're going with this really quickly.
So I'm going to go back over to my timer.
I'm going to find where we call on START, which is inside the start function and when we call it,
I'm going to pass in the value of this time remaining.
So when we first start our timer this time remaining, that value is going to be how long the timer
is going to run in total.
So in on start we can receive that.
As an argument that I will refer to as total duration.
So then it's back over here rather than storing something like current offset right there and going
to delete that.
And I'm going to make a new variable called simply duration.
And it will set the value to total duration whenever the OnStar function is called.
So we'll say duration is total duration.
So then finally inside of on tick, we can actually implement the correct offset when we update the
stroke dash offset.
So we no longer have to make a change over time.
So I'm going to delete that line instead at every tick.
We're going to take the time remaining.
We're going to take the total duration.
And we're going to take our perimeter.
And we'll use it to figure out exactly what the offset value should be.
So I'm going to delete current offset right there.
I'm going to give myself a little bit of space and we'll write in our formula.
So remember right above, we already defined our perimeter.
So we'll say perimeter.
Time's time remaining divided by the duration, and we'll subtract from that the perimeter.
And that's it.
Now I know this, like, explanation of all the math is really nasty, but when it really comes down
to it, this is what's really going on.
So I'm going to save this.
And we can do one last test.
I can make sure I save both files.
Of course.
Flip back over, I'll hit start.
And now we can see the timer working as expected.
By the way, the animation is always going to play a little bit more smoothly if you close your console.
So close your chrome console if it seems like it's a little bit laggy.
So now we can wait for this to count down all the way to zero.
And when it hits zero, we should see the animation finishing like right there at the very top end point.
So nine, eight, seven.
Well, you can count.
So I'm going to wait for this thing to finish up and make sure that it finishes at the correct location.
And there we go.
So by the time it hits zero, we have cleared out that entire circle perfectly every time.
Now of course I can always update the timer to say 3 seconds hit start and it's going to play it again.
Okay.
Well, let's see.
This looks pretty good.
Now, the only thing that we might change here.
When I use three, you'll notice it still looks a little bit choppy.
So if you want to, you can always go back over and adjust the interval that we do this update at.
So instead of 50 right here, we could always take it down to say 20.
But if you update it right there, just make sure that you update how much we change time remaining
by for every tick.
So if we take that to 20, we would want to subtract 0.02 from time remaining.
So I'll save this.
I'll refresh.
I'll try again with 3 seconds.
Yeah, that definitely looks a little bit more smooth.
Okay.
Well, this looks pretty good overall.
So now the last thing we have to do is just a little bit of styling to make sure that the input, the
start and pause button, all that stuff shows up inside of the circle.
So let's take care of some styling in just a moment.