Now that our timer is working pretty well, we need to apply a little bit of styling just to make sure
that everything shows up inside of the actual timer.
The first thing I want to do is replace the start and pause buttons with the icons for like pause and
or start and pause right there.
So to show those icons, we're going to use a free icon library called Font.
Awesome.
I'm going to open up a new browser tab and navigate to font.
So this is a free resource so we can use to show tons of different icons inside of our application.
The first thing we have to do is wire up this library to our app.
To do so, we're going to open up one other page.
I'm going to go to CN JS.
Once here we can search for font.
Awesome.
And we'll see a link right here.
So notice that this is a CSS file.
That's how we make use of font awesome inside of our project.
We're going to hook it up as a CSS file, so I'm going to copy that link.
We'll then go back over to our HTML document.
Here it is right here.
I'll go up to my head.
And I'm going to add in a link tag.
So I'll say link.
We're going to use a rel of stylesheet.
And then an F and we can paste in that link that we just copied.
Okay.
So now that we've wired up font awesome, we can take a look at the font awesome documentation and figure
out which icon we want to show.
So go back over to the font documentation.
On the top left hand side is a little search box.
So when you first get start with the icons, of course, you're probably going not going to know exactly
what the name of any icon is.
So it's really up to you to just kind of take a guess.
When I look at these icons, the words that come to my mind are, play for that right there.
It's like a play icon and pause.
So I'm just going to take a guess and I'm going to search for play.
And when I search for play, we're going to eventually see some results.
Here we go.
So these are all the different icons that match that search string.
Looks like that one right there.
Looks pretty good.
So I'll click on that one to figure out how to use it.
Now sometimes font awesome website is a really slow, so I'm just going to give this a second to load
up.
Hopefully it resolves quickly.
Okay.
Very good.
So now to actually make use of this icon, you'll see right underneath play is a little eye tag right
there.
So that's the HTML that we're going to show in order to show that icon.
So I'll click that thing to copy it.
I'll go back over to my HTML document.
I'm going to find my button that says Start.
I'll delete the text that says Start and replace it with that ID tag.
So now I can save this.
Go back over to my browser, refresh and I'll see the play button right there.
Okay.
So that's definitely good.
So we can definitely repeat the same process to get the pause icon as well.
So I'll search for pores.
Wait another couple of seconds too for it to load?
Yup.
That definitely looks good.
So I'll click it.
And click on the eye tag again.
I'll go back over to my HTML document, find where we have.
Pause inside the button.
I'll delete it and replace it with the eye tag as well.
Yes.
I'll say this the second time.
Refresh.
Okay, well, that looks pretty good.
All right.
So for the rest of the styling, I'll be honest with you, it's really just a bunch of CSS and whatnot
that we're going to throw into our HTML document.
So we're going to take a quick pause right here in the next video attached to the video, you're going
to find a zip file inside.
That zip file is going to be an HTML document and a CSS file.
Make sure you download that zip file.
It's going to be called something like timer oh 25 template or something like that.
So make sure you download that zip file and find the HTML CSS file inside.
So make sure you grab that and we'll start to integrate that or merge it into our project in just a
moment.