Attached to this video, you're going to find a zip file called Timer zero 25 template with template
in all capitals.
There are probably two different files attached to this lecture, so make sure you get the one with
the name template inside.
Once you get that file, we're going to unzip it and then take a look at the two files inside.
So we've got an indexed HTML file and a style CSS.
So all I did here was add in a couple of additional HTML elements, some class names and some CSS just
to apply a little bit better styling to our timer.
The only reason I'm giving you this is that, well, this really is, of course, about JavaScript.
And so for the most part, we're going to skip over a lot of styling stuff.
I still want you to have some neat looking apps, though, which is why we're usually going to have
some HTML and CSS being provided to you.
So to use these files, I'm going to open up my editor.
And I'm going to first begin by dragging and dropping the indexed HTML file into my editor.
So here's the HTML file that we were just given.
I'm going to select everything inside of here with a command or control a depending upon your operating
system.
I'll copy everything.
I'm going to go back over to my indexed HTML.
So the one that we've been working on for our project.
I'm going to select everything inside of here, delete it and then paste.
So now as we look through here, we're going to see just about everything is the same.
So we still have an SVG element, we still have a circle, the input, the buttons and all that stuff.
Just a slightly different structure.
Next up, I'm going to create a new file called Style CSS.
I'll go back over to where we have those two files from the zip file.
I'll find the style case that we just downloaded.
I'm going to drag and drop it into my editor.
I'll select everything inside, copy it, and then paste it into the styled CSS file that we just created
and save.
All right.
So now that everything is saved in updated, I'll flip back over to my browser.
I'll refresh and we get something that looks like this right here.
If I zoom back out to 100%, you'll probably see something that looks like basically that.
So now I can click in here to run the timer.
It's all the exact same logic that we just had.
Nothing changed.
All the JavaScript code is identical because, well, we didn't change any of it.
Right?
And now I can click on that thing.
It is the actual text input there, so I can click on it and change it to say 30 seconds and then run
it down.
I can pause it, change it again to say 60 seconds, run it down, and so on.
So that's pretty much it.
Now, one thing I want to really highlight is that that really is a text input.
The only thing we did was some CSIS was make sure that it doesn't display a border and it also doesn't
get highlighted when you actually select it.
So if I actually do a little bit of fancy stuff here really quickly.
You'll see that there is an outline property being set inside the style CSS file of none.
So that's why it doesn't really look like an input, but it technically is.
All right.
Well, I hope you enjoyed this project.
We definitely learned a lot along the way about SVG things, handling set intervals, classes, where
to store information and all that kind of stuff.
We still have a lot of code to write and a lot of projects to work on, however.
So let's take a pause right here and start working on our next project in just a moment.