Hey.
Welcome, everyone.
We've made it to my very favorite topic in the course and honestly, my favorite topic in all of teaching
web development, the DOM.
So this is very exciting stuff in my opinion.
I look forward to it every time I teach and when I teach bootcamps in person, it's my favorite week,
favorite two weeks.
It's really fun stuff because we start to connect JavaScript with HTML and CSS.
This is where I think JavaScript starts to become a lot more exciting and certainly more visual.
You can start to make things with interfaces, things that you can see enough with the contact logging.
So I always look forward to it.
Hopefully you're excited about it, especially if you've never worked with the DOM.
You don't know what it is.
There's a lot to cover here.
It won't fit into one section.
We have multiple sections.
I have a couple of examples I'd like to show of things that we could build after you learn how to manipulate
and work with the DOM.
So there are some simple ones like here's a form where as I start typing, notice the placeholder text
here that says last name.
If I put something in here like Chaplin, notice how the text went down below as a label, and then
if I delete it, it goes back up.
Very simple, little tiny touch, but that's done with JavaScript.
So we have the form that is just HTML and CSS.
We don't need JavaScript to make that work.
If I comment the JavaScript out, well, I just deleted it.
Let's comment it out.
We still have the form here, but now we're not getting that interactive element.
It still looks the same, but we don't get that behavior.
Here's another example.
This is a fun.
Well, fun is relative.
It's a game that is a memory game where you have to match different cards and flip them over.
I'm terrible at it, but I really like the interface at the beginning.
When you start, you get this nice little flip of the card when you click instructions, and then you
can click here to actually begin the game and select a level.
So the content itself is HTML and CSS.
If I comment all of that out, select it, commented out, we still have the exact same interface.
It just doesn't do anything.
I'm clicking.
Maybe you can hear that through the mic, but we don't get any behavior.
We're just seeing that content.
It's basically static little blocks of color with some letters, but we add JavaScript in and now they
do something.
When I click and I can play the game, go to casual.
Like I said, I'm horrible at this game, but the just very active clicking on something and having
it change in any way, changing the color, having it flip, revealing the symbol that is all JavaScript.
The cards themselves are HTML and CSS.
It's very hard for me to even attempt to play this while talking.
So I'm already terrible to begin with.
But as you can see, we've also got this timer going across the top.
Highly stressful.
I'm just clicking randomly at this point and one more match before the end.
All right.
So again, this is all JavaScript functionality.
This is JavaScript that is making the game logic that is checking.
If we get a match, it's checking.
Oh, geez, it's checking to see if a card has already been clicked on or if the timer has finished,
if you still can play or if it's game over.
Here's another example.
This is another nice form where we have different steps of the form, little animations that are triggered.
So we go from step one to step three.
Each time I click, I'm just seeing HTML and CSS.
If I remove all JavaScript one more time, we still have the exact same content.
It just doesn't do anything.
I can't go from one step to the next.
We add JavaScript in and it's now an interactive, almost like a different set being shown on a stage.
When you go see a musical or a performance, a new set being swapped in and the colors are changing
up here to tell you which step you're on.
So nothing crazy, but this is all done with JavaScript, all the interactivity.
And then now for something a little crazier, much more complex.
This is on YouTube.
This is a recorded live stream of a really cool musician, very funny guy, Mike Rabbit.
It doesn't matter who it is.
Anyway, over here we've got comments.
Hopefully nothing super inappropriate.
And as I play the the video, you can see these comments start to come in and they're synched to when
they were actually submitted back when this was live.
I can click to hide, I can show it again.
This is all happening through JavaScript.
These elements are being added to the page in conjunction or in time, in sync with this video.
They're being added here.
So even something just like hiding and showing is done with JavaScript, being able to pause video and
have this stop.
We don't get those new comments.
Now that's done with JavaScript.
If I fast forward, I get new comments that's done with JavaScript.
So JavaScript, the DOM, very exciting stuff.
This is where we start to take HTML and CSS and control it, update it, or even just read it and understand
it using JavaScript.
So something like this is.
Is made by a team, obviously a huge team at YouTube, but things like a form or a memory game, the
code is really not that bad.
But the thing about the DOM that I'll tell you right now is that you have to use tons and tons of methods
and properties that we haven't seen before.
So remember when we saw arrays or we saw strings and I talked about here's 20 methods that arrays have
when we work with the DOM, we have at least 20, maybe 50 different methods, 50 different properties,
and it takes time to get to know the ones you'll use the most.
And it's also imperative that you don't try and understand and learn every single property.
That's something I'll bring up as we make some more progress.
The DOM is just a huge thing.
There's so much to that you could stress about trying to learn and memorize.
Don't approach it that way.
We're going to go step by step and in the next video we'll take our first step into this beautiful promised
land of the dom.