Before we move on.
There are some prerequisites, some things that you need to be comfortable with before you can really
master the DOM before this content will make sense to you.
Those topics are basic HTML and CSS.
The good news is that HTML and CSS are really pretty easy to learn the basics of.
At least we're not talking about making beautiful websites.
We're not talking about crazy complex layouts that are responsive.
You just need to understand how to create simple elements on a page, how to nest things together,
how to work with IDs and classes, how to write simple CSS selectors to select based off of elements
in classes and IDs.
Maybe attributes.
You need to understand how to change colors with CSS and fonts and how to resize something the basic
properties.
So if you don't have that understanding right now, I recommend you take an hour or two to go follow
a tutorial online.
You can check out my YouTube channel.
I have a basic HTML and CSS intro, but there are also tons of great courses paid and free and books
and free blog posts.
You don't need to go buy an expensive course or even buy anything.
Just take some time and set it aside so that this section in the next few sections actually make sense
to you.
Because this stuff is really exciting, it's fun.
But if you don't have that understanding of HTML and CSS, it's just going to be intimidating and make
it a lot more challenging than it needs to be because this Dom stuff is actually not hard.
Where it gets tricky is when people try and learn it before they understand HTML and CSS.
So I'm going to do a little demo slash assessment that you can self assess based off of.
I'm going to write some simple HTML and CSS to show you the level of understanding I'm looking for.
So I have an HTML file already created.
I'm going to add some simple elements in here.
We'll add an H one and this will say my web page.
I'm going to add a simple ul an unordered list with a couple of allies.
First thing, second thing and third thing.
So I have an ally here or three lies in an unordered list.
I'm going to add an image.
I'll set the source to be this nice grizzly bear image from Unsplash.com nice images that we can use
for free.
And I will also go ahead and add in maybe a paragraph tag or two paragraphs.
Just let's do some lorem ipsum so I can just type lorem in vs code and then I'll add another one of
those lorem just random text.
I'll add an ID to my image and I'll call this image.
We'll just call it Beyer photo.
So if you're still with me, if this is all making sense and feels like very basic stuff, that's good
news.
If any of this is confusing, you're not sure what these elements are.
You don't know what an ID is or a source.
Take some time.
Go learn that stuff because you'll need it.
You absolutely need it for the next couple of sections, and I don't want you to feel bad or get lost.
All right, so we have our H one.
I'll also add a class to my Liz.
Two of them, at least this class will be called special.
Okay.
So I have two paragraphs.
I have my H one, I have allies that have a class of special.
I have an ally that doesn't and I have an idea for my image of bear photo.
Now I'm going to make a stylesheet, so I'll just make my file here.
I'll call it CSS and I'm going to start by styling my H one, just something simple color purple font
size 20.
Now that's going to be very small.
How about 60 pixels?
So I haven't connected my stylesheet, but let's just make sure my content is showing up.
All right?
Now I'll connect my stylesheet using a link tag and the ref is app dot css and my h one should change.
It's purple now and larger.
So if this syntax is new to you, you haven't seen it.
You don't know what font size does or color.
I guess that's pretty self explanatory, but if you're not sure about this syntax here, then take some
time and review that.
Let's also go and select the bear image.
So here's the first little part of the assessment.
How would we style this bear image to give it a width of 250 pixels using the ID?
All right.
So I'm going to come in here and select it with bare dash image and I need to make sure I add in a bear
photo.
Oh, geez.
Horrible name.
Can't even remember it.
I need to make sure I add in my hash symbol there to make it clear it's an ID and I'll give it a width
of 250 pixels.
Refresh my page.
Much more manageable.
The next part of the assessment, I'd like for you to make the class of special.
These two lies.
I'd like them to be teal and 30 pixels, font size and give them a one pixel border.
Also teal.
So we'll select the class, which was called special.
I need to use the dot because it's a class.
And I'm going to start with color.
What did I say?
Teal.
And then font size.
I think I said 30 pixels and border was one pixel teal.
Let's see what we get.
All right, so there is my special class.
So I've styled the H one, the image with the idea of bear photo and the two items.
The two eyes that have a class of special.
It looks horrendous.
It's very gross.
But this stuff is very important.
Don't worry about the styles.
But if you feel like any of this was new or confusing, you need some clarity on it.
Go look online and get some practice.
Now, here's one more thing that you could use as a little assessment.
Let's add in a form.
All right, so I'll add a form element right here.
And in this form I'm going to add an input type equals text.
I'd like to give it a placeholder of what should we do?
Bear name and then another input below that.
And instead of type equals text, what are our options here?
We'll do type equals.
How about password?
And then give it a placeholder.
Of password.
And then one more input we'll do type equals submit.
Well, refresh and we have our form here.
What I'd like you to do is select only the input that has type of password and give it a different width.
You can change it to smaller, larger.
Just give it a different width and height.
So you'll have to select based off of the type, not off of input.
Don't add an ID, don't add a class.
Select it as is.
So I'm going to do that over here.
If I just did input like I did for H one, that will target all three.
And if I do height, let's do 50 pixels with 100 pixels.
That does work.
But I only want to target this one right here so I can add in an attribute selector type equals password.
And now only this one is affected.
The other inputs are unchanged.
So that's it for the stuff.
I mean, that's not everything you need to know, but that's a general sampling of the kind of HTML
and CSS experience you need.
You need to be able to do basic styles, understand CSS syntax, key value pairs, semicolons, selecting
based off of classes, ids, elements, attributes.
There's a bunch of other selectors and we may come across some of them in the course, but this is most
of what we'll be selecting based off of in our JavaScript.
And then as far as elements, things like inputs, definitely paragraph tags, H once all the headings,
buttons, list items, all the different text elements, paragraphs, semantic elements like block quotes,
sections, articles.
You don't have to be an expert in everything.
Just I want you to be comfortable enough where you're not focused on the HTML and CSS so much and trying
to understand it that you're missing out on the DOM stuff, which is fun.
All right.
So now we're going to move on to the DOM again.
Please take this seriously.
I mean, you're obviously able to make your own decision and do what you think is best.
And if you want to just plow ahead without HTML, CSS experience, it's definitely possible you'll pick
it all up at once.
But for the best experience, I recommend that you you get some practice first, take some time away
for just a bit.
You're not going to miss out too much.
The course will still be here for you.
Get better with HTML, CSS and then come back.
All right, so let's get going.