All right.
Now that we have all that housekeeping out of the way, all the HTML and CSS prerequisites, we can
now dive into the DOM.
Very fun stuff.
We're going to start in this video with kind of a taste of the dom.
I'm going to show you some code, different snippets.
We'll play around and tweak a web page.
And the goal is not for you to understand every line or remember it, because I'm showing you code that
we'll see in this section later on or two sections from now, we're kind of looking ahead.
So it's it's more of a sneak peek.
Okay.
So the document object model or the DOM is our window into HTML, CSS and the web page in general through
JavaScript.
It is our portal into the world of a web page.
So we can write JavaScript that can figure out how many ones are on a page or how many inputs are in
a form, or we can get the value from a form.
If a user is typing into the form, we can change the value of a form.
We could change images, make them bigger, we can change styles of anything.
We could add animations, we can listen for clicks or drags or hovers or any sort of event that a user
could trigger and then have some behavior that happens in response.
A user clicks on a game piece and it will change color.
Or if a user clicks and drags a chess piece when they drop that chess piece, you should check.
We should write code that checks.
Is it a valid move?
If it is, then move that chess piece to the square.
If there's a piece there already, then replace that piece and remove the captured piece from the board.
We add logic in with JavaScript that controls, that interacts with, that reads and understands the
contents of a page.
And the key thing to understand about all of this is the object part document object model.
When your web page loads up, whatever the web page is, this simple one that we were doing here in
the last video, when it loads up, the browser is going to turn it into a bunch of objects, just JavaScript
objects, and these objects are all constructed and put together to form the DOM.
It is a virtual representation or a JavaScript representation of the content on a page and it consists
of a bunch of JavaScript objects.
So I probably spent way too long making this image, but we have HTML, CSS and some other stuff that
goes in and the browser interprets it, it reads it and it creates the DOM for you.
It spits out JavaScript objects representing the HTML and representing the CSS.
So here's a simple example of what I'm talking about.
If this was our HTML, a very simple web page, we have an H one, we have a UL, we have two lives.
The browser will read this in which on its own doesn't mean anything.
It's just text.
It's text content.
The whole job of the browser is to display it in a way that makes sense to humans, to make this larger,
to make this a bullet point if it's inside of a UL.
So the browser reads it, it does all of that, and at the same time it creates a virtual representation,
a JavaScript object of the H one.
There's another object for the UL, another object for the Li and another for the LI.
So that's what this is representing over here.
Each one of these little circles or nodes is an object.
They're telling you that I'm an object.
Me too.
In case you had any doubts.
So they're objects.
And those objects have a bunch of different properties.
The simplest one that we could see from here would be what their content is, what text is inside the
object water plants.
So we have one that has a property called text or something like that.
It's actually called inner text set to water plants.
We also have tons of other properties for different attributes, CSS styles.
We have methods that we can use so that I could delete one of these with JavaScript and it would be
deleted from my web page.
I could update one of them and change the text.
I could even change the type of element I could.
Instead of having an H one, I could replace it with an H two.
All of that is done through JavaScript where we interact with these objects.
All right.
So now for the part, that is the taste of the DOM, a little preview of where we're going.
So I'm on Google.com, just a regular home page.
I'm going to just type some code in the console.
The first thing we'll see is proof that we get a bunch of objects.
The DOM just consists of objects, so why don't we pick something?
Maybe this button right here, it is an input.
Does it have an ID?
Uh, it doesn't have an idea.
Okay, this one has an ID.
Is this the I'm feeling lucky button?
I'm going to copy this ID and use that to select that element.
So this is new.
We haven't seen it before.
Or at least not in this course.
Don't worry about it.
I hate saying that, but don't don't stress about what it is.
Okay.
So if I save this to a variable const button object.
If I look at that button object I've selected based off of some ID and I have a representation of it.
Unfortunately, in the console, it looks like it's not an object.
It looks like it's just HTML.
But if I do console dot dear, which you've seen a couple of times, button object and open this up,
you can see it's just a regular JavaScript object.
It's massive, it has tons of properties, tons and tons of methods and properties here, and they all
relate to this one button.
Let's take a look at one of them.
How about the value of the button?
If I scroll down, go down to value, it's set to.
I'm feeling lucky.
We also have things like classes and IDs.
If I go up to I, where are you?
Okay, there we go.
Here's the ID.
We have attributes like hidden.
So this is not a hidden element.
So it's set to false.
We have tons of other things that we're not going to get into right now, but you can see that it's
an object and everything we see on this page is represented with its own JavaScript object.
But let's start with this one.
So we have our button object, and I can read the value of that button, which is I'm feeling lucky.
I could also change it.
I could set it to something else.
I am not lucky.
Does anybody use the.
I'm feeling lucky.
I haven't.
Not on purpose at least.
And we can see we just changed it.
It now says I am not lucky.
So that's our first interaction with the Dom.
The page loaded, all this HTML was turned into stuff we see visually and at the same time it was turned
into JavaScript objects.
We can select and interact with those objects.
We can change them in JavaScript.
It's just like if I had an object here where I had a value set to four, just call this.
Oh, and then I said zero value is now equal to 56.
The main difference, of course, is that when I change zero value, nothing happens.
Oh is different, but there's no side effect.
The browser doesn't care, it's not changed.
But when I change one of these objects from the DOM, there is an impact.
It's reflected in what we see.
So changing this JavaScript object is linked to seeing that change in the page.
So when we change a style, when we change the text, when we add new elements, we do it through JavaScript
objects and then the browser knows about it.
The browser knows, Hey, this thing just changed.
I better update it for the user or in the browser so that we can see that change.
And we'll try one more fun, mildly fun thing.
Not, not exceedingly fun.
We're going to add an event.
So when I hover over this button, I want to console.log something or change the text, although it's
already being changed here we get this nice animation that's from Google.
We're not going to deal with it.
So why don't we just start by alerting something so we have our button object BTN obj and again this
is something we haven't seen before, but we will see it.
So we're not going to go into detail here.
But this says Add an event listener, whoops, add event listener to the button.
The event we're listening for is a mouse over.
And then here's the function I want to run.
When I do mouse over and I'll just do an alert.
Hi.
Okay.
Let's see what happens.
There we go.
I get high every time I hover over that button anywhere else.
It doesn't change.
Nothing happens.
But I go over that button.
We get a nice alert so we could replace that code with anything else.
Usually we don't alert.
We might change the content of the button.
We might.
Instead, we could.
I mean, we could do anything.
We could change the color, we could add new elements to the page.
We could delete every single thing from the page.
We could animate things.
We could send a request to get information from an API.
It doesn't matter what we do, but the point here is that we can do it.
We can run code when an event happens or when it occurs based off of a particular element in this case,
that button.
So we will get to events in due time.
First, we've got to start with the basics of the DOM and in the next video, I'm actually going to
do one more kind of fun demo where we're really going to just wreck this home page for Google.
We're going to animate everything so that it just randomly bounces around and rotates.
It's going to be kind of fun, maybe, but if you don't feel like watching that, you just want to get
to code and you want to start from the beginning.
That will be two videos from now.
The next video is just another taste of the DOM Part two.
All right.
So to summarize everything we saw here, the DOM document object model is just a bunch of objects,
plain old JavaScript objects.
We've worked with them before, but not ones this large, not ones that have so many methods and properties.
These are made by the browser based off of the incoming content, the HTML and CSS.
Other information about a web page.
It's all turned into a JavaScript representation of objects that we can use, we can interact with,
and we can change.