All right.
Welcome back.
This is part two of our Taste of the Dome little demonstration.
So I'm going to go ahead and play around with Google, the home page of Google again.
But I'm going to do something a little bit more visual, more intense.
I'm going to take every element that you see on the screen and animate it around randomly.
So it will just end up being a huge mess to try and use.
And yeah, just to show you that we can do things like change styles and move things around and animate
them.
So I'm going to open up my console.
Oh, almost there.
Command option J.
There we go.
And the way I'm going to write my code instead of just typing it in the console because I'm going to
have probably ten or 20 lines, I'm going to make a snippet.
And in Chrome to make a snippet, we go to sources and then there's a tab called snippets.
If it doesn't show up for you, you can click the arrow and go to snippets.
This allows me to write some code, so I'm going to click new snippet.
I can write code and then run it at any point in the browser without having to make a separate file.
And it will be evaluated and I can do things with the current web page, so I'm just going to try something
like console.log two plus two, I'm going to save it and then I can run it either by hitting where's
that button right here, clicking this or using the shortcut, which is what I use.
Command Enter on a mac.
If you're on a PC, it will tell you what to use right there.
So I just ran it and if I look at my console, you can see four was printed out.
So we're not going to be using console plugs or anything right now.
I'm instead going to interact with the elements over here on the DOM.
Get rid of that triangle.
Some fun top Google searches How to make French Toast, Jobs, Hiring and funny cat videos.
Can't argue with that.
All right.
So the first thing I'll show you is that we can create new elements.
Super easy.
Well, it's relatively easy.
Don't worry about any of this syntax.
We'll go into the details about how all of this works.
But I'm going to make a new image.
I'm going to give it a name.
My image.
I'm going to give it a source.
My image source equals and I have a URL of copied from Unsplash, a free image we can use.
And then I'm going to add this image to the DOM, I'm going to insert it.
So I'll do document body.
Dot append my image and if I run this code, I'll hit command.
Enter.
Oh, there's my image.
Very large image.
But it's showing up.
If I want to amend it to be smaller, my image dot style dot width equals let's do 200 pixels.
Run this code again.
I'll have to refresh my page and run it.
Now we have this image of a dog wearing goggles.
Okay, so that's the first bit.
Now, if I want to move it around, there's a lot of different ways of doing this.
The best way would be to do it mostly via CSS.
But what I'm going to do is in JavaScript, I'm going to generate some random numbers, an X and a Y
coordinate or a position and use that to move the image to that location using a CSS transform.
So if you haven't seen transforms and CSS, this is going to be new, but it's really just a demo of
like cool stuff we can do, so don't worry about it.
What I'll do is get my image, my image style, dot transform.
And before I animate anything, I'll just assign a transform.
Like, how about translate?
And then I give it a number, like 300, comma, 200.
Let's see how that looks.
If I run it.
Oh, I think I forgot the pixels that I need to add 302 hundred pixels.
Let's try that again.
Okay.
So now I transformed the image.
I moved it over here, I translated it.
So that's how we can do it just once.
Now, if I wanted to do this randomly and I want to repeat it, I could do it using a set interval.
So set interval I pass in my function.
I'll use an arrow function just for some diversity here.
And we also need the duration or how long that interval should be.
So every 2 seconds we'll run this code and we will transform that image.
But let's generate two random pixel values and I'm going to use the dimensions of the screen which I
can access using document.
Dot body.
Dot client.
Width and height, height.
So that's something we will see and talk about in greater detail.
Document dot.
Body dot.
Client width times.
Map random.
Make sure I add my friends and then I'll floor that whole thing as we've seen before to get a whole
number.
So this will give me a random number between zero and whatever the width of the window is, which changes
depending on the actual width.
So here we get a different width versus here we would be getting 400 pixels.
All right.
So messed up for I'm going to save that to a variable called X and then duplicate this and do the same
thing for a variable called Y.
I'm just getting two random numbers mapped out for document dot body.
I'm going to do client height here and then I'm going to plug those numbers in right here.
So this does need to be a template literal, not single quotes.
So I'll put that around my string and then interpolate x pixels and then y pixels and the moment of
truth.
Let's see what happens.
Okay, we're getting something.
It's not pretty, it's very jerky.
But every 2 seconds it is moving around.
And if I wanted to make it smoother in my case, I would add in a transition property.
Although right now I don't have a CSS stylesheet.
This is Google's website, so I'll just show you that you can do it through JavaScript.
My image dot style.
Dot transition.
Equals.
And then I'll say one.
What is it all?
1/2.
Let's do 2 seconds.
If this interval is 2 seconds, I'll have it take 2 seconds to translate.
And does it work?
Ooh, look at that.
It's moving all over the place.
Okay, so kind of fun.
We're picking a random X and Y on the screen and moving the image.
That image, for the record, was not there when the page loaded.
We're adding it in, so we're seeing a whole bunch of different features already.
We created a new element.
We updated its source attribute, we added it to the page, then we added some CSS to it.
We changed the width to make it smaller.
We change the transition property to make it smoother when it moves, and then in a interval we're picking
random numbers and using that to generate a translation, a transform across the screen every 2 seconds.
Now for the extra fun part, let's do it to every single thing on the page.
So this same logic.
But I want it to happen for every element and there's a lot of ways of doing this.
What I'm going to do is select all the elements using this document dot body, dot children.
Again, this is getting to stuff where you have not seen we haven't seen any of this, so please don't
worry about it.
We will get to every every single line of code we're writing here will have at least a video addressing
it and how it works.
So Document Dot Body Children will give me all the elements that we're seeing on the page.
I don't want to select every element in the DOM because there are elements like script tags and link
tags and the title tag.
We don't want those.
We want just the stuff showing up.
So document body children.
I'll just call this all ls.
All elements, and then I'm going to loop over all elements inside of my interval.
So for let L of all L's, I'm going to pick an X and a Y.
I'm going to use that X and Y to update the transition excuse me, the transform of that element.
So let me make this easier to see.
Instead of my image style, I'm going to do L.
So I select everything on the page, and then for each one I'm going to give it a new transform with
a new random x and y, and we'll do it every 2000 seconds or 2000 milliseconds.
We'd be here quite a long time if I did it to everyone.
Whoops.
All right, let's go back.
Try it again.
Run my code.
Fingers crossed.
All right, so we only have the dog image that is transitioning smoothly.
Everything else is just jerking around.
Let's also rotate everything so we could pick a random rotation here.
We'll call this rotation, which needs to be a number between zero and 360.
So we'll do math random times 360.
That should give us a random rotation.
And then the way that transform works in CSIS is that it wants us to pass in a number of degrees.
So we'll do it just like this dollar sign rotation.
And then afterwards we need to write deg for degrees like we had to do for pixels.
And this should be rotate, not rotation.
Let's try it out.
And there we go.
Things are rotating.
They're just not animated except for our one image.
So the last thing we'll do is apply a style to everything in the body.
We'll add a new part to the style sheet and I'll just paste the code in for that.
Here, what I'm saying is make a new CSS style sheet.
Basically, that's what I'm saying.
And then add in a new selector, select everything via CSS, give it transition of 2 seconds and then
I'll add that stylesheet in again.
Don't worry about any of this code whatsoever, but let's just see if it works.
I'm going to run it.
Fingers crossed.
Hey, look at that.
Everything's all rotating and going crazy.
Moving across the page.
It is kind of annoying that this whole thing is treated as one element.
This, I think, is called viewport is the element.
So we might be able to break that up a bit.
But you can see what I'm trying to show you is that we can select things, we can screw with them in
maybe not so nice ways like animating them, but these principles apply for everything we would do.
We can interact with the form, get the value out, or change an image source to make a slideshow widget.
We can add events like we saw in the last video.
We can pick random things and mess with them with random numbers and transformations.
Maybe not all that often, but you can do that.
We can add new styles to a stylesheet, we can make things have a transition.
We can create an image out of nowhere and add it to the page.
So I tweaked it ever so slightly before.
What was happening is I was getting every element in the body, which is really just this one div and
it contains everything.
And I was animating this one div, so this whole piece of content was animating together.
But now what I've done is updated it so that I'm animating these elements inside that div instead,
which you can see here.
This is what this line does.
If I run it now, we end up with some independent rotation and moving around anyways.
The whole thing is useless and silly, but it illustrates this idea of changing objects and seeing those
changes reflected in the actual browser.
So everything we've done has been manipulating JavaScript objects, hence the object model part of the
DOM.
So really, really important idea behind all of this.
The page loads and all of that juicy content is run through the DOM machine, the DOM Maker 3000, obviously
not what it's called, but it takes that content, it understands it digests it, and it spits out a
bunch of JavaScript objects, some of which we interacted with in order to make this happen, and some
of which we created from scratch, and then told the DOM or told JavaScript to insert them with the
rest of the content.
Okay.
So now that we've had a somewhat overwhelming taste of the DOM, now we're going to go into the basics
and start from the beginning.
How do we do some of the stuff we just did?
We'll go into detail around selecting and changing styles and different attributes and events.
There's a lot to talk about.