All right.
So it's time for our first official video in the the real learning part of this Dom stuff.
We saw some demos, we got a little taste of the DOM.
We talked about HTML and CSS and what you need to know.
This is really video one of learning the dom.
So we're going to start with the most important part of the DOM, the document.
Remember Dom stands for document object model and the DOM is just a representation of an actual document
made with a bunch of objects and they're assembled into a tree.
This shape that we see over here, there's a hierarchy there, not just sitting out there in some random
order.
They're not in an array, for example.
I mean, they could be.
But then how would we know the relationships between parents and children and the structure?
So they are put in a tree like structure here with branches, and in every tree there is a top most
piece, what we call the root of the tree, which is kind of the opposite of a regular tree, I guess
the roots down at the bottom.
But anyway, we've got the root of the tree, which when we work with the DOM is an object called document.
So document is an object you have in every single browser window that you ever open.
You can type document every web page.
Here's one of mine.
This one, this simple HTML and CSS demo.
If I type document right here, I get a annoying printout.
This is not what it actually is.
This is the dev tools just showing me the HTML in the document.
But if I do consul dear document we can see the actual underlying object.
Now this object represents the entire page, this entire document.
If I go to the MDM page, this is actually the docs for the document.
If I look at document and do the same thing, console dear instead.
We have another object and they follow the same pattern.
They have a URL, right?
There's a URL right there.
My URL is different over here.
I'm on a file protocol.
I'm just viewing my HTML file versus here.
I'm looking at developer dot mozilla dot org and the document contains tons of properties, tons of
methods.
This is really where we start with everything.
So all of the other objects, all of the other pieces of the DOM are located within the document somewhere.
It's all nested into a kind of large, confusing structure if you are trying to navigate it yourself.
And if you recall from the last couple of videos, everything that I was doing, I was typing document
dot something, document dot get element by ID, document dot, body, dot children document dot, get
elements by tag name.
There's all of these different methods and properties and they're all contained within the document
object.
So the document is the entry point that we use to access the DOM, to manipulate things, to just view
the content in the DOM, but also to add events and add functionality.
It's all located inside of this one object.
The document and everything else stems from there, so it's created for us automatically.
We don't just like we don't create the dom ourselves.
The browser does it when it loads the page.
Same idea.
The document will be there for you when a page is opened in the browser or when you view a web page.
If we take a look at my web page again, here's the document that I printed out as an object.
We'll see a couple of other things that might make sense right now.
How about images?
This is a collection of images on the page.
There's one image right now.
If I go to the N version and I look at document dot images.
We have, what, 12 images on this page?
If we go back to my version and we instead look at something like, how about documents?
All right, here.
This is a property that contains every single element on the page, things we see and don't see.
So the title meta tags, the head script tags, if we have any.
They're all included here.
Every single one is turned into a JavaScript object and itself has tons and tons of properties.
And as you can see here, if you were trying to navigate this manually and trying to understand it all,
this is just completely overwhelming.
But fortunately, we really don't need to know most of it.
So the main takeaway here is that we get all these objects for free.
We load up the a web page in the browser, whether it's a file or we're going to some website and the
DOM is created, all of it is stored inside of one object called the document.
But the document has references to all those other objects, as you can see here.
If I go to document, all this is just one way of looking at other elements.
I've got 12 know what?
21 different elements.
If I do it on MSDN, that document object all has holy cow.
18,940 elements.
And each one is going to be a big, massive, crazy object that has tons of stuff inside of it.
So that's it for now.
The document is our entry point, and that's why all of these methods we run, all of these properties
we'll look at, or at least the majority of them start with document something, documents do something.
So we'll see our first batch of methods in the very next video.
Very exciting, I think.
Maybe by.