All right.
So now that we've seen the document and all of its craziness, all the methods and properties that it
holds inside, obviously we didn't see them all or talk about them all, but you saw how many there
are.
We're going to start by taking a look at the first batch of methods that you should know, the most
important methods that have to do with selecting.
So selecting is a really important part of the DOM manipulation process.
Typically, we select an element or multiple elements and then do something with them.
So here's a simple example with paint cards or paint chips, we select one and then give it a new color
or do something with it.
We could animate it, we could move it around, we could delete it, we could select something and then
add a new child within it, a new element.
We could select a form and add two new buttons to it.
We can also do things like add events, so we select an element, a button.
We did this early on, actually, two videos, three videos ago we selected a button on Google and then
when you hover over it, we alerted some text.
So when we want to add some events and interactivity, we still start by selecting and there's a bunch
of different ways to select using the document.
I'm going to show you a couple.
The first one we'll tackle is called Get Element by ID.
This is a method on the document, so we call it as document get element by ID and it does what it sounds
like.
It takes an ID and it finds the matching element that contains or that has that ID on it and it returns
that object.
So if we go back to this simple example, we could have any markup.
But the markup I have to keep it easy is from a couple of videos ago it looks like this we have an H
one some paragraphs I've got a UL a form and I have an image that has an ID bear dash photo.
Let's add one more ID, let's do this paragraph here.
ID equals text.
No.
How about main?
Sure.
So I have two ids on this page.
Now I can select those elements using document dot get element by ID.
So it's a method that exists on the document and I pass in an ID as a string.
So I have bear photo.
That was one.
I'll try that.
And you can see what I get back.
It returns an element to me.
What's annoying?
I went over this a couple of videos ago.
It prints it out as HTML, which is not very useful.
But if we save it to a variable just to make it easier, I'll call this image and then console dot die
r image.
We can see its true object form as we talked about earlier.
Here are all the properties I have.
So this selects based off of an ID, but it's not returning HTML to me, even though it looks like it
is.
It's returning an object and this object represents that one image with the ID.
And if we scroll down we will see ID is set to bear photo matching this ID right there.
We also have properties like the type of the element tag name is set to image.
We could find the image source right here.
This is the image URL.
So when we call document get element by ID, pass in a string if there is a match and only if there
is a match for that ID, we get that element back as an object.
The DOM representation of that element, this image.
Remember, you're only supposed to have one ID on a page or one of each ID, so there shouldn't be multiple
bear photos.
And if there were, for some reason we still only get the first one that matches, so we'll only ever
get one element back.
And if we pass it an invalid ID or something that's not on the page, let's do document, get element
ID of get element by ID of bear.
In all caps we get nothing.
So no error, we just get null because there isn't an element with that ID.
And we'll do one more example.
We have something else with an ID this paragraph the ID is main.
If I select that ID using document get element by ID main, I'll save that to a variable called p.
We look at P, it looks like it's HTML, but remember it's actually an object console.
Dear P here is our object and it contains a lot of the similar properties, a lot of the same methods
as our image, but different values.
For example, we scroll down all the way down here.
We don't have a source attribute because it's not an image.
We have tag name set to P because it's a paragraph, it's a P tag.
We have the text content, lorem ipsum, blah blah blah.
That's the content of this paragraph.
And there's a whole bunch of other things.
One other important topic that will see a couple of times in this section is that this object here is
of a particular type.
It is something called an HTML paragraph element.
If we look at our image, do I still have it here?
Let's do a console dot dear image and we look at what type it is.
We scroll down to the bottom.
It's called an HTML image element, so they're both HTML elements.
But one is an image element.
One is a paragraph element.
Now, in this course, we haven't talked about prototypes.
We haven't talked about constructor functions and classes.
So we won't go into much detail here.
But all you need to know is that there are different categories of elements on the page, and some of
them have their own type, like an HTML paragraph element and an HTML image element.
Every image element has a source.
For example, a paragraph doesn't.
These are just different patterns for these objects.
So whenever we get an element by ID or any of the other select methods, we'll see in the next couple
of videos they return some sort of element to us.
It could be an image element, it could be a paragraph element, it could be something else we haven't
seen yet.
And that's kind of it for document get element by ID, so we call it on the document, we pass in some
ID string and if there's a match, we get that one element represented as an object.
If there's not a match, we get null.