Next up, we have another method on the document to select elements but slightly different.
It's called Get Elements by tag name.
And once again, it does what it sounds like rather than selecting by an ID we select by a type of element.
I want all the images or the paragraphs or the ones on a page.
So to use it, it's exactly the same.
We do document dot and then the name of the method.
So instead of get element by ID, we want get elements with an s by tag name.
And that S is significant because we will get more than one element or potentially we could, and that
means that the elements returned are going to be stored in a list.
We're not going to get a single element back like we got from get element by ID, so let's try it.
What do we have in our page?
We've got a couple of paragraphs, we have a couple of inputs.
Why don't we start with that?
Let's get all the inputs.
So I pass in the name of the element as a string and there we go.
I'm getting three inputs returned.
It looks like an array.
It is not an array, but we'll come back to that.
And if I look at each one of these elements once again, they are dom objects.
We have an HTML input element this time instead of a paragraph element or an image element.
If we try the same thing with a different type, like a P tag, we now get the different paragraphs
we have in our page.
So there we go.
We have two paragraphs, the first one and the second one, if I try it instead with what else do we
have a bunch of lies on the page I get three lies.
Each one is an object.
If I try it on an element that is not on the page like an H three, there are no H threes.
We get an empty collection back and if I instead try it on something where there's only one on the page
like h one, we have 1h1 on the page right here.
I still get a collection, it just has one element in it.
So we don't get we don't ever get one element back on its own like we did with get element by ID it
returned the actual object, not a collection, but because we're getting multiple potentially, we
always get a collection back.
Now let's talk about this collection.
What is this h HTML collection?
It is an array like object that is not an array.
So think of the arguments object that we saw a couple of sections ago instead of a function.
Every function has this arguments array like object.
That is not actually an array.
It's a similar idea here.
This is a collection of objects.
It's called an HTML collection.
It is something that it's a type in the DOM, it's a type of collection.
You get back frequently.
It is not an array, but we can do some array ish things.
So let's save one of these to a variable.
Let's select the inputs.
So I'll just go back to this line, save it to a variable cost inputs, and now I have my input variable.
Let's clear this and let's try accessing the first input.
That works.
We can use array indices and brackets, same syntax.
It looks like an array.
I can get the second element, the third element, and there is no element at index of three.
I can do input dot length and I do get a length.
But if I want to try using array methods like pop.
No luck.
Same thing with push with includes with index of.
We really don't have much at our disposal.
In fact, if we look at inputs and you just type dot in the dev tools.
Here's what we've got.
We've got length.
We've got a couple methods.
These actually come from objects and nothing else.
So what do we have here?
It's just a bare bones collection that allows us to access elements using indices.
And fortunately we can also iterate and that's it.
It's not supposed to be some useful data structure.
It's a very lightweight structure that stores elements.
So if you wanted to, you could turn it into an array.
You could also just iterate over it like this.
Let's do four lit inputs of inputs.
Why don't we just cancel that log input for now?
There you go.
We're printing out each input.
Remember, this is not what they look like.
They're actual objects.
I hate that the browser does this chrome devtools.
I don't understand who why.
It just doesn't seem that useful to me most of the time.
We want to look at the object, but maybe that's just because I'm a teacher and I need to show the objects.
Who knows?
All right.
So we can iterate over them.
And since it's an iterable, that means we can also use our friend spread.
So if I wanted to get these three inputs, the inputs HTML collection, it's not an array.
If I want to turn it into an array, I can spread it into an array.
If you skip the videos on spread, probably go back, check those out.
So now I'll just call this array equals inputs.
If we look at array, it's an actual array of those inputs.
But honestly, at the end of the day, a lot of the time what we end up doing is just looping over things
and doing some sort of or making some sort of change to each input or each element that could be adding
a style.
It could be reading its current value.
If this is a form a user clicks submit.
If we were using JavaScript, we could intercept the form and get the values out what a user had typed
in and then do something with them so we could select all inputs and then loop over the inputs and look
at input value.
We can actually try that right now if you want, we'll just do console.log input dot value.
And before I do that, why don't I put some values in here so bear name will go with Maxim must Maximus.
That's a good bear name.
I'll put a password in there just gibberish password and take a look.
We looped over all those inputs and I console that log input value that is a property on each input
element.
It has a value and I get Maximus from the first one as well from the second one.
And the third one is actually a button as well.
And that button does not have a value.
And if I look at inputs of two, that last one, it's that button type set to submit.
It does not have a value.
So that's just a is what it is.
We don't get a value.
Okay, so let's get elements by tag name.
Remember it returns this array like object.
It's not an actual array, but we can iterate over it.
Each element in that array like object is an element, it's an actual object and it has a bunch of properties.
We can do things with it.
And when we call document get elements by tag name, we passed in a string representing a tag name you
pass in an invalid tag.
You won't get anything, no error.
It's just not going to find anything with that type of tag name.
So we've seen get element by ID, we've seen get elements by tag name.
Next, we have another way of selecting.