Next up, a third way of selecting.
Not by ID, not by tag name, but by class name.
So we use a lot of classes traditionally in our markup so we can style them with CSS.
And if we want to select based off of those classes, we have a special method to do just that.
Document dot get elements.
It's plural again not singular like id get elements by class name.
And that s right there.
The plural sized s on elements tells us that we'll get a collection back, we'll get multiple elements,
or we could get one element, but it will be in a collection just like we had in the last video.
So what classes do I have?
I've got a class called Special on two Liz So I could use that and I think that's the only class I have.
Maybe I'll add something to my h one here.
Let's go with class equals header.
Okay.
And I will refresh my page to get that change.
Now if I run document get elements by class name of header.
We get that each one notice it's in an HTML collection.
Once again, another array imposter.
It looks like an array, but we don't get any of those array methods.
We could also select multiple.
So we have this class called special.
If we select using that class name.
We get two elements.
Each one, once again is an object, has a bunch of stuff in it, and if I select something that is
not found like the class name of chickens, nothing has that class name.
We get an empty collection if I try and select based off of an ID.
We had an ID called What Do We Have?
Main It's not going to work.
There's nothing with the class name of Main.
There's something with the idea of Main, different methods, different goals, and that's pretty much
it.
Get elements by class.
Name does what it sounds like.
It's very similar to get elements by tag name, except it uses a different criteria tag name versus
class name.
We can iterate over it using a for loop.
You could use a regular for loop a for of loop.
One last thing I'll show you.
It has to do with all of the methods we've seen so far is that you don't have to call them only on the
document.
If I had a very complex document, let's say, with like thousands and thousands of elements, if I
wanted to select one element and then further search within that one element, I could do that.
So here's an example.
Let's say I have the class of special somewhere else on my page.
Let's do it.
I don't know.
I'll just put it here.
I'll make a paragraph with the class of special and just put some stuff in there.
Refresh my page if I want to search for elements with the class of special.
If I do document, get elements by class, name special, I'm getting all three.
If I only want to get the element with that class inside of this UL, I can first select the UL so I
can do that with get elements by tag name, get element by tag name and I want UL that gives me a list.
So I'm going to take the first one from that collection and save it to a variable called UL.
So now I have this variable UL, which is an object and it has its own copy of Get Elements by class
name or tag name so I could search within this UL and pass in special.
And now I only get those two lies that have the class of special because I narrowed it down.
I narrowed my search first to the UL, I stored it in a variable and then I searched for special as
a class within that UL versus earlier.
I looked for all elements in the document with that class and I got three so I could mix it up and use
tag name again instead of the UL ul.
Get elements by tag name and then pass in ly and I get the same thing.
And now I get three elements because there are three lies.
I'm not using class, I'm looking for any lie in the UL.
One very important note here is that get element by ID does not work this way because IDs are supposed
to be unique across the entire document.
There should only be one element with whatever id bear photo.
There's no functionality to search within another element.
You don't need that.
You just search based off of the entire document.
So we don't have access to UL get element by ID, we only have well, a mistyped ID if I type get element,
you can see get elements by class name and by tag name.
We don't have ID.
All right.
So you can winnow it down like that.
You can find one element, save it to a variable search within that if you need to.
And that's it for these three basic ways of selecting get element by ID, get elements by class name,
get elements by tag name.
Next, we're going to see a whole new way of doing it, a little bit of an improvement, a nicer way
of selecting where you only need one method.