So we just saw three different methods that we can use to select elements.
But there's actually a fourth method that rules them all.
It's called query selector.
And I put an image of a Swiss Army knife here because query selector is like the Swiss Army knife of
DOM selectors.
It can select everything that we used.
It can replicate the functionality of all of these selectors here.
We can select by an ID or a tag name or a class name or many other criteria.
The way it works is that we pass in a CSS style selector so we can select a ID using CSS where we pass
in the hash symbol or a class, we use a dot.
We can select an element just by writing the name of the element, just like we do in CSS.
Over here in my stylesheet.
Where are you?
Here we are.
We're selecting by ID, we're selecting H one.
So we're selecting by class.
We can select by attribute.
We can do the same thing using query selector.
So query selector has not been a thing from the get go.
It hasn't been around as long as things like get element by ID, which is why the other ones exist because
this one is so much more versatile.
Query selector seems like it's all you would ever need and you can use it for everything.
It just hasn't been around as long, but it is supported in all the modern browsers, including Internet
Explorer.
It does work there, unlike a lot of other features that we wish would work.
And there are two versions of query selector.
What we're looking at here.
Query selector and also query selector all which does the same thing except it returns a collection
query selector.
This slide only returns a single element at most.
So let's try it out over here.
If we want to select the H one on the page, we could do document dot, query selector.
H one and we pass in the string h one and we get that h one right there.
If we wanted to select the paragraph, the first paragraph, we could do it this way.
But remember, it only gives us the first match and there are two paragraphs on this page.
So we only get the first one.
I could also select the first input and this is essentially replicating get elements by tag name.
Except we're getting the first match.
Remember that get elements by tag name gives us a array like list versus query selector.
Just gives us the first item, the first match.
But we can do more complex things we could select by an ID.
We have to use the hash sign in order to select an ID, just like we do when we're writing CSS.
So I have better photo I think if I can remember.
Yep.
That's our ID for the image here.
I also had a different ID.
What were you main?
We could select the second paragraph by using hash and then main.
So this is just like document get element by ID main.
But here we don't say it's an ID, we just pass in a string.
It's assumed it's an ID.
When we use query selector, we have to be more specific.
We pass in the CSS style selector.
So I'm getting the same paragraph now.
What does query selector actually return to us?
Why don't we save both of those to a variable?
So the first one I'll save to a variable called main one and then the second one where we use get element
by ID, I'll save to main two, I'll clear my screen and then let's do the annoying console.
Dear Main one.
Open it up.
It looks like an object.
It is an object.
It's an HTML paragraph element.
Let's do the same thing for main two.
It looks like an object.
Scroll down.
It is an object and it's also an HTML paragraph element.
All right, so they both give us the same thing.
In this case, it's just two different ways of selecting.
We can also select by class.
If I wanted to select these elements, I can only pick one, remember.
But this class is used in three different places.
It's called What is it special?
So I can do a document query selector.
Of the ID special where I need to use a period to signify it's an ID.
So that gives me the first match this paragraph here.
But because I can pass in a CSS selector, I can get more complex.
I can say the first lie with the class of special and this is just valid CSS.
So this is no new syntax, assuming that you have some experience with CSS.
And that's why I did that whole video about making sure you're cool with HTML CSS.
Anyway, let's go ahead and try something a little more complex.
I'll add in a second UL with a couple of allies, but instead of doing it just out in the open, inside
the body, all come down to the end and add in another UL.
But I'll put it inside of a section tag and then I'll have my UL and a couple of lines.
I'll do vegetables, I guess.
Carrots, peas and broccoli.
Broccoli is there to season that?
Yeah, I think so.
I don't know if I'm wrong.
I'm really sorry.
Okay, so you've got those in there.
Let's give peas the class of special as well.
So if I want to select this lie right here using query selector, I need to refresh my page and I want
to select that lie right there with query selector.
It's not going to work just by selecting the class of special because we're getting the first special
which is up here, and it's not going to work to say lie with the class of special because we have this
first one that has an ally or it is an ally with the class of special.
So how could I get more specific?
Well, this one is located inside of a section tag so I could do this.
This is valid CSS section, like special.
I could even get more specific.
It won't make a difference here, but it's also nested in a UL instead of a section.
So this is saying find me a list item with the class of special that is nested somewhere in a UL that
is itself nested somewhere in a section tag.
I mean, I could even do this if I really wanted to body and get extra specific.
So that's another variation of query selector.
That's just a valid CSS selector syntax.
We can also select based off of attributes.
So if I want to get this password input right now, if I do document that query selector of input,
you know what will happen.
We have multiple inputs.
We only get the first one which is right here type set to text.
If I want that second one, I can do input where type equals and then password.
So this is using the CSS attribute selector syntax.
And now I get that input and we saw this syntax a couple of videos ago with CSS.
We did the same thing.
It's the identical selector.
We just moved it into a JavaScript string and passed it into query selector.
So we're not styling anything using this, we're purely selecting.
All right, so we've seen that query selector is pretty powerful.
We can get a lot more specific.
We can even ignoring that, ignoring the fact that we can get more specific and detailed, we can use
query selector in place of all those other methods we saw.
And then we have query selector all which uses the exact same syntax, except it returns to us a collection.
So not just the first result.
So if I do document query selector of input, I get the first input.
If I do query selector all, I get all inputs that match and there's three of them.
If I did document query selector all dot, let's do the class of special.
We have four items.
The paragraph was special and then the three ls if I do lie.
We get six of them because there's six total lies on this page.
If I do something like the ID of did we have one called Main?
I think so.
This paragraph or this paragraph is the idea of Main.
We still get a collection just with one item in it.
Notice something kind of odd.
This result that we're getting back is a node list.
But when we do document dot, let's do get elements by tag name.
Elements by tag name of Liz.
We get an HTML collection here.
We got something called a node list.
So what is a node list?
It's another type of a collection.
You don't need to worry about it too much here.
But if we look at what the node list contains, this paragraph is still an HTML paragraph element.
It's just put in a different container from query selector all.
That's how it works.
A node list is another array like object, and if we play around with it, we can save it to a variable.
So let's get all of the which one should we do?
Let's save all of the special class elements to a variable.
We'll call it specials and I'll clear my console, make some more room.
So we have specials.
It is an array like object.
So I can do specials of zero.
I can do specials dot length.
And then if we do specials dot and then look at what else we have, there's really not much else, but
we do have four each.
So this was not available to us with a HTML collection.
It is available with a node list, but don't get bogged down.
Don't worry about it.
Honestly, it's not a big deal at this point.
I just wanted to highlight that there is a slight difference.
They're not the exact same type, but they're not the exact same collection that we get back or the
container is different.
Both of them are fake lightweight versions of a race.
So that is one difference when you use query selector.
And also another difference to know about query selector is that it is a little less performant.
It's really not a big deal for the stuff we're doing, but as you can imagine, depending on the selector
you pass it in.
It could have to do a lot of work compared to some of these older versions, like Get Element by ID
or get elements by tag name.
Generally those are a little bit more optimized or a little faster.
But I definitely, definitely would recommend you go with query selector and it's not a good enough
reason, it's not a good enough difference to not use or to avoid query selector.
All right.
So query selector, query selector, all very useful.
It's what I'll be using for most of the course here, because we can get more specific.
But also it's just nice to use one method and not have to worry about those other methods.
You pass in a CSS selector as a string and you get back either the first match if you're using query
selector or you get back a collection of all matches if you use query selector all.