Hey.
Welcome, everyone.
In this section, we're revisiting our good friend, the object.
So there's a lot more to talk about with objects than what we've seen so far.
Object Literals are useful to store key value pairs like we've been using them to store arrays or numbers
or strings or even other objects.
But there's much more to talk about with objects.
Objects are very central to JavaScript, not only in the code we write, but also to the way JavaScript
actually works behind the scenes.
So this section I'm calling the Secret Life of Objects, it's not really a secret in any way.
It's very well known stuff about objects.
So we have a couple of goals here.
We're going to cover a pretty diverse group of topics.
They are all united by the thread of objects.
They all have to do with objects in some way.
We'll start by talking about new syntax enhancements, nice little shorthand or shortcuts for common
things we do with objects.
So we'll start there.
Then we'll talk about methods.
How do we add methods to objects or how do we create methods?
We'll talk about prototypes.
And this last point here is an important one.
We'll talk about the keyword.
This the bane of many JavaScript learners existence, something that will spend a lot of time on in
the rest of the course.
We're not going to cover everything you need to know about it right now, but we'll get our first taste
of this and see how it works.
But we're going to start with a nice new syntax enhancement called Shorthand Properties.
Shorthand properties are a new addition to JavaScript with IS 2015.
They are not supported in Internet Explorer, but that shouldn't stop you from using them.
It's a nice, easy way to create an object literal when you have variables and you want to create a
property where the key name is the name of your variable and the value is the value in the variable.
So here I have a function called get stats which is passed in an array.
I need to just update this.
I just move this into a new function.
Okay, there we go.
So it passes in, we pass in an array and we calculate the max of the array, the min, the sum of every
element and the average.
So when I call it here, I'm passing in the reviews array representing Yelp reviews or something similar.
What I want it to do is return an object that contains all of these stats.
So something like this return max is set to Max.
The men property is set to the value of men.
Some is set to some.
And average is set to average.
So this works.
And this is how we had to do it until is 2015 with the shorthand syntax came along.
So if I run this right now and I take a look at stats, we do get an object back and it's what you expect.
We have the keys.
Some men, max an average and their values are set to the corresponding values from the variables.
But with this shorthand syntax, what we can do is write it like this return.
And then we simply write max, min, sum and average.
And this will create a key with the name of max, the value with the value of Max.
So we're taking variables that we have and using them to both set the key name and the corresponding
value.
If I refresh my page over here and I look at stats, we have the same exact output or the same return
It's just shorter.
We don't have to duplicate the key and the value it's done for us automatically.
So that's pretty much it for the shorthand syntax.
Here's an example from early on in the course when we covered functions, one of the exercises was to
build a get card function which returns an object.
I'll just call it over here containing a suit and a value.
This would be representing a single playing card, and the way that I wrote it was I have a pick function
that picks a random element from an array, and then I have my cards, the values and then the suits.
And I'm picking a value, saving it to a variable called value, picking a suit, saving it to a variable
called suit, and then returning an object where we have value set to value suit set to suit.
So we could just improve this very quickly by just doing this instead.
And if I save and run it one more time, it still works.
All right.
So a nice shortcut syntax.
Just remember, it doesn't work in Internet Explorer like almost everything else.
It's nice to use in JavaScript.