Next up, we have another nice new syntax addition to objects called computed properties.
So computed properties are just an improvement for the object literal syntax where we can add a property
with a dynamic key.
Right now, if we want to make an object with a dynamic key.
For example, if I want an object where I have the key set to the value of role, which is host, and
then the value for that key would be Jools Holland, the variable person.
If I make my object const, let's call this jobs or how about team?
If I tried to do a role and set that to person.
We've seen this before.
Early on, we'll just end up with the key of roll.
That's not what we want here.
If I look at team, we have roll set to Jools Holland.
So person is evaluated.
This is computed.
We get the variable value and that's stuck in the object.
But roll is turned into a string.
It's not checked.
If it's a variable, it's not computed.
So what we've done in the past in order to make this work, if we want a dynamic value for the key,
is to go back after we initialize the object.
Do square brackets team of roll equals person.
And now if we look at team, we have host set to Jools Holland and let's say I had one more concert
role two equals.
How about director?
I don't have the actual any person in mind, but we'll go with person two equals James Cameron.
Okay.
And if I wanted to add this in as a pair, I would need to then do team of role.
Two equals person to.
And now we have two properties with dynamic keys and we have to use these square brackets as we have
seen.
If you tried to use the dot notation, you're just adding the key of roll.
But now with this new syntax for computed properties, we can do this all at once.
We can define our object and then dynamically add in a key based off of some computed variable and expression.
The code will be evaluated.
First, we'll retrieve the variable value and use that as a key.
And this is what it looks like.
We use the same square brackets, but we wrap it around the key in our property definition in the object
literal.
So here a user will be evaluated.
First we get joules and that set to admin.
So if we try it over here, we would have role in those brackets set to person and then I could do a
second one role to set to.
Person to.
Let's take a look.
There we go.
The exact same object that we created up here.
But now we're doing it all at once.
All of our properties are in the object when we are defining it.
We're not having to do it after the fact.
We don't make an empty object and then add a property.
And the second property we can just do it all at once.
And that's kind of it for computed properties.
You could also put in more complex expressions in here.
For example, I could do one plus six plus nine and set that equal to how about 16?
If I evaluate this, take a look.
We have 16 set to 16, so this is going to be evaluated and then turned into a string like all the keys
we've seen and then used as the key in the object.
Here's one more example.
Let's make a function that accepts an object and we'll return a copy of that object with a new property
added in.
So we'll call this function add property or just add prop.
It will accept an object and then a key and a value.
And we want it to return a new object based off of this OBJ parameter with a key and a value pair added.
So without this computed properties new syntax, we would do something like this.
Make our copy of the object all use spread object.
That's an easy way to make a copy.
And then we would set copy of K equals V and then return copy.
And if I call this now, I'll use my team variable.
We would do add prop.
Of team.
Let's add in a new property.
We'll go with Happy and then the corresponding string will be a happy face.
So we have a key and a value.
We'll save this to a variable const rez.
Let's look at results.
Okay, so it works.
We ended up adding in happy as a key and a happy face.
The string as the value.
This is not using computed properties, so we had to make the object.
Then we had to go ahead and update adding a new property with the dynamic key and a value.
If we instead wanted to rewrite this using computed properties, we could do it on one line.
It would be an annoying one line, but we could do it on one line.
I'll do an arrow function this time.
So const add prop equals object key value and then we'll return a new object that contains everything
from OBJ.
We're spreading it in or copying it and using square brackets.
Compute the key and set it equal to the corresponding value.
So this does fit on one line.
But when I saved my editor it decides to auto format it to multiple lines.
You could also use an implicit return to even shorten it more, but let's just make sure it works.
Let's look at rez.
We get the same result.
So that's one use for a computed property.
When you are creating functions that either return objects or add things into objects, it's pretty
common that you might want to add a dynamic key in.
Now, just as a bonus here, we're done with the computer property stuff, but if we wanted to refactor
this to be a one line arrow function or at least an implicit return arrow function, remember that when
we return something implicitly, we don't need the return keyword and we don't need the curly braces
so we could write it like this and then just move it all into one line, except for the fact that JavaScript
will get confused because this looks like it's a function body.
It looks like the curly braces are for a function.
It doesn't know that we're trying to implicitly return an object.
If we had something like five here, this would implicitly return five.
But when we have an object, it gets confused.
So we do have to put parentheses around it and I'm pretty sure it's going to auto format to multiple
lines anyway, but this is valid on one line.
Okay.
So that's computed properties.
We use the exact same square bracket syntax that we've been using so far, but now we can use it directly
inside the object definition.