Next up, we have a really important topic in the world of objects, the idea that we can add functions
to our objects.
So we've seen that we can pass functions around, we can store them in variables, we can store them
in arrays, we can pass them as arguments, we can return them from a function.
We can also store them in objects.
Now, why we would do this is a bigger topic that we will get to in pieces.
The first, simplest reason we would do this is just to group functions together, to group functionality
into some sort of cohesive unit.
So here's an example.
We have a math object that contains different functions that have to do with one another.
So they're just grouped together and it's just a nice organizational structure.
So we call these methods when we add a function into an object, and we've been using the word method
quite a bit when we do things like Hello Dot to Uppercase.
This is a method and I mentioned this a couple of times earlier, when we define a function on our own
and restore it in a variable or just a function declaration const add equals, function x, comma y,
return x plus y.
This right here is a function right there.
But when we add it into an object and it lives on something and we call it with the dot notation, it
is now a method.
So these are built in methods.
But now we'll see how to add our own methods to objects.
It's very straightforward.
We already saw it on the slides.
One question you might have is I thought strings were not objects.
I thought they were primitives.
Aren't strings just a value?
How do they have methods?
That is something we'll get to in due time.
So we're going to put that aside for now.
But let's go ahead and define our object.
We'll call it math, and I'll show you a couple of different ways of adding functions in.
So right now I have a function called ADD.
I've used a function expression, saved it to the variable ADD.
I could just do this.
We saw this short hand a couple of videos ago.
I now have a object called math.
If I run my code over here, we look at math, the key is ad and the value is the function stored in
ad.
So we have ad is the key and then you can see a function right here.
If I want to call it, I need to use the dot notation, math, dot add and then pass into numbers.
Now, because of the way I wrote this, I also could just call, add and pass in values to five.
I'm calling this function from here versus if I do math ad where referencing the same function it's
the same variable or the same function in memory, but I'm accessing it in a different way.
So it's pretty uncommon to define your function first and then add it into an object.
Normally you would do something like this add colon function and then add our arguments and put our
function expression right here.
So we'll just return X plus Y.
And if we want another property, if we want to do multiply, we can add another function at our arguments,
X or our parameters X and Y, and then we can return x times Y.
So now I have two properties, both of which are functions.
I can still add in non functions.
I can add whatever I want to the object.
I could do numbers and that could be an array.
One, two, three, four, five.
If I run this code, we look at math, we now have two functions in here add, multiply and numbers
which is an array and I use the exact same syntax.
Math numbers is how I access that array.
Math add is how I access that function, but I'm not executing it until I add the parent five and six.
Same thing with multiply multiply with no parent gives me a reference to the function I'm getting the
function if that makes sense.
I'm asking JavaScript, does this thing exist?
Tell me about it.
Now I'm saying I know it exists, let's run it and we get 42 when I multiply six and seven.
So again, right now this is just a nice way of grouping functions together, putting them in an object
so that they're just in some sort of container rather than having a bunch of functions floating around.
I now have this math object, which is the same idea as the existing math that we have in JavaScript.
We've seen a couple of these methods math random.
It's grouped inside of math.
Instead of just having a floating random function, we call we have a math object that contains a bunch
of different functions or technically methods.
So the terminology one more time we have functions which we've seen on our own, but when we add a function
as a property in an object, we call it a method.
So these are two methods.
Well, students see some additional things we can do instead of methods, some new constructs or new
features.
The keyword.
This will come up very soon in this section, which will make these methods more useful or more flexible.
Right now, it's just purely a container.
This object just stores, functions and groups them together so that we can carry them around just like
a purse for all of our belongings.
Next, I'm going to show you a new syntax that makes it a little shorter to define methods.
And then we'll go on and talk about the keyword this.