So that's the basics of adding a method to a object.
It's just a key value pair.
The function is the value.
Now, I didn't show this.
You can use an arrow function.
It's not that common for reasons you'll see in just a moment once we talk about the keyword this.
But in addition, there is a nice new shorthand for adding a method to an object where we don't have
to use the key value pair syntax, where we have a key colon and then a function.
Instead we can write a function like this.
So we give it a name and this name will be used to create the key.
We still need our commas to separate the properties, but now we don't have to do the key colon value.
So this is a newer syntax.
If we want to try it out, we'll make an object here called Auth and we'll have some dummy functions
like log in and log in.
We'll simply console that log logged you in like that.
All right.
So nothing very extravagant, but we have a function in here and it's actually a method.
If we look at Auth, this is what it turned into.
We have log in as the key and then the function that corresponds to it as the value.
So it uses this to create the key.
And again, we do need commas if we have more than one property in here.
So instead of auth if I wanted to add username is Tommy boy Tommy.
But sure we need a comma and it still works.
We now have two properties to add another method in.
Same thing.
I need my comma here and then we can go with log out and we'll cancel that log.
Goodbye.
Now we'll take a look at Auth one more time.
And we have three properties.
If we leave that comma out, it's not happy with us.
It doesn't know what to do.
We are in an object.
Even if we're using this nice shorthand, we still need to separate all properties by commas.
And that's kind of it.
It's a nice shorthand.
It is new, so it's not something that you may see all the time in older tutorials, but it's here for
a reason.
We do this so often we add properties to an object.
This is just cleaner.
We don't have to write this log in key colon and then a function expression.
We don't have to clutter our code with the function keyword or if we use an arrow function we still
would be cluttering this.
Just show you that we can do an arrow function.
We still are cluttering our code here with the login key, the colon.
Just additional here.
It's a lot shorter.
Okay.
And that's it.
Next, we've got a big one.
We're going to talk about the keyword, this really fundamental thing in JavaScript that helps us write
much more useful methods in our objects.