Next up, we'll see one of the keys to writing useful methods in our objects.
It's called the keyword.
This now the keyword.
This is also pretty useful.
It comes up a lot.
Once we get to Dom manipulation, which is right around the corner, when we do things like add events,
click events and keyboard events will sometimes reference the keyword this and you probably come across
it if you've ever attempted to learn JavaScript.
It's a concept that How should I put this?
It can be a major point of confusion and misery and hardship in general, suffering in the life of a
new JavaScript developer.
At least that's the perception a lot of people have.
There are courage posters like this one.
One of the most courageous decisions he'll ever make is to try and learn the JavaScript keyword this.
Well, actually, I just made this slide myself.
But the point is, a lot of people have this perception of this being this terrifying, confusing thing
when in reality it's not that bad.
What is tricky about the keyword this is that the value of it is sometimes it seems unpredictable.
It seems like you expect it to do one thing and it behaves a different way.
But there's a set of concrete rules that dictate what the value of this is.
At this point, we haven't even talked about what this is.
What's the point?
So this is a keyword.
Think of it as a reference to the current execution scope.
It is going to give you an object back.
So depending on the scope and depending on the rules of how this works, which is the confusing part,
that object changes.
It could be a reference to the global scope, which is what we're going to see right now.
If we type a function, let's call it, say hi console.log, something in here high and then let's also
console.log the value of this.
Remember, we'll get an object here when we console.log it.
This is an object and it refers to the current execution scope.
So if I run my code here, I call, say hi, we get high and then we see an object called the window.
So what is the window?
The window is the global scope in the browser.
We've been working with it stealthily or it's been stealthily looming over us this whole time.
When we define a function like say hi, it looks like it's floating on its own in the middle of nowhere.
We didn't put it in an object.
It's not a method like we called earlier.
We had math had that was a method or lowercase math.
In our case, say hi.
Looks like it's just floating in the middle of nowhere.
But if we look at this window object scroll all the way down here to the se okay.
Lots and lots of methods.
Take a look that say hi.
So when we define say hi like this, it is added as a property.
It is a method on the window object.
The window is the global scope of our browser.
If I type window at any point in my console, we'll get the same thing.
So this inside of a function, just a regular function normally refers to the window, at least in the
browser.
In Node it refers to something else.
But there is a global object.
It's not called the window, but there's a global object in Node.
But remember that this can change.
It's a bit of a shape shifter, so it does depend on how it is called.
So I don't want you to leave thinking that any time you write this in a function it refers to the window.
But in this function, the way that we executed it, it does refer to the window.
And just to talk more about the window for a moment here, the window contains all sorts of different
properties.
We've been using different methods, things like alert, if we call alert.
We get our alert in the browser.
It's a built in function and we call it like this, but it's a property on the window.
So I could also call it like this window alert something.
And I still get the same result.
Another very important thing about the window.
When we declare a variable with var, I'll go with var color equals teal.
That color or that variable color is added to the window.
If I look at window again and I find color on here, there you go.
It's added to the global scope.
It's added to the window.
So another way of referencing it.
Oh, my gosh, I regret this decision to scroll here.
Another way of referencing it is window color, but that does not apply for LUT in concert.
We'll just do one.
Let's use lut let num equals 400.
If I try and access window num, it's not there.
So let in const are not added to the global scope.
They're not added to the window object in the browser while var is.
So none of that really matters at this point.
We're still just talking about functions.
The value of this inside of a regular old function.
You haven't put on an object, just a function we've defined like this one.
It could also be a function expression const how about greet equals function?
And then f we don't need any arguments.
We'll just console.log this.
So we're not even greeting.
It's a lie, but we'll just console.log this.
If I clear my console over here.
Refresh the page I call greet.
This is still the window.
So in a function, this is going to refer to the window, except when it doesn't.
And that's coming up next.
So just remember that this is a reference to an object and that object represents the current execution
scope.
So this seems like it might not be that useful here.
And yeah, it probably isn't that useful to reference the window because we could also just explicitly
write window if we wanted to print the window or do something with it.
But what we'll see in the next video is where this is extremely useful when we're working with methods
in an object.
So if you're confused, if you're feeling like you need that courage from this slide right here, if
you're feeling like this skull down here, you need a bit more courage.
Just hang in there.
It will start to make sense as we see the other pieces.