Next up, we'll see where this starts to become a lot more useful.
If we have an object like a person object where we have a first name.
How about share?
What does shares full name?
Well, thanks to Wikipedia I have it Sherilyn Sarkeesian.
So we'll make first name.
Sherilyn will make last Sarkeesian.
And let's also add in a nickname.
Let's do a nickname, camel case it, which will be share.
All right, so we have this object.
If I add a method to the object, let's do something simple.
Like greets or how about full name?
Let's do a method called full name.
We can use the shorthand that we saw a couple videos ago.
Or I could do it this way.
I'll do the shorthand though I think it's nicer.
And inside of this method let's console.log the keyword this to start and now let's run it.
So person dot full name execute it.
What do we get?
Okay, so this time it is not constant logging the window, it's constant logging something else.
Compare that to say hi, which is a function not in an object.
We got the window object, the global execution context, the global scope.
The window is what this is right here versus here.
The value of this is different.
The value of this is the object itself, the person object right here.
So the value of this has been set to a different object, not the window, but the object that this
method is inside of.
Now, why is this useful?
In the next video we'll see that this is not always the case, and depending on how you call full name,
it could reference the window.
But we're going to put that aside for now.
Let's talk about why this would be useful.
Why do you care about the current object that you are inside of?
It allows us to reference these properties or other methods so we can have a method that is aware of
the other contents in its object.
So for full name, if I wanted to print out first name and last name together, I could reference this
dot first.
Let's start there.
Refresh my page.
I'll call person full name and we're getting Sherrilyn.
So this again, is a reference to the object.
First, we'll give me this value.
So I could now update this to instead console.log.
How about first?
So this dot first.
Space.
And then afterwards, this last.
And then if I wanted to use the nickname, let's just start here.
Make sure it works.
Refresh my page.
Try again.
Sherilyn Sarkeesian.
And then afterwards, let's do a.k.a..
This nickname.
Try it again.
Now, this is a good opportunity for us to use the structuring.
We're having to write this quite a bit.
I could add a separate line and D structure those properties from this first last nickname.
If two camel case nickname equals this.
Now I can remove this from here and here.
It should still work.
Let's verify.
Oh.
Did I not save?
Here we go.
This needs to be uppercase.
One more time.
Now we get Sherilyn Sarkeesian, aka Cher.
And if I change one of those values in person, let's go with nickname.
Person.
Nickname equals Cher with a bunch of R's in all caps.
So now person has a new nickname.
If I call full name again.
That change is reflected.
It's looking up the value of nickname on the current execution scope, which is what this refers to.
And it's set to this object.
So now we have the ability to write an object or a method that is aware of the object it lives in,
which means we can use objects not just to store different methods because they're related like we had.
Add and subtract and multiply and divide.
We group them together as a nice way of of just making a little container for our methods that are similar.
But now we have a way of also interacting with properties with other values or even other methods.
So our object can now be a little self contained world where we can have variables, we can have these
properties.
And this is a very simple example, but I'll show you some other examples as we go on.
We have a little more to talk about with the keyword this in the next video, but then we're just going
to see a bunch of examples of using this in methods and you'll be able to see hopefully why it is a
really, really nice tool to have, why you would want to do this.
So let me show you one more example here with the same object, we could also add another method to
the object and call a different method using this.
So we have full name.
Let's make let's make a method called bio, print, bio.
And what I want it to do is get the full name from full name.
So we'll call this method and then print something else we'll do.
Like Sherilyn Sarkeesian, aka Cher is a person that will be the bio.
So I'm going to change this to return instead of console.log.
So we now return that string and then instead of print bio, I can call this full name.
I just have to use this.
If I just called full name, it would not work.
We need this.
If I tried it.
If I call print bio person, print bio.
Reference error.
Full name is not defined, so we have to use this to reference the object.
I'm going to save that to a variable.
We'll call it full name.
Then I will console.log from here.
Just put.
Let's do a template string.
Put full name in there and then is a person and that's the entire bio.
So we'll try running it again.
And now we get Sherilyn Sarkeesian a.k.a there is a person, so we called a method that is located within
the same object using this.
In that method we actually accessed three different properties first last a nickname using this using
D structuring to make it cleaner.
But we're still referencing this.
The value of this in both of these situations here, both methods is referring to the object that they
live in.
And that's a great tool.
It's a great thing to be able to reference.
And you'll see a couple of examples, as I mentioned, as we finish up this section.
But of course, there's a bit of a twist here in the next video.
You'll see that sometimes this may not refer to the object, it could refer to something else.