All right.
So we've seen two different values for this so far.
We saw that when we declared just a regular old function.
We don't call it as a method.
We don't put it in an object.
This refers to the window object.
When we use this instead of a method, it's a way of accessing the parent object, the object that the
method is located in.
Like we used right here with this share object.
But that's not always the case.
The value of this depends on the invocation context of the function that it's used in.
What that means is the value will change depending on how the function is actually executed, not just
where you write it.
So yes, I wrote this inside of a method, but that doesn't mean it's guaranteed to reference this object.
It depends on how I'm calling it.
And here I'm calling it how you normally would call a method.
The natural way to call this would be person, print, bio or person's full name.
This is what is setting the value of this, the way that I'm actually executing or invoking this function.
So this is kind of a shapeshifter in this way.
That's why I have these different faces down here.
It's tough to come up with a good visual representation of it, but let me show you how we could actually
change the value of this.
What I could do is make a reference to this function print bio.
Let's work with that one.
I'll call this concept print.
Bio equals person.
Dot, print, bio.
So I'm just pointing this variable print bio to that function.
It's still a property on the person object.
I didn't remove it, I didn't delete it.
I just made a variable pointing to it.
And if I call print bio.
Oh, I got to refresh the code.
Let's try it again.
We get a different error.
This full name is not a function.
So why don't we add a console.log this at the end and see what's going on.
So if I call print bio again, this full name is not a function.
Well, I'm an idiot.
I'm concerned that logging after that error.
Let's do it before the error.
Okay.
Here we go.
It's referencing the window.
Just like we had up here.
If I call, say hi.
It references the window.
And that's because of how I'm executing the function.
If I instead execute it the way we've been doing.
Person What do we call it?
Print bio.
The name of this method right there.
This is referring to the object so you can think of it as if there is something to the left and then
a dot and then you're executing the function.
This will be set to that thing, to the left.
If there's nothing to the left, if we're just calling, say hi, or if we're just calling print bio.
This will be set to the global execution scope, the window.
So this is the confusing part of this.
It's not set in stone.
You probably won't call your method this way.
It's not something you would do all the time, but it's important to understand how it behaves.
There is a very significant difference.
So generally when you write this in a method, you're going to call it using the dot syntax, you're
going to call object, method, name, person, print, bio.
Everything will be great.
Everyone's happy.
This refers to the object itself, the parent object that contains the method, but that doesn't mean
it always is set to that value.
It depends on the invocation context, how you actually execute that function, the line that you write
that runs the code or that runs the function.
Later on in the course, we'll see that there are some additional rules in some ways of changing the
value of this.
There are three special methods that are usually grouped together call, apply and bind.
Those will come up later.
We'll talk about classes and prototypes and creating new objects.
That all has to do with the keyword.
This as well.
So right now, this is just a quick introduction.
I want you to be aware of how this works in two of the most common scenarios.
And then there's one more thing to talk about, which is arrow functions.
When we write an arrow function, this is one of the key differences between a regular function and
an arrow function.
Arrow functions do not get their own version of this.
It doesn't matter how you call an arrow function.
If you execute it as a method where you call object dot name of the function, or if you just call the
function directly, the value of this is not going to be changed.
So in that way they are very different from a traditional function.
And I'll show this very quickly.
Let's just make a function called, geez, this is the hardest part of teaching anything.
Coming up with examples, we have full name, print, bio.
How about laugh?
Okay, so we'll define our function, which will be an arrow function as a method.
I'll use this key syntax, key value.
But the colon in there and inside of this I'm going to console.log this and for laugh let's console.log
this dot let's do a template literal let's put this dot nickname says ha ha ha ha.
Okay, so we have this laugh method.
If I try and call laugh person laugh.
Okay.
First of all, the value of this is set to the window, which is very different than the value of this
in print, bio or in full name.
As we saw when we call print bio, this is set to the object, the person object.
An arrow function does not behave that way.
The value of this does not change in the arrow function.
It's a reference to the global scope to the window.
So sometimes that can be a good thing.
But generally this is why we don't use arrow functions as methods, because a lot of the methods we
write, we want to have access to the parent object or the containing object to do things like reference
properties or call a different method like we did inside of print bio.
We called this full name in an arrow function.
We couldn't do that, at least not until we see things like bind.
So for that reason, we usually don't use arrow functions as methods in an object.
But there's a reason that arrow functions don't get their own.
This if you only use regular standard traditional functions like this.
So annoying.
Like this one right here.
There.
Hopefully that's clearer.
Like this one right here.
Sometimes you can run into issues and I'll show you an example of where that can happen in the very
next video.
So to summarize what we saw here, the value of this is set by the invocation context.
It's not set in stone purely based off of where you write it.
In this case, we put it in an object instead of a function.
Instead of an object, we reference this and when we called it as a method person print PIO, this was
set to the entire object, the parent object versus when we made a reference to that same function and
instead called it just as a regular function without something to the left, without object dot something,
just print bio.
This was referring to the window.
So the execution context matters.
The way that you actually invoke it does matter.
And then the second thing we saw was that arrow functions don't get their own this.
And in the next video I'll expand on how that sometimes can be useful.