Next up, I'd like to expand upon arrow functions and this.
Why do Arrow functions not get their own this and how can it be useful sometimes?
So we're going to make a little example.
I'm calling it the annoying matic or the annoying or annoying Tron.
It's going to have a list of annoying phrases.
These phrases, these drive me insane.
Literally cray cray I can't even totes yolo and can't stop, won't stop.
They don't drive me insane.
That's a bit over the top, but I'm not a fan of these phrases, so we're going to make this little
annoying to that.
Every second, every 2 seconds, every 500 milliseconds prints one of these random phrases to the console,
and we just fill up the entire console with a bunch of annoying phrases.
And the way we're going to structure it is by using an object.
So I'm going to make an object here.
I'll call it a Noyer and I'm going to add this array and you could put whatever array you want in there
if you like some of these phrases.
I am very sorry if I'm offending you here, please pick your own phrases.
I'm sure you can find a good number of annoying phrases to draw upon just from my own courses.
I say at the end of the day, pretty much every video, no matter what time of day it is, or essentially
basically, oh gosh, I can't listen to my own videos.
Okay, so I'm going to add phrases as a key here into my object and then I'm going to add a method.
The idea is that I'll have a method called Start and another one called Stop, and I want to be able
to call another dot start and that will start printing one of these every second and I can call, annoy
or stop to stop it.
So to do this, we'll take advantage of a built in function called set interval.
Set interval is a global it's located on the window.
If we look at the window, it comes in your browser for free.
If we scroll way down all the way down to SE, where are you set interval right there.
So it's a function we call it, and we have to pass in a couple of things set interval.
We need to give it a func to run and a time or the interval.
So for us we'll start something.
We'll start with something easy, like 3000 milliseconds.
So whatever function I put here will run every 3 seconds.
So I'm going to delete that and instead add a method called start.
So after my phrases I'll add a method called Start.
I need a comma here.
Which will be a function.
And then actually I'll use a shorthand, get rid of the function keyword.
That's nicer.
I'm also going to add a method called pick or choose phrase or something so that we can easily get one
of these.
So I'll define that first.
How about just pick phrase?
And and here I'm going to reference this dot phrases which we've seen that works as long as I'm calling
this as a noise or pick phrase or something, dot pick phrase, I just don't want to be calling it as
a non method.
So this dot phrases will be the phrases, that's the entire array.
To pick one randomly, what I need to do is get the length of this array.
I'm going to need to do a math.
Random.
Multiply that by this phrase length and I'll probably make this its own variable.
Const phrases equals this dot phrases or d structure it const phrases equals this.
So math, random times phrases length.
And then I need to floor that.
So math dot floor.
And then I'll call this concert index.
So that gives me a random index from this array.
If we add two more to phrases, this will reflect to update that when I call phrases or pick phrase,
this dot phrases will reference the current version of phrases.
Okay, so that gives me that.
But then I need to access it out of phrases using that index and I'll return that.
So I used restructuring here just so I didn't have to reference this phrase, this length and this dot
phrases of index.
Maybe it's overkill, but we also just learned restructuring, so it's always good to get some reinforcement
there.
If I run this code right now, oh my gosh, I'm going to clear my console if it will stop lagging the
window.
Object made it very unhappy.
All right.
It should be back to normal.
Refresh my code.
Another dot pick phrase we got yolo and then cray cray.
I can't even YOLO.
Literally, I can't even totes.
Okay, so we're getting a random element each time.
Can't stop, won't stop.
Great.
I will stop.
What we're going to do now is call pick phrases instead of start using set interval.
So remember set interval takes two arguments.
The thing that we want it to call.
So I'll just write an anonymous function here and I'll start by just console logging some random letters.
And then the second argument is how often I want it to repeat, we'll do 3000 milliseconds.
So right now we're not using pick phrase.
I'm just constantly logging some gibberish.
And if I execute a newer dot start.
Wait 3 seconds.
Come on.
There we go.
We got our first one.
Three more seconds.
We get our second one, three more seconds, we get the third one.
But what I want to do is console that log pick phrase.
Now, this is where the keyword this comes in because we know instead of a method start, I can use
this to refer to the object so I could call this pick phrase.
So if we just tried it once up top here in the method console.log this pick phrase.
And I run this annoying start we get literally, and that works.
And then the set interval kicks in.
But if I want to call this code, this function instead of constant logging, I will do the exact same
thing console.log this pick phrase.
But if I move it in this function, everything changes.
The first one works because it's up top, but then we get an error.
This stop pick phrase is not a function.
So why is this different?
We're inside of this function.
Why is it not working?
Well, let's look at this.
What do you think the value of this is right here?
One more time, annoy your start.
Cray cray.
That's coming from line 11.
And then this is set to the window.
So why is this right here?
Set to the object.
But inside another function, it's set to the window.
Remember, this change is depending on how it's called.
Now we're executing.
Start ourselves as an object or as a method.
We're doing this annoy or start, but this function is being executed not by us, but by set interval.
It source code calls this function every 3 seconds or whatever number we have here, so we're not calling
it.
And that means that this, because of the way it's called, is set to be the window object.
Just like if we had a random function and we called this, we'd done this a couple of times in the past
few videos.
If we don't execute it as a method on an object, this is set to the global scope to the window.
So all of this has been set up to talk about arrow functions in the past.
Before, error functions were a thing.
If we wanted to make this work, if I want to have a reference to the object, the version of this we
have right here, I want to be able to call this dot pick phrase in this function, the nested function.
What some people would do is make a variable and store it.
You'd see things like const that equals this.
So we have a reference to this, which is the object.
And if I console.log that and I call a start, we'll still get an error because we're doing this stop
pick phrase.
But that is a reference to the previous this from the level above from the start function.
So this is not ideal writing it this way.
Also, they wouldn't have used cost because it wasn't a thing.
You would have seen var still not a great approach.
Once we talk about bind, call and apply, there are other ways of getting this to work.
But now that we have arrow functions, it's actually easier if we instead use an arrow function here.
We avoid the problem entirely.
Remember that arrow functions don't get their own.
This the this in an arrow function won't change from the this of its parent or of its nearest this the
local execution context that we have up here.
This has a value.
We've already seen it.
If I type this right here, it's referencing the object because I'm not using an arrow function.
I'm getting a new this.
But if I turn this into an arrow function instead like that, now we have no problem.
It shouldn't be an issue.
This is going to be the same in this arrow function because arrow functions don't get their own special
this.
That means it just relies on the this we have from start.
Let's make sure we'll run it and come on.
I can't even.
And 3 seconds later, can't stop.
Won't stop.
Oh, so annoying.
Who built this thing?
Cray cray.
And literally it's working.
So that's really what I want to focus on in this video is showing you that sometimes arrow functions
are better to use because you don't want a new this.
But the other side of that coin is that they suck as regular methods on an object because you don't
get access to the this referencing the object you're this references the window.
So that's nice in a situation like we have here because we will use the this from start but it's not
nice.
If I had tried to write start as an arrow function instead of a regular function expression.
Now, one other thing that's just not related to this.
This interval is going on and on and on.
It will keep going until I refresh the page or close the window.
It's best practice to provide a way to stop that interval, to stop something from repeating over and
over, not to mention the fact that it's incredibly annoying whoever built this evil piece of code.
What we can do is save the return value from set interval.
Set interval will return a ID and there's another function we can call called stop interval or no clear
interval, which will stop the interval from running.
So how could I do this if I wanted to have a stop method?
I want to call clear interval, but I need to pass in an ID, but I'm getting the ID from here.
This is going to return it if I just make a variable like const id equals set interval.
I have no access to ID over here.
What I can do is add it to this this dot timer ID, let's call it that equals set interval.
Let's take a look at what happens now if we inspect a neuer.
Open this up.
Well, I haven't executed.
I haven't called start, so I need to run that.
But now if we look at a neuer, we do have a timer ID that wasn't there before, but the code ran,
start was executed.
This is set to the object.
So this timer ID added a new property called timer ID just like we had done this.
Except the ID is not hardcoded as one.
If we have multiple timers, we have different IDs.
So to stop it, my method called stop would just call clear interval.
This dot timer ID.
So set interval, clear interval.
That's not really the focus of this video.
If you're struggling with the syntax, it's more about this and error functions and context and all
that fun stuff.
Let's add a quick console.log at the end.
Phew.
Thank heavens that is over.
Okay, so I'm going to run my code.
I'll do another dot start.
And eventually I will stop it.
I won't run it yet.
We'll get a few of them.
One more, one more other than cray cray and it stops iterating or it stops interval.
I don't think that's the right terminology, but it's not printing out those annoying phrases anymore.
All right.
So kind of an obscure demo, but hopefully this illustrates that sometimes arrow functions are great
to use because of the very fact that they don't get their own this.
So what seems like potentially a shortcoming and what is a shortcoming when it comes to defining methods
is an advantage when you have to deal with nested functions and callbacks and different execution contexts
where this gets really annoying.
Use an arrow function and you don't have to worry about it because this will be identical to the this
of the parent function of start in our case.
Oh, this is just just a joy to teach.
Hopefully you're still there, you're still alive, you're surviving.
And you're with me.
Next, we're going to see some examples of using this in methods.
And we'll talk more about why you would even bother creating methods, why organize our functions like
this?
We could have just written a function called Start and Stop.
We could have had a global variable called phrases.
So we'll talk about that in the next video.