In this video, I won't be covering any new syntax or features that we haven't seen.
I just want to give us some practice and a little bit of time to talk about objects, methods, designing
our code, why we might want to use objects with methods and comparing that to different approaches
that we've already seen so early in the course when we were talking about functions, we had a functions
exercise where I asked you to make a function called it was something like Make Deck, and I wanted
it to return a deck of cards, which was an array, and each element had a value like value of five
and then a suit of hearts or diamonds or something.
So five of hearts.
But the deck would have 52 of these each different, right?
We'd have five of hearts, five of diamonds, five of clubs and spades, and then six and seven and
jack all those different cards.
So that's the idea.
And we can totally use a function to do that just as stand alone function.
But what if I wanted to also have different features, different functionality for my deck instead of
just making a deck of cards?
What if I wanted to be able to draw a single card at a time?
Or maybe I want to have a discard pile?
Once we draw a card, we could put it in the discard pile so our deck would be shrinking, but then
we would have the discard pile that was keeping all of the previously drawn cards.
Or I could implement a shuffle so that we could shuffle the deck.
Or what if I wanted to refill the deck, start over from scratch.
There are so many different things we could do.
We could make a draw method that could take an argument like draw five, draw to draw one and to design
that to actually implement it.
We could start with a pure function approach.
So I could have my make deck function, which I need to actually call a function.
And then I would loop over these two variables that I've created already to save some time.
Here I have suits, which is an array and values which I made a string instead of an array only to save
a little bit of time, because typing this as an array is really annoying, having to do one and then
two and put quotes around everything.
And I did separate them by commas because that allows me if I come over here to do values, split on
the comma.
And get an array with the actual values.
The reason I had to do commas instead of just doing one, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight, nine.
Jack Queen.
King, is this little guy right here?
Ten.
If I were to iterate over this string, I would get each character one at a time.
And that works.
All of these values are a single character long except for ten.
So if I were to split, if I had ten in here, or if I were to iterate over this, it would do one and
zero.
I wouldn't actually get ten.
So that's why I used a string with commas.
But I'm going to start by looping over suits.
My goal is to return an object that has a suit set to one of these suits and a value set to one of these
suits and make them all unique.
So we have a combination of every possible.
We have an instance of every possible combination.
So for let value of and then I'm going to do values split on the comma.
So that gives me this array here.
So for every item in that array, we'll also loop over suits for suit of suits.
And then I'm going to create a deck array up here, const deck.
We'll start empty and then in here I will call deck, push and I'll push on a new object where we have
value set to value and suit set to suit coming from these loops.
But as we just saw very, very recently, we have a shorthand way of doing this.
If we want the key name to be value and we have a variable called value, I can just put value and suit.
All right, so let's return this deck.
Return deck, run my code.
Make deck.
Oop.
Forgot my friends and we're getting 56.
What did I mess up here?
Well, that was stupid.
I put Ace and one.
There is no one card.
So let's run it one more time.
Hopefully you saw that before me.
Now we have 52 cards, so we have this function.
Still no objects or methods involved.
I guess we do have this object that we're creating.
But no methods.
No this.
None of the stuff we've been talking about.
If I wanted to create a deck and then be able to draw a single card, I would need to save this deck
to a variable.
So make a new deck.
We'll go with const.
My deck equals make deck and then I need to make a new function called draw card.
And I would need to pass in the card excuse me, the pass in the deck as an argument and then we draw
the card so we could do.
Let's pop from the end, I guess.
Or we could take it from the beginning.
Either one works, but let's just pop one off.
So deck, dot, pop.
And if we try it over here, make dot pop, remember that pop returns the value and it also changes
the original array so I can simply return decked out pop.
Okay.
So in order to draw a single card, I make the deck, and then I need to call draw card and pass in
my deck because we need an argument here.
So then I would save that return result to const card.
One equals draw card.
And if I run it.
I take a look at card one?
We got the ace of clubs.
We haven't shuffled our cards at all, so they're all in order.
And then if we look at my deck, it should now be 51 items.
So then to draw a card again, I have to do draw card, pass in my deck.
And this is not great.
I have to keep passing this around.
I'm passing my deck into draw card over and over and over.
And if I were to have a shuffle function or a refilled deck or draw five, I would need to keep passing
my deck.
I guess the alternative would be to use global variables and make a variable up top called my deck cost.
My deck equals make deck and then inside of all of the functions we write, we could refer to my deck
specifically, but that's even worse because then we end up with just one deck.
I could do this concept.
Main deck equals make deck.
And then I would down here rewrite draw card to just return main deck dot pop.
But you can imagine that this is severely limited.
We can only have one deck, main deck.
How would I make deck two or a second deck or a fifth deck?
I would have to write a new function that didn't depend on it.
I would write a new one where I hardcoded in second deck.
So that's not a good approach.
So the best option for now is to keep passing them around, pass the deck in so that we can make draw
card somewhat modular.
Now this is where objects come in because I can use an object to store the deck and on that object I
can have a method called draw card and another one called Shuffle.
And we have access to the deck because of this, the key word, this.
So here is how I would rewrite that.
I would do something like concept deck or my deck or whatever equals an object.
And then I would have the property instead of calling this deck, let's go with my deck and then make
our property deck, which can start as an empty array.
Then we'll have a new method that will add in called make deck or refill cards or something.
What should we call it?
Initialize cards.
Initialize deck.
Sure.
And it is going to update the deck property.
So we're grouping the data with functionality.
So let's just copy most of this logic over.
Just move this over.
And it's not going to work right away.
We need to change a couple of things.
The first thing I might do is move these variables into properties on the object because we might want
them in other methods.
We don't need to re declare them every time we call initialize deck.
So I'm going to just copy this out or cut it out, make a property called suit and then another one
called Values.
And move that.
We'll get rid of that right there and then we can import them.
We're not actually importing, but we can use them in here because of this.
So this dot suits, this dot values.
We could also just use D structuring.
So cost suits, comma values equals this and let's also grab deck.
So now every time I reference deck, it's actually this deck values is this dot values.
I've just d structured them.
What do I have going on here?
Missing a comma.
There we go.
Okay, so I have those values now.
So for the value of values dot split.
That's right.
We get an array for each value.
We're also going to iterate over all the suits.
All four.
And now I can leave this as dot push instead of having to do this deck because we structured it up here.
Where are you?
Right there.
And then we can return the deck if we want.
But also we don't have to.
We're not going to lose that deck versus here.
We had to return the deck and save it to a variable.
Otherwise we're just making this array and then it disappears when the function is over.
But in our object we're actually changing the property of deck.
We're adding to this array.
So even if I don't return deck, it still should work.
Assuming I didn't mess something up when I copied it over.
Let's see what happens now.
I have this my deck, which is an object.
It starts with an empty array.
But if I call my deck dot initialized deck, kind of a long name.
Let's look at my deck now.
Or how about just my deck, dot deck?
We have 52 cards, so we successfully implemented this method that is updating the deck property.
And now if I wanted to implement a draw method, it's very easy.
I'll just add my comment in draw card.
And why don't we make this a little bit more exciting?
Well, we'll start with draw a single card.
So draw card and we'll access this dot deck and then we'll pop one off and we'll return that so that
we have access to the card that was just drawn.
But now we also are updating this deck.
So I don't have to pass anything around if I want to use it.
I just do my dec dot and let's initialize the deck and then we'll also do my dec dot and then draw a
single card.
We can save this to a variable concept card.
Oops, I didn't add my friends and I'm going to get an error if I use const again because I already
declared card.
Oh geez, I'm an idiot.
We can't update const.
All right, well, let's go with a different name.
Const card one equals my dec dot draw card.
And we look at card one, we have that card that we drew.
And if we look at the deck itself, my deck, dot deck.
Where are you?
We now have 51 cards, so notice we didn't have to pass an argument around.
We didn't have to do what we did here, where every time I want to draw a card I have to pass in the
deck we're drawing it from.
Instead, we group the method with the values we put the data and the functionality in a single object.
So now all we have to do is access this deck and we're updating this one object.
This whole thing represents a deck of cards, and we have different things we can do with the data.
We can initialize it again.
We can draw a card and let's actually add a new method that will draw multiple cards.
And before we do that, let's add a discard pile or a drawn card pile where we can keep track of the
cards that have already been drawn.
So instead of just returning this deck pop, we will pop an element off, we'll pop a card off.
But before we return it, we'll also make sure to add it to the drawn cards so drawing cards can start
as an empty array.
And then here when we draw a new card.
We'll do this next pop, but we'll push that on to the drawing cards array.
So we could just put this in a variable called card equals this dot dot pop.
And then we can do this dot draw on cards, dot push card and then return card.
So now if we run it.
My deck.
Initialized.
Deck.
My deck.
Dot.
Draw the first card.
We'll draw a couple.
Now let's look at my deck.
We have drawn cards right here and it has six elements, six cards that we've drawn.
And now if I want to make a method to draw multiple cards, we could just make draw cards or draw multiple,
which will be a method we'll pass in a number of cards, num cards, make sure to add my comma here
and then I would just loop num cards times and take advantage of our draw card method we already have.
So let's do a regular for loop for lit i equals zero i less than num cards i plus plus.
And then we want to call this draw card, this method here.
This draws a single card, it adds it to the drawing cards array and it returns that card.
So we'll call that multiple times, but we want to return all of the cards that we're drawing.
So if somebody says draw eight cards, draw multiple of eight, we want to have an array.
We'll just call this concept cards that we return.
So we'll draw the card and push that on to cards.
Cards push.
The card that we get back from.
Draw a single card, draw card, and then at the end, we will return cards.
Let's see if that one works.
So we have my deck, initialize deck and then my deck dot draw multiple of four.
We get back in array with four cards.
Let's look at my deck.
Does it, in fact, have a smaller deck?
Yes, it does.
We're down to 48 and drawing cards has four elements.
Cool.
Next, we'll add a shuffle method.
Now I've gone ahead and written a simple shuffle method.
Shuffling things is actually not as straightforward as you might think.
There's a ton of ways of doing it.
And sometimes you run into issues with randomness and random numbers not being as random as they should
be.
So this is not by any means the best shuffle that there ever is.
But I'm going to walk through how it works in like 30 seconds.
This is an algorithm called the Fisher Yates Shuffle.
It's used to shuffle an array.
And I'm going to console.log in this loop the array that we pass in so you can see how it works.
I'm going to call shuffle on this array of strings and we can see what happens each step of the way.
So we loop over the array backwards.
We start at the end of the array.
So the original array looks like this.
So we're starting with F and then we pick a random index before F, so any of these and we swap the
two.
So the choice that was made the first time three was B, so we swapped F and B and then the loop moves
on to this letter, E or this index, and we swap it with something before it.
We pick a random index between zero and whatever this index is and we swap.
So we swapped with C that time.
So then we move on to this index.
And so we're shuffling it from the back, moving towards the front.
We swap with some random index before and then we move on.
We swap a something before move on and we end up with this.
And if I call it again, we'll likely get something different.
As you can see there.
So not the focus so much of this video, but here is a simple implementation if you want.
Definitely look into more complex implementations.
It's kind of fun, different ways of shuffling, but I'll just add some quick notes, loop over array
backwards and then here, pick random index B for current elements.
And then swap.
Now, this right here is a nice shorthand way of swapping elements using D structuring.
Don't want to get too sidetracked here, but I'll show it to you briefly.
If we have this array from earlier, we'll call it letters.
If I run this line, let's do letters.
Of zero comma.
Letters of.
How about three?
So that should be A and D equals.
And then do the inverse letters of three comma letters of zero.
What this will do is swap our elements in place.
And if we look at letters now.
Dhe is now where I used to be and a is now where DH used to be.
The shuffle is not really the focus of the video, but in order to make our deck slightly more useful,
we should add shuffle.
So let's go ahead and do it.
We'll add in our method shuffle, which I need to change a couple of different ways.
First, I need to make it a valid method on our object.
I'm not going to pass in an array.
It should just shuffle the deck, right?
It shouldn't shuffle an array we pass in.
So any time I have that reference to a R, I'm going to replace it with Deck.
So I'm going to structure deck this.
I don't know why I'm writing this backwards concert deck equals this.
So that is structuring the deck out of this and then we're going to replace array that time there there
there with deck.
So now we have a shuffle method.
This deck, we don't have to pass anything in.
Let's make sure it works.
So my deck, initialize deck.
And as we've already seen, the way we built the initialize is that it just puts them all in order.
So we have, what is it, two of hearts and then three of hearts and then four of hearts.
Or did I do it backwards?
I think we have two of hearts.
Two of diamonds, two of spades.
But let's just look.
So we do my deck.
Deck.
Open this up.
And yeah, we have all the twos, all the threes, the fours.
So let's shuffle my deck.
Dot shuffle.
Fingers crossed you didn't mess anything up.
Let's look at my deck and.
Open up deck.
There we go.
Totally shuffled.
Awesome.
So hopefully you can see from this example that putting our code in an object is not something we always
need to do.
It's not the end all, be all.
There's lots of these different patterns out there for organizing your code or for structuring designing
your code.
This is just one option where we put things in an object, and this is still a very, very simple version.
There are other patterns we'll talk about once we get to prototypes, once we talk about creating constructor
functions and working with JavaScript classes, which is all coming later on.
But this is this is still nice.
We don't have to pass anything around.
I will quickly.
I'll fast forward through this so you don't have to watch, but I will reimplement all of this outside
of an object and show you how we would achieve the exact same thing.
And we can compare how ugly the code is or isn't.
All right, so I took our object from down here that we created my deck and I rewrote it as just standalone
functions.
So we have our initialized deck.
This used to be called make deck, but I renamed it just to match what we have in our object.
Initialize deck creates the deck of cards in order.
Then I have draw card and we need to pass in the deck.
And if we want to keep track of the drawing cards, the cards that have already been drawn from the
deck, we need to pass in a second array called drawing cards.
If I want to draw multiple, I need to pass in the number of cards to draw the deck to draw from and
the array to put the drawing cards in that pile of cards that have already been drawn.
First shuffle I need to pass in the deck.
So here's what it looks like when I start using it.
I'll have things like draw multiple pass in the number of cards to draw the deck.
The array that I'm drawing from and the drawn cards array that I've made, an empty array called Drawn
Cards.
So every time I want to draw a card, I'm going to have to pass in all of these arguments.
If I want to get a new hand, let's call it const poker hand equals.
I guess most poker hands are five cards.
Let's go with blackjack.
And I was going to say I was going to write BJ hand, but that might not be.
Umm hmm.
I guess we'll go with poker hand equals draw multiple.
I guess we can draw two for each of these and then our poker hand will draw five.
We need to pass in the deck that I made up here and the drawn cards array.
So this gets pretty tiresome.
Not to mention if I want another deck.
It's really annoying because I'm going to have to keep making these variables and I'm going to have
to keep track of them and pass in the correct drawing cards.
If I have two different decks, I'll have one drawing cards array for one deck and a second one.
We haven't seen how we can use our object and use it to make multiple decks from it.
So we'll get to that in the next video.
But for now, here we go.
This is one approach.
No objects except for the actual cards themselves, which are an object with a value in a suit.
Everything else is functions.
We're passing things around.
It gets kind of annoying, but let's take a look, make sure it all works.
We've got our deck has 43 cards left because we drew nine of them.
If we look at hand one, it has two cards.
Also the deck should be shuffled because I called it right called shuffle.
If we look at poker hand it has five cards and if we look at drawn cards, it should have nine cards.
So that's all great.
Now down to our object version to do the exact same thing.
Let me just see what we did.
We drew two, two and then five.
To replicate that, we would call my deck, initialize deck, my deck, shuffle, my deck dot, draw
multiple and we'll do two.
And we can save that to a variable concept.
We'll call it H one for a hand, 1h2 to draw two and then h three will draw five and that's it.
We don't have to keep passing a bunch of arguments in afterwards like we did here.
It's a lot easier because all of the relevant information, all the values are stored together in my
deck.
I don't have to manage the drawn cards versus the deck array.
I have it together.
It's all here versus in this example.
I have to keep track of drawing cards myself, pass it around.
It's just not ideal.
So I recognize this has been extremely long and probably not the most enthralling video I've ever made,
but it gets at some very important stuff that using objects is a great way of organizing your code of
grouping content together, or a better way of saying it is grouping values with functionality, things
with actions, and we've grouped them together in a logical way where we can start writing our methods,
our functions in a clean syntax, where I don't have to pass a bunch of stuff in, I don't have to save
everything to a new variable because everything is done on the object itself.
The object stores those values, and then these methods act upon those values, thanks to our good friend.
This next up, we'll see how we can create multiple decks.
Right now, I'm stuck with one deck.
That is probably the big disadvantage to what we saw up here.
Here, I could make another deck at any point by just calling initialized deck.
I still have to write a bunch of code to get the deck, make a new drawing cards, shuffle the second
deck.
But I can do it here.
We have one object.
So how do I make another one of these?
That's what we'll see next.