Okay.
So if you're still with me, we made our deck of cards.
Object called my deck.
It's a single object.
And right now, I don't have a way of making another one.
So I'm just going to show you a quick and dirty approach to creating multiple decks.
This approach I'm going to show you is not the end all, be all.
This is not the best way of doing it.
But we haven't covered things that we would need in order to structure this in a nicer way.
We haven't covered constructors, we haven't talked about the new keyword, we haven't talked about
classes.
There's a lot of stuff we have to get to where we could refactor this nicer, nicer.
We could refactor this in a better way.
But what I'm going to show you here is a very basic approach where we could just make a function that
makes one of these decks for us.
It's long, but I could just copy this.
Define a function down here.
I'll do an arrow function for the sake of variety.
Let's go with make deck.
And make DEC is going to return.
This whole object.
So our entire deck.
This thing I copied, except for the variable name and the equal sign I copied from curly brace to curly
brace.
So now we have this function called make deck, and I could just delete this entirely.
We're returning this whole object.
And we could even do this implicitly if we wanted to.
Just put Perrins.
Get rid of the return keyword.
So to use it instead of calling my deck dot initialized deck, I now need to say const my deck equals
make deck.
And this returns to me a new deck.
Let's make sure it works.
My deck.
There we go.
So we have this deck I drew.
How many cards from this?
Nine cards.
If we want a second deck, we'll go with cost.
Deck two equals make deck.
Do it again.
Let's look at deck two and then let's also initialize it.
So deck two.
Initialize deck and deck two.
Let's not shuffle this one just so we can see the difference.
So we have deck two now.
It has 52 cards, no drawn cards.
It's all looking good.
And then if we look at my deck, it has 43 cards and they are all shuffled, as you can see here.
And we have nine cards that we've drawn.
So we have totally separate decks.
They are separate objects because we made a function to return an object.
So we're returning a new deck each time a new object with these methods draw card, draw, multiple
shuffle initialized deck, a separate deck array, a separate drawing cards array.
And we return that every time we call make deck.
So now we have a way of creating multiple.
But just to reiterate, this is not the best way of doing it.
It's the best way of doing it with what we know right now.
And it's certainly better than doing it with all those functions and all the stuff we saw in the last
video.
This is still pretty clean.
It's not too bad.
And I'm going to stop here.
So we're going to move on to Dom manipulation for a bit, take a break from all this object stuff and
working with this, we'll see how to work with HTML and CSS through JavaScript, how we can add events
to our page, lots of fun stuff, and then we'll come back to objects because it's a big topic.
We'll talk about classes and constructors and we'll see different ways of structuring this code already.