Hey.
Welcome, everyone.
In this section, we're doing things a little bit differently.
I'm calling it other useful things JavaScript assortment, hence the assorted bread on the right.
As we've gone through this course so far, I've been trying hard to integrate new features, new JavaScript
features as organically as possible, wherever they make sense.
So we introduced string template literals really early on when we were talking about strings, we talked
about Lead and Const, which are new ways of creating variables.
We talked about them right?
When we introduced variables, I introduced four of and four in along with the regular for loops and
while loops.
Now we can't do that for every single feature in JavaScript as much as I would like to, because some
of them are more advanced or they require a whole bunch of previous knowledge in order for them to be
useful.
So that's what this section is here for.
This section is going to cover this group of three new features in JavaScript.
It's really more than three rest and spread are kind of separate things, but these are not necessarily
related except in the fact that they are new features in JavaScript.
So I couldn't find an easy way to integrate them organically into another part of the course.
So they get lumped into this assortment section.
So we're going to talk about rest and spread de structuring and default function parameters.
We also have some other new features we haven't covered yet and those will get their own sections.
So we're going to return to objects.
Then we'll talk more about classes and then later on we'll also cover asynchronous JavaScript and async
functions.
So this section, as I mentioned, is really focused on rest and spread default function parameters
and D structuring.
So that's what we're here for.
We're going to start with the second one, default function parameters.