So the first of these new features we'll see has to do with adding default function parameter values.
So we could do this in the past.
We just now have a newer, more compact syntax to do it.
Here's what I'm talking about.
If we have a function, make sure I'm in the right window.
We'll just go with our standard.
Multiply two parameters x and Y.
We return x times Y.
Right now, if we call it with two parameters, it works great.
Actually, these are arguments we're passing in to arguments, but if we leave one off, we get not
a number.
And that's because y is set to undefined when we don't specify a value.
So if we wanted to have a default value for Y, if a user or another function call or a developer does
not pass in a second argument, we want a default value.
We could in the past do it this way.
We would manually check if type of y equals undefined.
And if you don't remember how type of works, it does not return the actual value of undefined.
It returns a string containing the type.
So if I declare a variable w, the value of w is undefined.
If I do type of w, I get the string undefined.
So I see people do this sometimes and this won't work because you're always going to get a string back
from type of.
So we need to make this a string.
So if type of y is undefined, then we'll say y equals one.
And this is the older way of doing it.
If we call multiply a four now we're multiplying four times one and we get four.
But if we pass in a value for Y, we get 12 in this case.
So this is only happening if there is no Y.
There's a shorter way of doing this manual check before we get to the newer way, the newer feature,
you could use a ternary operator where you set Y equal to and then we have our condition type of y equals
the string undefined question mark.
If this is true, we'll set y to be one.
Otherwise Y stays as y.
So if you pass in a value like five for y, this is false.
So this doesn't run.
This is what we end up setting y equal to y equals y.
If you don't pass something in and it's undefined, this is true.
So we end up setting y equal to one.
So this works, but it's still pretty clunky.
It's not very user friendly or developer friendly.
We have a much better way thanks to the new default parameter syntax.
It looks like this right here.
So we define our function and right inside the parents where we are listing the parameters.
We can add a default with equal sign and then a default value.
So here is the exact same thing, except with A and B instead of x and y, where B will default to one
if a value is not passed in.
So I could rewrite this.
If I comment it out, get rid of this entire line.
Y equals one.
And this just means if no y is passed in, if it's undefined, use this value.
So I'll run my code again.
Make sure it still works.
If we only pass an eight, we get eight.
If we pass in two and eight, we get 16.
Let's do one more example.
If we were to define a function called greet, let's do it with an arrow function this time.
So const greet equals a function and this function will take a person and then a greeting.
And the way I want greet to work is that I can call it like this greet Tim and then some greeting like
yo.
And it will print out yo Tim with an exclamation point, let's say.
But if I just call greet Tim, it should default the greeting to hi the string.
Hi.
So all we need to do is say greeting equals hi and that will give it a default value if greeting is
not passed.
So let me move this over, Ted.
Let's add in our simple console.log.
I'll do a template, literal string, and then we'll add in the person, which is the first parameter
and then the second.
Actually, I guess we want to say greeting first, right?
Yo, Tim.
Hi, Tim.
So we'll do greeting with our curly braces and then a comma person, exclamation point.
Let's try it.
We'll do greet of Tim and won't pass anything in and we get.
Hi Tim.
But if we do greet of Tim and yo.
We get.
Yo, Tim.
Okay, so that's another example.
We're using a string this time as the default value.
You can also do things with arrays or objects if you wanted to.
I'll just make up a dumb example.
If we have a function called const blah and let's say there are two parameters and Y will default to
the array.
One, two, three.
Let's just console.log x and y.
So this does absolutely nothing.
But I just want to show you that we can use an array or an object or any other value in JavaScript as
the default value.
So let's call blah with one and we can see that x is one, y is the array.
But if I pass in one and three, now X is one and y is three.
One really important note about default parameters is that the order absolutely matters.
So if I add in a third parameter here, let's say for greet, I want a person greeting and then, I
don't know, punctuation, which is this exclamation point at the end.
If I want it to default to exclamation point, that's fine.
I can do this if I call Grete right now and I only pass in.
Oh, I need to update this so that I'm actually using the exclamation point or punctuation.
If I call greet again and I pass in on you, we get high on you with an exclamation point.
So both of those default parameters kicked in.
Greeting is high, punctuation is exclamation point, but it does not work.
Of course, if I tried to pass in person and punctuation like this, the way that they are interpreted,
the way that JavaScript knows which one needs to have a default value is purely based off of the order
you pass them in.
So there's no way for me to say here I want to pass in person as an you and punctuation as a question
mark and use the default greeting.
It doesn't work that way.
So all the default parameters also need to come at the end of your parameter list.
You can't make the first thing default and then have non default parameters afterwards.
So if we went back to multiply this example, I couldn't do this x equals one and then just regular
y.
If I try that and I multiply to what happens here, well x is going to be two and y is undefined.
So there's no default for y.
If I pass in two numbers, it works fine, but the default is never going to work the way I want it
to work unless I'm fine with y being undefined as well.
So this is not something you really see and it's not something I recommend you do.
Your default parameters come at the end and that's pretty much it.
So you can have as many as you want.
Although if you're finding yourself adding a ton of defaults to your parameter list, there's probably
a better way of writing the function, but it's a really nice addition.
Just new syntax compared to doing something like this where you're manually checking for type.
So that's it.
That's the newer way of adding default parameters.