The next new feature we'll take a look at is called Spread.
And the first thing you should know about spread is that like every other feature we're seeing in this
section, it's not supported in Internet Explorer.
However, that shouldn't stop you from using it.
So spread is extremely useful, but it's also not that easy to explain because it does many things depending
on the context.
This is the official definition from MSDN.
I guess it's not official, but this is the mean definition.
Spread syntax allows an iterable such as an array to be expanded in places where zero or more arguments
for function calls or elements for array literals are expected, or an object expression to be expanded
in places where zero or more key value pairs for object literals are expected.
You got it.
Okay.
So I think that's good enough, right?
You understand at this point?
Yeah, I know.
Very funny, Colt.
There's a lot to spread.
The key word that I bolded here is expanded.
So in all scenarios, there's really three use cases spread in a function call, spread in array literals
and spread in object literals.
It all has to do with expanding some iterable into some other place, some destination.
So the word spread is a nice choice, I think, because that's kind of what we're doing.
We're spreading, we're expanding something.
What I'm going to do is break it up into three videos, one for each of the use cases, and the first
one we'll see is spread in a function call.
So spread syntactically is always three dots here when we're using it in a function call here in an
array, literal three dots here in an object, three dots, always three dots, but they mean something
different or they they behave differently depending on where you use it.
At the end of the day, it all has to do with expanding and iterable, meaning an array, a string.
There are many other intervals, but those are the two main ones we've worked with, expanding them
into some other destination.
And when we use it in a function call inside the parentheses, it will take that iterable and break
it up into individual arguments rather than passing in a single argument.
So the example I used with Matt was Max, which accepts multiple arguments.
Here's a bunch of arguments I just passed in.
And it returns the max.
So in this case, the maximum argument was 99.
There's also math min, which does the same thing except the other way around.
It tells me the smallest argument was three.
But this only works if you pass them in as separate arguments.
If we have a list of numbers or an array of numbers.
It will not work.
It treats it as one argument.
And if I do math max of numbers, I get not a number.
It expects each argument to be a number.
This argument that we passed in is not a number.
It's a list of numbers, but itself is not a number, so it does not work.
Instead, we can use spread.
So spread allows us to break this up into five separate arguments.
It's the equivalent of passing in 45, comma 33, basically stripping away the array brackets.
So this is what it looks like.
Dot, dot, dot, nums.
Just like that, we are spreading this iterable into individual arguments.
So again, it's just like doing this 45, 23, 34, seven and five and we get 45.
So to show you the other side of it, if you wanted to write a function, let's call ours.
Give me four.
And this is going to be a useless function, but it wants four arguments.
So A, B, C and D and then we'll just console.log each one of them.
I'll do it like this a comma a and then duplicate this a couple of times and then update this to b b
and then do the same thing for C and D.
All right.
So it's going to print out the arguments that we get.
Give me four.
I'll pass in four numbers four, five, six and seven.
And we see A is four, B is five, C is six and D is seven.
If I had an array of numbers or an array of anything, let's go with cost colors.
We'll have red, orange, yellow and green.
If I call, give me four and I pass in colors.
We're only passing in one argument.
So you see what we get a is set to this whole array.
B is undefined.
C and D are also undefined.
But if I instead use spread 1 to 3 dots, we're now spreading that entire array into separate arguments.
So now those array braces are essentially gone from the function call.
We don't change the array in any way.
Colors is exactly the same as it always was, but when we pass those values in, they now are for arguments.
So A is red, B is orange, C is yellow and D is green.
And if we had more arguments right now, our function doesn't handle them.
It only wants four.
But if we had colors that had ten things in there, each one would be passed as an argument.
We just wouldn't be using it in the function.
But shortly in this section we'll see how to write a function that accepts any number of arguments.
Right now we're having to hard code how many we want this is for.
If I want five arguments then I need to add in another parameter.
But we'll see how we can add in RN number and collect all arguments in a single array or a single structure.
That's coming up soon.
The other thing about spread is that it's not only applicable to arrays, so we could also do something
like this.
Let me make some space here.
If I have a string const, we'll just call it str equals.
How about goat like that?
If I spread a string, a string is actually an iterable.
What do you expect to happen here?
If I call, give me 4... str.
It passes each character as its own argument.
It iterates over this and it's iterable.
We've done it before.
You iterate one character at a time and you end up with one character g being the first argument, then
the second and the third, then the fourth.
You can think of it as just like this.
Each value or each character is passed at its own argument and we would get the same result if we did
it this way.
Give me four.
But the main difference is that this sucks to type and this is hardcoded.
If we use spread, this could be 20 characters, it could be two characters.
It's not that common that you spread strings, at least in my experience, compared to arrays.
But whatever you're spreading when you spread it into a function call that iterable is iterated over.
Each element is passed as a standalone separate argument.
So that's the first use case for spread.
We have two more to go.