Next up, we'll see the second use case for spread.
If we go back to this paragraph of gibberish from Indian spread, syntax allows an iterable such as
an array to be expanded in places where zero or more elements for array literals are expected.
So we can use those three dots inside of an array literal.
We just saw how we can use it in a function call in an array literal.
It does something very similar.
It takes an iterable and it spreads it out.
It takes the individual pieces, and in the case of an array, it copies them over into a new destination
array.
So we can use it to combine arrays to make a copy of an array.
There's a whole bunch of situations where you may end up using spread.
So let's check it out.
I have a simple example over here.
I have some arrays of really cool animals, some of my favorite animals out there.
We've got cephalopods which are basically squid, cuttlefish, nautilus.
So there's a couple of examples in here.
We've got gastro pods, giant African snail variable neon slug, a really cool animal.
And Nigeria, which include things like jellyfish and in corals and hydra and a couple of other things.
Anyway, we're going to combine them in a few different ways.
Also, stick around at the end.
If you want to see some photos and videos of these, some of them are pretty cool, but I won't waste
your time in the middle of the video with that.
So quick biology lesson.
Both of these right here, cephalopods and gastro pods, they're both considered mollusks.
So if I wanted to make an array with both of them called mollusks or mollusks I think is the correct
Latin term I could use spread like this cephalopods, comma, dot, dot, dot gastro pods.
And this will make me a new array with both contents of those arrays combined into one.
So let's take a look.
What do we have over here?
Mollusk has six elements.
We had three from cephalopods and three from gastro pods.
Notice the order.
I put cephalopods first, so we get those three elements first and then gastro pods afterwards, and
the original arrays are untouched.
We're just making a copy or actually a new array with copies of both arrays inside.
If I instead did it the other way around and I did three dots with gastro pods first, and then three
dots spread with, uh, cephalopods.
Cephalopods.
You can see the order is different now.
So we have the first three from gastro pods, the second three from cephalopods.
The order does matter.
Also, we could add in other elements if we wanted to that weren't present from these arrays.
I could add in up front.
What's another mollusk?
We could add?
If I wanted to add at the beginning the garden slug, it would look like this.
I just add it as an element and then comma and then spread comma.
Spread more.
And there we go.
I could also combine more than one array.
I could do all three of these arrays.
They would be considered invertebrates.
So const inverts equals and then dot, dot, dot.
Let's do Nigeria first.
Dot, dot, dot, gastropub, dot, dot, dot.
I need my comma.
Dot, dot, dot.
Cephalopods.
And if I look at inverts, we now have an array of eight elements, all of them combined.
Spread is great in situations where you need to combine arrays, but it's not doing something we couldn't
do before.
We have already seen how to use cat.
So for example, cephalopods can cat.
Gastro pods.
It gives us the same result that we had from this line where we're taking the data from cephalopods
and combining it with gastro pods.
And if we look at the originals, they're still unchanged.
This is just a shorter syntax.
It's easier to see and easier to reorder as you like.
And we can add an element wherever we want to.
We can do multiple arrays combined.
There's a lot we can do.
And one of the most common use cases for spread is actually just to make a copy of an array.
If I just want a second version of Nigeria, actually let's go with cephalopods.
Nigeria is annoying to spell.
I could do const sjef copy equals array literal brackets.
Dot dot dot cephalopods.
And if I look at C.F. copy, I now have the same data and they have unique references so they are not
triple equals to each other.
SCEF copy triple equals cephalopods.
Is false versus if I had just made an array like const or I made a variable const copy equals cephalopods.
Copy Triple equals cephalopods will be true as we've seen before, because they are referencing the
same reference.
They're pointing to the same reference.
But when we use spread here, it is going to make a clone a new array in memory with a new unique reference.
But that does not extend to nested arrays.
Or if we had objects inside of the arrays, those won't be cloned.
The references will remain the same, so it does not go multiple levels deep.
So we can do this with arrays.
We can also spread other types of data into an array.
There's not many that you would do it with, but one example would be a string.
If we wanted to get a string, like let's say we had a BCD EFG, imagine this is the whole alphabet.
And I wanted an array where each character was one element I could do split, which we've seen already.
And you pass in an empty string saying, Split this string on nothing, split on every character.
And it gives us an array just like that.
But I can also do this abcd cfg and spread it.
One, two, three.
And it's the same idea what we had here with an array.
When we spread it, we're telling JavaScript to iterate over this iterable and for each item in there
add it as an element in the array, which is what we did earlier with a different array rather than
a string, but the same process.
So we can spread strings.
Probably not that common that you would spread a bunch of them into one array, but we could we could
do a, b, c, d, e, f, comma, hello.
And then spread these guys.
And that's what we end up with a B, C, D, E, F and then hello at the end.
So that's pretty much it for spreading into an array literal same idea as spreading into a function
call.
We're taking an iterable and breaking it into pieces and moving them or copying them to a destination.
In this case, it's an array that we're creating, and as promised, I'll show you some of those animals
if you want to check them out.
Some of my favorite guys on earth, guys favorite animals.
We've got the Dumbo octopus.
Very adorable, tiny octopus, very cute, giant African snail.
Horrifyingly huge snails.
They're giant as their name tells you.
Quite, quite intimidating.
I would not want to hold one of those in my hands.
Then we've got a really cool animal called a variable neon slug.
It's a species of nudibranchs these really cool flatworms that live in the ocean.
Lots of them have beautiful, beautiful colors, as you can see here.
And then finally, my favorite, the flamboyant cuttlefish, they're are tiny, adorable little creatures
with incredible skin and the ability to display these patterns and change their the shape of their body.
Very hypnotic.
Anyway, so those are some of my favorite animals.
Thanks for joining me on Colt's Animal, our back to JavaScript.
That's coming up next.
More spread.
Wait, wait.
I forgot to show you the best part.
Here we go.
The way that they eat this appendage comes out horrifying and then snaps back.
Okay, that's it for that.