Next up, we have the third context we can use spread.
It's down here at the bottom of the paragraph and object expression to be expanded in places where zero
or more key value pairs are expected.
So here's what it looks like.
It's the same dot, dot, dot, but we put it inside of curly braces instead of an object literal,
and it will copy over key value pairs properties from other objects into a destination object.
So effectively we can make copies of objects or we can create combinations of objects, we can put them
together.
So that's what we'll see in this video.
I have two existing objects, one called feline, one called canine.
They just have two stupid properties, their family and the number of legs for cats and furry.
Is that too true for canines?
If I wanted to make a new object that included these properties, but also more properties like a dog
dog object will include everything from canine.
And I'll also set is pet to true and adorable.
True.
If we look at dog, if I run the code over here, we have those two properties from canine, the family
and furry set to true.
So those were copied over.
We could also do the same thing for cat.
Concept feline.
Let's go with what's it?
How about house cat?
That's fine.
We'll spread feline and then also add in.
Is grumpy, true and personality unpredictable.
At least my cats are.
And if we look at house cat over here.
We've got properties coming from feline, plus the properties we set right here.
Now, what can happen is sometimes you might have conflicting properties, like if we added legs for.
To K9 as well.
They both have legs of four.
What happens when we merge them together?
So let's do Konst cat dog equals and dot dot dot canine.
Dot dot dot feline.
What do you think happens?
Well, in this case, it's pretty simple because we know what happens in an object where we try and
have two properties with the same key.
They just overwrite each other.
So we only have one leg's property.
But but what if let's say we have a three legged dog can't tripod equals and I copy in canine and then
I set legs to three.
What do you think Tripod looks like?
Well, it does have legs set to three, even though we had legs four in canine.
The reason is that the order matters.
So we copy the properties from canine first and then afterwards legs is updated to three.
So if I switch them.
Here and then dot, dot, K9, try it again.
We look at Tripod now.
Legs is set to four.
Legs was three originally, but then those properties were copied in and that overrode it.
So the order does matter.
If you have conflicting properties with the same key name.
We can also use spread to create a clone of an object so that we don't have the exact same reference.
We're creating a copy of the object, but just like with a this is only one level deep.
It will not clone nested objects or nested arrays.
So if I wanted to copy of one of these existing objects, how about cat?
Dog I could do concept cat dog clone equals dot dot dot cat dog.
So cat dog itself exists or is created from two other objects.
Two objects properties have been copied over.
And then I'm copying that cat dog object over into cat dog clone.
Refresh my page.
We have cat dog clone.
And if we triple equals to cat dog, it's false.
They are unique references because we made a copy.
It's not the same reference.
Another very important thing about spread in general.
This is the only context where you can spread an object when you're spreading into another object.
If you tried to do it inside of an array, we'll do it over here.
Let's see.
How about canine or dog?
This does not work.
We get an error.
Object is not iterable.
So in the context of an array, it doesn't work.
In the context of an object though we can spread objects, it does behave differently and the same holds
true.
If we were trying to pass this in to, I don't know, math max or something, which wouldn't even make
sense.
But we can't spread the object either.
It's not an iterable.
It only works if we're passing in an array that we're spreading a string or some other iterable.
But an object literal is not one.
Now, what do you think happens if I try the opposite?
If I have an object literal and I try to spread an array into it, the array of four or five six.
What happens here.
No error.
Instead, we get key value pairs based off of the indices.
So zero is the key.
Set to four.
1 to 5.
2 to 6.
Probably not that common that you would need to do that.
But the same thing holds true with a string.
We can spread a string into an object, but just kind of a weird thing to do.
Never really seen it done.
And the last thing I'll show you here is that we can create array literals that also contain object
literals where we use spread in different contexts.
So let's say I was making an array and I was spreading in the string.
Hello for some reason.
And then I also have an object as one of the possible values in the array and and there I spread in
cat dog.
So I'm combining them inside of an array.
Let's create a variable here const random equals get rid of that extra sw.
Random is an array with string characters first that we spread, and then an object that contains object
properties that we spread.
So we can nest them.
We can create more data structures or nested structures where we spread.
But the context matters.
The way that spread works inside of this object is different than the way spread works right here.
Because here we're in an array.
Here we're in an object.
Yes, technically it's nested in the array, but that doesn't matter.
It behaves just the same as it did here or here.
So that is spread.
We saw three different situations where it works.
We always use three dots.
The first one we saw was passing into a function.
Math min was the example I used where you can spread a bunch of values, let's say an array into individual
arguments, so they're passed as separate arguments.
Then we saw how to use spread in an array literal, super useful, which helps us copy data from one
array into a new array.
We can combine arrays essentially a nicer way of concatenating, or we can create a clone of an array.
And then in this video we saw how we can use Spread in Object Literals to copy properties over from
one object to a new object.
We can create a clone of an object.
We can create a hybrid where we take properties from two objects or three or four and combine them into
one.
We can add new properties in.
Just remember that the order does matter if you have conflicting properties like we did with the legs
situation.
So legs here, if we want legs to remain three, should come after.
All right.
That spread a lovely, lovely new feature.