Next up, we have another new operator or feature in JavaScript called Rest.
Now I wrote that it looks like spread, but it's not because we use the exact same three dots in text
dot, dot, dot, but rest behaves very differently.
It's almost like the opposite of spread.
What it does is instead of spreading data out into arguments or into a new object or an array, it actually
collects things down into a single array.
So it's used when we want to make functions that accept an unlimited number of arguments or a variable
number of arguments.
For example, we've seen this method a couple of times mathematics, where we can pass in as many arguments
as we want and it returns the maximum value.
So how would we write this?
How would we write code for a function?
Let's call it Max or let's do one called some instead.
Some will return the sum of any number of numbers.
So we could have two numbers passed in.
So we could add two parameters.
But what if we want to support 100 or 20 or one?
We would have to do something like this, maybe a, b, c, d, e, f, g, h, i, j k.
And even then we would eventually run out of letters and have to switch it up.
And then how would it work?
Because sometimes they would be undefined if you only passed in three arguments.
So this is not the answer.
There is a way of doing this without rest.
It's called the arguments object.
So in every function we have access to something called arguments.
It's a special name arguments and it kind of looks like an array, but it is not an array.
It's 100% not an array.
We don't have things like push and pop and all the common array methods you might want, but it is a
list where we have indices and we can loop over it with a for loop.
So this has been around for a long time.
This is not new.
We're starting with the old way and then we'll see the new way with rest.
So using this is as I wrote here, may it's not very it's not great, it's annoying, but I'm going
to show it to you quickly.
Inside of any function we have arguments, so let's just console.log arguments.
Notice that my function does not have any parameters listed.
That doesn't matter if I call it right now.
Some of one comma two come a three arguments prints out and we can see it has three values in it.
One, two and three if I call it with a whole bunch more arguments.
Six seven 2345 6666 arguments has eight elements in it.
So if I wanted to make some actually work, I wanted some all elements let's use reduce which we saw
earlier on.
We'll get some practice again with it.
We have arguments and what I might want to try is arguments reduce and then remember our syntax.
Here we have the total and then each current vowel.
Let's go with curve out and we'll return total plus curve.
Val.
And let's see what we get here.
I also will return that this will give us the sum and then we return the sum.
If I try it, though.
One, two, three, four, five.
Oh, no.
Arguments that reduce is not a function.
Again, arguments is not actually an array.
It's an array like object.
It looks like an array because we can access arguments of zero or we can loop over it.
But it does not have array methods.
If I wanted to make this work using the arguments object, what I could do is turn it into an array.
And one way of doing that we just saw is spread dot, dot, dot arguments.
And then I could call this args array and then iterate over that args array.
Now if I try it again, it works.
We get 15, right.
That's.
I think that's correct.
Yes.
So that's one of the shortcomings of the arguments object.
Here's another situation where it's not ideal.
If I wanted to define a function called Let's just go with full name, it accepts a first name, a last
name, and then a bunch of titles like optional titles.
Someone could have like, I don't know, Order of the Making These Up, Order of the Phoenix or Royal
Badass or whatever titles there are.
I know there's a bunch of them.
Oh, Junior, there we go.
Or the third.
And somebody could have I think you would just do this.
Right.
So how you do the third, somebody could have multiple titles, but everyone needs to have a first and
a last.
And then what I'd like to do is just have everything else.
Any titles that were passed in collected maybe in the arguments object, but there isn't actually a
way of doing that.
If I do first and last and here, if I cancel that log arguments, it just contains everything.
So if I call full name of Tom Jones and then pass in a couple of other things like Third and Order of
the Phoenix, if those are his titles, if we look at arguments, it just contains all four arguments.
So we could still implement this function.
We would just need to make sure to skip the first two if we're trying to get the titles that were passed
in.
Tom Jones The Third Order of the Phoenix, we would want these two.
We already have first and last.
We still have access to those.
I can print out first.
I still have access to it.
You can see Tom.
It's just that arguments includes everything.
So I just have to be mindful of that and know that the first two in arguments are already first and
last with rest, which we're about to see.
That's not a problem.
And there is one last issue with the arguments object.
It does not work in arrow functions.
If I define an arrow function which I'll call multiply if I try and console that log arguments.
We'll call it multiply pass in some numbers.
It does not work.
Arguments is not defined.
So the arguments object is not a thing in arrow functions.
So there's a couple shortcomings to some of this.
Up first, it's not a real array, so you have to turn it into an array if you want array method.
Next, there is no functionality provided for collecting remaining arguments like we saw here.
Arguments contains every argument passed in even if we captured the first two in parameter names.
And then lastly, the arguments object does not exist at all in arrow functions.
So we've set the stage to see the new fancy syntax using rest.
That's coming up next.