All right.
So we just talked about the arguments object and some of its shortcomings.
It's been around for a long time.
It's doing the best it can.
Now we have a new, nicer syntax in rest.
So rest is three dots.
One, two, three.
Just like we use for spread.
But we put it inside the parameter list of a function definition.
And what it does is it collects all remaining arguments into a 100% real actual array.
Not an array like object, not an array, imitation, a real array.
So earlier we wrote this function called Sum.
Using the arguments object.
We had to convert it into an array.
If we want to write the same function using rest.
What we do is we put three dots right here and then we decide on a name and that will be the name of
the array that contains all of the arguments in our case.
All arguments will be collected.
So let's go with nums and then we can start by just contact logging nums.
We need to match that name that we gave it here.
Let's call some on four or five, six, seven.
And it's an actual array.
It's not an array like object, it's a real array.
So I could implement the same functionality where I return using reduce on nums.
So nums dot reduce.
And then we have our reducer function which will be total and then current.
Val, I'll use an arrow function and we just want to return total plus curve.
Val let's check it out.
It works.
We get 22.
So this is the simplest way to use rest.
We're collecting all arguments.
Everything passed in, whether it's 20, the first one, the last one, they're all combined into the
nums array.
But we can also use it in a different way.
We can use it to collect the remaining arguments, which is what I wrote here collects all remaining
arguments.
So not just every argument, no matter what.
Instead, it collects the remaining arguments that have not been matched with a parameter.
So if we go back to that example where I had full name and I wanted a function where we have a first,
a last and then a list of titles I could use rest right here to collect the remaining titles first last.
Those will be their own parameters.
Then everything else is collected here.
So I'll start by just constant logging first with first and then I'll do the same thing for last and
then one more time for titles.
And if I call full name where I'm passing Tom as first, Jones as last, and then a bunch of arguments
to be the titles.
You can see what we get first is still Tom last is Jones, but titles only contains the remaining arguments.
When we tried the same thing with the arguments object, it contained every argument, including first
and last or Tom Jones.
But in this case it is only collecting the unclaimed arguments, if that makes sense.
So we have them collected in titles and it's an array and I could use titles to do something.
I could iterate over each title, but I'm not going to bother with it.
I just wanted to show you that we have a way of separating them out.
We have first, last, and then everything else.
Because of the way rest works, it collects everything.
You wouldn't have multiple rests, JavaScript wouldn't know what to do.
Because the logic here is combine everything that has not been put in a parameter already into the titles
array.
So how could we have something afterwards if we just claimed everything before it into the titles array?
You can name these whatever you'd like as we've seen, and along with that, the order definitely matters.
If you tried to do this, it's not going to work.
Last would never have a value ever.
And if you tried to do it this way.
Titles first last.
Let's see what happens.
Hmm.
Rest parameter must be the last formal parameter.
So JavaScript doesn't even let you try.
It's telling you it has to be the last parameter.
That's the only option.
And then the last thing that is nice about it is that we can use it in an arrow function.
So I could rewrite function some this function statement, the declaration, I could rewrite it as an
arrow function.
Just copy this and define it down here.
Let's go with multiply actually.
So const multiply equals our arrow function and we'll call the parameter nums the rest parameter that
accepts everything into an array.
And then let's do an implicit return.
So we don't need to say return any more.
We'll do nums dot reduce and then multiply instead of add.
And we can use a double implicit return if we want to just do it on one line.
Okay.
So we have our arrow function here where we're using rest, we're calling the array nums and because
it's an array we can call reduce and then I'm just returning total times curve l in my reducer function.
If you skipped over the reduced videos, I really recommend you check those out.
I know they're a bit painful.
Trust me, I had to teach it.
It's not it's not that exciting.
But it is something that you'll use all the time.
Anyway, let's make sure it works.
So we'll call multiply, multiply.
How about four or five?
Six, seven and we get 840.
Let's do something we can verify easier.
Two, three and four gives us 24.
Great.
So we can use an arrow functions which we could not do with the arguments object.
We can use it as an array because it is an array unlike the arguments object where we had to convert
it to an array.
And lastly, we have more discretion over what it collects.
We can tell it to only collect the remaining arguments after certain specific parameters.
Hence the term rest versus the arguments.
Object just contains everything, every argument, no matter what.
So when I say that rest is kind of like the opposite of spread, maybe you can see what I mean.
We are collecting elements or collecting arguments into an array.
We're not copying them over.
We're not spreading.
If we do something like this where we are using spread, we're taking a single element and breaking
it up into multiple pieces into an array.
We're copying it over one element at a time versus when we use rest.
We're doing the opposite.
We're taking multiple disparate elements, arguments and combining them into an array.
So the syntax is the same, but that's why we have a different name rest versus spread.
I guess there's a world where it could have just been spread, but it's called rest.
It has its own page on the docs because it behaves differently and it's sort of the opposite.
So that's it.
For rest, we have a couple more new features in JavaScript.
One of my favorites is coming up called D Structuring.