The next new feature we'll see is called De Structuring.
Now, de structuring is a really nice, clean way to unpack values from data structures, from arrays
or from objects into their own separate, distinct variables.
I really liked this clip art that I found showing this man unpacking, taking a piece, one box out
of this cluttered mess.
It's kind of, I guess, a visual metaphor.
I also like this one.
I couldn't decide which one was better.
Here we're doing the same thing.
We have a collection in that van, and then we are removing one piece or a couple of pieces individually.
We're selecting them and, I don't know, creating variables with them.
That's what you're supposed to think based off of this image.
D Structuring is kind of like spread in that we can use it in different ways.
So I'm going to break it into a few short videos and the first one will see the first option when we
do structure is to de structure arrays.
When we d structure an array, we can unpack specific values out of that array into new variables.
So here I have an array of marathon results from the men's 2016 marathon at the Olympics and they're
in order.
So the gold medal went to Elliot Kipchoge all the way down.
I think I go to sixth place here for Jared Ward.
If I wanted to create variables for, let's say, the first three and I wanted to make a variable called
gold and make it set to Elliot Kipchoge I could do it this way.
Cost gold equals race results of zero and then duplicate that and do silver here equals race results
of one and bronze equals race results of two.
And that works.
Of course, that's sort of standard array stuff we've seen before.
Pre structuring, this was the only option.
This was how you created variables based off of an array.
You referenced a specific index and you saved it to a new variable.
But now we have a much cleaner, shorter syntax where we can unpack the values all at once in a single
line.
Here's what it would look like equivalent to this we would write const array brackets and then we write
our variable names in here gold, silver and bronze equals race results.
So what this will do right here is go into race results and use the order that we wrote them in right
here.
These new variables will be created in this order based off of their position.
So gold will be set to the first item in race results, which is Elliott Kipchoge.
Silver will be set to I'm sorry if I'm butchering these names.
Faiza, Alissa and Bronze will be set to Galen, Galen Rupp and we'll have three new variables, so
we won't have new variables for these, the final three results or the final three elements, but the
first three will each be assigned to a new variable.
So I commented out the original version, but if I look in my console, I still have gold, I have silver
and I have bronze.
The race results array is unchanged.
I'm simply making a variable referencing the value at each index, just like we had before here.
This doesn't change race results in any way.
We're just accessing and making new variables.
Same thing here.
So the position matters.
If I were to swap them and do silver and then gold.
I would end up with Silver as Eliot Kipchoge.
That's the first index in our structuring statement.
So we get that first index in the array and gold would be set to face the LISA.
So this is the basics of structuring.
We could do a variable for each element, but there are some other things that we can do as well.
If we wanted to skip an index, let's say I want the first and the fourth results and I want a variable
called first.
I could do that.
Race results.
That one is easy enough because we know first is going to be the first element.
If we take a look at first, we have Eliot Kipchoge again.
But if I want fourth, if I just write fourth here, we're going to end up with Faisal Alisa as the
fourth variable.
But if I add extra commas, so the first extra comma is going to skip one index and go to Galen Rupp.
If I take a look now, fourth is set to Galen Rupp, which is actually the third element.
So I could add another comma to get the fourth element.
And now fourth is set to Girmay Gebrselassie.
And another thing we can do is actually use the rest dot, dot, dot inside of our structuring between
the array races in order to collect the rest of an array into a new variable.
I could make a variable called winner to get Eliot Kipchoge and then everything else.
All the other five strings in this array could be collected into a new variable.
It would look like this constant winner comma and then dot, dot, dot.
Let's go with others.
It's not the best name.
It's kind of minimizing their accomplishments, the winner and then the others.
Meanwhile, all these people ran like two, two hour, ten minute marathons or faster.
But let's just go with others.
Race results.
And we'll have winner set to Elliott Kipchoge and others is an array of five elements, the other five
in that array and I could combine these so if I wanted to skip for some reason, if I use Lisa now,
others is going to contain four elements and we didn't capture the face of the LISA in a variable at
all, so I'll undo that.
But that's pretty much it for D structuring arrays.
You just come up with variable names, you assign them in one line like I have here, and you could
break it up if there's a super long line, but most of the time it fits in one line.
You set it equal to whatever array you're trying to unpack, and then you single out the elements you
want based off of the position.
You can use commas to skip elements and you can use dot, dot, dot, the rest operator to collect the
remaining or the rest of the array into a variable.