Next up, we'll see that we can use D structuring to unpack values from an object into standalone variables,
just like we could for an array.
But the main difference is that in an array we would unpack based off of position the index.
So the first variable would be the first element, second would be the second, and so on.
In an object we make the variables based off of the name of the property.
So here's an example.
I have an object called Runner.
I'm still going with the marathon theme we've got.
First is Elliot, last name is Kipchoge, country is Kenya and title.
This is pretty crazy.
I was checking out his Wikipedia page and he had this after his name.
Elder of the Order of the Golden Heart of Kenya.
That's a pretty awesome title.
It's a little long, but pretty cool.
If I wanted to create variables for, let's say, first and last, all I need to do is follow the same
pattern where instead of an array bracket, I use object curly braces and I'll set it equal to runner.
And then I single out the properties that I want.
The order doesn't matter at all.
It's just the name that matters.
First and last.
Let's run the code and we'll see that first is set to Elliot and last is set to Kipchoge.
So if it finds this property based off of that name, it will take the value and store it in a variable
with the same name.
So first and last we're both found and runner is unchanged.
It's still the same object.
We could also try something like How about time?
Which is not in this object?
What do you think time will be set to?
Undefined.
So no error.
We just made a new variable called time.
It still made the variable.
It's just set to undefined.
With what we've seen so far.
The variable names must be existing key names in the object, but we can give them new names if we wanted
to.
I'll do something similar.
Let's try const and let's grab the country, but instead save it to a variable called nation.
To do that, it looks like this country colon nation equals runner.
So this will make a variable called nation based off of the value found in country.
If we take a look at nation now, if I run my code over here, it's set to Kenya so I could try one
more.
Let's also do title.
What would be another name we might want to use instead of title?
I think this is also called an honorific, so we'll go with that title.
But we want to make a variable named called honorific.
Okay.
So fine title in this object if you do find it and then make a variable with that value called honorific,
let's run it.
We've got honorific over here.
Yep we do.
So title is not a variable.
Neither is country.
We just use those keys to access data from runner in a super nice short syntax.
The one other thing that I'll show you here with objects at least is that we can use the rest operator
just like we did with arrays.
I could single out country or first or last and then collect everything else in a new variable.
So I'll just do const first, last, and then dot, dot, dot others again.
Or just other equals runner.
I'll save.
Refresh the page.
So we still have first.
We have last, but now I have a variable called other which contains the other two properties we didn't
claim.
We didn't unpack them into their own variable, so we put them in the other variable thanks to rest.
If I left the dot dot dot off, it's a totally different meaning.
It's trying to find a value or a key rather in runner called other, but that doesn't exist.
All right.
So that's the basics of object structuring, similar to arrays, similar concept.
But rather than using position, we're using the property name to de structure to unpack.