Next up, sticking with the structuring, I'd like to show you how we can work with nested objects and
arrays and combine what we've seen so far to extract individual values into variables to unpack them.
So I have an array of objects still going with the marathon theme.
So each object is a marathon runner and they are ordered still by finishing position.
So we have gold, silver and bronze from the 2016 Olympic Marathon, the men's marathon.
If I wanted to extract, let's say, the country of second place right here, Ethiopia using D structuring,
I'm inside of an array.
So I'm going to start with the array braces.
I'm going to set the whole thing equal to results.
And in this array I want the second element.
So I'm going to skip the first one and then I'm now in the second element or I'm in that position and
we have an object.
So inside of that object I want country.
It's kind of annoying that my editor is putting it on multiple lines, so I'll leave it like this so
you can see it here.
If I run it right now, let's see what we get in country.
We get Ethiopia.
So this comma is crucial.
We're skipping that first element.
If I wanted to extract something from that first object.
Let's say I wanted to get first name, which is Eliot.
So I'll write first.
And if I want to give it a different name or a different variable name, let's go with gold winner.
I'll refresh and I'll look at gold winner.
It said to Eliot and our country variable is still set to Ethiopia.
So the point here is just to show you that we can combine the syntax, it can get a little crazy.
And I don't recommend nesting and doing a whole bunch of structuring with nested structures.
Instead, if you have like super nested stuff, I think it's a lot easier to understand what's going
on.
If so, rather than getting country this way, maybe it would be easier to understand if we did const
skip the first element and then go with silver medal equals results and then from inside of silver metal
we could extract country.
So it's an extra line, but some might say it's easier to read.
This isn't bad, but if you had more nesting that you were trying to work with and continue to structure
from, let's say, instead of country, we had an array.
Maybe someone is from multiple countries or they've competed for multiple countries before and we wanted
to extract something or unpack a value from there.
Then we would have another array and it just gets complicated to the structure from.
So just keep that in mind.
You can nest it.
That's it.
I'm done.