There's one more place you'll often see the structuring used, which is inside of a function definition
where the parameters are listed.
We can use the syntax, the same D structuring syntax we've seen to de structure an array or an object.
But if we put it inside the parentheses of a function definition, what this will do is extract or unpack
values from the arguments passed in.
So what I'm doing here is saying I'm expecting full name to be passed an object, hence the curly braces.
And I only really care about first and last.
So the object could contain a whole bunch of other things.
But I'm only going to extract first and last and use them.
So let's try it out.
We'll define a function.
We can use an arrow function, a regular function expression, a function declaration.
It doesn't matter.
Let's go with function prints.
How about just print?
And rather than just accepting a person.
Like this and then extracting the parts we want from person.
If we're going to print out something along the lines of Let's go with first, last and then title.
So if we pass this runner in, we would get Eliot Kipchoge, the elder of the order of the golden heart
of Kenya.
So we could de structure first, last and title from person contact first last title.
Oops, title equals person and then console.log here and I'll use a string template literal to display
first and then a space and then last comma and then title.
And this should work.
If I run print runner.
There we go.
Elliott Kipchoge comma elder of the Order of the Golden Heart of Kenya.
But if I wanted to instead de structure the object right here, I can shorten my code up significantly.
So I'm going to duplicate this and comment out the original and get rid of this line entirely and instead
de structure right here.
So when the data is passed in, we'll just grab the parts we want.
We'll unpack first, last and title.
We don't need the rest of the object here.
We have person so we could access country if we needed to or let's say there was 50 other properties,
we would have access to them in here.
But if all we need is these three, then why not de structure them?
Just make it cleaner.
Now if I run this code, it still should work.
Print runner we get the exact same output.
So that's pretty much that, at least for objects, we can do the same thing with arrays and I'll do
a slightly different example here.
I have an array that could represent a HTTP response.
If you're not super familiar with HTTP, don't worry.
Some frameworks and some some technologies will represent a response from a website as an array, and
each line of the response will be represented as one element.
And if I wanted to write a function that used the status code, which is the second element, what I
could do is define my function.
Let's go with parse response or something and let's de structure this element out of response.
So this is an array.
If I'm expecting an array to be passed in, I could grab each individual piece right here.
So this first element, let's call that protocol.
The second element would be status code and the third element would be content type.
Now inside of here, I have access to those pieces.
And let's just print status code.
Let's do status colon.
Status code.
And if I run parse response, whoops, parse response and I pass in my response.
Let me open this up a bit.
We get 200 OC, so we're d structuring in the exact same way when a value is passed in.
This is expecting an array to be passed in and we are unpacking all three elements or the first three.
If there were more, we would be ignoring them versus up here.
We're doing the same thing, but with an object and we're unpacking based off of the property name.
So you'll see this often, far more often with objects, definitely, where you just need one or two
pieces of the object.
Or more than that, it's fine, but you don't need every single thing and it's just a nice way to shorten
your functions up, make things cleaner, and not have to declare variables in the function.
You can just grab them in the definition when an argument is passed in and that's pretty much it for
DE Structuring a really versatile new feature.
You'll see it a lot in the real world as well, and I'm going to be quiet.