All right.
So now that we've seen a bit about prototypes, we are ready to move on to talking about basic object
oriented concepts in JavaScript.
So we have a lot to talk about, things like factory functions, constructor functions, the new class
keywords, constructors in a class, the new keyword, there's super inheritance, there's a lot of
stuff, but it all has to do with this one central idea, which is organizing our code, designing and
structuring our applications by breaking things up into distinct patterns of objects.
When I say patterns of objects can also think of recipes for objects.
So I have an example here.
This is a class that will be creating later on.
It's a little bit long.
It models a color.
Now that seems kind of stupid, but with colors we have so many different systems.
We have RGB colors where you can have a color like, I don't know this right here.
We also have hexadecimal colors.
I don't I don't know what the hexadecimal version of this color is.
I could just make something up f31 that is clearly not it vs code has given me a preview, but that
is another format for colors.
We also have HSL colors and HSL is is always tricky.
We have a number from 0 to 360 and then a percentage and another percentage.
And this gives me another format for colors.
Not to mention we also have Reba where we have an alpha channel for opacity, for how transparent a
color is from 0 to 1.
Now, a lot of the times when we're making colors or working with colors in the DOM, we frequently
may not need to translate between two.
Sometimes we would need to, but there are times where it would be easier if we had a color as HSL.
For example, if I want to find the opposite color of this color right here, it's pretty easy because
of this Hue channel.
So I don't want to go into too much detail, but we can take this hue and all you need to do is add
180 to it to figure out the opposite.
This is the saturation and the lightness, but all of the hue data is here versus RGV colors and hex
colors.
It's spread out across all of those different values.
So it's much, much more complicated to calculate an opposite color.
So I've made a class essentially a recipe for colors you pass in a name like Carat or Emerald, and
then our GB values, and we can easily translate between different colors.
So I have a color called nav color.
NAV color has a couple of different properties and it has some different methods.
If you look at these methods, things like opposite our GB, our GBR, so I could call nav color dot
GBA or let's do our GB and I get the GB representation.
But I could instead change that to Hex and I now have a hex color.
But what's more fun is that I can use it to find the opposite color.
I've added an opposite method.
So if I select that first H one, I'm selecting all of them.
I'm going to do it sort of in a hacky way.
Take the zero with one style background color and I set it equal to nav color dot and I'll just do an
RGB color.
All right.
So it gives me this orange color.
If I wanted to make this one the same color but slightly lighter, I could easily do it first by selecting
the correct H one and then calling the GBA method and passing in maybe 0.8 for the opacity.
Now I have a slightly lighter version, or I could keep going lighter.
I could do 0.5, or I could go with the opposite color opposite, which is another method I added,
which gives me an opposite hue across the color wheel, so orange to blue and it's all calculated using
these color values.
I also could go full saturation, which is another method I added I can't remember.
It's called full saturation, which will take the root orange color called carrot, I think, and make
it as saturated as possible.
As you can see there.
So there's many things we could do.
Point is that this color object for this carrot orange color has different values, that it's storing
different numbers and it has different methods, and they are grouped together in a repeatable reusable
object.
I made a second color here using the exact same pattern.
So this color, which I'm calling Emerald, has the same methods, but we get different results if I
use that color.
The variable name is logo color.
I'll clear this.
We run this code, but I instead use logo color, the name of that variable.
I now have that green and I could do the second H one and a slightly lighter version 0.7.
And it's lighter.
I could also do the opposite as we saw, and we get this purplish magenta ish color, the opposite on
the color wheel.
So the same pattern, the same recipe for a color, the same methods, the same properties, but they
have different values.
We get different results frequently.
So I could easily just have a bunch of functions and no objects whatsoever.
I could pass things around, which we've actually seen before back a couple of sections actually a while
ago when we were talking about this card deck example, I think this was in a section called The Secret
Life of Objects.
As part of an exercise I had, you create a function that returned an array representing a deck of cards,
so an array that had a bunch of objects where each one had a suit and a value.
So suit would be hearts and value would be, I don't know, five of hearts.
And then we'd have 52 of those objects in this array.
So we made a function to return that and it works fine.
I call it by calling initialized deck.
I'll run this code over here.
Refresh the page.
I can call initialize deck and I get a deck of cards back, but I have to save it to a variable.
So I'll call this DH or maybe deck one.
So I have that deck one if I want to shuffle it.
We made a function called shuffle.
Right now it's all in order for spades.
Four of clubs, four of hearts.
But I can turn it into a shuffle deck by calling the shuffle function.
So shuffle I have to pass in deck one.
And I get this shuffled deck, I can draw a card by calling the draw card function, but I have to pass
the deck in.
So this is fine.
This is what we started with back in that section.
But I made the point that it would be nice if we just had an easy way of making a new deck and it automatically
included the methods we wanted and the properties we wanted.
And we saw a way of doing that.
It looked like this right here.
I'll run it and show you.
We have a method called Make Deck and I save that to a variable.
I'll call this deck one equals make deck.
If we look at deck one, it now contains a whole bunch of methods draw card, draw, multiple, initialize
deck shuffle.
It has a deck here itself.
It's empty right now.
But if I called deck one dot initialized deck, now we look at deck one.
It's been updated.
All the values are in that deck array.
I can easily shuffle it.
I don't have to pass anything around.
I can call deck one dot draw card and all of my code is organized for all the values, the information
and the functions are organized in this one deck object.
And I can repeat it.
I could have a second deck.
If I was playing a different game.
I would just call, make deck and save it to another variable cost deck two.
And this is the basic pattern that we're going for, but we'll see some shortcomings with the approach
that we learned originally.
But this idea of having a repeatable recipe for other objects to be created based off of is central
to everything we'll see in this section.
And we've seen this before in a bunch of different contexts.
When we learned how to make Xlsx, which are XML HTTP requests, we ran this code new XML HTTP request,
save that to a variable like req request that made us an object with a bunch of different properties
and methods already baked in this line of code right here.
We haven't talked about this new keyword, but we'll get there.
But the key takeaway here is that we end up with this pattern.
Every time I make a new request, I end up with an object.
It may eventually have different values instead of just null everywhere, but it's the same pattern.
They're cut from the same cookie cutter, same thing with Dom stuff.
When we select an H one document query selector, just the first H one that h one.
If I do a console, dear, I forgot about that.
Let's take a look at that line there.
It's an object and it has the same properties we've come to expect, and that's because it is cut from
the same cookie cutter that all other heading elements are.
It's called the HTML heading element.
It is a recipe to make an object like this.
So I think I'm going on and on about this.
If you're already familiar with EOP, this idea of creating these classes or these object templates
that contain a definition of the properties and the methods for a given instance of that recipe or class,
this will all seem very basic and repetitive, but if you're new to this, it can be a little bit tricky
to wrap your head around up front.
So we're going to take it slow.
I'm going to start with one approach called a factory function, and I'll explain how it works and what
is not so great about it.
So that's coming up next.