All right.
It's called Hex.
We could call.
It simply takes some RTB value.
So three arguments we passed in.
Let's go with 255 125 that will spit back to us a hexadecimal color that looks like that.
So if I put this in my VTS code, you can see the color there.
It's an orange color.
And if I wrote the correct GB string just so we can double check.
It needs to be GB and then 255 125.
It's the same color, at least according to VTS code.
So we have this function.
I could also write another function to take three numbers like we have here RG and B and actually return
a valid GB string for use in CCIS.
I could just call that function GB.
It accepts our G and B and then it returns a template literal where we have our GB and then dollar sign
r comma dollars dollar sign B, comma dollar sign C.
And that should be it.
Let's make sure that works.
If I use the same values, but I call GB instead.
That's the name of our function which the VTS code extension is actually already giving me a preview
of.
Oh, this should be g.
Not sure where c came from if I tried running this.
All right, we get our string.
Okay.
So we have two different functions.
They are perfectly fine on their own, as is.
But if I wanted to make a nice little object where I can convert back and forth from GB to hex without
having to pass in numbers each time.
Kind of what I showed you in the last video, I could use a factory function which would make me an
object that automatically had a hex method and an RTP method and it stored the ARG and v values as values
or properties on the object.
So we could just make a function function and give it a name like colour, make or make colour.
And we would pass in R, G and B and then in here I could make a new object const color equals an empty
object.
I'm going to add some stuff into that, but at the end I'll return color so I could say color r equals
r, color g equals g, color dot B equals B.
Those are the values that were passed in.
So I would use this if I run the code by calling make color pass in some numbers like 30 5255255 and
then I get back this object r 30 5g255b255.
Now I could add in a method on this object color dot.
Let's go with our GB equals a function.
So I'm building up an object, hence the term factory.
We pass in some values and this factory makes us an object and returns it at the end so that I can use
it.
Okay.
So color ruby equals.
And then I'll basically copy this.
But instead of GB are B and g.
I just realized they're in the wrong order.
Are g b.
But instead of doing this in hard coding it, I'm going to use the keyword this which we also saw back
in that secret life of object section, the keyword this in this context, if I were to call first color
const, first color equals and then make color, I pass in some numbers three, five, two, five,
five and 150.
If I call first color GB in this method our GB right here, the value of this will refer to this object
to the left of the dot.
So if I use this, I can access this dot r, this dot g and if I just console.log this.
Just to give you a refresher, because that section was a while ago, I'll comment that line out.
We're simply printing this inside of this method.
So if I call make color some numbers three five, 150, 140.
Save that to a variable.
I'll call it C and I call C GB.
You can see that this is set to the same color object to C, so it has access to our G and B via this.
So what I would do is probably extract or D structure from this are G and B instead of having to create
my string and access to this are this dot G and this dot B, it gets kind of annoying.
So instead we can leave this as is.
And now the structure from this.
Let's see if it works.
I have this first color.
All access first colour.
JB and I have an R GB string.
I could also add in a hex function like we saw earlier, so I'll just paste it in and then I'll adapt
it.
I'm going to write color hex equals a function.
No arguments necessary unlike here where I have to pass them in each time to the function by storing
these methods on an object.
I'm calling it color here, but I'm returning it at the end.
The name doesn't matter, but because I store the methods on the object and that object also contains
the arg and V properties, I can access them just like I did here.
So I'm just going to repeat this line to extract or D structure.
RG And B from this just like in this function here, this referred to this color object, this entire
object we've been adding on to as long as I'm calling it like first color dot, GB or hex, just like
we would call some array dot push.
Right.
The dot is very important here.
We're not calling push and passing in the array.
We're not calling hex and passing in some numbers.
We're calling some colored dot hex.
We don't provide arguments.
It looks on this object.
So I could have another color, you know, I could have purple dot GB Purple Hex.
All right, so this should work.
Let's make sure the math doesn't matter whatsoever.
It's not the point.
I don't even want to take time to explain it honestly, because I haven't even looked at how it works.
I know that it's going to convert to base 16 at some point, I think.
Yeah, it's doing that right here, but really it does not matter to this video.
All right.
So it returns that.
Let's make sure it works.
I call first color dot hex.
There we go.
First color GB.
And I could also change the R value or the G value at any point.
I could say R is now going to be two, five, five full are.
Full red.
And now if I look at first color GB, it reflects that change.
So it may not be the most useful object on earth, but it can be nice because if you do have these color
values, working with them, converting them can suck.
And later on we'll add some more useful methods, like a light and method or a darken or a saturation.
All those different things opposite color.
Anyway, the focus here is on this function.
This function makes us an object.
It starts empty, but then we add some properties based off of arguments that we were provided.
Then we add some methods and then we return that object.
This is called a factory function and it does work.
This is one way of making objects based off of a pattern or a recipe.
We've defined a recipe for a color we call make color.
We pass in three numbers and we get back an object.
And that object contains a whole bunch of things.
Well, a whole bunch is an exaggeration.
It contains three properties that are numbers and then two methods.
And I could make another color, right?
Make color where let's say it's 000, same pattern, different values.
I get different outcomes from the methods, but the same pattern in general.
But this is actually not the main way most people create objects based off of a pattern.
This is not how people like to do it.
And to understand why, we're going to have to talk about our friend prototype in the next video and
we'll see a better approach.
So there's nothing wrong with this.
It's just not as ideal as it could be.
So we'll see another option.
Just hang in there.
So that's coming up.