Next up, we're going to talk about why this pattern, a factory function is not commonly used and why
instead we use something called the constructor pattern or constructor function.
So let's start with what you probably have seen at this point.
We've seen this new keyword occasionally, like new XML HTTP request.
I hate typing this, but we run this.
If we need to make an XML HTTP request, we're not using fetch, we're not using Axios.
Check out the request section if you're not sure what the heck I'm talking about.
This makes us a new object following a pattern.
Also, we can make an array with this syntax.
New array.
It's definitely lengthier.
It's not not commonly used at all.
You could do new string.
Notice I'm using capital letters.
What is that new keyword?
It's actually an operator.
And we'll get to it and we'll talk about why it's preferable to this approach.
But let's start with understanding the shortcoming here.
It's not a huge one, but it's important to understand.
Every time I make a new color object, we start with an empty object.
We have three unique properties right there, added directly to the object that makes sense.
But then these functions, they're recreated and a unique copy is added to each color object.
So each color object has its own RTB function.
Yeah.
The values are going to always be different.
Assuming that the colors are different, we have different RG and BS, we can end up with a different
result, but there's no reason to have a unique copy of the function itself.
Just like if we were to write a regular function called RTB out here function RTB, we could re-use
that with any inputs.
We don't need to have function RTB two and RTB three and RTB for any time.
We want to pass in different values.
We just make one function.
That is not what's happening here.
And I can show you that I have two colors I've created using make color.
I have first color and I have black.
They have different values that I passed in.
So we get different objects, right?
We have black where RG and B are 000 and we have first color, not a very original name.
35 255 150.
Notice they have their own copy.
Well, it looks like they have their own copy of Hex and RTB and we could verify that in a bunch of
different ways.
The simplest would be if we compare Black Dot, let's take Hex and compare it to first color dot hex.
They are not equal.
Triple equals for a reference type is going to check and functions our reference types as a reminder.
It will check to see if they are referring to the same function in this case and they are not.
But if we compare that to something like a string, any string.
Hi Dot.
What's a good method to use?
How about we use dot slice?
I'm not going to call it just hi slice.
Triple equals by slice.
Two different strings.
Notice that we get true.
Hmm.
What's happening here is that the slice method is not defined on every single string.
Or if I had worked with an array.
You know, if we look at some array.
One, two, three, four, the methods are not defined in this individual object.
Arrays are objects.
A weird part of JavaScript.
They are considered objects.
Instead, they are defined on the prototype.
Remember, we started this section off with prototypes.
Every array gets its built in array methods from one prototype array object.
This contains all of the methods and functionality that we're used to using a radar pop array that can
cat.
Same thing with strings.
The string prototype contains the methods.
So instead of having their own copy, this array does not have its own copy of pop.
This string does not have its own copy of slice there referencing one function and it's located on the
prototype.
With what we've set up here, we don't have an easy way of making that work.
So this is where the constructor function enters.
A constructor function is kind of a it's kind of a weird part of JavaScript, honestly.
It's pretty different than most other programming languages I've worked with.
But don't let that scare you.
It's not too bad.
If we go to MSDN, there's a nice little explanation of this new operator, which we will use.
But first, take a look at this code right here.
We have a function.
It's starting with a capital letter, which is just a style choice.
But inside the function, there's never a return value.
And we're referencing this directly in the function.
We're not in an object like we had here.
Right?
We created an object color and we reference this inside that object on a method.
Here, it's just a function.
This dot make equals something, this dot model.
What is going on?
Well, let's try it out.
So on the docks we had a function and it had a capital letter, which is really just a way of indicating
that this isn't a regular function.
It is a function that helps you create objects.
It's a constructor.
Function.
Color.
We pass in R, G and B, and then what they did on N was this dot r equals R, this g equals G and this
dot B equals B.
Okay.
Well, let's see what happens when I call color.
When they come over here, refresh my page.
I'm going to execute color and pass it in and I'll just do 2550 and zero.
I didn't get anything back.
It doesn't appear to be working.
If I save that to a variable, I would just see undefined.
What if we print out this, console.log this and let's print it out at the end after we've added those
properties?
RG And B, what do you think this is going to refer to?
Who refers to the window.
Why is that?
Well, if you remember back in the Secret Life of Object Section, we talked about the key word this
and how it behaves in the scope of this function.
It's not inside of any other object.
This is going to refer to the global scope, the nearest object, which is the window object.
So then why on earth would the docs talk about making a function like this and referring to this in
your function, not returning anything?
Well, the secret is this new operator.
When we call this function, but we call it with new before the function, call it behaves differently.
These are the steps.
I guess I'll just copy these over and show them to you here.
When we call this color function with new new color and then we pass in values to five, five, 40 and
100.
Just like that, it's going to create a blank plane JavaScript object.
It sets the constructor of this object to another object we'll come back to that passes the newly created
object from step one as the this in this context.
So it's going to make us a new object and it will set this to that new object.
So we'll be adding our G and B to that new object.
Then it returns this at the end.
So it's kind of doing what we saw earlier concert, let's just call it O equals an object and then this
would be referring to this object and then it adds these properties to that object and then at the end
it would return.
Oh, but it's doing it all implicitly behind the scenes for us.
This behaves differently here than it normally does.
As we saw, if we don't use a new keyword, this refers to the window object.
But when we use new, it's just how JavaScript works.
It's the magic of this operator.
It will be used to create a new object for you based off of this pattern.
So why don't we try it now?
I'm going to copy this over.
Go back to my code.
Refresh if we just call color like that.
Not good if we call it with new.
All right.
Take a look at this.
We get an object and this object has properties on it that we assigned using this.
I never told it to make an object explicitly and never said return an object.
It did that and it did something else.
If we look under a pro here, it has a constructor property set to color.
That was the first or the second thing links or it sets the constructor of the object to another object
using whatever we named this function.
So it sets the constructor to this color function.
What this allows us to do is now we can add methods not to the individual objects, not to the instances,
but to the prototype.
So if I copied what we did earlier, like this RGV method and I put it in here, I'll have to uncomment
some of this and fix it up.
We would have something like this GB equals that function and we can access this.
It should work fine.
This is not new.
This is kind of what we saw earlier.
Let's see what happens when I call new color again.
Instead of color, it still has to be defined on the individual object.
It's not defined on the prototype, but we have a workaround.
Rather than doing this, we would define that method on the prototype.
Outside of this constructor function, it's kind of odd, but that's how it works.
We call color dot prototype dot RGB equals this function.
So it's a little clunkier.
But we saw the syntax already.
We saw how we could change a prototype pop and overwrite it to be some other function that did nothing.
Same idea.
So we have now made this constructor function for color.
Any time we call it with a new keyword, it makes us a new object.
It sets the constructor to color of that object, and then it sets the value of this to that new empty
object.
We can add properties to it.
It returns that object.
So if I call new color 40, 50, 60, I save that to a variable cost color one.
I now have an object here that has RG and B, but not only that, if we take a look at color one.
It does not have that method rugby defined on itself.
On the actual object, it's defined on the prototype.
So I can still call colour one GB, which is the very important part.
If we couldn't, then it wouldn't be worth doing.
But I don't have a unique copy of it here.
I can still access it from the prototype object, just like with an array or a string.
So this is now better or more efficient than our factory approach where we returned a new object every
time it was called.
And on that object we added in individual methods that were unique each time.
Now I could have two colors color one and color two.
They could be totally different.
This one could be 0000.
And why don't I add in a second method, we'll do color dot prototype hex equals function.
And I'll just copy the code from right here.
Have to tweak it a bit.
Don't need that.
Uncomment you.
Save and everything else should work.
We still have access to this inside of these functions.
This will be set to whatever is on the left side of that dot.
So color one dot hex color one will be the value of this.
If I do color two, color two will be the value of this, even though the function is defined as a method
on the prototype.
So let's verify that color one dot hex is the same as color to hex because they are on the shared prototype
object rather than uniquely defined on each instance.
So we've defined a recipe for a color.
We've said every color will have this one prototype that has ruby and hex, and we need one copy and
one copy only of those methods.
Let's test it out.
So we have color one I can still call hex color to hex.
I get different results because the value of this is different inside those methods.
But then if I call color one hex triple equals color to hex hallelujah.
It's true.
They're pointing to the same thing and we can verify that.
Also, just open up this object here in the DevTools.
We don't see Hex and RTB defined here.
They're defined on the prototype.
So a key distinction from what we saw earlier.
All right.
So why don't we end by adding one more method in this method will be our GBA, which I could call by
color one GBA and I can pass in a number from 0 to 1 like 0.5.
And this should give me an RGB color or an RGB a color which follows the same pattern here, but it
has a fourth channel, a alpha which is in charge of opacity.
So I would define color dot prototype, dot g be a equals function.
And while I'm doing this, an important thing to note, you don't want to use arrow functions for this.
Remember that they behave differently with the keyword this so you can run into trouble.
So use traditional standard function expressions like I'm doing here so we could duplicate this line
to get our G and B.
We also want the parameter for the Alpha Channel.
And why don't we give it a default of one?
If nobody or if it's not passed in, we'll just do a full regular color.
It won't have any translucent alpha will be 1.0.
Then we have to return our string template literal and it should be rg b a and then we interpolate.
Are we interpolate g, we interpolate be forgot the dollar sign and then finally we interpolate a and
we also need the closing perron.
So let's test it out here.
We've got color one.
Let's see what color one looks like.
I don't even know.
Color one dot B gives us this color.
Is it at all interesting?
I'm just going to paste it in here.
It's pretty ugly.
Why don't we change that to be much?
How about much greener?
We'll try again.
Color one GB gives us this.
Let's take a look.
Okay.
Very bright green.
Now, if I want to use that somewhere, let's just do document dot body dot style background color equals
and I'll use color one GB There we go.
Pretty green.
Now let's try our GBA method.
It has a default parameter so it should be the exact same color.
But now if I pass in a number like 0.80, it's getting more translucent.
Let's go down to 0.4, 0.2, 0.1.
There we go.
So we've made this one method to find on the color prototype and it works across any instances of color,
any time we ran new color.
That's the main takeaway here.
The new keyword does these mysterious operations.
It's very confusing when you're starting out because if you look at this function on its own, it seems
like it shouldn't really do anything.
It doesn't ever make an object.
It doesn't ever return anything.
But you put that new keyword in front when you execute the function and it changes how it behaves entirely.
And then we saw that we can add methods to the color prototype so that they are only defined one time
rather than on each individual color like we had up here.
So as you can see, the syntax is kind of annoying and it leads to these long files where things aren't
really grouped together.
Right.
We have our color definition here, but then all of the methods are defined separately.
This is why the class keyword and the new class syntax which introduced, which is what we'll see right
after this.
Another way of achieving the exact same outcome, but a prettier syntax.