All right.
So next up, we're going to see an even better way of replicating the exact same functionality, creating
a template for a color.
In our case, where we have different properties like our G and B that are numbers in this case, and
then we also add methods that are on the color prototype.
So there is only one copy of them across all instances of that color.
And this better option is the new class syntax.
So it is just syntactic sugar for exactly what we've been doing.
Syntactic sugar, remember, is just like a cleaner, cuter way of writing something that behind the
scenes is going to turn into what we already have here.
So you still have to understand prototypes and the keyword this.
But I'm going to show you how we could rewrite this as a single class.
And the main benefit, in my opinion, is that we don't have to add methods to the prototype manually
like we have here.
We don't have to break up the constructor function and then separately add methods.
I hate doing that because you end up with this nice little compact function that explains the properties
of your object and then you realize, Oh, wait, no, there's all these other properties.
They're on the prototype, so they're defined separately and individually like this.
It just is kind of clunky.
So let's see the alternative comment this out and you'll have to hang in there with a bit of this syntax
up front.
So we have a keyword called class and then I can give my class a name.
And typically we use an uppercase letter to indicate that it is a class or a constructor function.
It is a pattern for some sort of object, just like we have XML http request where the x is uppercase
normally in JavaScript for a function name, you know, document query selector, we don't capitalize
the Q, but we do when we are creating classes or constructor functions.
So this gives us a class next.
Probably the most confusing part for beginners.
We always add in a constructor.
Now a constructor is a function that will execute immediately whenever a new color is created.
So it's kind of like this constructor function here.
So we would add in three arguments.
And if I called this, we'll console.log our G and B and maybe also console.log inside constructor like
that.
If I create a new color, we have to use the same syntax we've already seen.
New color.
Save it to a variable const what should we call it?
C one very boring pass in some numbers.
Two, five, five, six, seven, eight, nine.
And if I tried running this in my browser refresh.
You can see my inside constructor console.log ran immediately and I have RG and B print it out.
So those arguments are passed through.
So I never said run the constructor, I never called constructor or anything like that.
It automatically runs as long as it's name constructor.
So that is a must have.
Whenever you define a class, you have to have the class keyword.
You need to have the constructor which will run immediately.
Whenever we instantiate a new instance of color or whatever the class is, XML, HTTP request or the
dog class or the alert class or button class.
You have to call it with new.
And you need to have a constructor there.
So usually in the constructor, we're going to access this this dot a or this R equals R, this dot
B equals B and this dot g equals G.
So these are going to be added as properties on this color object that we get returned.
Just like we had this here and our constructor function.
Same idea.
This will automatically refer to a new object.
So when we call new color, it still follows those same steps.
Even though it's in a class, it's going to make a new empty object and it sets the value of this to
that object.
So this dot R will be whatever is passed in as ah, this dot B will be whatever is passed into B and
G.
The order doesn't matter, but it's driving me crazy to have B before g, so I would probably change
that up, but it won't change anything.
Let's also add in a name for the color.
We can do that last maybe this name equals and then this could be a name to describe the color.
So this name equals whatever name was passed in.
And you can change these.
They don't have to match.
Right?
We could have name and name it as color name instead.
But this is the property we are adding to the object and typically we use the exact same name.
It's very common to see that.
So as far as a name for this color, what even is this color?
Let's just take a look using VTS code here.
Let's just put RWB in front of that.
Okay.
It's a reddish color.
We'll call that tomato, so we'll pass that in tomato as a string.
Like that.
Okay.
So let's look at this.
See one?
When I run the code, see one?
It's an object.
It has a, B, a G and name and an R.
They were all set in this constructor.
So I never made an empty object myself, just like I never did it here.
The new keyword takes care of that.
All I did was say on this new object that will be created for me, even though I am not ever seeing
it and it magically is stored in the value of this.
Add an AR property, set it to this argument or this parameter.
Are same for GB and name.
All right, now let's look at the proto for this color.
This object, you can see the constructor is set to color.
All right.
So we didn't do that either.
But by using new, it all takes care of it.
Now, what about methods?
This is the real advantage, in my opinion.
We don't have to do color, prototype, whatever like we did up here.
We could do something trivial.
Like, how about greets?
I don't know why a color would have greets.
The easiest way to do this is with this adorable syntax that we can use instead of classes.
We can actually use this instead of objects in general.
We talked about it in our objects.
What we call it Secret Life of Object Section.
It's a new shorthand syntax for defining a method.
And here I can just return.
Hello from a color.
And actually, why don't we include the color name from.
I'll need to make this a template.
Literal back ticks this dot name, and then we'll add an exclamation point at the end.
So this is now a method on every color, but not on the instances.
This is a nice part.
It's just like we had done this here.
Color dot prototype dot greet equals some function.
But we don't have to type prototype.
We don't have to type color.
We just put it inside this class so we can group everything together, which makes things much easier.
So let's try it.
We have this color one.
Let's open it up.
It does not have greet showing here.
Instead, greet is on the prototype.
There's only one copy of greet.
See one dot greet.
Let's execute it.
Hello from tomato.
Let's make a different color.
New color.
Let's do two, five, five, two, five, five, two, five, five.
And I think that's white.
Save that to a variable cost white.
Sure.
And call white dot greet.
Hello from White.
All right, so let's actually add in some methods that we would want, like an RGB method.
We can copy the logic from what we did earlier.
We'll just return this string.
But we need to make sure we get our G and B and we have access to those just like we did here by using
the keyword this.
So this.
Any time we're inside of a class, this refers to the instance of the class, the individual color object.
So not the prototype or anything, not the function, not the window, unless you're not using the new
keyword that is.
But if you use a new keyword, this will refer to the individual object.
And then whenever we have an object, a color like white, great white is a color object.
When we greet the keyword, this was used instead of greet.
I got rid of it.
But we had this name.
This referred to the individual object, the instance.
So we can do structure.
We could do this.
Ah, this G, this dot B or just D structure r, g and B from this.
Now, if I call it we have C one.
C one rugby gives me this nice rugby string.
Take a look when you get that reddish tomatoey color.
Let's add another method in.
Let's go with this hex method.
So I'm just going to copy the logic and add hex.
And that relies on our G and B, which we already have on the object.
So I'm going to do structure again.
Let's try that one out.
See one dot x.
And did we have another color white?
I think I define that and refresh the page.
So let's define another color over here.
Let's call this one red and then another one which will be white and just have two, five, five, two,
five, five, two, five, five.
Now I need to save that to a different variable white.
Okay.
So if we check here white dot X, we get Fefe.
That's accurate.
I do know that one hex color.
And then if we do red dot hex, we get a different outcome and if we compare them red hex, not execute
them, but compare the references triple equals white dot hex.
They are the same function because they're on the prototype.
They are not in the individual instance.
They are over here.
And let's add in our GBA as well.
Let's see, this was our GBA, we'll copy this logic, but I think I'm going to refactor this.
If we look at our GBA, it accepts a parameter called Alpha.
We set it to be 1.0 as a default value.
It returns something very similar to our GB.
This right here is the same thing.
We just have a added after the fact in our GBA and we have our GBA at the start and GB at the start
of our GB.
So we could make a separate function, maybe call it inner GB like that.
And all that I'll do there.
Nice and easy is return this part of the string.
So I'm just going to copy the whole thing over.
You'll see what I'm going for.
I'm just going to return this string.
No parens, just a comma separated list.
So it would look like two, five, five, comma, two, five, five, comma, two, five, five.
So if I called this from within another method, I could easily do our GBE and put perrins around that.
Or I could add in another number and do our GBA around that.
So I just made a method that is going to help me out.
It's called Inter GB and now we get the opportunity to talk about how we would call one of these methods
from within another instance method, another method on this class.
To do that we just reference this same thing so we could call this dot inter our GB.
That should give us a string that will go on the inside of our GB right here and I need to escape that
with my dollar sign curly braces.
Let's make sure that works for our GB.
Refresh the page white dot GB.
That looks good.
We can verify if we paste that down here.
It is white, at least according to VTS code.
Now we can rewrite our GBA to do the same thing.
So I can get rid of that and replace it with this dot.
Enter our GB and execute it.
It is a function and then we add our GB a open per n and then closing print at the end as well as comma
the alpha value.
So very similar because we're using the same function on the inside.
It just gives us a good opportunity to call a function from within or a method to be more accurate from
within another method on the class.
So does white GBA work?
And it's going to be quite boring.
Not as exciting as let's do red GBA.
There we go.
And if we try 0.4, we get a more transparent color.
We could do the same thing.
Document dot body dot style dot background color equals red dot gba.
This is the full strength of that red color.
And this is half strength.
This is a 10th of the strength.
Cool.
So we've added a couple of methods and we've covered most of the basics of classes so far.
You define a class with the class keyword, you usually capitalize that name.
You should always capitalize it, although you don't have to.
You should.
And then inside of those curly braces, the first thing we need to add is a constructor.
This function will run automatically whenever you instantiate a new instance of the class, so we don't
call it manually inside of that constructor and instead of the entire class, if we're in a method like
I have here constructor or down here, the keyword, this will refer to the individual object.
So this are this dot g, this dot be.
I'm assigning properties to each color, not to the prototype, but to the color.
Then these methods I've added, they are added to the prototype automatically.
So I don't have to do any of this color dot prototype.
Blah blah blah.
I can keep everything together inside this class.
I don't have to have the separate constructor function.
Then later add my methods.
I can put it all in one happy family and define my class.
Define my pattern for every color.
Every color has an R, G and B and a name.
And every color has these four methods, but they're located on the prototype.
They look up to that one prototype template object.
So we're going to continue to add on to our class in the next video.