Next up, we'll continue to add on to our color class so we can get more practice adding methods.
So I have a very long, complicated function I found online.
I did not write this.
This function converts a RGB color into a HSL color.
HSL is a very interesting color system.
It stands for hue, saturation and lightness, and it looks like this.
HSL And then we have a hue at the beginning from 0 to 360, like a degree around the color wheel.
So let's do 130 then we have saturation, which is a percentage, let's go with 50%.
And then we have lightness, which is also a percentage from 0 to 180%.
So that is the resulting color.
Apparently, if I change lightness to be 100%, it's extremely light.
If I go to 20%, it's a darker green.
Let's go to 40.
If I change saturation to 100%, it's very saturated.
If I go down to 10%, it is not at all saturated.
Let's go around 80.
And then Hue is interesting because I can completely change the value of that color, the hue of the
color by just affecting one value so I can do zero will give me red apparently if I do 80.
90.
100, 200, 300.
I'm making my way around the wheel all the way to 360 where I'm back to read so I can change the color
very easily.
I could make a more saturated color by impacting the second value, the saturation.
I could make a different value entirely.
I could go from red to the polar opposite by adding 180.
So if 30 is the hue, I add 180, but it's 180 plus 3210, which gives me this blue and I can easily
lighten something.
Well, 100% it will be white, but I could do 90% to get a very light blue, or I could darken it to
a very dark blue.
So let's make a function.
I already have the logic, but let's use it to create HSL values and let's actually store HS and L on
our class instances because we could reuse them for different functions.
If I want to make a light in function or a darker or a full saturation or something like that, I want
to use those HS and L values.
All right.
So here's the function.
It's called Calc HSL.
It expects three arguments, and at the end we have three variables.
They're not being returned, but we could return H, s and L as an array.
Maybe we can make a string.
This has nothing to do with the class at the moment.
I'm going to move this into my class.
I'll put it down at the bottom because it's so long and ugly.
And I don't want to pass in RJ and B, I have access to them on this.
So my constructor runs right RG and B are set based off of whatever I pass in.
If I ever call Calc HSL, RG and B will be on this, then what I'm going to do is actually assign a
channel to the object to the instance.
I'll do this.
H equals h.
H is calculated up here as is calculated in the same function.
Again, the logic does not matter.
I have not even glanced at it.
I just took it from a website.
What did I find?
This they come Stack Overflow.
But it does work.
Who knows how elegant it is, but it works.
So now channel exist on the individual instances as long as I call calc HSL.
So let's try it.
I have.
Why don't we go with the white one?
Because white is probably easiest for us to tell if it's working.
So I'm going to refresh this and call white dot calc HSL.
And if I just look at white to begin with, it only has four properties.
RG Be in name if I call white calc HSL Assignment two constant my bed.
I think I can't use const here because the way the function is written it is updating.
As you can see here, divide equals slash equals.
So I'll use lit and now we should pick it to go.
All right.
So we don't return anything.
But if we look at white, it now has H, s and L and lightness is set to 100, which makes sense as
we experimented with a couple of minutes ago.
Lightness of 100 gives us white.
So now let's make a function called HSL that will actually display the HSL correct format string.
And to start before I get there, I'm going to show you that we can call a function from within the
constructor.
We can call one of these methods like this Calc HSL.
We'll just call it immediately after we assign our job in name.
We'll call that function automatically.
Whenever you make a new color, we'll calculate the HSL based off of the RGB that was passed in that
we then added to the object this is called it looks up.
RG And B from the instance of the actual class, the instance that was just created and then it adds
on it, tags its own new properties onto that instance.
So let's make our function called just HSL and it will extract the structure HS and L from this.
And then we can return our template literal, which is going to be HSL.
We need parentheses.
Then we have the hue, which is not a percentage.
It goes from 0 to 360.
Then we have saturation, which is a percentage, so we need to add the percent.
Then we have lightness, which is also a percentage.
Let's see if that works.
Refresh over here we have our color white.
It was created and now it automatically has S and L properties and I should be able to call White HSL
and get a string.
Let's verify on a different color.
We have red.
Let's verify that it works.
Documents.
Body style.
Background color again.
Equals Red Dot HSL.
And it works.
Okay.
So now we could have a little bit of fun and define some other methods, like one that I'll show you.
We'll call opposite, which will take H and generate an opposite color.
Remember to color wheel from 0 to 360.
So I'll just add a method called opposite and we can start by just duplicating this.
We're going to want to use H, but we're also going to want to make a new H, new hue equals.
And what we'll do is add 180.
So if we had 60 before we add 180, if we had zero before we add 180, it's 180 degrees.
The other side directly across that circle, the color wheel.
But if we're above 180, then if we add another 180, like if we're at 200 and you add 180, we're suddenly
at 380.
So what we can then do is modulo by 360, which will take us back to 20.
If you're lost on the logic, don't worry too much.
It's not that important.
But we can do h plus 180, modulo 360 to keep us on that 360 degree wheel.
If we go too far, we just start back at zero.
All right.
So then here we would put new hue instead of the existing hue.
H Let's try it out.
So I'm going to refresh.
I'll run the same code red HSL.
Did I lose the line?
Here we go to update the body.
Now let's do red dot opposite, which gives us that color.
They are opposite on the color wheel, at least as far as the hue, the saturation and lightness are
still the same.
Let's do one last one.
Let's make one called full saturation.
And it's just going to have the existing hue, the existing lightness, but set saturation to 100 full
saturation or fully saturated.
All we need are H and L.
We don't care about saturation because we're always going to return saturation set to 100%.
Let's see if that one works.
So we'll set the background color to read HSL and then we'll update it to Fully Saturated.
And was it already at 100?
Well, that's disappointing.
It was already 100 saturation.
Let's try another example.
Here's a different color.
I'm giving it a name which I have been leaving off for the record, which is actually not the best idea.
So I should either add a default name, which I can do just like any other default parameter, or I
should just pass in a name like I did here.
Even though we're not using it anywhere, it's just good to have on there.
We don't want to have just undefined all over the place.
So let's save that to a variable const orange and then we'll do the same thing where we change the background
color, but we'll change it to Orange Dot, HSL or RGB.
It doesn't matter.
We should get the same thing.
It's not 100.
Now let's do full, saturated or fully saturated.
I don't know if you could see that, but it did change.
If you go back to RDB or Hex or any of these other ones, it's slightly duller now, fully saturated.
And how about opposite?
So be our last one.
Hey, nice, beautiful blue.
So this is our color class.
A lot of the logic to calculate the HSL to convert from RGB to HEX really doesn't matter.
Don't focus on that.
Focus on the interplay of the keyword.
This the idea of the constructor adding in values to this to the individual instance as properties calling
methods on this which allows us to access other methods in the same class and then using the new keyword
to instantiate new colors.