All right, we've made it.
We have one last important topic around classes in JavaScript.
It is the keyword extend along with a keyword called super.
They both have to do with subclasses, essentially inheritance.
This is a way of sharing functionality between classes.
So typically I would want to show something more realistic kind of what we did here.
This is nothing crazy, but I mean, I've used plenty of libraries that are color libraries.
They exist just to do this.
Some of them are more more fully featured.
But this is not totally unrealistic.
It's not the typical intro to classes idea of dog and cat or bank account or deck of cards.
It's something slightly better.
But for this video on inheritance and extends and subclasses and super I'm going to dial it down.
We're going to go back to the basics.
The most cliche possible classes.
Let's define a class called Cat.
I know.
And we'll pass in a name and an age.
How about that?
All right.
And then we'll set this name to be name and then this dot age.
To be age.
So the reason I'm going simple is so we can focus on the concepts and not get too bogged down in the
actual logic of things.
The logic here will be incredibly simple.
So a cat class and we'll have a simple method called eat.
And then here we will return the string.
Let's do this.
Name is eating.
Okay.
So I can make a new class or a new cat.
New cat?
Save it to a variable cost.
Monty equals new cat.
Monty, who is technically dead, but I'll say nine.
Let's look at Monty.
It has name of Monty, age of nine.
And I call Monty.
Monty is eating.
All right.
So now let's say I have another class.
This class is called dog.
Dog is very similar.
Surprise, surprise.
It's almost like I planned it that way.
That was stupid.
I don't know why I said that.
I'm sorry.
So a dog also has a name and an age.
We set this name to be name.
This dot age.
To be age.
It also has an eat method.
Let's just copy that.
Over.
Okay.
Let's make a dog.
So I'll call new dog.
I'll pass it in, Wyatt.
Cost.
Why?
It equals new dog in an age.
He's also dead.
Yikes.
We look at Wyatt.
It's an object.
Has a name and an age, and it has a method.
They're basically the same thing.
Just different names.
But we could go ahead and add some method to cat that doesn't exist on dog like meow.
And then it can just return meow.
And we could do the same thing for Dog.
We could have a method called bark which returns woof.
Okay.
So now they're slightly different, but there is a lot of duplicated functionality.
So one of the options we have in JavaScript is to move this duplicated code from here and from cat and
from dog into a separate standalone class that both of these classes could extend.
So you can think of it as kind of like a parent child relationship.
We could have a parent class, I'd call it probably animal or pet.
Let's do pet class pet.
And let's just copy this entire thing here like that and remove all of that from cat.
All of that from dog.
So right now, I'm not going to be able to make a new cat.
I won't be able to make a new dog.
I can make a new pet.
But if I try and rerun this code and make a new dog, let's look at why it is an empty object.
There's no constructor, no constructor on dog and no constructor on Cat.
So here is how we can tell Cat and Dog to include the functionality of PET to extend PET.
It's as simple as saying class cat extends PET.
I'll do the same thing for dog.
Class Dog extends pet.
So now does it work?
Well, let's see what happens when I make a new cat or a new dog.
All right.
I just made a new dog.
Look at that age and name, we're already filled out.
But I don't have a constructor in Dog.
It doesn't matter because I extended from PET.
It's going to use that constructor if it doesn't find one on my dog or on this dog class, which it
didn't.
So it looked to the constructor from Pet.
So we end up with age and name and take a look.
We also have bark bark, which is defined on dog.
And even more exciting, we have access to eat, which is not defined on dog at all.
So we don't see it here, right?
We don't see it there.
I don't see it here.
But if I look at this pro here and pro again, there we go.
So we have dog.
This is a functionality from dog which is just bark.
Then we have the functionality from PET, which is eat.
So I can call why it eat?
Even though I never defined eat on the dog class, we are extending the functionality from PET both
on cat and dog.
So I could do it again with a cat.
Let's just make that.
Monty, where are you?
Here we go.
We have Monty Dot.
Eat.
Not defined on cat.
Monty Meow is defined on Cat.
That's the basics.
A couple of other things that are important to note.
If I had another method on, let's say on dog, also called eat and this one returned, I need to use
a string template literal.
Something else like this name scarfs his food.
Like that.
And now I make a dog.
If we call Wyatt eat, which version of eat does it call?
It calls the dog version.
So if it doesn't find eat on dog on the dog prototype, it will look up on the pet prototype where it
does find it.
And if it didn't find it there, it would look on the object prototype.
If it didn't find it there, it's going to be unhappy and it will let you know.
So I'll leave that there so you can see how it works.
The other important keyword here that we haven't talked about yet is called super.
So sometimes you want to rely on the exact same constructor from your super class from PET.
In this case, Cat extends Pet.
We don't have a constructor.
But if I wanted to have some additional information for Cat, like I don't know what else could be passed
in.
Let's say you pass in a name and age and we want to pass in about lives left which will default to non.
Very good.
It's a cat nine lives.
And here I could manually set this dot name equals name.
This dot age equals age.
But I'm already doing that here.
So really all I want to do is set this dot lives left equals lives left.
And if I don't want to duplicate that, I can use the super keyword.
Super is going to reference the class that we are extending from.
So if I call super inside of here and I pass in name and age, it's going to call this constructor so
we can see this in action.
Let's cancel that log in Cat constructor and then duplicate this up here in Pet constructor.
And let's see what happens.
We'll make a new cat.
I'll pass in a number of lives.
Actually, I won't.
It will default to nine.
Take a look in Cat constructor.
In Pet constructor.
If we look at Monty, Monty has a name.
Monty, an age nine and lives left, was set to nine.
So we re-used the functionality from this constructor, but we added on our own for Cat.
So very important.
Super is going to be a reference to the superclass.
It can be confusing.
Definitely trips people up, but it's a reference to what we're extending from which is pet.
So we could do it.
We could use it instead of dog.
But just to save you time and not bore you to death.
We'll keep it simple here.
So this is a common pattern.
You have some basic class.
You have other classes that extend from it.
And in this case, if dog, we didn't add any new properties in, it's the exact same constructor as
Pet.
And that's fine.
It will call that constructor automatically if we don't define our own.
But in the case of Cat, which is common when we're building more realistic things, we have other data,
just a simple lives left, which we want to add on to this.
So we call super.
We can take advantage of this constructor and then add on lives left as well.
And that's the basics of inheritance.
I mean, you can continue to go multiple levels.
We could have pet extend from animal, we could have animal extend from living thing.
There's so many different things we could do.
And you'll see this with things like HTML element in the DOM that extends from like five or six different
classes.
But remember, when you extend something and when you define a class, it's all just setting up these
constructor functions and calling it with new and adding methods to the prototype.
So this is all just nice syntactic sugar.
OC.