All right.
So let's talk about our first loop, the for loop.
If you've never seen four loops before, buckle up.
The syntax is a little bit odd the first time you see it, but you'll use it so often that eventually
it just makes sense.
So this is a representation of the syntax, sort of the pattern.
I know it looks like a lot.
It looks very confusing, but let's take it step by step.
So a four loop is very similar to a conditional not in the way that it works, but in the syntax.
We have a conditional statement here.
We have if and then something in parentheses, and then a block of code enclosed by curly braces.
And whatever code I put in here will only run if this condition is true, this code is associated with
that.
If when we write a for loop, it's the same pattern we have for which is the keyword.
It has to be for not uppercase for not fo u r it needs to be f0r and then we have perrins and we'll
talk about what goes in there in just a moment.
And then we have curly braces, a code block, and whatever content is in here, we'll run every time
this loop repeats.
So if I loop ten times, this code is going to run ten times.
I'm not sure if that's how you pronounce that.
So what is the syntax?
What goes in here?
It's it's a little tricky to explain.
There are three separate pieces.
A lot of times people come to JavaScript or students who come from other languages ask, is there an
easy way to just run something ten times no matter what?
Some languages do have a really easy way to say, make this happen ten times.
Let's say I have console.log.
I want to console.log.
Hello?
Ten times without a loop.
The obvious way is to do this and that sucks.
And I think I'm only at nine times.
But there we go.
Ten times.
But this is obviously horrendous and this is only ten times we're running something.
But there are many situations if we have an array of 10,000 items or even 1000 items, each one is different.
If we had to write it by hand to print out each item in the array, that would be a nightmare.
We would do something like console.log array of zero and then manually array of one and array of two.
If we have even just 100, my fingers are going to fall off by the time I finished typing that out.
So we use loops, but a for loop is not as easy as saying make this happen ten times or 20 times.
There are three separate pieces.
The main idea behind a for loop is that we define a variable and this variable is like a counter.
It's a counter for that loop and we started at some value.
If I want to run something ten times, I'll just do ten total times.
I could start a variable at zero at one, I could start it at 50.
It doesn't really matter where it starts, at least in this case.
And then I define a stopping point.
So if I went from 50, I'm going to go upwards.
I'll say we'll stop when we hit 60, that would give me ten iterations.
And then the third step is what happens to this variable each time through.
So if we're trying to run ten times, I would say add one to the variable ten different times.
So there are three pieces the initial value when to run the loop and then how to change value each time.
This kind of looks like gibberish here.
So let's revisit our slide.
We have four and then in parens we will define a variable.
Let's say it starts at zero, then we'll say a condition.
And this condition is something like while that variable is less than ten, run this loop and then we
increment that variable by one or by two or by negative five.
It's up to us.
So here's a simple example.
We're going to define a variable in this loop.
That's the first piece.
The initial value for a variable.
Usually people will use the variable name I because it's short and it doesn't have to mean very much.
I think originally maybe it stood for index or integer.
It doesn't matter, but you'll see people use IJC.
You can name this whatever you want.
It's just a variable you're making.
Let's have it start.
Let's go with one.
We'll have it start at one and then we need a semicolon.
Then we have a second piece which tells JavaScript when this loop should continue running.
Four So we're going to run as long as AI is less than or equal to ten.
As soon as we're past ten, it should stop and then we tell it how to update I each time through the
loop.
It's pretty standard to do plus plus because a lot of the time you want to loop one number at a time,
one and then two and then three and then four.
But you could also do plus equals three.
This would loop by threes.
So we would start with one and then we add three.
So we get four and then we add three and we'd have seven, then we add three and we hit ten.
And then if you did it again.
We would get 13, at which point we're past this so it no longer runs.
But let's just add one each time using that nice shortcut.
Plus plus.
And we could start by simply console logging.
Hello.
Ten times.
I'm going to refresh my code over here.
Oh, so annoying that the chrome console does this.
It collects all those ten identical contact logs and displays them as one with the number ten next to
it.
So it did print out ten times.
It's just hard to see.
So why don't we also print out I?
So I'll just do a hello colon and then the variable I which is our loop variable, I'll refresh the
page and there we go.
So to step through this one more time, so make a variable.
I started at one, keep looping if I is less than or equal to ten and then add one to I each time through.
So I started at one that's less than ten.
So we're going to console.log I Which gives us hello one which is what we see here and then is incremented.
So I becomes two because we did plus plus is I still less than or equal to ten.
Yes, it is.
So we cancelled that log two.
So that's printed out.
Now I is going to be added one or have one added to it again till we get three.
This keeps going until I is nine, at which case we're still in the clear.
We add one, I becomes ten.
This is still true because we have less than or equal to ten.
So that's fine.
But then we print out hello ten.
After which I is incremented to 11 and then this is no longer true.
I is not less than or equal to ten.
11 is greater than ten.
So we are done with the loop.
So this loop is going to run ten times because of the way I set it up.
But if I instead said I starts at five, it only runs five times or six.
I can't do math because we're including ten.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
If I instead did I equals one.
But instead of I plus plus I did plus equals three.
I'll duplicate this.
So we have a record of the original.
I'm now going to increment by three.
Refresh the page and this is what we get four total times that it ran and the value of I was one for
seven and then ten.
Afterwards it became 13 and the loop stopped.
So if you feel comfortable with the syntax at this point, go ahead and move on.
We have more to talk about with four loops in the next couple of videos, but if you want some more
practice, I'll do a few more examples.
Let's generate the first 20 perfect squares.
Now a perfect square is just a number of times itself, so the first one is one times one.
Then we have two times two.
We have three times three, which is nine, four times 416 all the way up until 20 times 20.
So to print those out, I would need to loop from 1 to 20 and then console.log each number of times
itself.
So to loop from 1 to 20, we need to initialize a variable at one and we can name it.
Anything like I said, is very, very standard.
But just to prove it that it doesn't matter.
Let's go with NUM.
So we'll start at one.
NUM is one.
We'll continue while NUM is less than or equal to 20 or alternatively less than 21.
I like to do it this way.
If I know I want to include 20, I like to put less than or equals instead of this.
I don't know why it's an extra character.
Other people prefer it the other way around, but I'll do it this way, and each time through we will
add one to NUM.
So let's make sure we're generating the correct numbers by just constant logging each num 1 to 20.
Now we want to print the perfect square instead, which is num times num.
And I think I'm actually going to do a little string template literal so that I print something out
like four times four equals 16.
So I will interpolate here and display num and then x for multiplication and then interpolate again
with the dollar sign display num again.
Let's just see what we get now.
One times one, 20 times 20, and then I'm going to add my equal sign and then interpolate one more
time with the dollar sign and do my actual math.
Num num times num refresh the page.
Awesome.
One times one is 149 1625 all the way up to 400.
So this is looping in one direction.
We're going from a low number up to a higher number.
I'll also show that we can go the opposite direction.
So here's a loop where I starts at 50 and we subtract ten each time and we continue looping as long
as I is greater than or equal to zero.
So as long as it's positive or zero.
So 50 we subtract ten next time is 40 then 30 then 20 then.
Ten then zero then.
We're done.
So this is counting backwards and you can definitely do that.
We'll do one more example of that.
Let's comment this one out.
Let's count down from 200 and count down in intervals of 25.
So 201, 75, one, 51, 25, 100.
So we'll go back to using AI because that is the standard term, unless we have nested loops, in which
case you'll see we use other letters like J and K.
We're not going to start at zero.
We'll start at 200 if that's what we're going to do.
We'll loop while AI is greater than or equal to zero.
So not less than we definitely want.
Greater than if we have AI starting at 200 and we're saying run this loop while AI is less than zero.
It's never going to run because 200 is already greater than zero.
So if I tried that each time through, we will subtract 25.
Let's see what we get.
Console.log.
Does it work?
Refresh the page.
We don't get anything and that's because we wrote our loop in such a way that it's never true.
AI begins at 200 and this is checked.
Is 200 less than or equal to zero?
Nope.
So nothing happens.
We just move on to the next line.
So if I put this line down here after the loop, we would see that it is the only thing to run or the
only thing to print out.
So what I wanted to do was go from 200 down to zero.
So I want to go while AI is greater than or equal to zero.
I want to stop when I becomes negative and we'll subtract 25 each time.
Remember, this is a shorthand way of saying I equals I -25.
It's easier just to do minus equals 25.
Let's try it.
And instead of saying, does it work, let's just print out I.
And there we go.
201 75 150 all the way down until we hit zero, which is the last thing we print out the last AI, at
which point AI is zero.
We subtract 25, which gives us -25.
This is now false and we no longer print anything out and the code moves on and this runs instead.
So when we do have a loop like we have here, this code is going to keep running over and over and over
until the loop is false.
This condition is false and then whatever happens afterwards will run.
Okay, so for loops are a lot.
I know they're always a little tricky to teach to people who have never coded before.
Unfortunately, there's just a lot of there's not many moving pieces, but the syntax is kind of ugly.
Just remember the three pieces you're variable that you're using for the loop, usually called AI.
You give it some initial value.
Then the next part after semicolon is the condition that checks if the loop should continue running.
So the loop will run as long as this is true.
And then another semicolon and then whatever operation you're performing on, I usually adding or subtracting,
but you could also multiply, you could divide, you can do anything there.
But most of the time we're doing simple math and 99% of the stuff I do at least is adding one.
It's really, really common that you just want to add one to something, as we'll see when we work with
arrays and strings in just a video or two.
That's a lot.
I know.
Hopefully you're still there.
Good job.