Fruit Loops are great.
We use them a ton.
I'll show you a few more situations where we use them with strings, where we use them with arrays.
But first I want to talk about something that's not so great.
And this is true of many types of loops across all languages.
You can write infinite loops and an infinite loop is something you absolutely want to avoid.
Do not run this code.
It's not going to break your computer.
It's not going to set it on fire or crash anything but your window that you run it in on your browser
is going to be very unhappy and I might show you what happens.
I definitely have written many infinite loops accidentally and I'll talk about how that happens.
But the idea behind the infinite loop is that you write a loop where the ending condition is never met.
So the second part of your for loop in this case would always be true.
So here's an example.
I'm saying start at 20.
Add one to each time and run this loop.
While IE is greater than or equal to zero, it's always going to be greater than or equal to zero because
I'm always adding to I and it starts at 20.
So it will run on and on and on and on and on until either JavaScript freaks out or the browser freaks
out.
You'll see what happens.
I guess I'll show it to you.
I've committed to it at this point.
So you want to be careful about this when you're writing a for loop and especially when you write while
loops, which we'll cover next.
So let's try and create one an infinite loop.
Let's count, let's create an AI that starts at one and I'm going to add two to each time.
So maybe I'm trying to count two, four, six, eight and so on up until I hit 20.
So my condition, a poorly written condition would be run this when AI is not equal to 20.
But there's a problem here.
I'm starting at one, I'm adding two to it each time.
So we'll get three and then we'll get well, we'll get one, then three, then five, then seven.
We'll never have 20.
So it's always going to be not equal to 20.
We'll never hit 20.
We're counting on odd numbers because we start at one, so we blow right past it.
Oh, gosh, here we go.
I'm going to run it.
I'm being dramatic.
It's not that bad.
You can see what's happening here.
We've already hit 2903.
And did my browser stop?
Yeah.
Och, now it's lagging.
I can't scroll, I can't click, it's getting all jittery, it's just going to keep going.
And then eventually Chrome is going to ask me if I want to kill the process.
You might have seen that before.
If you're trying to open something intensive in the browser or page is being weird, a little window
pops up and says, Do you want to kill or wait on this web page?
I'll click kill when that eventually pops up and I'll be back in a bit.
Okay.
So eventually I killed it.
My computer is now very angry.
You can hear the fans going most likely through the microphone.
It got very warm because it's trying to do all these computations and there's no end in sight.
It just keeps going and going and going and going.
And that's not good behavior.
So infinite loops or something we want to avoid.
So in general, when you're doing a for loop, there's a couple of things to look out for before you
ever run the code.
The first is just pay attention and make sure you're going in the right direction.
This is a simple one, but if you're trying to count backwards from 200 or from 100, let I equals 100
and we'll decrement by one.
We want this code to run when AI is greater than or equal to zero.
But often, at least sometimes I do this.
I'm so used to doing I less than or equal to something that that's what I'll go with.
And that causes an infinite loop.
I usually catch myself, but it's just something to pay attention to make sure that if you're going
backwards or you're going forwards, whichever direction you're going, that your condition here is
appropriate.
And the other piece of advice that I have is that I would pretty much never use equality or non equality
in a for loop.
If you're working with numbers, it's much better to do greater than or less than because then we would
avoid a situation like this if I did want to count from three to 5 to 7 and I wanted to stop as soon
as we get past 20, it would just be better if I said, well, I is less than or equal to 20, because
even if we don't hit 20, exactly.
If we're starting at one, we add two, we'll end up with 19 and then we get to 21.
We skipped over 20, but the loop will still stop because this won't be true anymore.
So just two things.
Make sure you're going in the right direction.
Your logic makes sense here and generally try to avoid equality and non equality there.
I prefer to use greater than less than when I can, so I'm going to add a note here.
Don't run this.
This will cause an infinite loop.
I'll get rid of that one.
You probably will encounter an infinite loop or two, but at this point, hopefully you'll be able to
identify what's going on.
It will be very clear when your browser just starts freaking out at you and getting hot and jittery
and laggy, it happens.
It's nothing to be ashamed of, but it's definitely something you want to be on the lookout for and
try and prevent if you can.