We can also use for loops to loop or iterate over a string or an array.
We still generate numbers, but we generate the indices.
So for a string like lions, it's in an array here.
But if we're working with a string lions, we would start with an index of zero and generate IE up until
we hit 401234 and once we hit four, we're done.
And then we can use that index that I to access each character.
Or we could do it for an array, which is what I'm doing here.
We have three items in here.
We start with index of zero and we loop as long as the IE variable is less than the length of the array.
So let's try it out.
We'll make an array over here.
So if I have an array called exam scores, it represents maybe the test scores of one student or of
a teacher who has multiple students.
These are all the scores.
It doesn't really matter.
It's a silly example.
Either way, if we wanted to print each score out, we'll start with that.
We would need to iterate over this array and generate an AI or any variable in a for loop that starts
at zero because the first element starts at index zero.
And then we want to go up until the end of that array, but we don't want to go past it.
So we'll do four let equals zero and we'll keep going.
While AI is less than exam scores dot length, not less than or equal to.
Because remember, the length is always one more than the greatest index.
So we have one, two, three, four, five, six elements.
But the last item, the last element has an index of five.
So if we did less than or equal to the length, which is six, then at the last turn of the loop, the
last iteration, we would be accessing exam scores of six, which is undefined.
So AI is less than exam scores length.
Or we could do less than or equal to exam scores dot length minus one.
But that's longer.
So I like to do it this way and then we'll add one to each time and we'll start by just constantly logging
exam scores of AI and we can also console.log.
I first let's run it.
There we go.
So I starts at zero then one, two, three, four, five, it stops at five because the next AI is going
to be six, which is no longer less than the length, because the length is six and six is not less
than six.
And then we access using square brackets each individual element.
So we get 98, 77, 84 and so on.
Now I'm going to make an adjustment to this variable.
I'll be right back.
Okay.
So I made an adjustment, actually, that's a lie.
I made a new variable called My Students, which now that I'm thinking about it, is a little arrogant
because all of these students are Greek gods.
They're not actually my students.
Unfortunately, I did have a serious obsession with Greek mythology as a kid.
So each student is an object.
We have an array, each element is an object and they have a grade each and a first name.
So why don't we start by just pointing out Zeus scored 86, Artemis scored 97, Hara scored 72.
So we'll need to loop over the array for we can do I again let I equals zero.
This is a standard pattern to loop over an array.
We always start at index of zero unless we want it to go backwards, in which case we would start with
the last index and loop until we hit index of zero.
But usually we go left to right, so we'll go while AI is less than my students length and we'll add
one to I each time I plus plus.
And then what I'm going to print out is a template literal, so console.log and then back ticks.
I'll put the first name and this line is going to get quite long if I don't make a separate variable
because I is just a number.
So if I print I, that's going to be 012.
In order to access first name for each one of these, I first have to go through my students of I will
give me each object, but if I just print out the object, that's not going to get me where I want.
I also need to access dot, first name or square bracket first name.
So what I'm going to do is put this in its own variable each time through the loop, I'll call this
Let student equals my student of I.
So now student is going to be an object if we just start by constant logging student.
Comment that out.
Refresh the page.
My student is not defined.
My students.
And there we go.
We're printing each object out because student is simply referencing each element in the array at the
appropriate index.
So now I want to access student dot first name and student grade.
So I'll do my back ticks and the pattern I'll follow is Apollo got a 98 or scored 98 so student which
is just a placeholder variable each time through the loop.
Student First name and then outside of the dollar sign curly braces but still in the back ticks scored
and then another dollar sign student dot grade save refresh There we go.
Zoo scored 86 or scored 97 and so on.
If you feel confident with looping through arrays at this point, skip ahead.
Otherwise I'll do a few more examples and I'll actually start with looping through a string.
It's the exact same approach, except instead of an array, we're accessing a string using those indices,
but we still start at zero.
I'll make a variable called word.
It will start as stressed and I use const, so it's going to stay as stressed, which is fine.
I'm just going to loop over it, but I'm going to loop backwards so we could do the exact same loop
we saw here.
But I think at this point you understand how that works.
We loop while I is less than the length of the array or the string in our case.
So to go backwards we'll write a for loop and instead of starting at zero, which would start with SE
the first character, we want the last index which is going to be the length of the array or the length
of the string.
In our case, word length minus one word length will give us one, two, three, four, five, six,
seven, eight.
So the last index is seven.
So we'll start with I equal to seven.
I'm not going to hard code that because we could have a different string here that is 20 characters
and then we're going to loop while I is greater than or equal to zero.
Or we could also say greater than negative one, but we want it to hit zero.
So greater than or equal to zero.
And then each time through we'll subtract one from I and then we can start by just cancel logging.
I make sure that we get seven, six, five, four three, two, one zero, which we do.
And now instead we'll come to that log word of I.
Refresh and it didn't work.
I planned this out.
It worked, but it combined the two S's, as you can see here, which is unfortunate because now you
can't read what it spells, but stressed spelled backwards is desserts.
So we're now printing out each character in the string in reverse order.
And if we wanted to, we could even make a new string entirely that holds the reversed word so we can
make a variable up here called let reversed.
Word equals an empty string.
And then each time through here we'll do reversed.
Word plus equals word of I.
So we're starting with index of what is it, seven at the beginning or No.
Six, whatever this index is, we take that letter and we add it into reversed word, which is empty.
So we start, we add a D and then the loop goes again.
This time I is one less.
So we're adding an E and then an S and so on.
Let's make sure it works.
So at the end we will print out actually, why don't we just print out console.log reversed word each
time.
Right there, refresh.
And there we go.
D Dee dee dee is death, dessert, dessert desserts.
And so I'll just print it out at the end.
And we have successfully reversed a word.
Awesome.
One more really quick example.
Instead of printing things out, we did something slightly different here.
We reversed a word into a new variable, but why don't we try averaging all of the grades?
So in my students, we have four students that each have a grade.
What we need to do is loop over all students for each one.
We need to sum the grades together.
So we need a variable to accumulate or to hold that sum.
And then after the loop is done, we'll have a total and we need to divide it by in this case, for
the length of my students so we can keep this loop, I'm just going to duplicate it, comment the original
out.
And instead of doing this here in concept logging, we need to add student dot grade to something.
Remember, student is equal to each individual object because I'm doing my students of I, which gives
me one of these objects.
Then the grade gives me that number.
So I'm going to make a variable and I need to make it outside the loop.
I'll call this total and it will start at zero if I put total equals zero in the loop.
If I move this line right here, I will be re creating a re assigning total to zero every time this
loop runs, so we'll never actually remember the previous result.
I need to have it up top where we actually can sum each grade together.
So student grade will do total plus equals.
So add that grade to the total and then at the end we'll call that log total and see what we get.
Three, four, five.
That seems appropriate, right?
It seems like it makes sense.
That's not the average.
To get the average, we need to divide not by four.
We do need to divide by four.
But I don't want a hard code four because we could have ten students in here.
So we'll divide by my students length.
That's the number of students in there.
So my students length, we'll save refresh and the average is 86.25.
There we go.
So we covered a lot of different problems and sort of different examples in this video.
But at its core, we did the same thing every time.
Whether it was a string or an array, we start looping at zero and we loop until the last index, adding
one to each time we use AI that number to access individual elements or individual characters.
In one case, we went backwards, but it's the same idea.
We start with the last index and we subtract one each time as long as we're greater than or equal to
zero.
So a really common pattern looping or iterating over a string, an array or any indexed collection,
you generate those indices.