When we first saw conditional statements, we saw that we could test them inside of one another if and
then inside that if we could have another.
If we can do the same thing with four loops, we can test loops.
And I'll show you some situations where this makes sense.
But first we're going to try and walk through how it works.
Sometimes it can be a little bit confusing or difficult to wrap your head around, so we're going to
start with a single loop.
Let's just go from 1 to 10.
Let I equal one ie less than or equal to ten, and then a plus plus.
And I'm going to console.log the string outer loop and then also I and we get outer loop one down to
outer loop ten and now I'm going to add in a second inner loop.
Now this loop is going to go the other direction from ten down to one.
So we'll start with left and then what should we name the variable?
This is a really important topic and we'll actually come back to it in the next section in more detail.
But for now you should know you can get away with naming your variable again, which seems like it shouldn't
work.
If we typed in our console that I equal zero and then I tried to make another I with a different value,
I get an error says I has already been declared, but in this case these i's this let I and this let
I have a different scope.
We haven't talked about scope.
That's what we'll talk about in the next section.
So for now, we're not going to go with AI.
And in general, it doesn't make sense.
It's a bad idea to use the same name in a nested loop.
It's confusing to look at, and if you needed access to both these variables inside this inner loop,
you wouldn't have it if you name them the same thing.
There's no way to reference both of them, or at least not an easy way.
So that's not what we're going to do.
We're going to go with J, which is pretty standard.
If you use I then move on to J for nested loop.
And then if there's a loop inside of J, use K and usually you shouldn't have more or you should try
and avoid more nesting.
I try and just do two loops whenever possible at most.
Okay.
So we'll go from ten and we'll keep going.
While J is greater than or equal to zero and we'll subtract.
How about two each time instead of one?
So our outer loop is going to go from 1 to 10.
The inner loop will go from 10 to 0 by subtracting twos and in here I'll console.log inner loop and
then J Let's see what we get.
So let's take a look at how this is working, what I'm going to do to make it easier to see the difference.
I'm going to indent this string.
I'm just going to add some spaces on the inner loop, and that way we get some differentiation.
So if we look at the outer loop only, we're going from 1 to 10.
Here is the first time through that outer loop, then the second time, third time all the way down
to here.
But every single time this outer loop runs just a single iteration, the inner loop completes its full
cycle.
So that's why we end up with ten, 86420, and then we hit the end of this loop here.
So that means we're at the end of this first cycle.
Then it starts over.
I now goes up to two and we console.log outer loop.
Then we hit this loop and it has to finish executing so it does its whole thing ten 86420 and then that's
the end of this outer loop.
We start over.
So it takes a long time.
Well, it doesn't.
It's not actually a long time.
It's extremely, extremely quick, but it takes a long time, relatively, for the outer loop to run
again.
This inner loop completes its full cycle every single time.
The outer loop just iterates.
Once you can see overall we have a lot of iterations and the relationship here is if we have X iterations
on the outer loop and Y iterations on the inner loop, we will be running x y time.
So we'll have basically multiply the number of times this runs by the number of times this runs, and
that's how many total iterations you have.
All right.
So this example is kind of pointless.
If we were just trying to generate numbers, however many numbers this is, if we wanted to generate
these exact numbers, fine.
This is a good way to do it.
If for some reason we need one and then ten 86420, that's fine.
But this isn't really a great showcase of why you might want nested iteration or nested for loops.
So the first example I'll show you involves that Game 2048 from a couple of videos ago.
Here is a game board.
After I've lost the game, I just randomly pressed Arrow Keys to try and finish it and it is a four
by four grid.
Each cell has a corresponding value and then we'll calculate a score.
By summing all of these cells together.
And I structured my own version of this the data, at least in an array I'm calling Gameboard, and
it's based exactly off of this score or this board that I created by losing the game.
432, eight and four is the first row, 432, eight and four, and there are four rows.
So to sum all of the values here, I need to loop twice the first loop.
I'm going to move this down so we can group it together.
The first loop is just going to iterate over this outer array.
So one, two, three, four elements.
So for let i equals zero I is less than game board length I plus plus.
So this is going to iterate through game board or it's at least going to give me a number that I can
use to access game board of I and I could just console.log that, but I'll just be printing out each
individual row if I refresh the page.
There we go.
So I can't just sum this.
I can't say a total variable plus equals this entire array.
I need to then loop through each one of these sub arrays and for each value add it to some variable.
So the question is how do I loop through this array here?
What I would probably do is make a new variable.
I'll call it row, which will equal game board of I because this outer loop is just giving us an entire
row at a time when we access using AI, we get one row and then I'm going to loop over row.
So depending on how many items are here, it's always for I'm not going to hard code it because we could
have a five by five game board or an eight by eight game board.
I'm going to use the length of the row.
So to loop over row, all I need to do is for let let's go with j equals zero.
J is less than row length j plus plus.
And why don't we start by console logging row of I and up here I'll cancel that log the row so you can
just see the relationship.
Refresh the page and it's hard to see what's going on here.
Well, I actually made a mistake here, a pretty common one.
I use the variable I inside of this loop.
There's nothing wrong with it.
In a technical sense, JavaScript doesn't care.
But as far as my logic is concerned, the variable I want is j.
J is going to be referring to each element in a row.
I is referring to the actual row.
So in the first iteration I is zero and I'm then using that to access zero item zero, item zero, item
zero, which is why I get all of these forwards printed out.
So I want to access J because J will be changing each time and here's what we get.
So our outer loop starts, we get this row and then we loop over this 430 to 8 and four.
That's each value.
The inner loop finishes, there's nothing afterwards.
So the outer loop is done on that iteration and we start the next cycle.
So now I is set to one which gives us this index and we loop over this row, so why don't we sum it
all together?
Now I'll get rid of these constant logs and to do that I need a total variable.
Let total.
Let's go with total score.
Start it at zero and then in here I'm simply going to total score plus equals and then row of J.
Remember row is this entire element each time through.
And then J gives me a number like zero.
So I'm going to take row of zero.
Add that to total score row of one, row of two, row of three.
Add those all in and then the loop starts over.
And now we're working on this array and then I do row of zero and keep adding them in.
Let's see what we get.
If I refresh the page, I didn't print out total score, but you can see it over here if I type it 230.
So this is still kind of a silly scenario, but this is a very real example of when you would use nested
loops.
We need to have at least two loops to access each element because we have two arrays that are nested.
And if we had further sub arrays, we would need another loop.
All right, so that's it for now.
Just take away the fact that we can have nested loops each iteration through the outer loop.
We have a complete cycle of the inner loop before the outer loop increments or moves on to its next
iteration.