So we just saw how to use a while loop essentially to recreate a for loop.
We printed the number zero through five two different ways and that's great.
You can do that with a while loop, but that's not how I use them.
That's not how most people use them.
You would just use a for loop if you need to generate a set range of numbers 0 to 10, 100 to 10, whatever.
Where a while loop really excels is when you're writing a loop where you don't know exactly how many
times it's going to run.
We don't know that we're going from 0 to 10.
We don't know we want this to run exactly 20 times.
Instead, it might be something like the 2048 game example I showed you or a chess game where you continue
to have your game logic loop until there is a game over.
And for a good player, that might happen in the case of 2048.
It might happen after hundreds or thousands of turns in a bad player like when I was playing.
It might happen in 100 turns or ten or 20 turns.
So you don't code that in, you use a while loop.
And essentially it would look like while not game over or while still alive or lives left is greater
than zero.
So you don't know exactly how many times it will run, but at some point in this loop you will be changing
lives left or you will be setting game over to be true.
A simple version of this would be to make a number game and a guessing game where we won't even be guessing
ourselves.
Our computer or JavaScript will generate a random number from 1 to 10.
That will be the target.
We're trying to guess, let's say nine.
Then we'll make a second random number, which will also be from 1 to 10 and we're trying to hit nine.
So maybe the first guess will be five.
We'll have a wild loop that runs while the guess is not equal to the target.
And then as soon as they are equal, meaning that we've guessed correctly, the loop is over.
So let's start by generating a target number.
So let's target and that can be a constant equals.
And if you can recall back to how we do this, we start with math at random that gives us a decimal
between zero and one like 0.9 or 0.95 or point six.
And then I'm going to multiply it by ten and then we floor that to chop off the decimal.
That will give us a whole number.
If you need some review, you can go back and and watch the video where we covered this.
I think I said this then.
I am not a fan of how we generate random integers in JavaScript.
This is annoying.
Many other languages have a simple method like rand int, but JavaScript does not.
So this gives us a target number.
Let's just verify that console.log target we get six OC we do it again, we get nine.
Now let's duplicate this and generate a guess.
So we'll call this guess and I'm going to make this a let variable, not a constant, because we're
probably going to have to guess again, meaning that the value will change that is stored and guess
target will stay the same so we can make it cost.
Guess is most likely going to change unless we guess it right the very first time.
So now we should have two variables.
We have target and we have guess.
Guess is not the same.
We did not guess it correctly.
So now we can implement our logic.
Our loop is going to look like while guess is not equal to target.
So while we have not guessed or generated the correct random number, what do we need to do?
Well, this is the really important part of any well loop.
You need to eventually have a way of making this condition false so that the loop will stop.
Otherwise you end up with an infinite loop, which we've seen before with for loops is not good, not
desirable.
We need some way of making this false eventually so we can break out, and in our case it just means
guessing again.
So how would we guess again?
We would just copy this.
We don't need let because we're not trying to re declare.
We're not trying to make a new variable.
We're trying to update the existing guess.
So now we'll get a new random and let's console.log guess in here each time and just see what we get.
I'm going to refresh and it should loop a couple of times until eventually we guess the correct answer.
Let's at the bottom verify it.
We'll console.log target
and we'll put the variable target right there using a template literal and then guess and we'll do the
same thing.
All right.
And you can see we started with our guest being eight.
That was incorrect.
So we made a new guess that time we got seven.
So this was still true.
They were not equal.
So we printed out seven.
We made a new guess this time guess was one and that was the target.
We can see here what was printed out.
Target one guess one.
That means this is now false and it's done running.
So we go down to this line and that prints out target one guess one.
Awesome.
So that works.
I would change this up a little bit.
It would be nice to see each guess the entire way through.
So right here I'll print this out here so we can see it.
And then at the bottom I'll instead say Congrats, you win, even though the user is not doing anything.
And let's also print out this down at the bottom.
One more time, because right now what's happening is when you do guess correctly or when the guess
is updated correctly, this loop does not run.
So this line never prints out.
So we don't see what the target is and what the guess is.
So I'm putting it down here again and there we go.
So we have six.
What's the target?
The whole time?
Eight was the first guess, then nine.
Then we got six.
This line is printed after the loop right here and then congrats, you win.
And that's pretty much it for this example.
This is a really common pattern.
So if I were to break down this pattern we have while some condition
in the loop update or attempt to make that condition false, which is what we did here, we attempted
to eventually make this condition false.
It might take 100 tries, it might take 1000 tries, just like the 2048 game or a chess game.
You could play for hundreds of moves or it could happen really quickly.
And a four loop doesn't easily accommodate that.
A four loop is great when you are just trying to generate numbers from one index or one start point
to a stop point.
It's not as great when you have this uncertainty around how many times something will run.
So that's one I like to use while loops.
Just remember, if you do not update something that has the chance of making this false, you'll get
an infinite loop.
If we didn't change, guess and we only guessed one time this would go on forever.
And that's it for now.
There is a small change you could make potentially here.
You can see I'm duplicating the guess, the initial guess, and this guess down here.
I could just make guess undefined at the beginning and that would work.
Although my first console.log would also print out undefined here, which is not what we want.
So I'm just going to duplicate that code.
It's okay.