There's a special keyword in JavaScript called Brake, which we can use inside of loops to break out
of that loop to stop its execution whenever JavaScript encounters break, that loop that it's enclosed
in is done.
So you can use this technically in a for loop.
It's pretty uncommon, but we could.
And the reason it's uncommon is that for loop, you're writing the exact rules, you're writing how
many times it should run.
So four are equals zero.
Less than ten.
Plus.
I know how many times this is going to run.
Let's say I'll cancel that log each time and then I'll break when I is equal to five.
If I equals five, I'll call break and this breaks out of that loop.
Let's see what happens.
Zero one, two, three, four, five.
We encounter the break and the loop is done.
Like I said, it's not very commonly used in a for loop because why not just write this for loop to
go from 0 to 5 instead of zero through ten and then stopping halfway through.
But it is something that you can do.
Also, I should mention if you have multiple loops and you break in one of the nested loops, it does
not stop all loops from executing.
It will only stop the inner loop or the current loop that break is located in.
But like I said, not that common in a for loop, but it can be common in a while loop.
In fact, using break we can restructure our wild loop from earlier.
This one where we had a guessing game wasn't much of a game for us, but for the computer.
Maybe guessing a random number over and over until the guest match the target.
We could rewrite that using break and a while loop.
And this might seem odd to write this loop right here while true, but we can do this as long as we
break out at some point.
So this is basically saying loop forever.
But then in the loop we're going to say not so fast.
If this condition is true, break out of the loop.
If we wanted to get this exact same logic going, I'll just uncomment most of this.
We will pick our target and a guess.
And then, while true, if target equals guess, we will break.
Otherwise we will make a new guess.
Guess equals math for math random and at the bottom we'll print the target and the guess.
Once you've won, congrats you win.
And then let's also print it here so we can see what's going on and I can get rid of my original while
loop.
So we still have our logic to get the two random numbers and then we have this loop that seems crazy.
It seems like it should be an infinite loop, while true, just a loop forever.
But then we have our condition that says if target is the same as guess break.
Now if that break doesn't happen, we'll print out target and guess and then we'll get a new guess and
the loop starts over because it's still true.
While true, it's going to go forever until we break.
If I run this, you can see it still works.
Target is nine guesses seven target nine guess one guess was nine.
So the loop broke right there and then we print.
Congrats, you win.
Now I'm not such a big fan of this approach because of two main reasons.
One, it can be easy to end up with infinite loops, but the main reason I don't like it is writing,
while true, is just not very it's not very explanatory or informational.
If you look at it, I would prefer to write something that was maybe while game not or maybe not game
over.
I think that's better.
And have a boolean called game over and you could change boolean or change who came over from true to
false or false to true.
So for me, when I look at this loop here, you can change this and structure it in a better way while
still using break, but I just don't find it as intuitive to look at.
But I did want to show you break because it is used occasionally.
Again, it will break out of the loop it's located in, but if there are nested loops, it will not
break all of them.
It breaks out of its current loop.
It stops its execution cold in its tracks, even if it was set to go off 1000 more times.
If it encounters break, then it's done.