Next up, we have a new loop called the four of Loop.
So it's new to us in this course, but it's also new to JavaScript.
It's only been around a couple of years and unfortunately it is not supported in Internet Explorer.
If we go to MD and scroll down to the bottom, there's a whole line of red right there for Internet
Explorer.
So again, it's not a reason to ignore it or to stop using four of.
It's just something to be aware of.
It's not going to work automatically in every single browser, but Chrome, Firefox, Safari, they
all support it.
So four of is a really simple syntax and it addresses a common use case for a loop where we want to
iterate over an iterable and iterable could be something like an array or a string.
There are other items that are iterable in JavaScript.
That's something we'll talk about later as well.
I hate saying that, but it's true.
For now, we'll work with arrays and strings so the syntax is super clean.
Instead of creating a for loop, a regular for loop where we generate a variable.
Let's say I set to zero.
We add one to each time we keep going.
While is less than the array dot length.
Instead of that we simply write four and then some variable of iterable so of array.
And that variable we assign will store each individual element of the array or of the string.
So here's an example.
We have an array called subreddits, just some strings of different Reddit subreddits using a regular
old for loop.
I would have to make a variable I while I is less than subreddits dot length C++ and then let's just
console.log each individual element.
So that would be subreddits of I.
So we're only using AI here to access each element.
It's kind of a lot of work.
It's not very attractive or clean to look at, especially if we're only if we only care about soccer,
pop heads, cringe and books.
We don't care about the numbers.
We don't care about the indices.
We just need them in order to access those elements.
So another alternative is the four of and that looks like this for lit and then we decide on a variable
name and this variable is going to represent each element.
So the name, it doesn't matter again, just like AI.
You could use AI, but that's generally not a good idea.
Most people, when they see AI are going to imagine or assume that it's a number, an index.
So I would go with something like sub or subreddit or element l, I'll go with sub of subreddits console.log
sub.
So we don't have to access the array using square brackets and a number sub is going to automatically
have each element it's stored in at each time through the loop.
If I run my code over here, we loop twice the first time using a for loop, the second time using a
four of loop.
Hopefully you can see this is a dramatic improvement.
It's a lot easier to read.
It kind of approximates English instead of this where we're generating these random or not random,
but these ugly indices and we're not using them in any way.
So I much prefer four of which is why I was added in.
Not because I prefer it, but because it's such a common scenario where you need to iterate over elements
in an array or a string and you don't need those numbers, so why bother?
So this was added in it was proposed and added in to the spec and for of we'll work on anything that
is iterable in JavaScript.
Another example of an iterable is a string.
So we could do a four let character or char car of and then some string.
How about hello everyone.
Actually, you know that's let's do let's do -- a doodle do.
I don't know if that's how you spell that noise, that sound.
And then let's just cancel that log character and let's do car cha two uppercase.
So each time we're going to uppercase that character and there we go, -- a doodle do so we can iterate
over each character in a string, each element in an array.
We don't need an indices or an index.
We don't need a number.
We don't have to do any of this logic.
All we do is say for each thing in subreddit so let sub of subreddits let item plot element let character
let letter.
It's up to you.
It's a lot cleaner and a lot easier to work with.