Next up, I want to continue talking about for of we'll see another example and we'll also talk about
situations when it doesn't help you.
And you might actually prefer a standard for loop even if it's longer and uglier.
Here I have a simple two dimensional array.
It's representing a magic square.
It's I don't know if you've seen them before.
It's a square of numbers, a grid where each row sums to some number, in this case, 15.
So you can see all of them sum to 15 each vertical.
So each column also sums to 15 and each diagonal sums to 15 if it's a correct magic square.
Now we're not going to write code to verify every single direction, but if I wanted to just sum each
row and verify that they equal 15 using a for loop, a regular for loop, it's kind of annoying.
Let I equal zero.
I'm going to have to do a nested loop less than magic square dot length and then I plus plus.
And that's going to get me each row, one row at a time.
So then I need to loop again to get those inwards each element in the row.
And what I'd like to do is make a variable called row and just set it equal to magic square of I.
So now row in this loop is going to refer to one of these nested arrays and then I'll loop over row.
So for litt j equals zero j less than row length j plus plus, and then for each j we could start by
just contact logging j to make sure it works.
Does it work?
Okay, so kind of we're printing out the indices.
We need row of J and now we're getting those numbers.
But I want to sum them together three at a time.
Each element are all elements in one of those rows.
I want to sum them together and print out ideally 15.
So what I'm going to do is make another variable up top called sum.
So not all the way up top, but each time through the loop, the outer loop, I want to reset it to
zero because I'm looping over this, summing them together.
But the next time this outer loop goes, it iterates.
I want it to start again at zero so I can sum these up without having the previous sum in there as well.
And then I would just do some plus equals row of J and then after this inner loop I could console.log
some.
I'll probably do row added to I'll just add the whole row right there summed two and then dollar sign
sum.
Let's see what we get.
Two, seven, six, some to 15, some to 15.
So this is OC with a regular for loop, but if we instead rewrote it using a four of loop, I think
it's much cleaner.
We would just do four let row of magic square.
We'd still make our sum variable, let sum equals zero and then four let.
Let's go with numb element.
I'll just go with numb.
I think that's fine of row so I don't have to make the second variable here.
I don't have to use I or J just for let row.
I have access to row in here.
Row refers to each individual nested array each row.
Then for letting some of those rows of each row I'm going to sum plus equals num and then I'll copy
this line here this console.log down below.
I'll comment out that original one with the for loop and we get the exact same output.
But this is much cleaner and easier to see and understand.
So that's an example where a four of really helps.
And I also wanted to show a nested example.
Now here's another example where it's actually not to your advantage to use four of I have two arrays
of strings, words one and words two.
I want to loop over the first array and for each element I want to also print out the corresponding
element from words two.
So mailbox, milkshake, bathtub and BlackBerry.
Using a for a traditional for loop is the way to go because I need to have an index.
I need to know which number we're printing out or which index we're accessing in words one.
So I can do the same thing in words too.
If instead I did a four of loop, I would have each value mail and milk, but I wouldn't have that number,
that index to access the corresponding value from words to.
So I do want a regular for loop here let i equals zero I less than words one length I plus plus and
then I'll just simply console.log.
Words one of I comma words, two of the same I.
So I will be zero where it's one of zero male male words.
Two of zero bucks.
Let's test it out.
Mailbox milkshake.
Bathtub, BlackBerry.
Technically, if I wanted them to be one word, I could use tactics, interpolate each one, do it again,
maybe add a hyphen.
I don't know if they're supposed to be hyphenated.
We'll just do one word.
Same thing here.
So now we should just get one word.
If we tried to do this with a four of loop, it would not be easy at all.
We would have to use four of on this first loop and then work backwards to figure out what number,
what index is male at, what index is milk at.
We could do something like index of and then get that number and then take that number and plug it plug
it into words two, which is just not ideal.
So my point here is that four of is great a lot of the time and it's really common just to need the
data in an array or a string.
But if you need to care about the index, the position like we did here, then it's not going to work
out for you or it won't be as easy as it would be to just generate those indices using a traditional
four loop instead.