So we saw that we can use a form of loop with an object as long as we also use object keys or object
values in conjunction with it.
There's also another type of loop called a four in loop, which we'll talk about in this video.
The very last loop we have to cover if you have not seen Amadeus yet.
Oh, fantastic movie.
I forgot about how great that movie is.
There's a reason it's the only ten on the list.
Okay, so four in syntactically is very similar to four of we have four per n's variable in an object
instead of of an array or an iterable.
The main difference is that a four of will iterate over the actual values in an array or an iterable
in a string.
Each character in an array, each value a four in will loop over the keys the properties in an object.
So here's an example object jeopardy winnings.
This represents Ken Jennings.
If you are familiar with him, I think he's the all time winningest Jeopardy!
Contestant.
It's how he made all of his earnings or his money from Jeopardy!
It came in different pieces.
His long stretch of gameplay was two and one half million.
He participated in this IBM Watson challenge, where he played Jeopardy against a supercomputer.
He got 300,000, 500,000 for a tournament of champions.
It doesn't really matter if you don't watch Jeopardy!
Then you must be bored at this point.
So we'll move on.
So let's try using a four in four and then we make a variable for let and then we could just call it
property in jeopardy winnings.
We'll console.log.
Prop prop.
It's not a great name, but sometimes it's tricky to figure out what to name that variable because in
this case it's kind of easy.
We have very similar data, but if we had a user object where we had username and then we had age,
we had email, what would be a good variable name that would make sense to hold any of these property
names?
Prop is going to be good enough for now.
You'll see people do key or K.
I'll go with prop.
Let's console.log prop and you can see what we get the four keys.
So it's very similar to what we did with four of where we had objects keys, but we don't have to do
that.
This will loop over the keys automatically as long as we have in instead of of I changed that to of
we get an error.
It's not iterable for of once an iterable for n wants an object and that's what we get.
So if I wanted to print out also the value I would do console.log jeopardy winnings of prop with square
brackets.
And there we go.
If I wanted to sum them all together to figure out his total earnings, I'll just duplicate this loop
for prop in jeopardy winnings.
I'll make a variable to store the total.
Let total equals zero.
And then each time through I'll just add jeopardy winnings of prop to total jeopardy.
Winnings of prop is going to be one of these numbers, so we still loop over the keys.
That's the only option we have with a four in.
It's going to loop over the properties, the key names, and then we use that to access the value to
get that value out.
Just like a dictionary, as we saw earlier in the object section, we have a word, we look it up in
the dictionary to get the corresponding definition.
So if I print out total at the end, let's do a template literal.
Ken Jennings total earnings and then dollar sign curly braces total $3.4 million.
There we go.
So that's four in.
One thing that I do want to point out is that technically you can use four in with an array, but there's
not really a good reason to know this gets into that murky area we briefly talked about at the end of
the object section where arrays are objects, they technically are objects, which means that we can
use a four in with an array.
So let's do just a simple hardcoded array.
Four let k four key in this array.
How about 88, 99, 77, 66.
What do you think K is going to be when I print it out here?
What will we see?
So for each property in this array.
Console.log.
K.
Hmm.
Zero.
One, two, three.
No matter what values I had in here, if I have four values, the property names are always zero one,
two, three.
So we're not looping over the actual elements.
The values don't matter.
We're looping over the properties.
When we have an object Jeopardy winnings and I want to access a piece, I use a key, a property name
like regular play.
And I get a value out when we have an array.
We do the exact same thing, but the key is our numbers.
When I look at Jeopardy winnings and I expand it, we have the keys and the values.
And if I look at an array and I expand it, we have keys and values.
So arrays are just special cases.
There's special objects where the keys are an ordered set of indices numbers starting at zero.
So that's what we're looping over.
We're looping over the keys here, which is not all that useful, especially when we already have a
four of loop, which automatically gives us the values.
The other thing to know about for RN is that the order is not necessarily set in stone and that's another
reason it's not great to use with arrays the way that for in loops can vary from browser to browser.
On the MD docs, it says it's an arbitrary order.
In my experience, it's pretty stable most of the time in one browser it can change when you go to another
browser, but also if you are updating or manipulating properties that can change the order as well.
Unlike an array where the order is set in stone, the first item is always index zero.
The second item is always index one.
So don't use a four in with an array even though you can.
It's just kind of an odd thing to do.
And that about wraps it up for loops.
We've seen a ton of different loops.
Well, I guess not that many, but we've seen a ton of examples.
We started with four loops, then we talked about while loops and we saw four of remember four of loops
are not supported in Internet Explorer at the moment.