All right, my friends, in this video, we're going to start working on our next project now.
I'm really excited about this next project because it's a little bit different than anything else we've
done in this course or anything else that we will do.
So let's talk about what we're going to be building.
All right.
So we're going to be making a little maze game that is going to run directly inside the browser.
So when a user starts up our application, we're going to show them a maze like the one you see right
here.
A user is then going to manipulate a little ball like that blue one right there to move it around the
maze until eventually gets to some target location, specifically this green square on the bottom left
hand corner.
So a user is going to have to use the W, A and D keys on their keyboard to move the ball around like
so and then eventually touch that green square.
And as soon as they do, they're going to win.
So that's it.
That's what we're going to be building.
Now, this is not obviously a traditional web application.
This is much more like a game.
The thing I really want to focus in on this game that we're going to build is some of the data structures
that we're going to use to actually generate the maze.
Let's have a quick discussion and highlight some of the big challenges we're going to run into as we
start working on this.
Okay.
So some of these are probably going to be pretty obvious when it comes to challenges of building this
app.
So the first big thing we're going to run into is how do we generate a maze at all?
We're going to be building the maze from scratch.
We're going to write the code to actually form that thing up.
So we need to make sure that our maze has some valid solution.
It also has to, you know, have some level of difficulty to it.
The next thing we're going to have to think about is how we're going to draw that maze on the screen.
So are we going to use traditional HTML elements or are we going to figure out some other method or
solution out?
We also have to make sure that we can somehow get the keyboard keys to control that ball as well.
So whenever a user presses W, A, S or D on their keyboard, we're going to move the ball up, left,
down or right.
And then finally, we need to somehow detect when the ball touches that green square on the bottom right
corner.
So for each of these challenges, let's talk about a solution very briefly.
The first big issue is how do we generate a maze?
Well, there are many different algorithms out there to use to generate a maze.
We're going to use a pretty simple and straightforward algorithm to generate our maze.
But we are still going to have to learn a little bit about a data structure called a tree.
We're going to also have to write out a little bit of code for recursion as well.
So that's where we're going to kind of get pretty far down into the weeds and learn how to build the
maze.
You actually draw the maze on the screen?
We're going to use a JavaScript library called Matter JS.
Matter JS is used to draw or kind of simulate physical elements.
So like a ball or a board or a spring or whatever else it might be best to just take a look at the documentation
from outer space.
You can find it at this link right here.
I'm going to open up a new tab right away and visit it.
And once you go here, you're going to see several different physics demos right here on the main screen.
You can also click on See all demos and if you on this page find the dropdown at the top, you can select
all the different demos they have available.
So for example, I'll check out Double Pendulum and there we go about Stack.
There we go.
And you'll notice that a lot of these you can actually click and drag these elements around.
So we're going to be using meter jazz and we're going to learn a pretty good amount about it to actually
implement the maze and all this other kind of stuff.
Next up, how do we actually have the keyboard keys, control the ball?
Well, we're making use of matter DJs and that this library has the ability to map some key presses
to the movement of some shape or element on the screen being drawn by this library.
Finally, how do we detect whenever the bulb touches the Green Square?
Once again?
Mataji It gives us the ability to detect collisions between different shapes or different objects inside
of our app.
So we should be able to write some code that's going to detect whenever the blue ball collides with
the green square.
And again, that's going to be essentially our win condition.
Okay.
So again, just a couple of big things for us to think about as we are starting this thing off.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
We'll come back the next video.
We're going to do a little bit of initial project setup and then immediately start writing some code
to get a better idea of how matter JZ works.