All right, let's do a little bit of project setup.
I'm inside of a workspace directory of sorts inside of here.
I'm going to make a new directory called Maze.
I'll then change into that directory and then start up my code editor inside there.
Our project set up is going to involve a simple HTML file and a JavaScript file, which is where we're
going to write all of our application code.
So inside this new project directory, I'll first make a new file called Indexed HTML.
And I'll throw a little bit of boilerplate in there.
So get my HTML tag.
I'll get ahead.
And a body.
And then a script tag with a source of index dot js.
Like so.
I'm also going to add in a script tag inside the head element.
We're going to use this additional script tag to get access to the matter.
JS Library.
So I need to make sure that I provide a source right here to the Matter Jar Library to get that, I'm
going to go back over to my browser.
I'm going to navigate to see an JSP.
And then once here I'll search for simply matter.
And I should see it matter.
Dash jazz as one of the first results.
So there's a link to the library, so I can highlight that and copy it.
And then put it into the script tag right here.
Let's also make sure we create the index case file.
They'll do a quick console.log and say hi there once again, as usual, just to make sure that everything
is linked up correctly.
So that should be it.
Now we can go ahead and open up that indexed HTML file.
Inside of our browser.
So I'll go back over to my browser.
Open up the HTML file.
Check my console and just make sure that the console log that I added to the indexed HTML file or indexed
file is there.
Yep.
Definitely looks like it is.
Okay.
So that's all the setup we have to do, believe it or not.
Yep.
Not a lot of stuff going on in that regard.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to start to discuss the matter JS Library.
We're going to write out a pretty quick example over the next couple of videos to get a better idea
of how it works.
And then we'll start to focus on building this maze.