Now that we have done a little bit of project set up, I want to give you some high level notes on the
matter.
Just library.
Just so you know, matter.
Case has some really good documentation and you can always read it by going to the main page, the RMI
matter JS and then finding documentation on the left hand side.
On the left here, you're going to see all the different objects inside of this library.
I'm going to tell you about all the different objects you need to be aware of.
But if you get stuck at any point in time throughout this application, you can always come and check
out the documentation to get a better idea of exactly what we're working with inside this library.
I want to give you a couple of highlights of the different things we're going to be working with in
here.
In general, this is just going to be some terminology so that you understand some of the code that
we're going to be writing very soon.
Okay.
So here are some of the important pieces of terminology that you need to be aware of.
The first piece of terminology that is used inside of the matter Library is World.
This is an object that contains all the different things or shapes inside of our application.
So if we go back over to the official docs or the official page and take a look at all the demos and
look at the Mixed Shape demo, you're going to see a bunch of different shapes all over the screen.
The entire scene that we see right here is essentially represented inside of that world object.
So this world thing that we're talking about right here, it tracks the location, position, speed,
because see how these things can move.
So the velocity of each item as well, they all get tracked inside that world object.
The next piece of terminology we need to be aware of is engine.
This is a object that has a bunch of different functions in it that's going to read in the current state
of the world from the world object.
So the world object knows where every shape is right now.
It knows every shapes, velocity, weight and so on.
The engine is going to read in all that data and it's going to calculate changes in positions for all
those different shapes.
So we can imagine that the world is kind of like a snapshot of everything as it stands in an instant
in time.
The engine is responsible for transitioning from one snapshot to another.
The runner is what makes the world an engine work together.
So the runner is going to essentially run about 60 times per second until the engine to process all
the data stored inside the world object.
The next big thing is the render object.
So whenever the engine processes an update and says, okay, here's a new snapshot of data, here's
a new version of the world, the render object is going to take a look at all those different shapes
and it's going to show them all on the screen.
So the render object is essentially what takes all of our data and shows it in this little element right
here that we're playing around with.
Finally, last piece of terminology is body.
This is going to be a shape that gets displayed.
There are many different types of bodies available to us when we're making use of matter DJ's.
So we can create a body that represents a circle or a rectangle or an oval or a triangle, or just about
anything else.
Any kind of arbitrary shaped polygon can be created using the body object.
So the application that we're going to create, the Maze Game, is going to have many of these different
bodies inside of it.
Now, one thing I want to mention here is that I'm going over this terminology rather quickly, because
at the end of the day, you don't really need to understand the terminology here to write a better job
application.
That's kind of the beauty of it.
The only reason I'm telling you about these different pieces of terminology is that we're going to very
quickly start to write some kind of boilerplate code to set our application up.
And so I just want you to have some idea of what all these different terms mean for the purpose of writing
that boilerplate code.
But honestly, it's essentially write that code once to set up the application, and that's pretty much
it.
After that, the only things that we really need to be aware of is the body object, because the vast
majority of code that we're going to write inside of our application is all about showing different
bodies on the screen, essentially the different walls of our maze and the ball that the user is going
to be manipulating.
And this green square at the bottom, every shape inside of this diagram right here will be represented
inside of our wrap with a body.
So again, we really just need to understand what a body is and all those other pieces of terminology
I'm just throwing out there so that you're vaguely aware that they exist.
Okay.
So now we've got a little bit of terminology put together.
Let's take one more pause and we'll start writing some code in the next video.