Now that we have a better idea of some of these different pieces of terminology, let's start to write
some code rather than directly focusing on creating a maze like this right here, which will end up
being rather complicated.
We're going to instead do a little demo first just to kind of get a handle on exactly what matter JHS
is.
So we are going to implement this demo that you see right here where we essentially have a bunch of
shapes all in a pile, and we can drag one around and move them all when they all get kind of collisions
between each of them.
So first we'll build this, then rebuild over to the maze type implementation.
So let's get to it.
I'm going to first go back over to my code editor and inside my index file are going to first get started
by requiring in or getting access to a couple of different objects out of the matter library.
So I'm going to say const.
I'm then going to do some DE structuring and I'm going to get access to engine render, runner, world
and bodies.
And that's all going to come from matter like so.
So when we included the matter script tag back inside of indexed HTML that added in a new global variable
of matter and that is essentially the matter.
JS Library.
So everything we're going to work with is contained inside that object in order to create an engine,
render, blah, blah, all this stuff, we're going to pull out some of these different objects and
then work with them inside this file.
Now you'll notice that a lot of these terms right here are the same ones that we just discussed in the
last video.
So we were going to use the engine to essentially transition from a current state of our entire world
or all the shapes we have into some new state.
The render is going to be used to draw this stuff onto the screen.
The runner is going to coordinate updates between the engine and the world.
And then I had said on that diagram, Body Bodies is kind of a reference to the entire collection of
all the different shapes we can create, essentially the same thing we saw on the diagram.
So a bodies object represents our ability to create circles, rectangles, squares and so on.
Then instead of here, we're going to write out some boilerplate code.
Now, once again, it's not strictly necessary for you to 100% understand all the lines we're about
to write.
I just want you to have some terminology so you understand some of the boilerplate.
But at the end of the day, a lot of the stuff just just gets duplicated between all the different matter
apps you might end up creating.
The first thing we're going to do is create a new engine by saying engine create.
We're then going to get access to a world that got created along with that engine.
So let's say cost world is coming from engine.
So technically when we create an engine, we get a world object along with it.
And again, a world is kind of like a snapshot of all the different shapes that we have.
After that, we'll then create our render object.
So this is what is going to actually show some content on the screen.
Let's say const render is render create and we're going to pass it in options object.
Inside of here, we're going to tell the render where we want to show our representation of everything
inside of our HTML document.
So I'm going to say element is document dot body.
So in other words, go and render the representation of the world inside of documents body.
And this is a additive process.
In other words, it's not going to destroy all the content that we already have inside of our body element.
It's going to instead add in a new additional element to the body element.
After that, we're going to specify what engine to use.
And they'll pass in also an options object.
Inside the options object.
I'm going to specify the height and width of our canvas element that's going to be used to display all
this content.
So I'm going to put in a width of 800.
And a height of 600.
So these are pixel values right here.
So we're saying give me something that is 800 units wide and 600 elements tall.
Then after that, we're going to tell our render element or our render object to start working and start
to draw all the updates of our world onto the screen.
So I'll say render run.
Now I'll pass in lowercase render.
So that's the actual render object that we just created.
And then I'll call runner run.
With runners create and engine.
So again, the runner right here is what coordinates all these changes from state to state B of our
engine.
So it's just that we should be able to save this and then go back over and see something appear on the
screen.
It's going to go back over to my browser.
I'll refresh and I see a big black box appear.
So this is where we're going to eventually see all of our shapes up here over time.
So now we can start to think about how we just add a very simple and plain shape to add a simple shape
to our world.
Down here, I'm going to say.
Collins shape.
Is Bodies, dot rectangle.
And I'm going to pass in a couple of dimensions for this thing.
We'll talk about exactly what these dimensions represent in just a moment.
I'm going to put in here 200, 250, 50, and then an options object.
And inside that options object, I'll say is static is true like so.
Then after that, I'll call WorldCom and I'll pass in the world that we got just a little bit ago when
we created our engine right there.
And then as a second argument, I'll pass in the shape that I just created.
Like so.
Okay.
So we'll talk about what that code is doing in just a moment.
But first, let's save this.
Go back over and we can see a shape up here inside of our element.
So that's the basics of getting something to show up on the screen.
But obviously, we just wrote out a lot of code that's possibly really mysterious.
So let's talk about what's going on here after a very quick break.