In the last video, we wrote out a little bit of code to get a simple rectangle to show up on the screen.
In this video, I want to go over some of the code that we wrote just a little bit more and clarify
a couple of points.
Once we get this final clarification out of the way, we'll then start to work much more quickly on
the application that we're trying to build.
So back inside my index file, the first thing I want to point out is where we had created that render
object.
As I mentioned, we provide the element property and this tells matter where we want to show our essentially
drawing of the world inside the dom.
If we open up our element inspector inside of our development tools, we can see that this representation
in the world or this drawing is a type of HTML element called a canvas.
A canvas element is, for lack of a better term, a canvas of sorts that we can use to draw any kind
of arbitrary shape that we want.
Usually we might use some kind of third party library like Canvas or like Mat or JSS to work with canvas
elements.
We can work with canvas elements directly using some browser based APIs, but they are just a little
bit tedious.
So usually any time we want to use a canvas, we will commonly make use of a third party library like
MAT or JZ or something similar.
When we created the canvas, we assigned a height and width to it.
So if we ever want to change the height or the width of that canvas element, we could easily modify
it right here.
So for example, I could decrease the width to 400.
And if I save and refresh now, this thing is going to be half as wide.
The first half of this application, we're going to just show a canvas element of 800 by 600.
But if we have our final product, like our actual maize show up in just that 800 by 600 frame, then
it's not going to be that great because if some user tries to play our maize game on a really, really
big monitor, the maize is going to appear to be really, really small to them.
So we're going to eventually add in some code to make sure that our canvas element spans the entire
width of the screen and the entire height as well.
So it's going to play equally as well on a small screen as a large one, but we're going to worry about
that later on.
Okay.
So back over here.
Just a couple more things I want to point out.
Down at the bottom, we use that bodies object to create a new rectangle.
When we created the rectangle, we assigned it to the variable shape and then had a second line of code
to add it to the world object.
Just creating a shape or creating a rectangle doesn't make it show up on the screen.
So, for example, if I comment out the world, add statement.
And then refresh.
Well, nothing appears whatsoever.
So we can create as many shapes as we want.
But they all have to eventually be added to our world object in order to get them to actually show up.
I want to show you something kind of interesting around that world object as well.
Several times as we are writing out this application, I would encourage you on your own to open up
your console and print out the world variable.
So this world variable is the same one that we have created back right here.
Well, technically up here, but the same one we are referring to right here.
So as I've mentioned, this world variable contains a representation of all the different shapes inside
of our world.
If we print out the word variable, we can then expand it and see that it has several different properties.
One property in particular.
Well, let me refresh.
Sorry, really quick.
I need to make sure the shape is visible.
So once the shape is very visible, I'll look at world again and then look at the body's property.
As soon as I do so, I'll see that there is a single object inside there.
This is the object that represents this rectangle shape.
It has a lot of different properties in it that describe its physical representation in the world.
So for example, it has an angular velocity, which is how quickly this thing is rotating and which
direction it is rotating as well.
It also has some other properties such as position.
So that is the physical position in the world in X and y coordinates.
And then it also has a velocity property that describes how quickly this thing is moving to the left
or right or up and down.
Okay.
One or two more things here.
When we created our rectangle, we passed in in options object of is static.
True.
That means that we want to show the shape and we don't want it to ever move under any circumstance.
If we remove that property and then save and refresh, we'll see that the shape then falls down to the
bottom.
And every time I refresh, it starts back at the same spot and falls again.
So by default, gravity is enabled in our simulation, so gravity is going to take that shape and automatically
accelerate it downwards.
So it is the static is static true property right here that's going to make the shape stay exactly where
it is.
So if I save again now the shape stays right there.
Last thing I want to mention is some of the different dimensions or values we are passing in when we
are creating the rectangle.
The first two numbers represent the position in the world to place this rectangle at.
These dimensions are measured from the top left corner to the center of the square.
Just to make sure that's really clear.
The top left corner of our canvas element is the 00. of our entire world.
Our x axis or the x direction runs from left to right, and the y axis goes up to down.
So when we say place a shape or a rectangle at 202 hundred, that means start right there on the top
left corner, go over 200 units and then down.
And or see me go over 200 units and down 200 units.
And that is where the center of our rectangle should be.
We can verify that by trying to do the same kind of rectangle, but instead placing it at zero zero.
If we do so, then I would expect to see the rectangle or the center of the rectangle based on like
right there.
So we're just going to see the bottom right corner of the triangle or seeing the rectangle now.
So if I now refresh.
Yep.
Sure enough, I just see the bottom right corner.
So as you would probably guess, the other two numbers inside of here, the 50 and 50 are how wide we
want the rectangle to be and how tall it should be.
So I can change the width to 100 and now this thing is going to be significantly wider and I can change
the height to 200.
And it'll be significantly taller.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it.
That is some of the very basics of matter.
Jazz essentially.
Once again, everything that we wrote down to about line 14 or so is all boilerplate code, and we're
not going to really change that stuff very often.
In order to get some more functionality inside of our app, we're going to be creating a variety of
different shapes or rectangles or circles or whatever else, and then adding them all to our world.
That is the primary means.
So we get some level of functionality inside of our matter app and that's pretty much exactly what we're
going to be doing for the vast majority of our maze application as we start to put it together.
Okay.
So now that we've got a better idea of what's going on, another quick pause and we'll start writing
some more code in the next video.