Rather than start working on our maze application right away, I first want to try to recreate this
demo very quickly.
Making this demo is actually gonna be easier than you might think, and it's going to just get us a
little bit more familiar with matter just before we dive off the deep end and start worrying about Maze
Generation and a bunch of different crazy topics.
So in order to create this demo right here, we're going to create a variety of different shapes.
We need to make sure that they can all be clicked on and dragged around with the mouse.
We also need to make sure that we show four rectangles along the edges of the canvas as well.
So I need one on top, one on the right, one on the bottom and one on the left.
The purpose of these different rectangles is to just keep our shapes from flying off to the outside
world.
If we go back over to our application right now and we turn off the is static right there, so I'm going
to comment it out and then refresh.
We saw that our shape can very easily just fall off the face of the earth.
So in order to keep this thing on the screen, we just have to show some rectangles around the border
to make sure that it doesn't fall off.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it.
We're going to make sure that we can show a rectangle on the top, right, bottom and left.
So to do so, I'm going to go back over to my index case file.
I'm going to find where I'm creating a rectangle right now, and I'm going to delete it.
And then I will replace that with a comment that says simply Walls.
As we start writing matter G's code, we're going to be creating a variety of different shapes inside
of our index file over and over again.
And so it's usually very good practice to add in some comments to describe the bunch of shapes we're
about to add right here, because otherwise it's going to be kind of challenging to remember exactly
what code creates, what shapes.
So then I'm going to create an array called walls like so.
And inside of here, I'm going to create the four different rectangles that we need.
I'm going to first start with the top rectangle, so I'll call bodies dot rectangle.
Remember that the first two arguments are the x and Y coordinates of the center of the rectangle, and
the third and fourth are the width and height of the rectangle.
For this very first one, let's take a look at a diagram and just make sure that it's really clear what
numbers we're going to put in here.
Yes.
The rectangle you see right here represents our canvas, as we saw just a moment ago.
Our canvas is 800 units wide.
The rectangle that we want to show is essentially going to be like this right here.
Notice that the rectangle is not completely inside of our canvas, and that's totally okay.
That is actually what is going on on the demonstration back over here.
We can see that this rectangle is actually only halfway on the screen.
And that's evident because that little red line right there, the red line is essentially at the center
point of the rectangle.
So the rectangle doesn't have to be all the way on the canvas.
It can be half on, half off.
And that's what we're going to do as well, just to make our code a little bit easier to understand.
So we need to first provide the x y coordinate of the center of this rectangle.
So the center will be approximately right there or so.
So that's going to be 400 units over and it's going to be zero units down.
So a Y of essentially zero.
Then in total this thing is going to be 800 units wide and its height, well, the height doesn't really
make a big difference.
We just need to make sure that we have some kind of rectangle there.
We might use a height of like 40 or so, but really it's totally up to us.
We can have any height whatsoever so long as it has a defined height.
It just can't be zero.
Okay.
So let's now take those values.
Back over to our editor.
So back over here.
I'm going to do a 400.
So that's 400 units over zero units down 800 units wide and 40 units tall.
And then I'll put on the options object, which is static is true.
And then after that, I'm going to make sure that I add this wals array to my world.
So just a second ago we saw that we could call world add with lowercase world and then whatever our
rectangle was.
So like bodies, dot rectangle or whatever.
So we can pass either a single shape in to the world add method, or alternatively we could pass in
an array of shapes as well.
And that's why I created this as a walls array.
So I'm going to pass all these different walls that we're going to create in at once.
So I'm going to save that.
Go back over.
Refresh.
And now I can see the top wall on there.
Okay, so that's a good start.
So now we can repeat that same process for the three other walls as well.
Only just very quickly draw out what the next two or three are going to be.
So for the next one, let me just do a little bit of erasing here just to make sure things are nice
and crystal clear, easy to read so we can do the bottom one next.
So once again, this is going to be.
400 units over.
It's going to be.
Now 600 units down because remember, our overall canvas is a 100 by 600.
It will be 800 wide and once again, we can use 40 tall.
So I'm going to call.
Body is not rectangle again.
We're going to be 400 units over this time.
We're going to be 600 units down.
We're going to be 800 units wide and 40 tall.
Then is static.
It's true.
So once again, save, refresh, and now I can see the bottom border.
Kate, let's get through the last to here really quickly.
So I think you get the idea now.
But honestly, we're going to have to do all this dimensional stuff so often for this application that
it's kind of worth just putting in a little bit of time from the get go to make sure that these different
values are really clear.
So let's now do our left barrier.
So this one will be slightly different.
So again, we are 800 by 600 overall.
So we're now going to go down.
300 units.
We're going to go over zero.
This thing is going to be 40 units wide now and 600 units tall.
And then something very similar for the right hand side.
We're going to be.
Throwdown.
You're going to be 800 over.
So 800 to the right.
We'll have 600 tall.
And 40 wide.
Yes.
Let's do both of those.
Ortiz Dots rectangle.
So we'll do the left hand side first.
So this one is going to be zero over 300 down.
40 wide, 600 tall.
And then finally the right hand side.
So we'll do 800 over.
300 down.
40 wide, 600 tall.
And I'll get the static.
True as well.
Okay.
So let's save that.
Hopefully I didn't make any mistakes.
If I did, we'll do a little bit of troubleshooting very quickly, but I'll refresh and okay, it actually
all was correct.
So I've got top, bottom, left and right.
So now if we go back over once again.
And I add in one last rectangle, like the same kind of plain rectangle that we had before.
And this time, rather than assigning it to a variable, I'll just add it into the world directly.
So I'll do a world ad with the world bodies dot rectangle.
And this time I'll do 202 hundred 5050.
Save this refresh, and now our rectangle falls down.
But it hits that other one and it just stops right there.
Okay, so that's definitely a good start.
So let's take a pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to throw in a ton of other shapes and we'll make sure
that we can drag them all around with our mouse.
So a quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.