Now that we have these borders around the edge of the screen, I want to try to enable click and drag
functionality on this single little square right there.
So more or less the same behavior that we see over here when we click and drag on a shape.
Adding in this click and drag functionality is really surprisingly easy to do.
This is something that matter DJs wanted to make, really easy to add to any project.
So it's just a couple of lines of code to add in the ability to click and drag something to move it
around.
To get started, I'll find my index file.
I'll go up to the top and find where we are.
Pulling off some different properties from the matter library.
I'm going to pull off another property called Mouse Constraint.
So we're going to use this object right here to set up something called, you guessed it, a mouse constraint.
This essentially means that we're going to set up something to respond directly to mouse input.
I'm going to go down right after our runners run line and I'm going to create the constraint and then
add it to our world.
So I will say world ad world.
And I'm going to pass in as the second argument mouse constraint create.
As the first argument to that I'll pass in my engine.
And then as the second argument, I'll pass in an options object that's going to have a mouse property.
And for that I'll say mouse create render dot canvas.
And I think I missed one other thing that we have to require into this file or de structure off of matter.
We need to make sure we grab mouse as well.
So I'm going to go back up here and just make sure that I pull in the mouse object as well.
Okay.
So believe it or not, that is pretty much it right there.
So I'm going to save this.
I'm going to go back over and now if I refresh, I can click and drag on that object and throw it around
the screen.
You'll notice that when I click and drag, I get that kind of green line that's supposed to represent
a spring or essentially a force that we are trying to apply to this little square.
So now all we have to do is start to add in a bunch of other shapes to this thing, and we'll have something
very much like the demo that we saw back over here.
So another quick pause and let's try to add in a bunch more shapes in the next video.