Last thing I want to do to replicate that little demo we were looking at over here is to just make sure
that we can show a bunch of different shapes at the same time.
And there's not really any magic to this.
And that's why I want to show you how to do it in a little demo.
When I say that there's no magic to it, I mean, essentially we're going to do the same thing as what
we did before.
We're just going to create a bunch of different rectangles and add them into the world.
That's it.
So I'm going to find where we're creating that one single lone rectangle by itself right now.
I'm going to get a little comment right above it that says something like random.
Shapes.
Again, just to remind myself of what this code right here is about to do, and then I'll set up a four
loop around that statement.
So I'll say four, let I starting at zero i less than 20 I plus plus.
And I'll throw that in there like so.
Let's save this.
This should create 20 rectangles all on the exact same spot with the same size.
So if I go back over and refresh, we're going to see very quickly that they kind of like spread out.
That's because matter just wants to allow all these shapes to just contact each other on the edges.
When we create a bunch of different shapes on the exact same point, Maddox freaks out and tries to
distribute those all around the screen.
And that's why we end up seeing them all kind of stack up like so.
So a slightly better way to handle this would be to slightly randomize the starting positions of 202
hundred.
In order to randomize those starting positions, we can multiply the starting position by.
The width and the height of the canvas overall.
And that should give us some even distribution all around the screen to make sure that I multiply by
the width and the height correctly.
I'm going to define the width and the height up here at the top as constants.
They'll say width is 800.
And height is 600.
So now down here at options, I can replace the numbers with just width and height.
And because the keys and the values are the same, I can leave it just like that.
And those will be expanded to width is width and height is height.
You might be curious why we're pulling out these separate variables right here.
Well, it's because I essentially want to refer to the white height and width later on down the file.
If we start to reproduce numbers like 608 hundred down here on this line of code, it might be hard
later on to figure out exactly why we are using the numbers 806 hundred.
And so by defining a constant at the very top, that means that if we ever want to change these values,
we can change them in one location.
And that will make updates all throughout the file.
This is a technique that we're going to use quite a bit when we start working on the Maze version of
this app in just a moment.
So now we can use those two variables to do some random placement.
So for the position on the x axis, I'm going to say math random times with.
And then for the position on the y axis, I'll do math.
Random.
Time's height and I'll save just to get that all down to multi lined like so.
Okay.
So that should now give us some random distribution about the entire canvas.
So let's now save this, go back over refresh.
And there we go.
That's a little bit closer to the demo we saw over here where they all get kind of randomized.
All right.
So now the last thing that we need to do is to just try to create some different kinds of shapes instead
of just squares.
So for that inside of our for loop, we can add in a little if statement.
I'm going to create a random number.
So again, math random.
Remember when we called math random?
That's going to create a number between zero and one.
I'm going to check to see if that is greater than 0.5.
If it's greater than 0.5, then I'm going to go ahead and create a rectangle.
Otherwise I'm going to create a different shape altogether.
So if we don't create a rectangle and we have a value less than 0.5, I'm going to instead try to create
a circle.
So I'll do another world add.
I'm going to add a shape to the world.
And then as the second argument, I'll put in bodies dot circle.
The Circle method right here is very similar nature to rectangle.
The first two arguments are going to be numbers that represent where we want to put the circle in the
world, and we have to put in those two values as XY coordinates so we can use the same trick we use
right above.
So I'll say.
Math at random times with.
And math random.
Times height.
Then the third argument is a little bit different.
The third argument is going to be the radius of the circle.
So in this case, I'll do.
How about a slightly larger circle than the rectangles we're adding right now?
So I'll do a radius of.
Well, actually, technically, it'd be like, how about 35 or so?
That's the radius.
So the entire diameter or like the full width of the circle will be 75, which will be just a little
bit larger than the rectangles we're adding in.
It's all save this as well.
Refresh.
And there we go.
Now, if you want to, we can adjust the number of shapes we're adding in.
So instead of the 20 right there, we could do like say 50.
Just make sure that you don't add in too many shapes because otherwise your browser is going to lock
up due to the processing power from trying to figure out what to do with all these shapes.
So I'd say that's pretty close to the demo we just saw.
Now you will notice that these the demo over here has those little lines.
The lines are meant to indicate the orientation of each shape.
We can easily add those in by just adding in another option or two.
We will worry about that just yet.
But there is one other option I thought you might be curious about.
Right now we are operating the entire canvas in what is called wireframe mode.
In wireframe mode.
That means that we just see the outline of each shape.
But if we want to.
We can go back up to where we create our render.
Here it is right here.
And to the options object we can put in wireframe is false.
So that means try to render a solid shape as opposed to just the outline.
And we do a wireframe at false.
Excuse me.
I think it's capital F.
Let's try that.
Nope.
I'm totally wrong.
Wireframes.
That's what it is.
Sorry, I was going off of memory here.
Lowercase, f, plural.
That's better.
Okay.
So when we set wireframes to false, we're going to get solid shapes and the colors for them will be
picked at random.
There we go.
So now you can even see that the bordering shapes or the bordering rectangles are solid as well.
Personally, I like the wireframe just a little bit more, but when we eventually put the mace together,
I think you're going to find that showing the maze with some solid shapes instead of wireframes just
makes the maze look a little bit more interesting.
Last thing I want to mention is that we can customize the color that is being used.
If we go to where each shape is being created.
So let's say that for each circle, maybe we want them all to be the color red.
We can find where we create the circle.
So that's the body start circle right here.
And then as the last argument, we can put in an options object.
And inside there we can add in a little render property.
So this is going to customize how the circle gets rendered onto the screen.
So inside of this new render object, we can add in fill style.
And that can be any valid CSS color.
So it can be like a normal color, like red.
It could be a hex value and so on.
I'll try out Red really quickly.
So I'll save now all the circles are red.
Or I can do, say green.
And now I've got a bunch of green circles.
All right.
So that's pretty much it for the demo we've seen, basically, believe it or not, just about everything
that you need to see to build out the maze.
There's only one or two additional topics that we need to be aware of when it comes to matter.
That is to actually build the maze out.
And that's really just understanding how to control a single shape using the keyboard instead of the
mouse.
So we'll figure that out.
Honestly, that's not the worst thing in the world at all.
It's actually rather easy to add in the keyboard controls.
So most of the stuff around the maze that we're going to be doing is just discussing the algorithm we're
going to use to calculate the shape of the maze.
All right.
So let's take a pause right here.
We'll come back to the next video and start working on our Maze code.