Now that we understand the general algorithm, I want to give you a couple more details that's really
going to flesh out how we're going to implement this in our version of building out this maze.
So as I said just a moment ago, we're going to end up having a grid of sorts and this great is going
to be a two dimensional array.
It's going to have some number of rows.
In this case, it would have three rows because there's one, two, three, and there would be three
columns.
He goes one, two and three.
Having the grid alone is not quite enough or not the most convenient way of writing out this algorithm,
however.
So we're going to introduce one other data structure or really technically to other structures inside
of here to kind of keep track of how we're going to actually generate this entire grid.
So when we spoke about how are we going to build this thing out in the last video, I said several times,
Oh yeah, we're going to remove this wall between two different cells.
So the real question here is how are we going to track where there is a wall and where there is not
a wall?
Well, to keep track of where there are walls and not, we're going to add in two different pieces of
terminology.
We're going to say that if there is a wall between two different cells that are right next to each other
on the same row.
So this wall right here, we're going to call that wall a vertical wall.
If there is ever a wall between two cells in a column.
So like this one and this one right here, we're going to call this wall right here.
A horizontal.
So there are two types of walls that we're going to be concerned with, vertical and horizontal.
To keep track of where there are any walls.
We're going to add in two additional arrays.
These are also going to be two dimensional arrays that we're going to keep track of in addition to the
grid one.
So we're going to introduce another variable or another to array here called verticals.
And that's going to keep track of wherever there is a vertical wall.
And another one called, as you would probably guess, horizontals.
And this is going to keep track of wherever there is a horizontal wall.
Now, you can just about guarantee 100% that you're going to get confused by the terminology, verticals
and horizontals several times as we are writing out this code.
So please right now really committed to memory that the verticals array is going to keep track of walls
that go up and down and the horizontal array is going to keep track of walls that go side to side like
so.
Inside of both these arrays.
Like I said, they're going to be two dimensional and they're going to contain a bunch of different
Boolean values.
Each of these Boolean values is going to be either true or false.
A value of true.
Means there is no wall.
So a value of true inside of verticals or horizontals essentially can be interpreted as true.
This is like an open space.
Pulse.
It means that there is a wall.
So now with this knowledge, we can start to take a look at some different sample mazes and get a sense
of the different verticals and horizontals array so we create to represent each one.
So I'm going to do a little bit of your racing here.
And now I want to imagine how we would build up the vertical array and the horizontal array.
If I start to make a couple of changes to this little demo maze that I have right here.
Sorry.
Give me just one minute to clean this thing up.
There we go.
That's better.
Okay.
So I want to imagine for a second how I would build out the horizontals array and the verticals.
One, if I remove that that about that one right there.
That will drop just a few more.
Like so.
So this right here would represent a valid maze.
So now I want to imagine how I would generate or what the different verticals and the horizontals arrays
would look like.
Let's first consider the horizontals.
So again, this would be a two dimensional array.
So I'll put in my outer brackets like so.
And then I'm going to have and this is critical to in-air arrays that represent the two kind of lines
of horizontal bars or walls that I can have.
The first one is right here.
That is one line of horizontal walls.
There's the second one right there.
So in this case, remember false means there is a wall.
True means there is no wall.
So right here there is a wall.
So I would do false and I'll split f or false and then open.
Open.
So true.
True.
Then down here.
Open.
Closed.
So.
True.
False.
So that's how we get from having these different gaps into this horizontals array.
So now we can repeat the same process and consider what this would look like for the vertical array.
So again, let me delete some of this stuff on here very quickly.
And there we go.
That's about good enough right there.
So now we can consider the vertical array.
What would this look like?
Well, once again, this is going to be a two dimensional array.
It's going to have two inner rows inside of it.
The first one, the first row of verticals is going to represent this spacing right here.
And there's the second row right there.
Now I'm using the row, the term row here because I'm talking about like this row and this row.
I'm not talking about like that line because I would really call that a column.
So I'm really talking I'm saying that like this space right here would be the first element.
Then that is the second element.
Third one and so on.
Okay.
So now let's consider how we would fill out the verticals for this case.
So we have open, closed, open.
So that's true.
False.
True.
And then over here we once again have open, closed, open.
So true.
False and true.
So that is the general idea.
Oops, I misspelled verticals, by the way.
So that's the general idea of how we're going to keep track of these different walls.
So we have three data structures in total.
We've got the grid to track all the different actual cells that we have.
So we have nine cells, then we have horizontals to keep track of the walls that run from left to right.
So like along that line right there and that line right there.
And then we have verticals to keep track of the different walls that go from top to bottom.
So right there and right there, one of the most challenging things to understand about this is that
the verticals, horizontals versus the grid array are going to have different dimensions.
So notice that the grid array in this case would have would be a three by three because there are three
columns and three rows.
But the verticals are going to have some very different dimensions.
The verticals are going to have two rows.
So here's row one, row two and three columns inside there.
So one, two, three over.
So a three by two or a two by three versus a three by three for the grid.
All right.
So this is another one of those topics.
We're done with all the diagrams.
This is another one of those topics where obviously, as I'm telling you, this stuff, it's probably
really complicated.
And you might be sitting there thinking, what in the world is going on here?
And by the way, Stephen, I can't read your handwriting.
Totally fine.
We're going to write out the code here.
And as we write the code, I got to tell you, the algorithm actually ends up being kind of clear about
what is going on.
So we're going to write out all of our code.
And I really think that rather quickly you're going to get a good understanding of how this maze is
really being put together.
I can tell you right now from building this thing out several times and figuring out the best way to
explain it, the hardest part to understand about this is the different dimensions between the grid
array or the array that keeps track of which cells we've actually visited and the verticals and horizontals
array.
That is by far the biggest challenging thing, just understanding that there are different dimensions
for each one that we need to be aware of.
So understand that we're going to come back to drawings like this several times as we start to write
out that code and just make sure that every step along the way it is really, really clear where all
these different numbers are coming from.
So that's pretty much it.
Let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to start to write out some code to create the grid
array, the vertical array and the horizontal array as well.
So I'll see you in just a minute.