In this video, we're going to start to refactor our index file and get it ready for a maze.
So we've got some code inside of here right now for that quick little demo.
I'm going to delete a lot of the code related to this demo.
So if you want to, you can always make a copy or a backup of the index JS file as it is right now.
So you still have access to the code for the demo, but I don't really need that code anymore, so I'm
going to delete some of the stuff in here related to creating all those different shapes.
So inside my index file, I'm going to first get started by finding where we created that mouse constraint
right here.
Remember, this is what allowed us to do some click and drag on each of those different shapes.
Our Maze program is not going to have any click and drag functionality, so I'm going to delete all
that mouse related stuff.
I'll also go back up to the top and delete the two D structures we have for the mouse related stuff.
So mouse constraint and mouse.
Next up, I'll go down to the very bottom where we create our random shapes.
So I don't need any random shapes anymore.
It's going to take everything from that comment down to the very bottom and delete it.
All right.
So now the last thing I want to change really quickly, one more refactor.
If we go back up a little bit, you'll notice we've got the height and width right here.
I'm going to change the width to be exactly equal to the height.
So 605, 600.
The reason for this is that some of the logic around our maze actually ends up being a lot easier to
write if we have a perfectly square maize.
So as tall as it is wide.
As soon as we start to get a rectangular maize, some of the math gets just slightly more complicated.
So we're going to first build a version of our maize that works perfectly with it being square, and
then we're going to eventually refactor it to be rectangular in nature as well.
Ultimately, we're going to make sure that the maize spans the entire size of this window.
So like from this top left corner down here to the bottom.
Right.
But for the first implementation, we're going to have it fixed as just 600 by 600.
Now at the 600 by 600, that means we also have to update the placement of some of our different walls,
because these walls currently rely upon a 600 by or 800 by 600 canvas.
So now we have to go through here and update some of these values.
I want you to recall that one of the reasons I said that we would create the height and width variables
up here is to just have the ability to change these numbers right here and have all the appropriate
variables inside of our file update.
So as we start to rewrite or update some of the numbers inside of here, rather than using fixed values
like 406 hundred and 800, I'm going to instead have these numbers be references back up to the height
and width variables up at the top.
So in other words, we're going to have our walls lay themselves out automatically based upon the overall
dimensions of our canvas.
So that means that we will only have to do this one more update.
And then as we start to change these numbers later on, as we want to test out different shapes of mazes,
all of our different walls will relay themselves out appropriately without us messing around with this
code at all.
So we're going to go through here and update each of these rectangles.
We're going to have as few fixed constant numbers as possible.
So let's get to it.
The first rectangle we created represented the top rectangle.
So that's this one up here at the very top edge.
Remember, the first number represents the distance from the top left coordinate to the center of that
rectangle.
So that's essentially the width of our canvas divided by two.
Then the second number or the second argument represents how many units down from that top left corner.
In this case, we are zero units down.
Then the third number was the total width of that rectangle, which would be the width of the canvas
once again, and then the height of that rectangle.
We're going to leave the forties in here as forties, but we might eventually extract them to be assigned
by a variable as well.
All the other numbers inside of here are going to be either zeros or a kind of function based upon our
height in our width.
So let's do these updates.
So the first one right here, again, that's going to be our width divided by two because we're going
to go from the top left halfway over to right there.
So that's the entire width divided by two.
Then the second argument will continue to be zero, because we're going zero units down the entire width
of that rectangle is going to be with.
And then its height will just be 40.
Like I said, we'll leave that as a constant value inside of here for now.
The next rectangle is the one at the bottom of the edge.
So bottom edge of the canvas, that right there.
So in this case, we're going to once again go over width divided by two units, but we're going to
go down height units.
So the entire height of the canvas, we're going to go down the height of the canvas.
So once again, go over to the right with divided by two and I'll go down.
Height units.
The width will once again be width, and the height of the thing itself will be 40.
It's the next one.
The third rectangle that we created was the left hand wall.
So in this case, we are going to the right zero units.
So essentially staying in the same plane or we're going down height divided by two.
So that's still going to be zero.
We're going to have height divided by two.
The width of this thing is going to be 40 and the overall height of the shape itself will be height
units.
In other words, the entire height of the canvas.
And then finally we've got the right hand rectangle as well.
So with this one, we want to go over the entire width of the canvas.
We want to go down with divided by two or be height divided by two.
That's better.
And then the entire height of that rectangle will be height.
So same height as the canvas itself.
So let's save this.
I'm going to go back over.
I'm going to refresh and there we go.
So I've now got a square canvas.
The walls are kind of hard to see here just because the color is not that distinct.
So if I wanted to, I could disable wireframes mode so I could or I could enable wireframes mode so
I can set that to true refresh.
And now those walls are a little bit easier to see.
So as you can guess, the benefit to this approach is that we can now change height with as much as
we want.
So for example, I could go back to 800 by 600 and the walls are going to adjust themselves automatically.
I could go to 1200 by 600.
I could go to 1200 by, I don't know, five or how about 100?
Whatever.
Doesn't matter.
At the end of the day, the walls are going to lay themselves out appropriately.
We're going to try to write out code like this as much as possible, because, again, later on, as
we decide to mess around with some of the different values inside of here, it's going to be a lot easier
to change one number at the top as opposed to messing with a ton of code as we create all the different
shapes.
So it's looks good.
Let's take a pause right here and continue in the next video.