In this video, we're going to start to implement those three different rates we just discussed.
We're going to first take care of the grid array.
I want to first begin by giving you just a very quick reminder on what the grid array does, because
there's a very particular way that we're going to initialize it.
And if you don't really understand what the grid array does well, a lot of the stuff that we're going
to right here is not going to make a lot of sense.
So we're going to have one array called grid and this is going to be a two dimensional array.
It'll be a two DH array.
And every value inside of it is going to start off as false.
The reason that we're going to start off as false.
Remember, the purpose of the grid array is to record whether or not we have visited each individual
cell.
So when we first initialize this thing, it's going to start off as a 2D array.
If this is the maze that we are going to be building, then we're going to have three rows and three
columns.
So here are my three rows.
I'm going to have three columns inside.
And every element is going to start off as false.
So I'm going to put in an F for each one.
We're then going to pick a cell at random.
So maybe the first cell that we pick is this one right here.
We would now say that we have visited the cell because we have essentially done some processing work
on it.
Because we have visited this, we need to update our grid array.
So I'm going to find the element inside the grid array that corresponds to that cell.
So in this case, it would be that element right there.
So I'm going to take that false and I'm going to update it to be true instead.
We can then imagine that we start to go through the algorithm.
Remember, the primary step of the algorithm is to take a look at all the different neighbors.
So that one, that one and that one, and then pick one at random and visit it.
So let's imagine that I go off to the right like so, and I'm now at this cell.
So I would now find the element inside of my grid array that corresponds to that cell.
It is this one right here.
So I would take that false.
Remove it and update it to be true instead.
Yes, that's the purpose of the grid rate.
Let's just focus on creating this array first.
So at the end of the day, what we really want is a two dimensional array that starts off with all false
values inside of it.
And if right now we're going to imagine that we are building a maze that has three rows and three columns,
so we're going to hard code those threes in four right now, but we're going to update those to be a
lot more flexible in just a moment.
So to get started, I'm going to go back over to my code.
I'm going to put a little comment header here that says Maize Generation, again, just to guide myself
through this file.
There's a couple of different ways that we can create this grid array.
I'm going to first show you a very basic way and then we'll refactor it into a little bit more fancy
style.
So a very basic way to do this would be to define a grid array and then iterate using a double nested
for loop so I could save four.
Let I equals zero.
Lesson three plus plus and I'll set up another four loop inside there.
So for let j equals zero j Lesson three j plus plus.
Then in the outer loop, I'm going to use this.
To push in each individual row.
And then inside the inner loop, I'm going to process each of those rows and add in starting values
of false.
So I'll say grid at I.
Dot push false like so.
So I'm then going to console.log this.
I'll save this.
I'll go back over and I'll do a quick test.
So as soon as I reload, I can see the console log right here.
I definitely have the correct structure to start off with, so I've got false plus false false sales,
false and so on.
So this is definitely one way to approach this.
But any time that we start using for loops like this, well, life gets a little bit challenging because
now we've got all these different values and symbols floating around, as we've seen several times throughout
this course.
Usually using a for loop like the one we have right here is not the best way of achieving just about
anything.
So we're going to instead use a little trick to initialize the grid array.
At the end of the day, the code we're about to use is 100% equivalent to what we currently have, but
it's going to be a lot more concise.
So here's what we're going to do.
I'm going to say that cost grid is array of three.
So this means create an empty array that has three possible places in it.
And when we create an array like this, we don't get some imaginary or we don't get some actual values
initialized in there.
So the array is told that it's going to have capacity for three elements, but right now there's no
elements inside there.
So if we were to run a four loop or a four of loop on this or a four each, it would not do anything
at all.
So we have to actually finish initializing this array by calling fill and then putting some default
value inside there.
So in this case, to initialize this thing, we can throw any old value in and I'll show you why we
can put any value in at just a moment.
Right now, I'm going to put in null.
So let me do a console log here and you'll see what we get out of this.
So I've now got.
No, no, no.
Like, so.
So we now want to replace each of those null values with another array that has false values inside
of it.
So to do so, we're now going to map over this array.
And for each element inside of here, we're going to return an array of length three that has the values
of false inside of it.
So that's why it doesn't really matter what value we put inside of here to start.
It doesn't matter that we throw in null because we're just going to replace it right away with a mapping
statement.
So we'll come back here.
I'm going to chain on a mapping statement.
So I'm going to say for each element inside there, throw away the value of null.
We don't care about that.
Instead, return a brand new array that has three elements of false.
So to do so, I'm going to use a very similar statement.
I'll say create a new array that has length three and fill every value inside there with false like
so.
Okay.
So let's save this now.
We'll go back over.
And now you can see that we've got the exact structure that we're looking for.
You might be kind of curious, why do we have the map statement here as opposed to just like throwing
in with a Phil, like, why can't we just put in false, false, false like so?
Well, the reason is, in this case, we are creating one single array and then throwing it in at every
location inside of grid.
So in memory, there's only one inner array.
And if we made a change to this inner array, it would affect every index.
Let me show you that really quickly, because it's actually a really neat little trick.
To do this, you would not expect it to happen.
So here's our Ray.
Those three inter arrays are the same exact arrays in memory.
So if I do grid at zero and I push in a value of true and then I print out grid again, take a look
at that.
It added it to apparently each of these well it didn't add it to each it add it to just the one, but
it's the same array in memory.
So modifying one modifies all.
So that's why we can't just do a direct fill like.
So instead we have to do the map statement.
And when we do the map statement, that's going to run the inner function three times and each time
we're going to generate a brand new and different array.
All right.
So we're going to using this trick right here several times, because at the end of the day, even though
right now it might be kind of hard to read, it ends up being a lot easier in the long run to understand.
And it also makes it a lot easier to come back and adjust the different values to change the size of
the array.
If we ever want to add more rows to our grid, that we're going to change that value of three right
there.
And if we ever want to add more columns, we'll change that three right there.
So imagine for a second that we decide that we want to instead have a.
Extra column on here like so.
So let's say that we want to have a rectangular maze, so we want that to be the starting point.
To get something like that.
We would come back here, we would change the inner arrays to length for instead.
So now we've got four columns instead of the previous three.
So now I could save this refresh and now I can see one, two, three, four.
So, like I said, much more convenient way to create our nested arrays.
All right, so that's it for the grid.
We're going to take a pause right here.
Come back to the next video.
We're going to tackle the verticals and horizontals, arrays as well.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.