In this video, we're going to generate our verticals array and our horizontals array.
Once again, quick reminder on what both those do.
So we have our verticals.
Array and horizontals.
The vertical array is going to keep track of every vertical while we have.
So those right there.
Remember that these arrays are going to have some different dimensions than the grid array.
So in this case, if we have a three by three, the verticals which only represents those labeled segments
right there is going to have.
Three rows.
So there is one row.
There is row to.
And Row three.
But in that side of there, it's going to have two columns.
So to start off, you would have false, false, false, false, false and false.
So then if we start it off randomly right there and decided to move right there, we would find the
corresponding entry inside of verticals that represents that wall segment.
So that would be that one right there.
We would take out that false and update it to true instead.
So then horizontals is very similar nature.
Horizontals is going to keep track.
Let's change the green here of all these horizontal segments.
So likewise, it's also going to start off as a 2D array.
It's going to have two rows.
So Row one and row two.
And then inside those two rows it will have three columns.
So we have false, false, false.
Like so.
So then we can imagine if we started off in this cell right here on the very bottom left hand side,
the matching element inside of our horizontals array.
Is that right there?
If we then go up.
We would change that.
Too true to say that there is now an opening right there which would represent something like that.
Like so.
Okay.
So with this reminder, let's now go back over to our code.
We're going to create verticals and horizontals.
And again, the big thing we have to keep aware of or stay aware of here is that these are going to
have slightly different dimensions than the grid array.
Yes.
Back over.
I'm going to create my array of verticals.
I'm going to create this array inside.
We're with the same style that we use just a moment ago.
So for verticals, I'm going to make an array.
As we just discussed, this thing is going to have three rows inside of it.
So the outer array is going to have length three because one, two and three.
So back over here.
I'm going to create an array with like three.
And then going to fill that up with NULL.
And then map over those values.
And inside, I'll create a new array.
And here's where things get interesting.
The inner array is going to have length to this array right here, two elements to it.
So I'm going to make sure that I do a map and I'm going to get an array with two elements inside, and
I'm going to fill that thing up with a value of false like so.
So now I can repeat the same process for horizontals as well.
So I'll do an array here.
Once again, horizontals is only going to have two rows, so the outer array will have two elements
to it.
I'm going to fill that up.
With any old value because we're going to replace it.
In just a moment.
I'm going to map.
I'll do an array and I bet you can guess what goes there.
The inner arrays on horizontals has 1 to 3 elements.
So I'm going to go back over.
I'm going to make sure that this thing has three elements.
I'm going to fill that thing up with false.
All right, so let's now do a console log of verticals and just make sure we generate the thing correctly.
So I'll flip back over refresh.
So I got verticals as the three rows and it's got the two columns for each.
So that maps up perfectly because we are representing that segment, that segment, all these like so.
And then we can update our console log.
And instead do a horizontals.
Save it.
Go back over, do the refresh.
Check this thing out, Kate.
And this looks good as well.
So we're looking at horizontals now, remember, that's going to represent that that that that, that
and that.
And so we definitely want to have row one, row two, and each of those is going to have three false
values inside of it.
Okay.
So it looks like we've generated all of our data successfully.
Believe it or not, this right here, this is definitely the hardest part.
Without a doubt, just understanding what the purpose of these arrays.
So now we have this stuff together.
The rest of the code we have to write is actually going to be kind of surprisingly easy.
Believe it or not, it's really not the worst thing in the world.
There is one last change I want to make to this code, however, so quick pause.
We're going to come back and you'll notice we've got the value three and two inside of here all over
the place.
So we're just going to make sure that we abstract that out into a configuration variable, just like
we did with height and width up here a little bit ago.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.