At the end of the last video, I mentioned how we've got some hardcoded values inside of here of threes
and twos.
So the values that we currently have inside of here work perfectly for a three by three maze.
Okay, I've really drawn the heck out of this thing, but you get the idea it only works for a three
by three maze.
So if we ever wanted to have some different dimensions for our maze, well, we would have to go back
through and start to update all these different values by hand.
And I can just about guarantee you that we would make a typo somewhere and end up breaking our code.
So I think that we should abstract out these different numbers into a configuration variable.
So I'm going to go back up to the very top of the file.
And I'm going to create a new variable that I'll call cells.
I'm going to start this off as three.
Now the value cells right here is talking about either the number of cells in the horizontal edge or
the vertical edge.
So for right now, we're going to imagine that the variable cells is talking about the number of cells
either that way or that way, because all of our mazes right now are going to be square.
It doesn't really matter which dimension we're talking about.
Again, we are going to eventually allow the creation of mazes that are not square.
So like a three by five.
But right now, everything we create will be square.
So calling that variable cells right now is more or less okay.
But another engineer, if they looked at this, they might think that this is the total number of cells
that we have.
So the name isn't the best thing in the world.
Whatever.
We are going to change that in just a little bit as soon as we add support for rectangular mazes.
So now we can use that variable to go back down and replace all the hardcoded numbers we have inside
of here.
So, for example, I can find three.
Change it to cells.
Change to cells.
Cells.
And cells.
And the two values of two.
Well, as you might guess, those are just going to be cells minus one.
So now you should not have any values of two or three inside of here at all.
One good thing to test right now would be to try to change the value of cells and then console.log out
our grid verticals and horizontals and just to make sure that they still make sense.
So I'm going to try to increase the value of cells to five instead.
I'll then go back down.
I'm going to change the council log to take a look at the grid.
So when I now console.log the grid, I would expect to see a grid of five by five.
So five inner arrays, each of which have five elements inside them.
So if I go back and refresh?
Yep.
There is a five by five, without a doubt.
I can also do the same thing for verticals and refresh.
Yup.
That definitely looks correct.
And I can do the same thing with horizontals.
And I've got a four by five also looks correct.
Now, if you want to, this is a good spot to pull out your pen and paper and draw out what a five by
five maze would actually look like.
And then just make sure that we actually do have the correct dimensions on the verticals and the horizontals
arrays.
So I'm not going to flip back over and mangle my diagram anymore.
I'll let you do that just in case you want to double check those values.
But I think overall this is looking good.
So now we can start to write in some code after these arrays right here where we're going to essentially
walk through that grid, pick those random cells and figure out exactly how we're going to remove all
those walls from the verticals and horizontals arrays so quick, because we'll start that up in the
next video.