Now that we have created those starting data arrays that are going to keep track of the state of our
maze, we can start to implement our actual algorithm.
So step one is to pick a random starting cell, to pick a random starting cell.
We essentially need some starting dimensions or index that points into the grid array.
So if this is our maze right here, we currently have three rows and three columns.
So to pick a random starting cell, I need the index of some row in column inside of here.
So that essentially means we just have to generate a value between zero and two.
So maybe we start off with zero.
And then we need another zero and two.
So maybe we start off with zero as well.
So this would mean row zero and column zero.
So that would be right there.
If we instead got something like a row of two.
And a column of one.
Then we would go to row two, which is right there, and column one which is right there.
Remember, we're starting off at zero here because we're using a ray index notation.
And so with a ray index notation, we have zero one and two and zero one and two.
So to generate these numbers, we essentially just have to take a look at that cells variable that we
just created.
We're going to multiply it by a random number and then we're going to take the OR round that number
down to the lowest integer.
So let's get to it.
Back inside my editor.
Right after we create the horizontals array, I'm going to create a new variable called Start Row,
and that's going to be a math floor.
Of math random.
Times sells.
And I'm going to repeat that same calculation for my starting column as well.
So now if we console.log out those variables.
Of start row and start column that's going to tell us exactly where we're going to start our iteration
at.
So, as usual, a quick test here.
Refresh.
And we get one and three.
Now, that's okay.
If you recall just a second ago, I had changed cells up here to five.
I'm going to take that back down to three really quickly, just to stay in line with the diagram that
I just showed you.
So now if I save this again, now we are going to get some realistic values.
So this would mean start iteration at zero zero 0 to 1 zero and so on.
We can keep refreshing and it's going to show us these different starting points.
So that's a good start.
So now that we've got that starting point.
I'm going to define a function that we're going to call over and over with the starting row and starting
column.
And inside that function, we're going to go through this algorithm where we're going to go through
each of these steps that we just discussed right here.
So I'm going to make a function.
Called Step Through Cell.
That's a ridiculous name if you think of a better name for it.
Feel free to do so.
In my original notes for this, I called it recursive because we're going to eventually do some recursion,
but honestly, call it whatever you want.
Just make sure that it's kind of clear that this is going to be iterating through our maze or a collection
of cells or whatever else.
So when we call this function, we're going to pass in some row in column that we want to visit inside
of our grid.
So then right after step three sell, I'm going to make sure that I call it right away with start row
and start column.
So I'll do step.
Through cell.
And I'll pass in my start row and start column.
So then inside of here is where we're going to start to put together all of our logic.
I'm going to first begin by putting a couple of comments inside of here just to guide myself and make
sure that I put down the correct sequence of steps.
I'm going to generally be using this right here as a template for what I need to do inside of this function.
So to get started, I'm going to first say if I have visited these cell at row column.
Then return.
So remember, if we visit a cell already, then we should return early.
We don't want to do anything if we've already visited this cell.
So if we get past that little check right there, then we'll say, mark this cell as being visited.
Remember to keep track of what cells we visited, we have the grid array.
So if we look at the grid at some index and we have a value of false, that means it has not been visited.
So when we say that we want to mark the cell as visited, that means that we want to go into that grid
array and update some element inside of it to true.
That's what makes a cell being marked as visited.
Then after that, we're going to assemble randomly ordered list of neighbors.
Then for each neighbor.
So I bet you can guess that we're going to do some iteration there.
So for each neighbor, we're going to do a series of steps.
First off, we went to check to see.
If that neighbor is out of bounds.
So at some point in time, with all this logic inside of here, we might end up trying to visit, like
or be out of cells, say, right here.
And if we try to look at all the neighbors around us, well, obviously there's above into the right.
But we might also kind of accidentally write into our code that there is a cell below or to the left
when, of course, there isn't one at all.
So to handle the case in which we accidentally try to visit some cell that doesn't exist, well, we
just need to make sure that we add in some code to check and make sure that we don't try to go in some
direction that doesn't exist.
So that's what this step right here is going to do.
After that, we will check to see if we have visited.
Visited that neighbor.
Continue to next neighbor.
So we're going to end up with two checks to see if we have visited a cell.
That's just to a little bit defensive coding.
We don't really have to add in two separate checks.
This is just for our benefit.
In case we ever make a mistake, we can eventually remove one of the two checks if we really want to.
So then after that, if we've gotten past these two checks.
Then we're going to go ahead and visit that next cell.
So we're going to say visit that next cell.
And of course, before that, we need to make sure that we remove a wall from either the horizontal
array.
Or the verticals array, and that depends upon whether we are moving to left, right, up or down.
And then when we say right here, visit that next cell, that essentially means call our step through
cell function again.
And pass in the row and column of the cell that we are now trying to visit.
So that is it.
That is the entire algorithm right there.
That's pretty much all the steps.
So we're really just going to come back through.
And for each of these different comments, we're going to add in like 1 to 3 or four lines of code.
So at the end of the day, like I said, the algorithm is really not the worst thing in the world.
As long as you've got a sheet of paper that you can use to kind of diagram out what we're doing at each
step.
So now that we've got some guiding comments here, let's take a pause and start to fill in our implementation
in the next video.