Now that we have these guiding comments, we can start to put some implementation together.
So to get started with the first comment right here, we want to check to see if we have visited the
current cell specified at row and column.
Remember, our grid array is what is keeping track of the different cells that we have visited.
So we essentially want to look in that two dimensional array, look at the appropriate element inside
there and see if it is true.
If it is true, that means we have already visited the cell at row and column, and so that means that
we would want to return right away.
So I will say if.
Grid at row.
So that's going to select our row and column is equal to true then return.
Now this is a funny little thing.
Here we are storing boolean values inside the grid, so grid at row column is either going to be true
or false.
So we don't really need the comparison there because if it's true, well, true is true.
And so we are going to enter the if statement and return right away.
So if we get past that check, then we will go ahead and mark the cell as being visited.
So we just need to look at that same element inside of the grid and update its value to be true, to
indicate, hey, we've been here.
We visited this cell.
So I'm going to say grid at row and column is true.
That's pretty much it for the first two steps.
Let's immediately do some testing.
Just we can verify everything is working as expected.
So I'm going to go down to the bottom.
We're going to call step through cell one time with our random start and column start row and start
column.
And then after that I will console.log out my grid.
So because we are calling step through cell exactly one time right now, I would expect to find one
element inside there that has been updated to true and it should be random.
So if I refresh the page several times, a different element should be getting set to true.
So go back over and refresh.
I can expand the console.log and there we go.
So one value inside of here has been set to true a refresh again.
And I now see a different element and a different element set to true.
So these are the starting locations of our iteration to build out the maze.
So now that we have.
Mark, that is true.
That means that we visited this cell.
So the next thing we need to do is assemble a randomly ordered list of neighbors.
So a quick reminder on what that means.
Let's imagine that we randomly select to visit that center cell on this grid.
On the first step.
So we randomly select that right there.
So we need to assemble a list of all the neighbors.
So that's going to be above to the right below and to the left.
So one, two, three and four.
In other words, we need to determine the row in column indices of each of these pairs.
So remember, our rows are on the left hand side, so zero one and two.
Those are the rows.
The columns are up top, so zero one and two.
So we need to say if we are at row one, column one, we need to select the cell right above at row
zero, column one.
We also need to get the cell at one zero.
The one at one two and the one at two one.
So this might seem like kind of a hard problem to figure out the different indices or these different
neighbors.
But in reality, it's actually really easy.
Let me show you how.
Right now, we know that we are at row.
One.
Column one.
That is our starting cell.
So we can actually figure out what all the different neighbors are by just doing a little bit of directed
manipulation or some arithmetic on these starting values.
The cell right above.
So I'll say here, the sell above is always going to be at row minus one.
And the same column.
We can actually check the math on this very quickly.
So I met one one to start.
If I want to go above to this cell right here.
Then I would take row minus one.
So one minus one is zero.
That puts me on that row right there.
And then the same column that I'm at previously are at right now.
So my column right now is one.
So row minus one and column is going to put me right here.
And that's going to work for any value of starting row and column.
Then if I want to go to the right and get the cell at the right, that's always going to be the same
row as whatever I'm starting at.
And call them plus one.
So in other words, I'm going to take the same row of one.
I'm going to take the column I'm at right now, which is one.
Add one to it and I get to.
Then to get the cell below.
They'll be at row plus one and same column.
And I think you can see where this is going to get the sell to the left.
It's always going to be the same row and column minus one.
So we really just have to add or subtract one to our different row and columns to get all of the neighboring
cells.
That's all we have to do.
So now that we understand this, we can build out a list of all the different neighbors or essentially
the coordinates of each of them by applying those rules right here on assemble randomly ordered list
of neighbors.
I'm going to say neighbors.
Is an array.
And I'm going to list out in a row column notation the coordinates of the different neighbors around
the current cell.
So using the list we just went through.
I'm going to first start off at the we'll start at the top first.
How about that?
So I'll do the row.
Minus one.
And whatever the current column is.
Next to the right, we'll do our row and column plus one.
Then below is going to be Roe plus one.
And the same column.
And then finally to the left is going to be the same row, but column minus one.
So those are the coordinate pairs of all of my different neighbors.
So now the next thing we have to do is randomly sort this list.
The randomly sorting part of this list is what's going to actually give us a randomized looking maze,
adding it.
The random sorting logic or the kind of shuffling logic is a little bit more complicated.
So let's take a quick pause and tackle that in the next video.