We now have our neighboring coordinate pairs right here.
So now we need to take that list of coordinate pairs and randomize them.
This is going to make sure that there is a strong randomization factor inside of our maze.
If we always use this same order to visit our neighbors, then our maze is going to always look the
exact same.
So this is what is going to generate our randomness inside of our maze.
Now, unfortunately, the JavaScript language does not have any functionality built into it to randomize
the elements inside of an array.
So we're going to have to write out a little function to do that for us.
So I'm going to go up to the top of this section where I've got my maize generation comment, and inside
of here I'm going to define a new function called shuffle.
So this is going to take some array and then randomly reorder all the elements inside of it.
We're going to write out the code for this pretty quickly and I'll explain what's going on along the
way.
So instead of shuffle, I'm going to first get the length of the array and assign it to a variable that
I'll call a counter.
Well, then set up a while loop that I'm going to run until counter or while counter is greater than
zero.
Then inside the loop, I'm going to get a random index inside of the array.
So I'll say let index or me const index.
Is math for.
Math.
Dutch random.
Times counter.
That's going to be a random index inside of the array.
And then going to decrease my counter variable by one.
So count your minus minus.
And then finally I'm going to swap the elements that are at the array at element or add index of index
and at the index of counter.
So this is what is going to be the actual kind of swapping of elements to randomize the order.
So I'll say Colin's temp short for temporary is RR at counter.
Well then update the value add index of counter to error at index and I'll update the element at index
to be whatever was previously at counter.
And then finally at the bottom, I will return the array.
So again, we're finding some random element inside there and swapping whatever that random index is
with whatever is at counter that will ensure that we swap each element at least one time.
Okay.
So let's go back down.
To where we generate all of our neighbors.
So right here, I'm going to wrap that function with Shuffle.
And then do a console log right after it.
Now to really test this out and make sure that we've got some correct values being generated and that
they are in some random order.
We should probably stick in some starting row in column to our function that we know is going to have
some proper input or excuse me, proper output.
So we know that if we start at this one one index right here, we should see outputs of 011, zero one,
two and two one.
So if we stick in one one, those are the outputs we should get, but they should be in some randomised
order.
That's going to make this a lot easier to test than if we stick in the random start row and start column.
So I'm going to update those two values to be one for just right now.
I'm going to change it.
Back in just a moment.
I'm also going to remove the console log of grid just so we can read the console a little bit more easily
without seeing a bunch of console logs start to stack up.
All right, so I'll save this.
I'm going to go back over and refresh.
So here are the four coordinate pairs that are around one one, and they should be in some randomized
order.
So let's see.
I've got one zero.
Let's check each of these off one by one.
I know it'll be a little bit disorienting, but let's go through it.
So one zero.
That's the first one.
We got that.
Next is zero one right there.
Next is to one.
Right there.
And then finally, one, two, right there.
So we definitely have all four.
Well, that's fantastic.
And the only other thing we have to do is make sure that they get randomized each time.
So I'll do another refresh.
So I now see them in a very different order.
And another different order and another different order.
So let's say that we definitely have this kind of shuffling logic down pat.
So this is looking pretty good.
I'm going to remove that console log.
We'll take a pause right here.
And when we come back in the next video, we're going to make sure that we add in some logic to iterate
through each of these different neighboring pairs and run some logic on each of them.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.