The next thing we have to do is make sure that we iterate over each of these neighbor pairs.
So I'm going to set up a four of loop to iterate through all these different neighbors.
So we'll say four let neighbor of neighbors.
I'm going to put the closing curly brace for the for loop right above this very last comment like so.
So then inside of here, we're going to do a couple of different checks.
We first need to see if that neighbor is out of balance.
So remember, if we centered on the element like right here, we have definitely got all four.
Sides covered inside of that neighbor's array.
So we definitely do not want to go above or to the left at all.
So to implement this, we can just add in a little bit, clever logic right here.
First, right above, I'm going to get access to the neighbor variable.
I'm going to pull a couple of variables out of it using array de structuring.
So I'm going to say next row and next column.
And that's going to come from the neighbor variable.
So next row and next column is essentially the cell that we are thinking about visiting next.
So to do this check and see if that neighbor is out of balance.
I'll say if next row is less than zero.
Or.
Next row is greater than or equal to cells.
Remember, we define cells at the very top up here.
That's going to be the total number of cells in both the horizontal and vertical direction.
So a check of.
Greater than or equal to cells is going to handle the case in which we are trying to walk off to the
far right hand side or the far bottom edge as well.
We can also check to see if next column is less than zero or next column is greater than or equal to
cells as well.
I'm going to zoom out for just a second so you can see that whole line very easily.
So if we encounter this situation right here and we do have a neighbor that is out of bounds that we're
trying to visit, we still want to iterate through all the remaining neighbors, but we don't want to
run any other code for this particular neighbor, period that we are looking at right now.
So to do so, we'll use the continue.
Keyword.
Remember, the continue keyword means don't leave this for loop, just don't do anything else for the
current iteration of the current step.
So essentially skip over all the rest of the stuff in here and move on to the next neighbor pair.
So then after that, this is going to be kind of a more challenging step.
We need to check to see or assume that this one is going to be easy.
We need to see if we visited this neighbor and if we have, we'll just continue to the next neighbor
to recall that inside of our grid array we are storing all those booleans of true or false to record
whether or not a certain cell has been visited.
So all we have to do here is look at if grid.
At next row.
Next column is true.
Then continue as well.
We could technically combine these two if statements together into one.
But personally I think that breaking them out separately, just make sure it's really clear about exactly
what's going on inside of our code.
And anyone else who reads this in the future can look at this comment and just understand exactly what
these two if statements are really looking for.
Okay, now here's the part that's going to be a little more challenging.
So now we need to take a look and decide if we are trying to go up or down, left or right.
And depending upon that, we need to update either the verticals array or the horizontals array.
So once again, let's imagine that we're at that center cell right here.
So if we are going up or down, we are crossing over a horizontal element and that means we need to
update the horizontal array.
Otherwise, if we are going left or right, we are crossing over a vertical element and that means we
need to update the vertical array.
Now, unfortunately, with only the information that we have inside of this for loop right now, it's
just a little bit challenging to decide if we are going up, down, left or right in order to really
decide that we could do some kind of comparison between next row and next column versus the row and
column variables that we currently have.
So we can essentially subtract each of these from each other and use that to determine which direction
we are traveling.
But there is a way easier way to do it than that.
Remember the array right here of neighbors we put together?
We said that row minus one was going to be above.
And then the next one is going to be going down and then the next one is going to be going to the right.
Or excuse me, did I get that in the wrong order?
Sorry.
That's going up to the right, down to the left.
So in order to make that really clear and communicate that ordering down into our for loop, we can
just throw on a third element to these arrays and we can use that third element as kind of a flag to
determine what direction we are traveling in down when we get to this statement down here.
So as the third element in these arrays, I'm going to say a string right here of this one.
We are moving up.
Then, right?
Then down and then left.
So then inside of our structuring statement right there, we're pulling out the next row in next column.
We can also get the direction that we are traveling excuse me, direction that we are traveling in.
So we can use that variable right there to decide which way we are going and use that to decide if we
are going to modify either horizontals or verticals.
Now, the rest of the logic we need for this step is just a little bit complicated.
So let's take a quick pause right here and discuss exactly what has to be done in the next video.