Last thing we have to do is to make sure that we remove the wall whenever we are traveling up or down,
left or right.
So I want to first get a quick reminder by taking a look at a diagram at how we're going to update horizontals
and verticals.
Before I show you the diagram, however, or before we walk through it, I just want to remind you that
inside this function, we have access to a couple of different variables.
First, we have access to the row and column.
That is the current row and column that we're working on.
We also have access to the next row and next column, and that's where we are traveling to.
So just keep specifically the row and column variables in your head for right now, because we're going
to use those quite heavily in this last block of code that we write right here.
Okay, so let's get to it.
So what I want to focus on is how we're going to update the horizontals and the verticals array.
We're going to first consider how we're going to update horizontals.
So we're going to imagine that we're at this center cell right here, which means that our initial row
is one.
And our initial column is one as well.
And then we're going to imagine that we move only left or right.
So only thinking about verticals right now.
As a reminder, verticals are that that all these walls that I'm circling right now.
So verticals in general.
Is always going to be, remember, a two dimensional array.
It's always going to have three rows.
So row one, two and three.
So here's row one.
Row two.
And three.
And then they all start off as false inside their.
So this false right here corresponds to that element right there.
This false corresponds to that right there and so on.
So what we really want to determine when we are deciding to go either left or right, right here from
the center element is whether we are flipping that to true or that to true.
That is the big question here.
And we need to decide which of these to flip based upon the direction we are traveling and our current
row and column.
So let's figure out how to take the current row and column and the direction and translate it into some
index that we can use to access the vertical array and update the appropriate element.
Okay.
So the actual row that we're going to update, that's actually pretty easy.
The row that we're going to update inside the verticals array.
We put Roe right here.
It's always going to be whatever the current row is that we're looking at because we're always staying
inside of the same row.
So row is never going to change when we update verticals or whenever we move left or right.
However, the same is not true of column.
So whenever we decide to move left or right, the column index that we want to update is going to be
either zero or one.
So either that element or that element.
If we are moving to the left.
And we want to update the element at column zero.
That would be that one right there.
So that's if we were going that way, we want to dump this element right here.
So that means we need to access the verticals array at column zero and update what is ever right there
to a true.
On the other hand, if we are moving to the right, then we want to update this thing right here and
flip it from true to false.
So that would be this element right here.
So if we are going to the right.
That means that we want to return an index of one because we want to get index of one and update this
guy.
So it's pretty clear here that when we are moving left or right, the row is always going to stay the
same.
But depending upon whether we are going left or right, we need to either assess verticals at zero or
one.
That's all I'm trying to establish here.
So now that we understand that, let's go back over to our editor and start to write out this logic.
Okay.
So I've got my statement right here.
We want to remove a wall from either horizontals or verticals, so we're going to first think about
moving left or right.
So let's say if direction.
Remember, we've got the direction variable that we stuffed into the neighbors array.
If that is left, then I want to access verticals.
At the exact same row that we were working on, because, remember, the road doesn't change at all.
It's only the column that changes.
So if we're going to the left, we're going to look at columns minus one.
And it's minus one, because remember, we start off with a column of one.
That's the column that we're at right now.
So we're going to take one off to get zero.
And then if we are, we're going to set that to true, which means there is an opening here so we can
handle the else if case.
Otherwise if direction is right.
And we want to look at verticals again still on the same row, but in this case at the same exact column,
we're going to update that to true.
And I apologize.
I typed in a columns right here that should be column singular like so column in both cases.
And that's pretty much it.
So in both cases we've got the same exact row we're updating, but if we're going left, we're going
to update at column minus one.
Otherwise, if we're going right, we're going to update at the current column to true.
All right.
So now it would really be nice to test this out.
So to test this out.
I'm going to go back up to where we establish all of our neighbors.
And I'm going to comment out the first three cases.
So I'm going to say the only possibility here is that we can travel left.
And then going to go back down.
And make sure that I'm still calling.
Step three sell with a fixed value of one and one.
And I'll save this.
Go back over to the browser refresh.
I'm going to print out the verticals variable and now I can see that I have correctly updated that element
like this one right here.
That one got updated to.
True.
So that definitely worked out correctly.
And that was for a move to the left.
So now we can repeat that same process, but I'll comment out everything but a movement to the right.
So now I'm going to only be able to move to the right.
So I'll save this refresh.
Burnt out verticals.
And now I see right there awesome updated to true because I was moving to the right and once again that's
because we wanted to update that one right there to true to represent an opening in that wall right
there.
Okay.
So I think that we've got our verticals put together.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
We're then going to repeat the same exact process, but with our horizontals instead.
So quick, follow us and I'll see you in just a minute.