All right.
We've established how to update verticals.
Now it's time to do the same thing for horizontals as well.
So we're going to once again imagine that we're sitting right here in the middle.
And we're going to go only either up or down.
So we want to update either that or that right there.
So let's think about the structure of horizontals again.
So remember, horizontals has some very different dimensions.
It's going to be a 2D array, but it's going to have only two rows inside of it.
And three columns because we are representing one, two, three and then row two is one, two, three.
So they all start off as false.
So just to be really clear, that element right there corresponds with that.
Well, that element corresponds with that wall and so on.
So now if we think about moving up or down once again, we're going to establish that we've got a starting
row of one and a column.
Equal to one.
And that represents the cell that we are currently in right here.
So we need to figure out how we can essentially take these values and depending on the direction, access
and update either that element or that element.
So once again, we can kind of ignore one of these variables.
In this case, it's column.
So whenever we move up or down, column is always going to stay the same.
So we are going to update the element at column equal to whatever the current column is.
However, the row variable is going to change depending upon the direction we are going.
So if we are going up.
Then Roe needs to be whatever the current ROE is, minus one.
To get that one right there.
And then if we are going down.
And Roe is going to be whatever the current ROE is to get this element right there, that wall, which
is that right there.
So in that case, it would be ROE, which is, in other words, one in our case.
So to get from the central element up, it's going to essentially be either row minus one.
And if we're going down, it's going to be whatever the current row is.
And then column either way is going to stay the same.
Okay.
So now we understand that let's go back over and write out these if cases as well as well.
So I'll say else if direction is up.
And we want to look at horizontals in this case.
We want to look at row minus one and the same column.
And we want to update that to true.
And then else if.
Direction is down.
And we'll look at horizontals.
I'm going to take whatever the current row is and the exact same column.
And I'll set it to true.
And that's pretty much it.
Okay.
So just like we did before, we're going to comment out a couple of the possible different directions
and just do a quick test and make sure that everything is working correctly.
So I'm going to comment outright and we'll first try up right here.
So again, if we are going to successfully go up, we want to update that element right there, which
will be an index of Row Zero, column one.
Yes.
I'll save this.
I'm going to go back over to the browser, refresh, print out horizontals.
Here's my two by three array and yep, I updated the correct value.
So now we can test the same exact thing as well going down.
So we'll comment out, up and uncomment down.
So if we correctly update down, we should be updating that one right there to true.
So I'll save refresh do a horizontals again.
And right there we've updated to.
True.
Perfect.
Okay.
So that's it.
I know this is probably been pretty nasty, but that is the hardest part of understanding this maze
stuff is just understanding that depending upon the direction we are going, we have to adjust the indices
of what we are, of what wall we are trying to update.
All right.
So last thing I'm going to do here is essentially restore my code to a working state.
So I'm going to uncomment all these different directions.
I'm going to make sure I get some commas back in there because my code formatter add on automatically
removed them.
I'll then go back down to my step through cell call right here.
And I'll throw in my start row and my start column.
Okay.
So last thing we have to do is visit that next cell.
So we'll take care of that in the next video.