Now that we are forming up the verticals and horizontals are raised correctly and we know we are because
we've done a pretty good amount of testing, we can now move on to the next neighboring cell and essentially
reverse through all of our different cells, calling step through cell each individual time.
Remember the entire idea here of how we form the maze?
We start off at some individual location, we then move on over here and then we repeat the same process
for this cell going to all of its neighboring cells as well that we have not yet visited.
So it is this recursion that's going to make sure that we walk through all the different cells of our
little maze.
Okay.
So to do the iteration or the recursion, we'll go back down to the if statements we were just working
on.
Here they are right here and right after the if statement still inside the for loop, I'm going to call
step through cell.
With next row and next column like so.
So now let's save this.
We're going to go back over to the browser.
I'm going to refresh and then I'll print out verticals and horizontals.
And now in both these arrays, we should see some number of values of both false and true.
I'm going to take these false and true values, and I'm going to go over to our little diagram right
here, and I'm going to manually erase some of the walls and see if it forms an actual maze like the
one that we're trying to generate.
Okay.
So we have verticals of.
I'm just going to write this down really quickly.
True, false, false, true.
And then horizontals of false.
True.
False.
So these are our verticals and these are our horizontals.
So again, this kind of value right here corresponds to that one right there.
And for example, that true down there corresponds to that wall right there.
So I'm going to go through any race, all the true walls.
Because remember, true means that there is no wall available or no wall present.
So first we'll take our verticals.
So I'm going to delete that one and that one.
And that one.
So now the only verticals remaining are that and that.
So I can repeat the same process for horizontals as well.
So I've got on horizontals.
False.
True.
So that's open.
That is open.
True.
And true.
And if we look at this pretty closely, we can see, yeah, without a doubt.
We've got an actual maze here.
So that's pretty much it.
It looks like we have successfully formed up the vertical and horizontal arrays and we can now generate
a maize.
Remember, one of the properties of our maize is that every single cell can be visited.
Essentially, there are no portions of the maize that are completely blocked off or inaccessible.
And this is what is going to allow us to make sure that we can always have a starting position for the
ball, that we're going to eventually show up there on the top left and the completion on the very bottom
right, like so.
All right.
So now that we are forming up the verticals and horizontals, we can start to take all this data and
render it out onto our matter.
JS Canvas.
So let's take one last quick pause right here.
We'll come back to the next video and we're going to start to take our.
Grid.
Verticals in horizontals.
We're going to iterate through all this stuff and we're going to figure out where we want to draw some
walls using matter.
JS So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.