Now that we have formed up our verticals in horizontals arrays, we need to take those two arrays and
use them to figure out where to draw the different walls on our canvas using matter JS.
One thing I want to mention right away is that the different walls that we're going to show are going
to be drawn using the rectangle shape that we've spoken about several times with Matthew excuse me,
with Matt or Jess.
So we're going to use a rectangle to represent each individual wall segment.
So now we need to essentially just iterate over all of the verticals.
And all the horizontals.
And for every false value that we find inside those two arrays, we need to draw a rectangle onto our
canvas.
Let's first start off with horizontals and we're going to figure out how to iterate over that thing
and then draw some number of rectangles using the data inside of it.
So I'm going to go back down to the bottom of the file and down here I'm going to iterate over horizontals.
Using a for each statement.
Now I want you to recall that horizontals is a two dimensional array.
So when we do a four each on it, we're going to receive one of the inner arrays, and I'm going to
refer that to that as a row.
And inside of here, I'll do a console log of row.
Just to verify that that is going to be a array of Boolean values that represent where I want to draw
some wall segments.
So I'm going to save this.
I'm going to flip back over refresh.
And there's the two console logs right there.
So now we need to iterate over these two arrays.
And whenever wherever we find a false value, that means that we need to draw a wall segment onto our
canvas.
Remember, false means there is a wall.
True means there is no wall.
So to iterate through those inner arrays, we'll do a row for each.
And I'm going to receive each Boolean value as an argument that I will call open.
The idea here behind calling it open is that we're essentially saying whether this is an open segment
of wall or not.
So if open is true, it means that it is open.
It's an open passageway and we do not need to draw a wall segment.
Then inside of my for each the inner one, I'll say if open is true.
Then just return.
So we don't want to draw anything in this case.
Now, of course, we don't actually have to do a comparison with true right here because open is a boolean
already.
So we can just take a look at Open and say, hey, if open is true, then return.
So.
Otherwise, if open is false, then we do want to draw a wall segment.
So I'm going to create a new variable called Wall and we're going to create this out of bodies dot rectangle.
So we need to now decide on exactly what arguments we're going to throw inside of there, what arguments
we're going to pass to Body Rectangle.
Remember, the first two arguments are the X-Y values to the center of this rectangle.
And the third and fourth arguments are going to be the length or the kind of width of the rectangle
and the height.
So calculating those values out is actually going to be just a little bit challenging.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, I'm going to show you a couple of different diagrams to help you
understand how we're going to calculate those different dimensions.