In this video, we're going to look at some different diagrams to understand how to calculate the different
dimensions that we're going to pass into the rectangle function.
So the first thing I want to do is go back up to the top of the file all the way at the top.
I just want to remind you very quickly that we've got a couple of different constant variables declared
right here.
We've got cells, which is the number of cells in either the horizontal or vertical direction.
And then we've got a width and height.
And very critically right now we are seeing that the height and width are always going to be identical
to each other.
Eventually, we're going to allow these two values to vary to get a rectangular maze.
But for right now, they are always going to be perfectly the same.
So if we think about these, the combination of these two dimensions together, we can start to imagine
that at the end of the day, every cell is going to be 200 units wide because 600 divided by three is
200.
So I'm going to define a little variable underneath here called unit length.
Unit length is essentially saying that every cell that I create is going to be this many units tall
and this many units wide.
So to calculate the unit width or something, the unit length, we would do a width divided by cells.
And of course, we could do height instead.
It really doesn't matter right now because again, height, width are always going to be identical.
So again, unit length is going to be the length of one side of one of our cells.
So just keep that variable in mind for half a second.
We're going to need to use that variable in order to figure out how to draw our individual walls.
So I'm going to go over to a quick diagram and let's draw some stuff out here.
Right now, we are iterating over our horizontals array.
We know that that is going to be a 2D array.
It's going to have the two different rows.
To represent that row and that row right there, each of those different well segments, I'm going to
throw some imaginary values in here.
So I'm going to say maybe we've got true, false, true.
False.
True.
So now, if I wanted to reflect what actual walls we need to draw, I'm going to erase a couple elements
here.
So we would have no wall right there.
We would have no wall right there.
And then we would have no wall right there.
Now using that information, we need to somehow figure out how we can draw this rectangle.
This rectangle and this rectangle.
We're going to first focus on how to draw the one at the top, this one right here.
So we need to figure out how to go from our origin point, which, remember, is on the top left corner.
That is our zero zero.
We need to first figure out how far over we need to go to get the center point of that rectangle.
And then we also need to figure out how far down we need to go.
To get the center point as well in the vertical direction.
So in other words, we need to figure out what that is right there.
Okay.
So when we think about the Y dimension, so this off here, it's the left hand side.
We're essentially saying that we want to go down the height of one cell.
So that is why we just created that unit length variable to get the center point right there, we're
going to first go down unit.
Length.
So in our case, that is going to be the whatever it was, was it 200 pixels?
So we'd be going down 200 units.
That'd be the center point right there on the vertical direction.
Then the x direction to that center point.
So this horizontal direction would be one and a half cells over.
So that would be unit length.
Times 1.5.
So that's how we're going to figure out how we get to the center point of that segment right there.
But just doing like unit length times 1.5 isn't super useful because if we start to think about how
to show these other ones like that segment or that segment, well, it's very clear that this is not
just a function of the unit length, but it's also a function of what row these center points or these
segments are occurring on and what column as well.
So in other words, as we start to think about how did the center point of that next one down, it's
going to actually be.
Unit length.
Times two.
So how do we kind of calculate that distance right there based on the unit length and what row it is
on and what column it is on?
Well, let me just show you the math, give you an idea of how this is all going to work out in order
to get these center points of all these horizontal segments, we need to get the column.
Index.
Though we are currently working on.
So in this case, for the top one that we were just discussing, let me do some deletion here.
So for the top element, this one again are right here we are operating on column index zero one.
So one in this case and we are operating on row index zero.
So we need to do the column index.
Times.
Our unit length.
Plus.
Unit length.
Divided by two.
So that's what is going to give us the direction or the distance like so we can try to use this equation
right here to figure out the X direction for each of these different segments.
So for example, if you want to figure out the X direction distance for this one on the bottom left,
right here, that would be column index of zero.
So we would do zero plus 200 or three times 200.
Zero times 200.
Plus.
200 divided by two, which equals 100.
So that means that we would have 100 units over to get to the X direction at Center Point.
So if we want to try to apply that formula again for this original one right here.
That would be our column index, which in this case is one times 200.
Plus 200 divided by two.
And that gives us 300, which is definitely correct.
And then finally, for the last one down here, that would be a column index of two.
Times 200.
Plus 200 over two.
And that would give us, what, 500?
Which is correct as well, because overall we've got 600, so we essentially want to go back 100 units.
That would be 500.
To that center point right there.
Again in the X direction.
Now that we've got that first little formula, let's try to write out that code back when we create
our rectangle and we'll think about the vertical direction after that.
So on body start rectangle, the x coordinate here will be at column index.
Times the unit length.
Plus the unit length divided by two.
Now, we don't have any variables inside of here called column index.
So how do we figure out what kind of column we are currently iterating over and what row we are iterating
over as well?
We'll remember the second argument inside the for each functions.
The first argument is the actual value where we are iterating over.
The second argument is the index of that element.
So for row right here, we would also have a second argument of row index and that tells us what row
we are currently operating on.
And for the second one, we have the column index.
That is what column we are currently iterating on.
Now we can repeat the same process for the Y direction as well.
So I'm going to do a little bit of erasure.
Okay.
Well, a little bit more.
And I'm going to draw in a couple more segments here by hand.
There we go.
So now we want to get.
That segment, that segment and that segment.
And now we're talking about this.
Why direction?
So how far down do we want to get this thing?
Let's first think about this segment right here.
So how do we get that segment based upon our row index column index and our unit length?
Well, in this case, it is going to be our ROE index.
So that is going to be like this direction or this row right here, which is our first row.
So it's going to be our row index.
Times the unit length.
And in this case, it's going to be plus the unit length.
So let's try to plug in some numbers to get the Y coordinate or the Y direction to that center point
right there.
So I would do a row index of one.
Times are unit length of 200 plus hour unit length of 200.
And that would be 400.
So that means to draw out the Y coordinate of this wall right here.
It would be 400 units.
And if we think about this one right here.
That would be a row index in this case of zero.
So zero times the unit length of 200 plus 200 gives us 200.
Does that means go down 200 units to get that one?
And then this one right here is the same math as that one that we did just a moment ago.
So that would be on rho index of one times 200.
Plus 200 gives us 400 again.
All right.
So I know that this math is kind of nasty, but this is pretty much what has to be done.
So, hey, we got to talk about it one way or another.
So now let's write out the equation where the Y coordinate of this rectangle as well.
So I'll put a comma in and then we're going to get row index times.
The unit length plus the unit length.
Okay.
Now that the third and fourth arguments, these are going to be way easier.
So this is going to be how wide and how tall we want the rectangle to be.
So in this case, we know that we want our wall to be like that long, like whatever the width of one
cell is.
That's how long we want it to be.
And that is the direction in the x axis.
So that is going to be the third argument right here.
We want that to be unit length units long.
So essentially the width of one cell and that is what unit length represents.
And then the fourth argument is going to be how tall we want the wall to be.
So essentially, like, is it going to be really tall like that or is it going to be just very, very
thin, like almost appearing to be a line?
Well, we can just throw in some test value.
I'm going to use like a fixed value of ten here.
So I'm going to say that my wall is going to be ten units tall.
All right.
So finally, a last argument to the rectangle creation.
We're going to make sure that we also mark this thing as static so that it doesn't kind of fly all around
once we start to draw it on the screen.
So let's say is static is true.
So now that we've created that wall, we can add it into our world.
And to add in that shape, we will call world add.
We're going to add to the world object we had created earlier.
And I want to add this wall.
Okay.
I know this has been some nasty math, but like I said, we had to go through it.
So now that we've got that done, I'll save the file.
I'm going to go back over and do a quick test and I can see one wall up here, right there.
Now I can refresh this and every time I'm going to see some walls up here in different locations to
represent kind of like the randomness of the maze we are creating.
Okay.
So that's definitely working correctly, or at least I think it's working correctly.
We won't know for sure until we also draw in the vertical segments as well.
So I bet you could guess what's next.
Let's take a quick pause right here.
We're going to come back to the next video.
We're going to add in some very similar looking code to handle the creation of all the vertical wall
segments.
And once we start to add that stuff in, then we will note that our maze for sure is working correctly.
So a quick pause and we'll take care of verticals in the next video.