Now that we've done all these calculations for the horizontals array, we can repeat that same process
for verticals.
So we're going to essentially do the same exact thing we did in the last video, but we'll do it way
faster since we now understand essentially what we're trying to accomplish here.
So underneath the horizontals for each, I'll add in a verticals for each.
Then inside of here, once again, we're going to receive each row and we'll get a row index.
Then inside of here, we'll do a row for each.
And on the row for each we're going to receive the Boolean value which will again refer to as open and
we get the column index that we currently operating on as well.
Then inside we can say If open is true, then return right away.
Otherwise we want to create a wall segment.
So once again, we'll do.
Konst Wall is bodies dot rectangle.
So all we really have to figure out is the different arguments to pass to body sort rectangle.
This time around, the math is going to be just a little bit different because we are operating on a
different direction.
So let's once again go take a look at the diagram and figure out how to calculate the center point to
the x and Y coordinates for each wall segment in the vertical direction.
Okay.
So here we are again.
I'm going to imagine some data for my verticals array.
So in this case, I'm going to have three rows and two columns, and I'll remind you why in just a moment.
So in this case, I'm going to throw in some imaginary data here.
I'll do true and false.
Paulson True and true and false.
So we have the three rows.
In this case because we're talking about that set of wall segments that set and that set.
So essentially this.
This, this, this, this and this.
And then we've got two columns because there's only two lines of those segments on here.
So if we consider the different true and false values inside of this array, I'm going to erase wherever
we have a true value.
So we want that to be open.
So no wall there.
We want that to be open.
No wall.
And we want that to be open as well.
So once again, let's imagine how we're going to calculate the X and Y center points for each of these
different segments.
We'll first start with this one on the top right hand side, and we essentially want to get the X and
Y coordinates of that X right there coming from our top left origin point at zero and zero.
So we need to determine that distance right there and that distance right there.
This time around, I'm going to basically give you the formulas as opposed to trying to demonstrate
exactly how they get calculated.
It'll save us a lot of time.
Essentially, it's the same thing as last video.
We just need to calculate that center point right there as a function of the row and column that we
are currently operating on and the unit length as well.
So for the X direction that X component right there, we're going to have our column.
Index.
Times.
The unit length.
Plus the unit.
Length.
So let's try out the math for this.
So in this case, we have a column index of zero, then one.
So our column index is one times 200.
That is our unit length plus 200.
And that is 400.
And that's definitely what this should be, because, remember, we're essentially saying go over,
sell one, sell two, and then right there, so each sell is 200 units.
So we get 202 hundred over.
And that takes us to right there.
So 400, definitely correct.
We can have repeat that for this next segment down here.
That would be a column index of zero.
Times 200.
Plus 200 is 200.
Yep.
That definitely looks right to me.
And then the last one down here on the bottom right is actually going to be identical to that first
calculation.
It'll be the one times 200 plus 200 equals 400.
So that definitely solves this in the X direction.
So now we get to repeat this same process.
But in the vertical direction instead.
They'll do some erasing.
I'm going to again try to find that segment right there.
Well, let me just kind of redraw some of the stuff just so we can get some actual clarity in this diagram.
So, like so and like so now we'll find the Y component of that element right there.
So just eyeballing this, it's essentially going to be we're going down half the length of one cell.
So I'm going to expect this to be about 100 units.
So the formula for this will be our row index.
Times the unit length.
Plus.
Unit length.
Divided by two, and we can easily plug in some numbers to verify that that is the case.
So right here our row index is currently zero.
I'll throw those on right now.
So we get zero times 200.
Plus 200 over two, which gives us the 100 that I definitely expected.
Then this one right here, we're talking about going half of one cell plus the full length of another
cell.
So, again, just kind of guessing, I'm going to say it's probably supposed to be 300.
Well, let's throw the numbers in.
So now I have a row index of one times 200.
Plus 200 over two.
Yup.
There's my 300.
And then finally for this one right here, I have two full cell lengths.
Plus half a cell length.
So that will be hopefully around 500.
In this case, my Roman index is two, so I'll do two times 200 plus 200 over two.
And yep, that is the full 500.
All right, so that's it.
So we have to now add in that formula and the one we saw just a moment ago.
For the X and Y positions.
So I'm going to go back over to my editor, will do a column index times unit length plus unit length.
And we'll do row index times, unit length.
Plus unit length divided by two.
And I got a little typo here.
I'm going to fix.
And then finally, we need to provide the width of a wall and the height of a wall.
So remember, the third argument is going to be how wide the wall is in the X direction.
So now we're talking about like if we have a really wide wall that looks like that right there.
What is this X direction?
So we'll once again use some arbitrary kind of small number to give ourselves kind of a thin wall.
And then the height to the wall, which is the fourth argument, is going to be a unit length.
So that's going to be like a full 200.
So as the third argument, I'll do a well width of whatever we had before.
Looks like it was ten.
And the height is going to be the full unit length.
And then finally as the last argument we'll throw on that same is static flag.
Like so.
And then finally underneath the wall will do a world add to our world object.
And I want to add the wall we just created.
Okay.
So that's a lot of code.
Let's save this once again.
Flip back over, refresh.
And there we go.
Here's our maze.
So we can refresh the whole bunch and we'll see all the different bases that we create in every scenario.
We should have like a solid, continuous path.
We should be able to visit every single cell and there should never be a blockage of any kind.
And as I refresh, the whole bunch, definitely looks like that's the case.
Now I know doing these formulas in the last two videos was really tedious, but the benefit to taking
this approach is we've now got this kind of configurable calculation going on.
There are very few static numbers inside of here besides the wall width, and we'll eventually abstract
that out.
So that means that in order to drastically change our maze, we can just manipulate these values right
here.
So, for example, if I want to have a maze that is five cells wide in a five cells tall, I can change
cells to five, and then everything else inside this file should automatically update appropriately.
So now I can refresh.
And now I've got one sell to sell three sell for sell five and same thing in the vertical direction
as well.
And we can start to really play around with that number a lot more.
So I can go up to say ten to make a much more detailed maze.
There definitely is a limit to the number of cells you can have practically.
I think that it's going to max out around 100 or so.
If I do 100, okay, maybe slightly over 100.
Since we're doing some recursion, we're going to eventually exceed the maximum call stack size, which
means we are doing too much recursion.
But you can see that once we have way too many cells, well, the maze is basically unusable anyways,
so it's not really that big a difference.
Let's try like cells 50.
That's still a little bit too much, about 30.
That's a little bit not quite useful, but we could very easily make it usable by adjusting our.
Wall size.
So that is the ten right here in the horizontals and the ten inside the verticals as well.
So we can change those to like, how about five?
Well.
Five right there in five right there.
Save refresh.
And now it looks a little bit more like a maze than it did before.
So this is great.
We've basically got a proof of concept for our maze.
I am going to take it back to cells of three because that's really nice.
For testing purposes, it looks like everything is pretty much working as we expect.
So pretty much the last one we have to add in here is the ball that the user is going to control.
We need to add in the success area down here at the bottom right hand side and then make sure that we
can control the ball with some keyboard controls.
So quick pause right here and we'll continue in the next video.