In this video, we're going to focus on showing the goal on the very bottom right corner of our maze.
The goal is always going to be exactly right here on the bottom right hand corner.
So this calculation is going to be pretty straightforward.
We just have to be aware that we probably want to adjust the size of the goal based upon our unit length
or essentially the size of each individual cell.
So in other words, if we have really large cells, as we do right now, we want to have a really large
goal that fills up most of that space.
But if we have some very small cells, like back just a second ago when I showed cells of 20 or 30,
then in this case, we want the goal down here to be really, really small instead.
So essentially we just need the goal rectangle or the rectangle that represents the goal to be just
about scaling itself with the size of our different cells.
Yes.
I'm going to go back over.
I'm going to go down to the very bottom.
And down here, I'm going to create a new variable called goal.
This is going to be a body start rectangle.
And then right away, I'm not going to worry about the configuration just yet.
Instead, I'll add in the code to add this thing to our world.
So we'll say world, add, world and goal.
So let's think about how we're going to calculate the arguments for the rectangle.
Remember, the first two arguments are going to be the x and y coordinates to the center of the goal.
Okay.
So quick diagram.
So we're essentially saying that we just want to draw a rectangle like right here and we need to find
the coordinates to that point.
So something like this right here.
We can see how that lines up with the center.
And about this right here.
Again, we can see how that kind of lines up with the center.
So in this case, it's really not going to be that hard.
We know that the overall width of this thing.
Is our canvas width.
So that's the like overall width.
And we know that the overall height is going to be height.
So we want to essentially take the full width and the full height and then subtract the width of half
of a cell.
Is that right?
There is one half of a cell and we are calling the variable that represents the cell dimension.
Remember, we are calling that unit.
Length.
So essentially the center point to that rectangle is going to be our width of the overall canvas minus
unit length.
Divided by two.
And then the Y component will be the overall height.
Minus.
Unit length divided by two, and that's pretty much it.
So let's take that information, go back over and add it in.
So the X coordinate is going to be bi width, minus unit length divided by two.
And remember this width variable right here is a reference back to the overall width of our canvas.
Then my y will be the height minus unit length divided by two.
Once again, I made a typo right there on unit length, so I'm going to get that fixed up.
All right.
And that's pretty much it.
So now we need to make sure that the size of this rectangle so its height and width, which are the
third and fourth arguments, also scale with the unit length.
So you can imagine that if we always had a fixed height and width to the rectangle itself, as soon
as we start to scale down the maze as we have right here, well, the rectangle would be way too large
inside of here.
So to make sure that this thing scales, we can just do a unit length and then multiply that by like
0.7 or something.
So that means I want the rectangle size to just scale with the size of a cell.
So I want the cell to essentially be 70% of the size of a cell.
I could do unit length again times 0.7.
And finally, I do want this thing to be static because I don't want it to move around.
They'll say is static is true.
Yes.
I'll save this.
I'm going to make sure that my cells variable back up at the top is back at three.
So we'll do it test with the very simple case to start.
I'll go back over refresh and there's our goal.
Now having the goal up here as this kind of outline and not that great, it's really not clear to a
user what that is all about.
We're essentially going to add in a fill to it as opposed to have it in a wireframes mode.
Once we add in a fill, we can make the thing green.
It will be a lot more obvious to our users that they're trying to like navigate to that thing right
there.
Now that definitely looks good.
But I want to point out a little issue.
If we increase our cells right here to say like 15 and save.
Then it looks like it's just about impossible to actually get to that goal because our bottom border
is overlapping or kind of intersecting that actual goal that we're trying to get at.
So I think that at this point, the borders that we have around the outside are way too thick and we
need to probably reduce their size so that they're not going to actually interfere with the different
elements of the maze itself.
So for that, I'm going to go back to the section where we created all of our different walls.
Remember we put on that helpful comment just to help ourselves find this thing in the future.
And I'm going to change the forties inside of here, which represent the width of that wall.
I'm going to change all four of them to.
How about just two like so?
That's basically really, really thin.
And we can just about not see them.
But now they're not really actually conflicting with any of the elements inside of our maze anymore.
So I think that's definitely a better approach to to take.
Okay.
So that's our goal.
Now we do eventually have to add in some code to detect a collision between the ball that we're going
to place and that thing to decide when the user wins.
But we'll take care of that in just a little bit.
Right now, let's take a pause.
We'll come back and we'll start to add in the ball.
That's going to start off at the top left corner.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.