Now that we have our goal, let's make sure that we show able as well that the user can manipulate by
pressing their keyboard keys.
I'm going to find where we just added in the goal of moment to go.
I'm going to add a comment right above it that says goal, just to remind myself that that is what that
code is for.
The variable name kind of explains that, but it's still good practice to have a comment anyways.
So then underneath that section I'll add in ball.
So this is where we're going to draw our ball out.
I'm going to first create a variable called Wall.
I'll do a bodysuit circle, because in this case, we want to create a circle, not a rectangle.
And inside of here, we could definitely have a fixed ball size.
But once again, if we have a fixed ball size, it might make a lot of sense on how large the ball is
when we have only three cells.
But as we start to have a tighter and tighter maze, if the ball is too large, it's not going to actually
be able to make it through the maze at all.
So we probably just need to make sure that we kind of scale the size of the ball along with the unit
length.
The other thing we need to be aware of is that the first two arguments to circle is the x y coordinate
of the very center of the circle.
So we probably need to make sure that we also adjust that starting location to always be at the very
center of that first cell right there.
So let's get to it.
For these starting x y coordinate, we're going to show the ball at unit length.
Divided by two.
That essentially means take the width of this first cell, divide it by two and put it right there in
the very center.
And we're going to do that both for the X coordinate and Y coordinate as well.
And for the diameter of the ball will do a unit length.
So that's the width of one cell and we'll make the ball half the size of a cell so we can do a times
0.5 or divided by two as well.
And I can go ahead and add that ball into the world.
So.
World.
Add.
World and ball.
It's.
I'll save this.
I'll flip back over, refresh.
And there we go.
Now the ball is looking just a little bit too large.
Well, I think I just made a mistake here.
The third argument.
I did this on my own when I was actually writing this application as well.
The third argument I just assumed was the actual overall diameter.
It's actually the radius of the ball.
So right now, a unit length divided by two means that the ball is going to be essentially exactly equal
to the width of a cell.
My mistake.
So the last argument here to be the radius correctly should actually be unit length divided by four.
They'll try that again.
Refresh and that's better.
So now the ball is half the width of a cell.
Yes.
Now, the last thing we really have to do is make sure that a ball can collide with the goal.
And we need to make sure that we press on our keyboard keys of ways and we apply some velocity or movement
to the ball as well.
So first, make sure that we can move the ball around.
Let's take care of that in the next video.