All right, let's make sure that when we press on the W, A, C and D keys on our keyboard, we apply
some movement or velocity to this ball right here.
The first thing we have to do is figure out how we're going to detect whenever a user presses a key
on their keyboard.
Well, to be honest, there's not really a lot of magic to this.
We're going to set up an event listener on our document.
And that means whenever a user presses any key on their keyboard anywhere on our application, we'll
be able to detect that key press.
So underneath my ball, I'm going to add in a document that add event listener and we're going to listen
for an event called Key Down.
As you can probably guess, the key down event is going to be triggered any time the user presses down
on a key on their keyboard.
So we'll then receive that event object and I'm going to do a console.log.
Of the event because we're going to see something really interesting in there really quickly.
So I'm going to save this.
Flip back over to refresh and then I'm going to click anywhere on the screen and slide my actual application
and then just press a key.
I'll first start off by pressing the key.
W If I then expand this event object, we're going to see a couple of different interesting properties.
So the one that is probably most relevant right there says Key.
So that tells us the key that was just pressed by the user.
There's also a key code property as well.
Traditionally we use the key code property to decide exactly what character the user just typed on as
opposed to the key property.
Each different key on your keyboard has a different code so we can look up all these different codes
to decide exactly what key was just pressed and then impart some appropriate velocity on the ball in
the appropriate direction.
So I can also do an A oops.
I need to select the actual app first.
There's my A that gives me a key code of 65.
I can do a down or a se in this case that represents the ball going down 83 and then a D is a key code
of 68.
Now, we don't really have to just click and press these different keys all day and look at the key
code to figure out which key triggers, which key code.
We can always do a Google search.
We can look up JavaScript key code.
One of the first results here is key code info.
This is a really great little site to figure out exactly what the key codes are for each key press.
So if I do a W, it'll tell me, Hey, that's 87 left is 65 down 83 right is 68.
So back inside of my editor, I'm going to remove the console log.
And I'm going to instead set up a couple of if statements.
So I'll say if events key code equals and what's the first one we should do?
Let's do up, which is a W.
So if a user has a key code of 87, that means they want to go up.
So inside of here I'll say console.log, move all up and then I can repeat that same process for the
other keys.
So I'll duplicate that if statement down.
Once, twice, three times.
So that's up.
I'll make this one a move to the right.
Down and left.
And we can just update the key codes for those appropriate directions.
So to move the ball right, I want to find my D key.
So that's 68.
So update the 87 right there to 68.
Going down would be 83.
And going left would be 65.
Yes.
Let's save this.
I'll go back over to my application.
I'll refresh and I can once again click inside of my application frame and then I'll go up.
Right down and left.
And I can definitely see that I'm doing the appropriate console logs for each of those different directions.
So this is definitely good.
Looks like we have a good start here.
So quick pause right here.
We'll come back to the next video and we're going to figure out exactly how we can take these directions
and actually translate them to adding some movement to our ball right there.
So another quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.