Plus we have to do inside of our event listener is make sure that whenever a user presses on the appropriate
key, we change the movement of the ball.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, essentially what we're going to do is take a look at the current velocity of the ball.
When I use the word velocity, that means the speed in which the ball is moving.
So we're going to take the velocity of the ball and then we're going to update it or add in some additional
velocity in the up, down, left or right directions.
To change the velocity of a shape, we have to get another object from the matter.
GS Library.
So I'm going to go up to the very top of the file where we are currently structuring a couple of properties.
We're going to de structure another property called body like so.
His body object has some different functions on it that allow us to update the different properties
inside of a shape so he can use it to change the dimensions of a shape, its position velocity, its
rotation and so on.
So now that we've got that body object, let's go back down to our event handler.
Down here.
We're going to first take a look at our ball and get its current velocity.
So I'm going to say concept X and Y with some curly braces because we are doing some de structuring
here.
Ball dot velocity.
So X and Y are going to be the current velocity of the ball.
Let's do a quick console log and just see what those values are printed out as.
Now we'll go back over refresh and refresh once again.
And right after I refresh, I'm going to press on the W key, which should trigger that code to go essentially.
Right here, like go or print out the console log so I can refresh and then press a couple of times
and we can see the console log of the x and y values.
So we'll see the very first console.log right here as the ball was falling down, we had an x coordinate
or an X velocity of zero, which means that the ball was not moving side to side at all.
But the Y value was 8.23, which means the ball was going downwards or it was moving downwards.
Over time, once the ball kind of hit that block right there and started rolling slightly, we can see
that these numbers got very, very small until now.
If I press again, they're at zero zero because the ball is not moving at all.
Okay.
So now that we've got these values, we can use those and add in some additional velocity to either
the X or Y coordinate.
So I'm going to take care of moving the ball up first.
I'll remove the console log and I'll say body set velocity.
This is how we update the velocity of a shape.
We'll say ball.
And then I'm going to get the same X that we have right now.
So I'll say X is x and remember we can use that key value shortcut when those variables are identical.
To reduce it down to just x.
And then my why is going to be whatever the Y currently is minus five.
We are subtracting five year because we want to move the ball in the other direction and to move it
up, we want to have a negative velocity.
So every single time that the user presses on the W key, which is key code 87, we're going to take
whatever the current velocity is, we're going to subtract five to it and set the velocity to that new
Y velocity.
So let's now save this and do a quick test.
I'll flip back over.
Refresh.
I'm going to refresh a couple of times until I get a nice column like this right here, like lots of
space to work with.
I'll press w a couple of times, and every single time I do.
The ball moves slightly faster and faster because every single time I press it, I'm accelerating five
additional or adding five units of velocity in the upwards direction.
Okay.
So that looks good.
So let's now repeat the same process for each of our different directions.
So I'm going to copy that set velocity and we'll take care of going right next.
So in this case, I'm going to clear out the X and Y inside of here.
If I want to move right, I'm going to do X of whatever the current x velocity is plus five.
And the same.
Why?
And I'll delete that console log.
Then to go down, I'll delete the council log.
In this case, I still want to adjust the Y value, but to go downwards faster, I want to do a plus
five.
And then to move to the left faster.
I'm going to do.
Same.
Why?
And an X of X minus five.
So again, to move to the left, we subtract from x.
All right, so I'll save this.
I'm going to flip back over once again.
And now we should have full control of the ball so I can go to the right.
Left?
I can go up.
And I can go down as well.
And that's pretty much it.
Now, if this thing feels laggy right now, that's totally fine.
You can always try to close your developer console, and when you do so, you're going to see that the
map or the maze is slightly more responsive and just a little bit less laggy.
It's not a total solution, but definitely having your developer console open adds in a little bit more
of a performance penalty.
Now we can easily start to navigate through our maze.
Okay.
So this is looking pretty good.
But I think that having the gravity turned on is a little bit distracting.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back to the next video, we're going to disable gravity inside of our maze, which is going
to make controlling that ball just a little bit more easy.
So a quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.