In this video, we're going to make sure that we disable gravity inside of our maze again.
That's going to make this ball just a little bit easier to control.
So to disable gravity, I'll go back over to my editor.
I'm going to go up to the very top and I'm going to find where we create the engine right here.
So in order to disable gravity, we're going to change a property on that engine variable.
We'll say engine dot, world dot, gravity dot y equals zero like so.
So that's going to disable gravity in the Y direction entirely.
So now if we go back over and refresh the ball is just going to stay where it is until we start to apply
some velocity to it so I can tap on the button and now I go to left, right, up, down.
And now it's a little bit easier to control than it was before.
It's still kind of challenging to control because the ball starts to move like really quickly, but
we'll start to address that over time.
Eventually, you're going to realize that having the ball kind of responsive is actually kind of nice
when we have a really large maze and it takes up essentially the full width and height of our screen.
So eventually we can add in some tweaks to make sure we don't accelerate the ball or set the velocity
of the ball quite so high.
But again, we'll take care of that in just a little bit.
So it's definitely works.
So now the very last thing we really need to do to complete the entire game is to make sure that when
the ball presses that completion block right there, we essentially end the game and say, Hey, congratulations,
user, you just won.
That's the last major feature we need to add in.
So quick pause.
Take care of that in just a moment.