The last big thing we have to add in to our application is to detect whenever our ball right here reaches
the goal at the very bottom right hand corner.
So what we're really trying to do here, put in a more simplistic way or a more kind of engineering
sense, is detect a collision event between two different shapes.
Let's write out some code that will allow us to detect whenever two different shapes inside of our matter
application collide with each other.
So I'm going to go back over to my editor at the very top.
I'm going to find the matter object once again.
And we're going to pull another object off of that thing called events.
So this is an object that's going to let us listen for different things that actually occur inside of
our world object.
Well, then go back down to the very bottom of the file.
And down here I'm going to add in a comment called Win Condition.
So the meaning here is that, well, this is how a user can actually win our game or win the maze.
So we're going to write out events on Engine.
We're going to listen for an event called Collision Start.
Double check your spelling on collision and make sure that you also have a capital SX on there as well.
And the third argument is going to be a callback function that's going to be called with some event
object.
So this event object is going to mean this callback function is going to be invoked every single time
that there is a collision between two different shapes inside of our world.
Right now I'll add in a console log of event.
So I'll save this.
I'll flip back over, refresh, and we'll do a quick test.
So I'm going to press the key and just make sure that my ball runs into some wall.
That counts as a collision.
So as soon as the ball runs into a wall, I should see a console.log.
And sure enough, I do right there.
Now you're going to very quickly see some really strange behavior as we start to console.log out this
event object.
The event object that is used by matter marriages gets reused between different events.
So in other words, and this is kind of hard to like internalize, but I'll show you some proof of it
very quickly.
This event object right here, there is one single event object that matter JS owns.
Every single time that any event occurs, it adds some properties to this event.
Object to describe what just happened.
It then sends that object into our callback function.
Immediately after our callback function runs, all the different properties of that event object get
wiped out and removed.
That might sound really crazy, but let's take a look at the console log that we just got and you're
going to see that in action really quickly because the weird behavior inside of our console.
So notice how when I got the initial console log like that right there, I see that pairs is an array
of length one.
So that means that there is a single element inside of the pairs array.
But if I expand this and look at pairs, it is now empty.
And that is because when we got the initial console log like right here, when we called console.log
on the event object, there was an element inside of that pairs array.
But the way that the Chrome console works is that it doesn't really evaluate or look at these different
properties too closely until you click on that little triangle and expand that thing.
So when you expand that entry right there, Chrome takes another look at that same exact object.
And when it takes that second look, it says, Oh, well, it turns out there's actually nothing in
pairs now because matter is, after it called, our event handler wiped out all the different properties
inside this object.
So that's why we're going to very quickly see some really strange behavior from our console as we start
to log out this thing.
So let's take another look at how we can console, log this thing out and start to get a real better
sense of what's going on inside this event object without having to worry about the fact that all the
properties inside of it get wiped out.
So I'm going to remove the console.log and replace it with event pairs for each.
So as we just saw, Piers is an array.
So I'm going to try to iterate through that array and I'm going to say for every collision.
I want to console.log that collision object.
Okay.
So let's try this again.
If I flip back over.
Oops, refresh.
There we go and get the ball to run into something again.
Now we're going to see a slightly different console log.
So now we get to see what is actually inside of that pairs array.
Whereas before, by the time we looked at it inside of our console, it was already gone.
It already got destroyed.
So now we can see what is actually inside of that pairs array.
We can see that it is some kind of object that has a lot of different properties that describes the
collision that just occurred.
The properties that you and I care about the most.
Is body A right here and Body be.
Those two properties describe the two shapes that just ran into each other.
So we can see that I just had something with the label of Circle Body run into something with the label
of Rectangle Body.
And as you could probably guess, that means that the ball right here ran into one of the walls.
So in order to detect whenever a user gets the ball right here to reach our win condition down at the
bottom right hand side, we need to just inspect the body and body be properties.
And if they are the ball and that little goal, that means that the user must have gotten to the goal
and they must have won the game.
All right, so let's write out some code to detect that kind of collision.
I'm going to first go back over to my editor.
I'm going to go up to the very top and I'm going to change cells down to just three.
The reason for this is that I want to be able to very easily win the maze, like really quickly.
So now this is a lot easier to win than what we had before.
So now if I touch the goal right there.
I can inspect this thing.
I do get multiple accounts of logs here because I accidentally ran into a wall.
So I'm going to make sure that I select a console log that actually represents running into that body.
There we go.
That's one right there.
So now I see that I've got a body, a of rectangle body and again, a body of circle body.
So these labels are not super helpful.
So we need some different way to identify whether or not we just ran into the ball and the actual goal
right there.
So to make sure that we can easily identify when body A and Body B are the ball and the goal, we can
go back to where we create the ball and the goal and we can add in a custom label to each of them.
So I'm going to find where I create the ball right here.
And then as a final argument to this thing.
I'm going to add in an options object.
And to it, I'm going to add in a label a property of simply ball.
I'll then find where I create the ball.
The goal.
Excuse me.
Right above.
So here's the goal right here.
I'm going to add in a label of goal.
So now whenever we see those console logs, we should have a more definitive label for both them.
So I'll save this.
I'm going to flip back over.
I'm going to try to win again.
There we go.
Now, if I inspect the console log, I get a label of goal and a label of wall.
So that's way easier now to detect when we have the ball and the goal contact each other as opposed
to trying to figure out when like one was simply bald and the other was rectangle body because every
rectangle was going to be printed out as rectangle.
It's now back inside of our event handler down here at the very bottom.
We can just do a quick check and see if pair A and a pair B are actually the ball and the goal.
Now if we start to write out in if statement here, we never really know if body a is going to be the
ball or body is going to be the goal and vice versa for body be.
So an easy way to kind of capture this and not have to write out a really long if statement right here
to compare all different possibilities is to create a little array that I'll call labels.
Am I going to have inside there?
Ball and goal.
And then I'll say if labels includes.
Collision.
Dot body.
A dot label.
And if labels includes.
Collision body, big label.
Then the user must have hit the goal.
Let me save that so you can see that whole line.
So inside of here I'll do a console log of user one.
Like so.
So again, if we tried to write out an if statement to just look if body a was ball or goal and body
be was ball or goal, well, that would just be a really long if statement.
So this is just an easy way to kind of collapse it down a little bit.
Okay.
So let's save this.
We'll go back over refresh.
And now I can run into as many things as I want and I don't see any console logs.
It's only when I run into that goal right there that I see the console log of user one.
So that's pretty much it.
That's how a user is going to win the game.
So let's take a pause right here.
Now that we can detect this win, we can start to tell the user, Hey, you won or whatever else we
want to do.
So quick pause.
We'll take care of that in the next video.