Now that we can detect a wind condition.
So whenever a user goes and hits that kind of completion area right there, it would be kind of fun
to tell the user in a interesting way that they have won the game.
So something a little bit more interesting than a console log.
I've got an idea for kind of an interesting way of doing that.
I think that when a user wins and they hit the ball against that kind of goal rectangle right there,
let's try to turn gravity back on.
And simultaneously we'll also take all the different wall segments we have and remove these static flag
from them.
The net effect of both those changes is that essentially the entire maze is going to kind of fall apart
and fall down to the very bottom, followed to like the bottom edge of the screen.
So again, we're just doing this to make sure it's really clear to a user when they win a game.
Yes.
Let's give this a shot.
The first thing we'll do is find the if statement we were just working on.
I'm going to to replace that console.log right there.
So inside of here I'm going to turn gravity back on by writing out world dot gravity.
Y equals one.
So that's going to accelerate all the different shapes we have down towards the bottom edge of the screen.
The next thing I'm going to do is to loop over all the shapes inside of my world.
I'm going to try to find all the different wall segments.
So like these walls right here, and I'm going to remove the static flag from each of them.
To make sure that we can easily find all the different wall segments.
I'm going to go back up to where we create all of our walls so the two for each loops.
Here's one right here.
Four verticals.
I'm going to find the options object and I'm going to add on a flag to it.
I'm going to say label of wall.
So as we saw just a second ago, we can use labels that are being applied to a shape that we create
to easily figure out what type of shape it actually represents.
So if I save this just for verticals right now, we can then go back over refresh and I can get a better
idea of exactly what shapes our verticals by printing out WorldCat bodies.
So this is telling me that I have ten different shapes inside the world.
And if I look at the different label properties or Yeah, label right there, I'll see that one has
a label of wall.
So that represents the one vertical piece that we have right there.
So we can repeat that same label and throw it onto our horizontals as well.
So I'll go back up to the horizontal section and I'll add in to that.
Options Object a label of wall.
So now if we go back over again, refresh, print out world bodies.
We can see that we've got several different walls inside of here.
The remaining rectangles are the actual kind of barriers or borders around the outside edge of our canvas.
And of course, we have the goal and the ball as well.
So now whenever a user wins, we can iterate over world bodies and we can update the is static flag
for each of the wall labels or these wall objects to false.
And that's going to essentially allow gravity to affect all the different wall segments that will cause
them to kind of collapse down to the bottom edge of the screen.
So to actually write out the code for that, I'll go back over.
I'm going to go back down to where we are computing our win condition.
And after I update my gravity, I'm going to do a WorldCat bodies for each.
And for each body that I am iterating over, I'll say if body label.
Is segment.
So this is not a segment but a wall.
I had previously used the word segment, but I figured wall made a lot more sense.
So we'll stick with that.
And then to update the static property, we're going to once again use that body object that we spoke
about just a little bit ago.
I'm going to call the set static method on it.
As you could guess, that's going to update the static flag on an object.
So we're going to take the body and we're going to update the static flag to false to say this thing
is no longer static, so gravity and other forces can now affect it.
I'm going to save this.
Go back over refresh.
And now if I go ahead and win.
Everything kind of falls apart.
So again, it's just kind of a fun little animation that a user can see.
Once they actually win the maze, we will eventually put on a big message to the user that says, Hey,
you one right on the very center of the screen to make sure that it's just super clear that they won.
But we'll add in one or two other features before we take care of that.
So now for a really fun test, we can go and update the number of cells we have.
So I might go to like six or so just to make my maze a little bit more complex.
And now if I win.
Everything falls apart.
And then a user can still kind of mess around and move all these different segments around.
Okay.
So this is looking pretty good.
So the last really big thing that we have to accomplish inside this app is to make sure that it's not
limited to this fixed size right here.
At present, we've been saying many times that the height and width are always going to be identical.
So if we start to change one of these values, like let's say I change the height to 800 and refresh,
well, everything doesn't quite work as expected.
So we're going to make sure that we can have rectangular mazes.
We're going to in particular, make sure that we can have a maze that fills up the entire screen.
And so we're going to have to update several sections of code to accommodate for that.
So let's take a quick pause right here and start that refactor in the next video.