Well, now that we've got just about everything working as expected, let's start to think about how
we're going to actually scale this entire game to fill up the entire screen.
So I want to make sure that no matter what size browser window the user is using, I want this canvas
to stretch from the very top left corner all the way down to the very bottom.
Right.
To do so, we're going to add in one CSS rule and we're going to change a couple of different variables
inside of our JavaScript file.
It's just about all the logic is going to remain the same.
We just have to make sure that at several different locations we respect a measurement in the Y direction
and X direction as opposed to what's going on right now, where we just assume we always have an identical
width and height no matter what.
So first things first.
What's with the CSIS rule that I just mentioned?
Well, if you open up your element, Inspector.
And take a look at the body elements right now.
You might notice that the body by default has a margin of eight pixels on it.
So that is preventing our canvas right here from getting truly to the top left corner of the browser
window.
So let's make sure that we can just remove that default margin on the body.
To do so i'll go back over to my editor.
I'm going to open up the index.html html file.
Here it is right here in the head element.
I'll add in a style tag.
And then inside there, I'll select the body.
And set margin to zero.
That's going to remove that extra little bit of space around our canvas.
By now, refresh, I should see the canvas go truly up to the top left corner.
All right.
So now how are we going to make sure that this canvas fills up the entire screen so from that corner
down to the bottom.
Right.
Well, if you take a look at your console really quickly, I'm going to type out window right here.
Remember, this is our window object, which is available to us by default when we are running JavaScript
code inside the browser.
One or two properties that this window object has is Windows inner with.
And windows that inner height.
These two properties are going to give me the entire visible area where the dimensions of it that the
user can see right now.
So it's going to be from that top left corner, just right underneath the back button, all the way
down to the bottom right corner of the viewable area.
It does not include any space that is taken up by the console.
So for example, if I pull the console out and then try to get the width again.
I now get a width that is much greater than what I had just a moment ago.
You can also see the inner height and width.
If you are using chrome as you drag around the console.
Just look at the top left hand corner or see me the top right hand corner right there.
So as I pull over the console, I'll see that the visible area gets smaller and smaller.
So we're going to use windows inner height and windows inner width to figure out exactly how large we
want our canvas to be.
So to get started, I'm going to go back over to my index file.
I'm going to find where we set up height and width right here.
And we will pull those values from the window object.
So I'll say windows inner width is going to be width.
And windows at inner height is going to be height.
Now, if I save this file right now and go back over and refresh, I will still see the maze up here
and it's going to take up the full space available to us.
If I close my console now and then refresh again, I'll see that it really does take up the entire browser
window.
However, because of our maze logic, which assumes we always have equal dimensions for the height and
the width, well, the entire maze doesn't actually show up correctly.
The ball is shown correctly and our square over here is showing correctly.
But the actual walls are not really placed in the appropriate locations.
So it's clear that we're still going to have to do a little bit more work to figure out how to get this
thing to work correctly.
So pause right here.
We're going to come back the next video and discuss the big refactor that we're going to do to a couple
of different variables inside of here to get everything else working the way we expect.