All right, let's get to it.
We're going to start to discuss some of the different variables we need to change inside of here to
get our map to display correctly.
So a quick diagram.
So this is the kind of maze we want to allow the user to have.
Now, I want to not only allow the entire canvas to be rectangular, but I want the number of cells
in the horizontal and vertical direction to be able to vary as well.
So we're going to introduce two new variables that are going to replace the single cells variable that
we have right now.
Remember, cells right now tells us the number of cells.
So we want to have both in the horizontal and vertical direction.
But now I want to to have a variable number in the horizontal.
And vertical instead.
So we're going to introduce a variable called cells.
Horizontal.
In this case, it would be equal to four because I want to have one, two, three, four cells going
from left to right.
We're also going to have cells.
Vertical.
And in this case, as you would guess, one, two, three.
Let's create both those variables right now and we'll discuss exactly how we're going to actually use
them.
It's about over here.
I'm going to remove the cells variable and I'm going to create cells horizontal.
Well started off as four and cells vertical and I'll start that off as three.
The next variable I want to point out to you is unit length right here.
Remember, that was supposed to be the length of one side of a given cell, either the height or the
width, because they were always identical.
Now that you're allowing for a very different number of cells in the horizontal and vertical direction
and the actual screen space allocated to this can be variable as well.
We need to calculate the horizontal difference or distance of a cell differently from the vertical height
of a cell.
So we're going to introduce two other variables as well.
One will be unit length.
X and the other will be unit length.
Why?
And as you would guess, that's going to be the X direction or the width of a cell and the height of
a cell.
You can calculate both of these by taking advantage of the height and width of the overall canvas and
dividing that by the number of cells on the horizontal and the vertical direction.
So back over here.
I'm going to change the existing unit length to unit length Y and then to calculate that we're going
to take the overall width of our canvas and divide by the number of cells in the horizontal direction.
So that is cells horizontal.
So I'll say it sells.
Horizontal like so.
Then for the unit length in the Y direction, I'll create unit length Y, and that's going to be the
overall height of the canvas divided by cells vertical.
And that's pretty much it.
Okay.
So now that we've established the meaning of these different variables, we're going to start to go
around this file and update all the different references we had previously to unit length or cells to
either use cells horizontal vertical or unit length X or y.
That refactor is going to be just a little bit painful.
And I want to put all of it into one single video.
So pause right here, come back to the next video and we'll do the entire refactor, hopefully in one
single go.