In this video, we're going to do a kind of nasty refactor.
So we're going to go through our code.
We're going to find every time that we had a reference to cells and remove it.
We're going to replace it with a reference to cells horizontal or vertical.
We're also going to find every location that we had a reference to unit length X and we will replace
it with a reference to unit length X or Y.
I can tell you right now that the refactor we're about to do is going to be really nasty.
It's very likely that we're going to make a mistake somewhere along the way.
So I know that this is going to be kind of annoying.
Refactor The reason that I decided to do this refactor at the end is that understanding all the maize
generation stuff is just a lot easier when the height and width of the maize was always identical,
and that's what we did from the get go.
It was a lot easier to take that approach and do the refactor later, then to break out the separate
or different values of cells in the horizontal and vertical direction from the get go.
That would have been a lot more challenging right away.
So I apologize for this video in advance.
I'm going to tell you right now.
But nonetheless, we got to get it done.
So let's get to it.
One more time, we're going to go round to find every reference to cells and replace it with one of
these two variables.
Bind every reference to unit length and replace it with one of those two.
Okay, let's start.
So I'm going to first take a look at the walls array right here.
Walls does not have any references to cells or unit length, so no change is required.
Well, then take a look at maize generation.
Nothing inside of Shuffle has any reference to those variables, so no problem.
And we get to the first place that we need to start to do a refactor.
So where we create grid verticals and horizontals.
Let me give you a quick overview of why these things need to change now.
So here's a demonstration or a maze that we eventually want to have put together.
So in this case, we have four columns and three rows.
So let's think about the grid array that we would create to represent this maze.
The grid would have basically the same structure as the maze that we're looking at.
So it would have three rows.
And inside of each of those rows, there would be four elements, one for each column.
So they would all start off as false.
So like false, false, false.
So overall, the grid, the outer array.
His length three.
The inner array is length four.
So we need to update the values that we're passing in here to accommodate for that.
So the outer array that we are creating right there that is going to have the number of rows and our
number of rows if we go all the way back up the top is cells vertical.
So cells vertical is the number of rows that we have.
So I'm going to update a ray cells.
The first call right there.
Two cells vertical, and then the second one will be cells.
Horizontal because remember the inner map or the inner array right here called we have inside the map
statement is building out each inner row and that's going to be the number of columns we have which
is tracked by the cells horizontal variable.
Now we can update the two other arrays that we generate in an identical fashion.
The outer array will be cells vertical.
And down here on horizontal, the outer arrays will be cells vertical minus one.
Then on verticals on the inner array, instead of cells will have cells horizontal.
And on this one right here inside of the horizontals, we will have cells horizontal.
So that's step one.
Next up, we need to find a random start row and a random start column.
So rather than having this be multiplied by just our total number of cells, we now no longer have that
variable, of course.
So we need to calculate either a random number from zero up to our cells horizontal or zero to cells
vertical, depending upon whether we are trying to get a random row or column.
So again, cells vertical corresponds to the number of rows that we have.
So I'm going to change the start row right here to cells vertical and the start column will be some
random number times cells horizontal.
Okay.
Next up, we'll move to step through cell.
Inside of here, we have just one reference to or I guess to right here, one place that we reference
the cells variable.
And that's where we check to see if we are out of balance.
So for next row right here, we're going to make sure that we are not exceeding the total number of
vertical cells we have.
So cells vertical with next column, we're going to make sure we don't exceed the total number of columns.
We have the least cells horizontal.
All right.
Just a little bit more.
Fortunately, the next one is going to be really easy and straightforward.
So I'm going to go down, down, down to where we iterate through horizontals.
So instead of horizontals, we've got a ton of different references to our unit length.
So we need to make sure we update each of these to either unit length, X or Y.
But fortunately, like I said, this is going to be really easy refactor.
Remember the ordering of arguments we pass into the rectangle function?
The first argument is the center of the rectangle in the x direction.
So as you would probably guess, we're going to update unit length both locations inside that first
argument to unit length X.
The second argument is the center point of the rectangle in the Y direction.
So again, as you would guess, we're going to now multiply by unit length Y and add in unit length
y.
And the third argument is the length of the rectangle in the X direction.
So unit length x.
Now take a look at this line right here or this block of code and make sure you do not have any references
to the plain unit length variable.
They should all be either unit length X or Y.
Okay.
So that's it for horizontals.
We'll repeat that same process for the verticals as well.
So again, first line will be unit length X and x second will be unit length y and y.
And this time the fourth argument, which is the height of the rectangle we are creating.
That needs to be of course the height.
So in the vertical direction.
So unit length y.
Okay.
Just a little bit more.
I know I said this was a nasty refactor, but we're almost done with it.
So for the goal right here we are multiplying by the unit length.
Again, we've got the same ordering of arguments.
So the first and third arguments need to take a look at the unit length in the X direction.
So here's the first argument.
Should go to X.
Third argument should go to X.
And then the second and fourth arguments are concerned with the Y direction.
So we'll do a unit length y and y.
So unit length.
X, y, then x and y.
All right.
Last a little bit.
Here's our ball right here.
So we've got three references to the unit length.
Remember, the first and second are the X and Y center points of the ball.
So we're going to change the first to X, the second to Y.
And then the third argument right here is going to be the radius of the ball.
So for the race to the ball, we might have a very different lengthy X direction in the Y direction.
So we should really take the minimum of those two and use that to decide exactly what the radius should
be.
So on the line right above, I'm going to declare a new variable called Ball Radius.
This will be math min.
Of the unit length in the X direction and the unit length in the Y direction.
So find whichever of those two is lesser and then we're going to divide it by two.
And then I'm going to take out.
The third argument right here and replace it with ball radius.
And, you know, I just realized I made the same mistake I did before the ball.
We are providing a radius here so we actually want to do two divided by four after the method in.
So that should be it.
So now at this point in time, we should be able to do a search on this file for unit length.
And if we search around, we should not find any reference to a variable that says just unit length
by itself.
So as I go around, I should see everywhere unit length X and unit length y.
I should will do the same thing for cells as well.
I should build a search for cells and see everywhere either cells horizontal or cells vertical.
So once I've done that check, I'll then save the file.
I'm going to go back over and refresh.
And that should be it.
I should now have my maize showing up in a properly scaled fashion, no matter what the dimensions of
my window are.
If you refresh and you see an error, I can 100% guarantee you that you just made a typo.
So at some location, you put in a reference to the wrong variable.
Take a look at the error message and take a look at what line it told you that the error occurred on.
You can then go to that line inside of your index file and that will tell you exactly where the typo
is.
Again, if you have an error where you didn't before.
No two ways about it.
I absolutely, positively guarantee you you have a typo.
So just make sure you take a look and figure out where it is.
Okay.
So again, I know that refactor is painful, but if we close our console and then refresh, we're going
to see that we get this nicely scaled, different sized maze.
Now we can do some really interesting things so we can have different number of cells in the horizontal
or vertical direction.
So for example, I can have 14 cells in the horizontal and just ten in the vertical.
And if I save that, there we go.
And now it doesn't appear that the maze is super squished or anything like that because we are allowing
for the different number of cells.
So now we can play this thing.
You don't have to watch me play it, but I'm going to just solve it really quickly.
Come on.
Yeah, if you don't want to watch.
Just pause here.
Move to the next video.
But I've almost got it.
There we go.
Done.
All right.
Well, I'd say that looks pretty good.
It's the last thing I want to do is just add in a little bit of color to this thing.
And I also want to throw a big message on the center of the screen whenever the user wins as well.
So last little task in the next video.