All right.
The last thing I want to take care of inside of our maze is to just add in a little bit of color and
also show a nice message to the user whenever they succeed so that they understand that they really
did just win at the game.
So we're going to take a look at some of the different shapes that we are creating.
We're going to make sure that we add on a fill style to them to just color them in.
In addition, I'm going to make sure that when I create my render so here's our options object right
here.
I'm also going to flip wireframes to false.
Remember, that is what's going to make all of our different shapes solid and allow us to apply some
colors to them.
So I'm going to update wireframes to false and we're going to go down and find where we create all of
our different shapes.
I'm going to leave the walls as essentially whatever random color we get assigned.
I don't really care about those.
What I really care about is the different walls, the ball, and the goal.
So I'm going to go down to where we create.
Our verticals and horizontals.
Here's the horizontals for each right here.
I'm going to find where I create the wall.
I'm going to add in a new property to this options object.
And remember, if we want to customize the color, we can add on a render option that they fill style
and we'll specify the color that we want.
So I'm going to try out a color of red.
I'll then go down to where we create our verticals.
I'll find the wall that we create in there.
I'll find the options object.
And I'll also put on a render.
But they fill style of red.
I'll go down to where we create our goal.
I'm going to add on a render.
But the fill style of green.
So just make it a nice green that the user can understand.
Hey, green is good, right?
And then finally I'll find where we create the ball and the options object.
I'll add on a render and a fill style of blue.
So blue for the ball.
Okay.
So let's save this.
I will flip back over refresh.
And now we've got some interesting colouring going on.
This is definitely a little bit easier to parse visually.
A little bit more interesting as well.
The only thing I don't quite like about it is that the ball is a very dark blue.
So if you wanted to, you could try out some different colours and find one that maybe suits you better.
Yes, it looks good.
So now the last thing I want to do is to make sure once a user wins, we show a message on the very
center of the screen that says very clearly, hey, you won.
So another quick pause.
Wrap this thing up in just a moment.