All right.
In this video, we're going to make sure that we show a really big sign on the very center of the screen
that tells the user that they won once they actually will win.
So to do so, I'm going to go back over to my index HTML file.
Inside of here.
We're going to add in a development with an H one inside of it.
Now, as a quick reminder, hey, I said a billion times, this course is all about the JavaScript.
So this is mostly all about styling.
So we're going to kind of speed through a little bit of styling to make sure that this message shows
up in the correct location.
So right above my script tag, I'll add a div with the class of winner and hidden.
And then inside the div I'll place an h one.
That says you win.
Then inside my style tag right here, I'm going to add in some styling properties to just style that
thing.
So first selector I'm going to add in is for the hidden class.
So I'm going to say that if an element has the hidden class, then I don't want it to be displayed at
all.
So I'll say display non important to make sure 100% this thing should not show up on the screen.
And then go in to select the H one.
I'm going to give it a colour of white.
And a font size.
How about 36 pixels, nice and large.
And then finally, to get this thing centered, I'm going to select the winner class.
So that's essentially this dive right here.
Now I'm going to add on a couple of different rules to it.
So I'm going to say display a flex.
I'll add on a justify content to justify dash content of center and a line dash items of center.
So that's what it's going to get it to be centered on the screen.
I'll give it a position of absolute.
And a Z index of one to make sure that it shows up on top of our canvas element.
And then finally, I'll give it a height of 100.
VH and a width of 100 VW, and that's going to make sure that it stretches out the full height and width
of the screen.
It's enough.
We save this.
No need to go refresh, because right now, if we refresh, we're not going to see anything because
we've got the hidden class on there.
And remember, the hidden class hides that div and everything inside of it.
So now in order to show this message to our user, once they've hit our win condition, we just have
to select this element and remove the hidden class that will get that div and the h one side of it to
be displayed.
So for that, I'll go back over to my index case file.
I'm going to go down to the very bottom where we are handling our win condition right now.
And then inside of our if statement I'll add in a selector.
So document query selector.
I'm going to select the element with a class of winner.
I'll get the class list.
And I will remove the class of hidden.
All right, I'm going to save both these files.
I'll go back over.
I'll refresh.
So I don't see anything on the screen right away.
I'm going to change my maze dimensions so you don't have to sit here and watch me solve this maze forever.
So really quickly I'm going to change to cells horizontal of, I don't know, six and vertical of four.
There we go.
Nice and easy to solve.
So now I can go on over.
Solve it.
And there we go.
I see you in.
I think that text could be a little bit larger.
So what the heck?
I'm going to dial up that font size inside of our style tag right here.
I'll go to just a I don't know.
64 arbitrarily.
Save that.
When again.
And that's good enough, I'd say.
Okay, so that's pretty much it.
That is our maze game.
The only downside to this thing is that once a user wins, they essentially can't do it, do anything
else until they refresh.
So one way you could easily fix that is to just add in a button, maybe to recall or wrap all the code
we wrote together and throw that all into a function.
And then once the user wins, maybe show a button that a user can click to build out the entire grid
and verticals and all that kind of stuff again.
But I'm going to leave that up as a exercise to you.
Give me something that you can implement on your own if you want to, because we've definitely spent
a pretty good amount of time on this application already.
So I hope you enjoyed this app.
I think that it looks pretty interesting.
And hey, who doesn't like a good maze to play around with?
So let's take a break here and continue on the next video.