Hey.
Welcome back, everyone.
We've got a very big topic here.
By big, I don't mean long, difficult, challenging, but more so central, hugely important, crucial
to all of JavaScript.
That topic is functions.
Functions in some people's minds at least are the one topic that you must understand to be a good JavaScript
developer.
They are central to the language.
I know I've really overused that phrase in this course because all the things we've covered so far are
important.
We use them in pretty much every application or script we ever write.
We're definitely going to use variables and data structures, arrays and objects.
We'll have logic with conditionals, we'll use loops, we'll use functions.
But more than that, functions are very important to the way JavaScript is structured.
They're crucial to JavaScript identity as a language.
And you'll see what I mean as we progress through the rest of the course.
It's not only about defining our own functions and learning the syntax, but also there are a lot of
quirks with functions, a lot of things we can do that are cool with functions that just take some time
to understand.
So it's a big topic because it's important, because it's something we use every single time we write
code basically from here on out.
So we're not going to understand and cover every single topic around functions in this one section.
We have a couple of main goals for this section.
We want to understand the basics.
What is a function?
Why do you use them?
And then mostly how do we define them?
What's the syntax?
And then we'll write a ton of example functions, we'll have some exercises, some code alongs.
We just need to get practice.
So functions are not difficult, at least writing your own functions.
It's pretty straightforward, but there are a lot of things to understand about functions different
variations, different capabilities or features, and that will all unfold across a couple of sections.
So it's not all concentrated right here.
Okay, so let's begin.
What the heck is a function?
A function is simply a reusable procedure.
It's a chunk of code that we've wrapped up in a function.
So it's a bunch of lines of code that we can call again at any point we can refer back to it.
So we can have a function called get latest Reddit posts and any time we called it, it would have code
inside of it that would presumably request new Reddit posts and send them back to us.
Or we could have a simpler one.
Find average in array or just find average, or we could have a function called square and it simply
squares a value every time we pass in a number like ten it should return the square 100.
So we make these chunks of code.
They're little machines, which is why I'm using this sort of imagery here, mechanical stuff.
It's a bunch of code that we put together and we wrap it up into a package.
And the advantage of doing this is that we can then call that chunk of code, we can call that function
later on, which is kind of what this visual is supposed to represent.
I had a really hard time coming up with a graphic for functions.
This represents the function, the machinery, and then this button right here is calling that function.
Every time we press it, the function does its thing, it does its action.
So there's a two step process for every function that we ever used that we write.
First, we define the function, we lay it out, we tell JavaScript, Here is how this thing should
work.
It's kind of like registering it or going to the, I don't know, the DMV filling out forms, saying,
here's this new function, but that doesn't do anything as far as running the code.
It's just defining it, telling JavaScript about the function.
Then the second step is to execute the function, to run it, and we can run it once.
We could run it 100 times.
It's totally up to you and when you need to use it.
But the point here is that it's a two step process.
You write it and then you run it.
We've been working with quite a few functions so far.
We've been calling the method, which is important.
It is a distinction in terminology.
It's one we will address later once we learn how to write our own methods.
But methods are functions.
They are actions.
They're chunks of code that have been wrapped up, given a name and made into a repeatable function.
So things like Hello Dot to Uppercase to Uppercase is a built in method, which again we'll just call
a function.
For now it's a built in function.
Every time I call it, I need to use parentheses.
It's referring back to the same definition, the same built in set of instructions that says Here is
how to uppercase works.
So we're skipping the first step because it's a built in function or method.
We're simply running that code.
It's already been defined or written for us.
But notice we use parentheses.
We've seen that before.
It's the exact same thing when we're running our own functions.
So we've been using functions, but we haven't been defining them.
How do we define our own?
There are quite a few different syntax and syntax, different ways of writing functions in JavaScript.
The one we'll focus on for now at least is called a function declaration or a function statement.
It looks like this the func.
Keyword, a space and then a name for the function, which is totally up to you.
As long as it's a valid name.
So you don't want to name your function const.
You don't want to name your function function or for or if.
But in general.
Name it.
Whatever you want.
Just don't put spaces in there.
It has to be a valid identifier.
Shouldn't start with a number and then parentheses, open and closing parentheses.
Sometimes we put stuff in there which we'll get to shortly and then curly braces and we write our code
in here.
Whatever code we put in here in the body of the function will be called when this function runs.
So here's a simple, trivial, obnoxious example I'm defining a function called Grumpy's.
It doesn't mean anything at all.
It's just printing out three grouchy console logs.
UG you again for the last time.
Leave me alone.
And every time we call Grumpy's, these three lines would be printed out.
So it doesn't seem useful because this is not useful.
Why would you ever need this?
Why would you need a function called Grumpy's?
We'll get to useful ones, but the pattern is very important.
Function is a key word space.
And then our function name with parentheses, curly braces.
We put some content inside.
So let's define it over here.
Function Grumpy's parentheses and then console.log.
Three things.
There we go and just copied it over.
We have three console logs.
I'm going to save this file and refresh the page.
Nothing happens.
All that we've done is tell JavaScript.
Here is a function called Grumpy's, but it's never running.
We're just registering it.
We're letting JavaScript know Here's a thing called Grumpy's.
So to run it, which is the second step, all we do is write the name of the function followed by parentheses,
just like we've done with string methods like two uppercase.
We add those parents if we leave them off.
You might remember we talked about this briefly in one of the videos.
It's almost like JavaScript is telling us, Oh yeah, yeah, I know what that thing is that was registered
with me.
It's showing us there is some code in this case, native code built in code, but it's not actually
running it.
We have to add those per N's.
So same thing for Grumpy's.
If I simply type Grumpy's and I don't add those per ns, I'm seeing from JavaScript that this is a function,
it's been registered, it exists, but I'm not running it, I'm just referencing it.
So I need those friends.
And there we go.
My three lines actually run.
The function is executed.
So Grumpy's, let's do it three times.
Grumpy is grumpy we'll save.
I'm going to refresh the page and now we get nine consult logs.
We've defined our function and we've executed it two steps and we can execute it like this.
We could execute it in a loop.
If I wanted to loop 20 times for less, I equals zero, I lessen or equal.
Let's do less than let's do 50 plus plus.
We've got a whole flock of grumpy faces I can call Grumpy's, refresh the page and we get a whole lot
of grumpy, grumpy text printed out, a very stupid and grumpy function.
But the point is not the content, it is the format, function, keyword, space, some function name,
whatever this name is, you must reference later.
So if I tried to call Grumpy with a capital G that doesn't exist, I get an error.
It has to match the name.
We gave it up here and then print in order to execute it.
All right.
So this is just the beginning.
We'll very quickly see some more useful functions.
We've got a lot more to talk about.