Let's try writing another function this time, something that doesn't just print grumpy text over and
over and over.
Let's do something with some variation.
How about generating a random dice roll or a single die roll?
So a number from zero?
Nope.
There's no zero die.
1 to 6.
And we'll name this function something that makes sense.
Like roll die.
So we need function, space, roll, die, curly braces.
And now we need the logic to generate a random number from 0 to 6.
So let's roll equal.
And then we'll do math at random.
You know how much I'm not a fan of this syntax.
Math at random times six.
And then we need to floor that math floor.
Remember, math at random gives us a decimal.
So it would be like 0.2.
And then we multiply it by six in order to get a larger range.
So we're no longer just from 0 to 1.
We're going from zero to, I guess right below six because the largest decimal will generate is 0.9
something we multiply by six and then we floor it to get rid of that decimal.
So now we have a number from 0 to 5, but our dice roll or die roll should be from 1 to 6.
So we add one.
The logic is not all that important really.
We're still focusing on the fact that every time we call roll die, this code runs.
This code happens to make a number from 1 to 6, a random number, and then let's cancel that log rolled
and then string template literal the rule, refresh the page.
Nothing happens because we never executed this, we just registered it, we told JavaScript about it.
So we will now execute it once we get rolled, two, rolled, three, four or five.
Cool.
And we can do this within a loop if we wanted to.
We can even call functions within other functions.
So some games we'll have you roll a bunch of dice at the same time, like Yahtzee.
I think you roll five or six.
I know there's a bunch of other games, not much of a gambler, but let's make up a function called
How about throw dice and throw dice will simply call roll die.
How about six times?
We could do it like this.
Or we could do it with a loop.
But just to make it simple and clear that it's running six times, I'll do it manually by writing it
out six times a loop would probably make more sense if we wanted to have throw dice in the future,
potentially change the number of rolls.
So we could have throw dice to throw dice six for different games.
But this is good enough.
We're not there yet.
We'll refresh the page.
Nothing happens.
And that's because I haven't executed either function.
So I'm going to call throw dice if I can spell it, which in turn calls roll die six different times
each time this code runs and we get some number printed out.
There we go.
Four, six, one, four, two, two.
So we've seen more repetition of how we define a function.
But also the new component here is that we can call functions from inside other functions.
We can call them in loops, you can call them in conditionals.
We can call them pretty much anywhere.