Next up, let's talk about function arguments.
Arguments is really a fancy term for inputs to a function.
And right now, our functions don't expect they don't accept any inputs.
They behave the same way every time.
So we wrote that silly grumpy function.
And this is kind of what happens here visually, at least if this is the function we don't pass any
inputs in, we just call Grumpy's the exact same way every time and we get the same output.
Those three consort logs.
Now, I didn't write them here because they took up too much space.
So we get this little grumpy kid instead, but it's the same output every time, the same three lines
that are printed.
Here's another example a function that I'm calling greet.
Just type it up very quickly and all it does is console, dot, log, hi.
Every single time.
If I run it and I call greet, we can't impact it.
We don't pass anything in.
It works the same way.
No inputs, same output.
Now this doesn't necessarily mean we'll always get the exact same output as we saw with our roll die
function.
We did get a different output because we're using random numbers, but we're not altering the behavior.
When we call it, we call role die the exact same way every single time.
We're not impacting it.
We're just saying roll a die and it picks random number.
But it would be nice if we could specify if this was a six sided die or a 12 sided die or something
like that.
And we would do that by passing in an argument.
So those inputs that we pass in, as I've already mentioned, are called arguments.
Here's an example of an updated version of greet where we could pass in a value for someone's name.
So if we call greet and then we pass in Tim, the output could be, Hi Tim.
If we did it with Ana, we could get the output of high on you.
Still very simple stuff.
Here's another example a hypothetical function called average, and it takes multiple arguments two
or four, maybe ten, and the output will be the average.
So it will sum them all together and then divide by the number of inputs.
So 20 plus, 25 divided by to 22.5.
These four numbers divided by four gives us four.
And we've already seen arguments quite a bit in the built in methods we've been working with.
Something like two uppercase expects no inputs.
We don't pass anything in it.
Just uppercase is something.
It's kind of like our initial version of greet.
It does the same thing, but then we have things like index of or includes or splice or slice where
we have to specify inputs.
We have to tell it in the case of index of what string we're looking for in hello.
And we get different behaviors and different outcomes if we pass in an H index of zero, if we pass
in an O, we get index of four, we're specifying additional information.
So how do we make our functions?
Expect arguments and use those values in the code, in the function body?
It's pretty simple.
All we do is instead of our function definition, instead of empty parentheses, we add in some variable
name.
So this has to be a valid JavaScript identifier.
It can't have spaces, it can't start with a number, but otherwise we can name it whatever we want.
And just like with a four of loop where we had four, let X of some array, let's say the array 1 to
3.
This X doesn't matter what we call it at all, but it will hold the value each time.
Through this loop of one of these elements, we kind of do the same thing for a function.
If we wanted to update our greet function to accept somebody's name, I would go maybe with nickname
or person and we put that in the parentheses.
This does not do anything on its own.
It will only work if we pass in a string or a number or some value when we call greet.
But let's console.log.
Nickname nickname will hold the value of whatever is passed in JavaScript doesn't care what the type
is.
If it's a string or even an array, it just cares that it's the first thing that was passed in and it
will be assigned to nickname.
That's just a sort of a placeholder name.
You want to give it something that makes sense, a name that is logical.
So nickname is fine.
Let's see what happens.
Now I'm printing out nickname on the first line that's called greet and then pass in Tim.
And there we go.
You can see the first contact log says nickname, which is Tim.
So nickname had the value of Tim because that's what I passed in.
If I pass something else in like a number.
Nickname has that value.
It could be an array.
How about an empty array?
We canceled that log.
Empty array.
And what if I don't pass anything in?
In some languages, this could cause an error.
In JavaScript, it doesn't care.
It says there's no value.
It's undefined, but it doesn't break anything.
It's just not there.
Nickname just didn't have a value.
So let's rewrite this just to be slightly nicer.
We'll use back ticks and we'll greet the person high and then dollar sign nickname and maybe an exclamation
point afterwards.
Run it again.
Greet.
Tim.
Hi, Tim.
So we're constantly logging something different based off of the input.
The input has a direct impact on what the function actually does.
Next up, let's try modifying roll, die or throw dice.
These two functions, let's pick one.
I'll uncomment them both.
Let's go with throw dice.
So right now, throw dice always calls, roll dice.
Six times.
If I call it over here, throw dice.
It rolls six dice.
It calls roll dice six times.
But what if we could specify a number of times how many times we actually want to roll?
Maybe we're playing a game where you have two dice, but maybe we're playing another game like Yahtzee
where you have five or six.
I don't remember how many it actually uses, but it's more than two we could pass in an argument and
let's give it a name.
We'll talk more about terminology here.
Technically, the variables we write here are called parameters, not arguments.
Let's go with times or num rolls.
Maybe that's better.
Num rolls.
And then in here we'll use this to repeat roll die.
So how do we repeat something?
We'll use a loop.
So we'll loop four.
We'll just do a for loop.
Let's I equals zero.
Well is less than num rolls.
Add one to I each time and we'll call roll die.
So if we pass in five we'll go from zero and then up to five, but not including five.
Or we could go from one and then less than or equal to num rolls.
I'll just go with zero because we don't care about what I actually is.
We just want a certain number of times, so let's see if it works.
Throw dice and I do need to pass in a number like three.
We got three rolls.
How about five?
We get five roles.
It combined two of them because they were identical.
Thanks.
Chrome console nine.
We get nine roles now.
We've written it so that we can impact the way it behaves based off of a single input.
All right.
So that's good enough for now.
In the next video, we'll see how we can have multiple arguments, how the order matters, and we'll
start writing some more complicated functions.