In this video.
We'll see how we can have multiple inputs, multiple arguments for a single function.
First, we need to talk about terminology very quickly.
If we have some function, let's call it square and square, except a single input.
Let's just call it num and we'll console.log num times num.
We'll call it over here.
Square of four it prints 16.
So I said, I want to talk about terminology.
We've been using the word argument to refer to the input, which is correct.
Four is an argument.
The actual value we pass in is an argument.
This right here num is not an argument.
The real term, the correct terminology is parameter.
And if I hover it actually tells me here.
Parameter called num.
A parameter is like the placeholder name.
It is this variable that we define when we're writing our function and then when we execute the function,
we pass in a value.
And that number here is the argument.
So argument when we call it parameter, when we define it, it doesn't really impact how anything works
or how you should understand all of this.
It's just technical stuff that sometimes people mix up and it's just important to get that out of the
way.
All right.
So let's see how we define a function with multiple parameters or another way of saying it is a function
that expects multiple arguments to be passed in.
Let's start with the classic super simple to argument function.
Some there are two parameters.
I'll call them X and Y and we will add them together.
Console.log x plus y.
Nice and easy.
We separate them by commas.
Otherwise it's the exact same syntax.
We just put some name in there, a valid identifier, and it will hold whatever value is passed to it.
And the order does matter.
Now, this is not going to do a great job of illustrating that because X and Y won't matter.
As far as the order.
I can pass three, comma four or four, comma, three.
We'll still get seven, but let's just make sure it works.
Four and five gives us nine, and obviously five plus four also gives us nine.
So now let's do an example where order does matter.
Let's just do a simple division function.
We'll call it divide and we'll do instead of X and Y.
Why not A and B, I guess X and Y are more standard for algebra, but A and B work as well.
And all we'll do is cancel that log A divided by B.
Okay.
Now let's call it.
Divide one by four and we get 0.25.
So whichever argument was passed in first, whatever value one in this case will be assigned to A,
so a will be one, and then the second value will be four, which gets assigned to be.
So the order is very important in this case.
If I tried to do four comma one, it's completely different.
Now A is four and B is one.
The order that we define these parameters in dictates the order that they are filled in from left to
right.
So one came before four, so one goes before four.
And if we had written five parameters here A, B, C, D and E, they would be filled in that order.
First one would be a, second would be B, third would be C and so on.
There are many, many issues with this function.
First of all, I mean, it works with numbers, but if I pass something in like a string and a number,
we don't have any checks to make sure that we're working with numbers and that's okay.
We're not focused on that for now.
So it takes us and it divides by four, which is not a number.
But what I'm trying to show here is that the function doesn't care.
It is type agnostic.
It's just going to do whatever you tell it to do with these values.
So what if we just passed in five?
Well, A is going to be assigned five, B will be undefined.
So we just did B divided by undefined, which gives us not a number.
If an argument is missing that parameter, whatever it's called, in our case, B will have a value
of undefined.
Just like if we have a variable called B and we don't give it a value, it's set to undefined.
It's the same idea.
We're essentially saying Here's a variable called B and the value will be passed in.
But if we don't pass it in, it remains undefined.