There's one more key function concept we have yet to discuss, which is the return statement returning
values from a function.
We talked about functions that take inputs.
And then on the diagram I had, if we go back a couple of slides, I have this arrow indicating output.
But right now our functions aren't returning a value, they are printing a value out.
And there's a big difference between the two.
If we take a look at one of the built in methods, any of them, how about hello to uppercase?
So the two uppercase method when I run that the console prints out hello.
And we see the text.
Hello.
But that's only in the console.
It's just being helpful for us to immediately see the return value.
If I paste that in to a file and I run this code, refresh the page.
We see nothing.
This code is run and to uppercase does return a value, but it's lost forever.
We're not printing it, we're not capturing it.
What we would normally do is one of those either print it out.
Most likely though, we just put it in a variable const scream equals hello to uppercase we refresh
now scream has a value stored in it, so this returned an output to uppercase return to value.
We captured it in screen.
So printing something to the console is entirely different than returning a value.
When we're working in the console they might seem similar, but there are still is a significant difference
if I run that code again.
Hello to uppercase notice this little arrow I get here.
It's pointing the other direction.
This signifies I'm looking at a return value now if I console.log the same thing Hello to uppercase
it's printed out differently This is an actual console.log I don't have the arrow This is a return value
So return values are extremely useful because we can capture them in a variable.
We could pass them to another function.
Remember that most of the time in applications that we create later on in this course and in the real
world, we don't print much to the console any given website.
If you open the console, maybe there's a line or two that a developer left in there.
Or sometimes if you go to a website like Facebook and we open the console, we have a message here.
In this case, it's to prevent people from running code or something that is fraudulent or scammy or
sketchy.
If someone told you to copy and paste something here to enable a Facebook feature, it's a scam, blah
blah blah.
But other than that, we're not usually contact logging things unless we're debugging or trying to test
something out.
Most of what we do when we write functions is we return a value and we use that value somehow.
Console.log is just useful when we're starting out.
We haven't talked about how we manipulate a web page, how we change HTML, how we display content.
So for now we just show it in the console.
But when we have a function console, logging something instead of returning is not a substitute.
If we take a look at this add function, add x and y, it console logs x plus y when I call it.
If I refresh my page here, add one and two, it prints out the value three.
But if I try and store that in a variable like const sum equals, if we look at some it's undefined.
There is no value returned from this function.
It prints something which is better than nothing, but it doesn't actually return a value.
There's no output.
So let's change that.
Let's add in returns to our functions.
All we have to do is use the return keyword.
So return and then some value.
We can have an expression.
This will evaluate first and then be returned.
So if we do that, add x and y, return x plus y, run my code again, add four comma five in the console
we see nine.
But that's not actually being printed out.
It's just the chrome console showing us a return value.
And if I save that to a variable cost total equals add for comma five, we look at total.
It now stores the value nine.
So we return something from the function which we can capture later, which is what I did here.
There are some rules to know about returning.
First of all, you can only return one thing from a function.
That doesn't mean you can't have multiple return statements, but when you actually return something,
there needs to be one value.
So if I wanted to return X and Y for some reason instead of the total, I could use an array and do
x, y, or I could do a string where I add x inside and y inside.
But I can't return two separate values so I can collect them in some.
In return that.
But I need to return one thing.
So I said we could have multiple return statements in a single function.
I'll show you an example of that now.