So we saw that we can use a return statement to export or return a value so that we can capture it later
in a variable or do something with it.
But there's another thing you should know about return statements, which is that they end function
execution.
So if you have a return statement in the middle of your function, the code afterwards is not going
to execute.
For example, if we have our function square, which takes a number and we want it to return x times
x if that's the parameter, if I add some code afterwards like console.log.
All done and I try calling this function square of four, I get 16, but this console.log never runs.
It's after this return statement.
Whenever JavaScript encounters a return, it just moves on.
It's done with this function entirely.
We could have 100 lines after this.
They would not run.
But of course, if we were using conditionals, if we had an if statement around a return, then it
may not run every single time.
So it's not a matter of if there is a return statement written anywhere in the function nothing afterwards
runs.
It's only if the return statement is executed if this code is run, which in our case it always is.
But we could write something else like a very stupid function called is purple, is purple, takes a
color as a parameter and we'll assume it's a string.
And if color is triple equal to the string purple, we will return.
True, I name this is purple which is a standard convention is something for a boolean method which
returns true or false.
So we have true or false.
We're returning true.
If color is triple equal to purple, if it's not equal to purple, we could return false.
So we have to return statements.
But only one of them is going to run.
If color is purple, this will run and let's actually make it a little more case insensitive.
So why don't we two lowercase color.
So if someone passes in purple in all caps, will compare it first by lowercase it to all lowercase
and then comparing it to purple.
All right.
So is purple of blue is false is purple of purple.
It's true.
Whoops.
All caps we still get true.
So this is not the best way of writing this function.
And we'll talk about how we could refactor it in a moment, ignoring the fact that it's not even a useful
function at all, not even remotely useful.
We do have to return statements.
Only one of them is going to run, but as soon as one of them does run, the rest of the code stops.
So in this, if if I had a console.log, yay, that's never going to run ever.
There's no scenario where this runs because either this is true and we're returning, which stops the
execution of the function completely or it's false.
And so this entire chunk is skipped and removed right to here, if I try is purple with purple, we
don't get it.
Okay.
So I mentioned there are other ways of writing this for especially for a simple, if else, a simple
yes or no.
We can rewrite this function a couple of different ways.
I'm going to copy this.
The first improvement we could make is to remove the else entirely because of the way return statements
work.
What we just talked about, where they end function execution.
The only way to get to this line is if this is false because we're returning true in here.
Execution stops.
So if color is purple, we're done.
Function over.
If it's not, this is the only way we would ever return.
False.
So it's just a shorter way of writing this.
You'll see people write functions like this that take advantage of the fact that a return statement
stops a function.
So this is one way of doing it.
We can just run the code again, make sure it still works.
Is purple of purple is true, is purple of anything else is false.
We don't have an LS now.
There's actually an even shorter way of writing this where we could basically do it on one line.
If we're just returning a boolean, true or false, we can simply return this right here.
Return color to lowercase triple equals purple.
This right here is a boolean expression.
Triple equals will give us true or false.
So if I have, let's say color is pink, I would call pink two lowercase.
Triple equals purple.
That's false.
But if color is purple, even if it's capitalized oddly, it still gives us true.
So we're going to return this value and that will be true or false.
This evaluates first, then it's returned.
So it's just another way of writing it.
We only need one return.
Now, this only works for a yes or no simple situation like we have here.
What if we wanted to check if color is purple?
We want to return.
True.
And if color is lilac, we want to return true.
Anything else is false.
We would need to rewrite this.
It would be harder to do in a single line.
And let's do one more example.
I want to show how a return will stop a function no matter where it's located in that function.
So it could be inside of a loop instead of a conditional.
It doesn't matter.
So we'll do a slightly more advanced version of is purple let's go with contains purple and this will
accept an array and we will loop over the array.
And if any element in that array is either purple or magenta, we'll return true.
Otherwise we return false.
So we'll loop over the array for let's color of array.
We'll use a for of if color is triple equal, purple or color is triple equal said magenta.
I think this magenta.
Purple or is it pink?
For our purposes, we're considering it purple.
If that's the case, we'll return.
True.
And then where would we return?
False.
This one is a bit different.
If we put return false here, or else return false, then as soon as we encounter something that's not
purple, let's say our array looks like this blue, pink, magenta.
The first time through the loop color will be blue.
So this is not true and we don't want to return false right away.
That stops the function entirely.
We're only checking the first element.
The only time we know that the entire array does not contain purple is if the loop is finished.
So if the loop is done and we haven't returned.
True, that means we never found purple or magenta as an element.
Then we can return false.
So we just move it down there.
So let's test it out.
Contains purple.
I'll paste that array in.
I do need to make sure I get rid of the semicolon, add my perin and we get true.
If we change this to no longer be magenta, we get false.
So this is showing us two things.
First of all, when we return, true, it doesn't matter that we're inside of a conditional inside of
a loop instead of a function, the function is done at least this single execution of it.
When we called it with this array, it's done, it returns true.
So it's not like a return is only going to break out of one code block.
It has the power to halt the entire function, even though it's in a conditional in a loop.
So this loop might run one time if the first element is purple or magenta, or it might run 100 times.
If our elements or if our array is 100 items long with no instance of purple or magenta.
And the second thing we saw once again is returning false or returning some value as a last ditch as
basically the last option, the last line in this function.
So if none of this returned true at any point, that means we've gone through the entire loop.
Then just return false.
We don't have to add additional logic.
We don't need an else.
We just know if you haven't returned by now, this is what we want to return.
So if this is true, the function is done and this never runs.
If we never return true, then this runs.
Okay.
So we've seen the basics of functions.
At this point we define a function at least one version.
All we've seen is the function syntax, function statement or function declaration.
We have function some function name, potentially different parameters.
We would add in A and B and then some return value.
And you don't have to return a value from every single function, but a lot of the time you want to
and we'll see a bunch of examples coming up because it's time to get some practice.