All right, let's get some practice writing functions with return values and arguments.
We'll have a couple of these challenges or code alongs.
It's up to you how you want to treat them.
If you want to attempt to write the function on your own, I highly recommend that approach.
But if you are completely new to functions and you're a little overwhelmed, then maybe take a step
back, follow along with me and revisit these later on.
So here's the first one.
There's some description, some text I wrote.
You can download this if you want and write your own function without looking at my solution.
The goal is to write a function called is valid password and it accepts two different arguments a password
and a username, and you can assume both of them are strings and this function should return.
True or false?
It's a boolean method.
If the password meets all of the requirements which we'll go into in a moment, it should return.
True.
If any of them fail, then it should not be valid.
So we return false.
So the password needs to be at least eight characters.
It cannot contain any spaces and it cannot contain the username.
So if my username is dog lover, which is what I have here, this is an invalid password.
It contains that text.
It's not as safe.
This is still not a very good set of rules for a password in general, but it's good enough for our
function examples.
So no username that cannot be contained anywhere in the string in the middle at the beginning.
Also we need to make sure at least eight characters so another example would be is valid password and
then if the password was only hello one, that would be false because it's not long enough as would
this because it does not have a space.
We don't need to return any specific reason for why it's invalid.
So don't return something like password to short.
It should be a boolean, true or false?
So go ahead and try this if you'd like.
Pause the video and then let's write a solution.
So I'll start off by defining my function is valid password two parameters.
The first one will be password.
The second one is username.
You could do it the other way around if you want.
I'm just following the pattern I laid out here, but you just need to make sure you have two parameters
and give them meaningful names.
So if we're calling this one password, then we better treat it as password.
So we have three different things we're checking for.
Let's start with the length of the password.
So we need a conditional.
We need to check if password length is greater than or equal to eight.
If that's the case, it is valid.
So we could write it this way.
But it's a little trickier because we need to make sure all of these are valid in order for the whole
thing to be valid.
So we need all of these to be true in order for us to return true.
So I couldn't just say if password length is greater than or equal to eight return.
True, because that might work if the password is eight characters like that.
But one of those characters could be a space at which point it's invalid.
So I need to make sure all of them are true so I could chain them all together with and I'm not a fan
of this approach for a bunch of pieces together, this could get quite long.
We have to check if there are spaces.
We have to check if there's username, if the username is contained in the password.
So I'm going to reverse my logic and say if password length is less than eight, return false because
only one of these needs to be untrue.
It needs to be false in order for the entire password to be invalid.
So we'll just check.
Is it too short then we know automatically return false.
Then I'll do another one.
Are there spaces?
So if password.
And then how do we check if there is a space in a string or any character in that string?
I'll just do index of the space character and remember index of will give us negative one if that character
is not in there.
So there's no space in ISDS and I get negative one.
So if password index of is not negative one, that means we have a problem.
We want it to be negative one in order for the password to be valid.
So we'll return false here.
That means there is a space.
And then how do we check if it contains the username?
Basically the exact same thing.
Password dot index of username.
So a username could be dog lover and dog lover is contained in this string we can use index of with
multiple characters.
I could do ASD as index of asd and it tells us it starts at index zero if I do so.
This is a terrible string to use but you can see it starts at index one.
So it's not only used for a single character at a time, if this is the case, we will return false.
Otherwise we can return true.
And we don't need an.
Else.
We also don't need to do if and else if and where to live if you could.
But since we're returning as soon as one of them is true.
If this is true, we return.
We're done.
We don't have to do if and elseif, but we'll refactor this in a moment or we'll talk about a different
way of writing this in a moment.
But let's just make sure it works.
So I'm going to try calling this let's do is valid password of something that is too short.
So asd like that and then some username.
It doesn't really matter.
We get false.
Now let's do another example where there's a space.
It could be, let's do one.
That's long enough.
But there's a space in there and then some username.
We still get false.
And now let's do our final test case where we have a long enough password like chicken.
One, two, three, four.
And the username is chicken.
That's not allowed, so we get false.
But if I no longer include chicken in my password and I instead change it to chicken spelled that way
we finally get true.
So we're now meeting the requirements.
This is OC and I actually kind of like writing it this way.
It's very explicit and clear what's going on.
We could write it using a single conditional.
It would just get really long.
We can link them together and say, if one of these is true.
So if this or this or this return false.
So we could do that.
I'll duplicate the function and rewrite it just so you can see what it would look like.
So we could rewrite it as if.
And then the first thing would be password.
Dot length is less than eight or password.
Index of space, not empty string, but space is not equal to negative one or password.
Index of username is not equal to negative one.
If that's the case, if one of those is true, return, false or more.
If one or more is true and then return true at the end, that means everything is valid and this works.
I would definitely just want to format it like we have here.
Make it easier to see one long line.
It's not so pretty.
Let's make sure it still works.
Let me comment out the original one here.
Refresh and try it again.
So this one is valid.
This one contained chicken, which is the username.
So it's invalid.
This one had a space in it invalid.
And this one was too short.
Also invalid.
So this is also nice.
This is not too bad.
Another approach you could take just by the way, if you are bored with this or you feel like you've
got a good grasp of it, go ahead and move on.
I probably don't even need to tell you that, but I will show you another approach.
What we could do is make each of these into a variable.
All of these return true or false.
So I'm going to get rid of this.
I'm just going to delete everything for a moment.
And I could make a variable here.
What would this be called?
Maybe is to short or to short.
So const to short equals password length, less than eight const.
And then this one would be has spaces or has space equals this line.
So these variables I'm making, three of them are going to be true or false.
Boolean Values.
Password.
Index of username.
So we'll call this const.
It's a short way of saying this contains username.
How about two similar
like that?
And then we can use those to make a conditional if to short or has space or to similar return false.
And I'll do this on one line.
There's nothing wrong with that.
I don't need those curly braces.
We've seen it once or twice for nice and short conditionals.
All we need is one line of code.
Return false.
Otherwise, return true.
Och.
It should still work.
That's invalid.
This one with a space in it.
Super long space still invalid.
Let's go with a different username like dog and then a password that contains dog.
I love dog.
One, two, three.
Still false, but now if I change username to be cat, password no longer contains it.
It's true.
And we've got yet another thing that we could change.
And to be clear here, I'm not saying that this is the best evolution or that this version will be the
better version.
I just want to explore some possibilities here.
So what we're doing right now is checking a bunch of conditions.
Well, it's a single condition that contains a couple orders.
And if this is true, we return false.
If it's not true, we return true.
So we want this to be false so that we return true, if that makes sense.
So we could invert this instead of saying if it's too short or it has spaces or it's too similar to
username return false.
We could say if it's not too short, if it doesn't have space and it's not too similar return.
True.
And we could write that like this function is valid password.
We can keep these variables.
But remember, any time I have a variable here, you could just replace it with a condition.
So we could say if it's not too short and does not have space and it's not too similar, we want to
return true.
Otherwise return false.
And it should still work.
Fine if I refresh over there.
This one is valid, but if I now change this to be love as my username, it's false.
If I just change the username to something and I add a space false.
And if the password is too short, we get false.
Now this also is good, but we can improve it even one more degree.
I shouldn't say improve, but we can shorten it if you want it to.
We're saying if this is true, return true.
If this is false, return false.
We could just say return this.
This evaluates to true or false so I could get rid of that.
Return this this whole thing will evaluate to true or false and then we return that value.
So that's false.
Let's do a longer one.
That's true because it does not contain this username.
I had a space.
We've seen this a bunch of times by now.
The logic still works and I'll stop here.
We could continue to flip flop and change the type of logic we're doing.
We could, instead of making a variable called to short and checking if the password is too short,
we could go the other way around and check.
Is this password long enough?
In which case we'd be checking password length greater than or equal to eight.
And then we could change our logic down here.
The point is, we could continue to alter the logic.
I'm not going to stress about it.
Looking at all of them.
I think any of them is good.
Even this first one, which is a lot longer in terms of the number of lines, it's still very easy to
see what's going on.
A lot of people obsessed, especially students who are starting out obsessed with writing compact,
super short one liner functions and really trying to do like hacky cool things.
And that's great.
It's always fun to see how short you can make something, but often that comes at the expense of readability
and expressiveness, just being able to understand it.
If someone walked into this code or walked into this file and needed to understand what was going on,
all of these are pretty clear.
And these in particular, I like with these variables.
Some people would say as you don't need those variables, you're wasting memory.
It's really a minuscule waste of memory if you want to call it that.
And it's not worth stressing about, but pick whichever one you're comfortable with.
I just wanted to show a couple different versions.