Let's do some practice with functions.
So in this example, I'd like you to write a function called average AVG or just average the word which
accepts an array of numbers and you can assume it's all numbers.
You don't have to check to see if each thing is a number.
So it accepts an array of numbers and it should return the average value of all those numbers.
So in a simple case like zero and 50, it should return 25, but it should work for an array of any
length, 100 numbers, 20 numbers, two numbers, return the average, so give it a shot.
There's many ways of doing this.
There's many ways of doing this, including some functions and some helpers we haven't covered yet.
That would make this even easier.
But we're just going to start with a good old fashioned loop and division.
So let's define our function, function a V and let's give the parameter a name of array a R.
So ah, you could also call it numbs values.
And our main approach here is going to be loop over each num, add them together, divide by number
of nums divided by the length of the array.
So we need a place where we can tally or some all of the values we we need a variable.
So I'm going to make a variable called total and I'll start it at zero.
Then we're going to loop over each num.
We could do a for loop.
I like four of so for lit num, I'll call it num or x or val value of the array.
We want to take that num and add it into total.
So total plus equals num.
So we start with zero and 50.
Total starts at zero num is zero.
The first time we add 0 to 0, then num is now 50.
So we're going to add 50 to total.
Total is now 50 and we've hit the end.
So we're not done because right now we would be returning the entire sum if we returned total.
What we need to do instead is return the total divided by the number of elements in the array.
So we can do this.
We can make a variable let result equal total divided by array length and then return result or rise.
Let's see if it works.
Average of zero and 50 is 2580 5.2.
For this array of test scores.
We could also just return this line without a variable.
It's clear enough we're just taking the total dividing by the length of the array and that's it.
We start with a total of zero.
We loop over each element, we add that into the total, so we end up with this sum, and then we return
that sum divided by the number of elements.
Like I said, there's many ways of doing this.
You could have used a for loop, a regular for loop.
Instead, if you know about things like for each, which we haven't covered, you could have used that.
But the main idea is you sum things together using a loop and then divide.