Hey.
Welcome back, everyone.
We've made it through all of the promises and asynchronous JavaScript callback hell stuff, and we needed
to cover all of that so that we can start making requests.
We're going to see how we can use JavaScript to get information from an API like load movie data or
search for planets and Star Wars or get a random joke, which you could also apply to things like logging
someone in via Facebook or sending some data off to your own server to save to a database.
It's all the same process.
We send a request from the client side and we have to understand asynchronous JavaScript and promises
for a lot of the requests that will be sending, because these requests take time.
We talked about that in the previous section.
These things aren't immediate.
It takes time.
They might fail.
They might I mean, it could take 10 seconds.
It could take half a second.
It doesn't matter how long exactly.
It just matters that it's not instantaneous.
So we have to worry about things like callbacks and promises.
So there are multiple ways of making requests.
We're going to start with the old school.
Quite, quite ugly and confusing and hard to remember way XML HTTP requests, which is standard across
all browsers, but a newer, much more modern and simpler syntax exists, which is called fetch.
So we'll see both of those.
Then we'll talk about a library that's really, really popular to help you make requests called Axios.
It's a third party script we can include.
It just simplifies the process.
So we're doing the same thing.
It's just a cleaner syntax.
But before we talk about any of those options, we need to talk about this idea of Ajax, which is a
term you may have heard.
If you're brand new to JavaScript, you might have come across this term Ajax.
It stands for asynchronous JavaScript and XML, which is kind of a misnomer because these days, most
of the time we don't work with XML, we work with JSON.
Nobody says age, but that's that's kind of what it is these days.
So if you don't know what XML or JSON are, we'll get there.
But let's just talk about this general idea.
Back in the day before, Ajax was really a big thing.
Before single page apps were common, we had one standard flow for loading new data or getting information
from a server which included a page refresh.
Here's an example.
MDM is not a single page app.
If I search for something here like React, I don't know if they have much on React actually, but if
I hit Enter you'll see my page does change.
I go to a new URL and the page actually reloads one more time.
Let's look for div.
Watch this little bar.
Here we go to a completely different page.
So what's happening here is the browser is sending a request for a new web page and it's going off to
one of MDM servers depending on this URL.
This is the URL that we requested by hitting enter.
This URL is then received.
The request is received by the server and the server wherever it is.
And it compiles a new web page for us, including the HTML and CSS and any relevant JavaScript.
It sends the entire page back.
Our browser refreshes and this is what we see a whole new page.
Contrast that with what happens here.
This is a website called Can I Use?
Let's go back to home and we'll search for something.
How about gradient?
I'm going to search for gradient.
The page never reloads.
I don't go anywhere else.
Data is being loaded.
There is communication with the server, but it's happening behind the scenes.
It doesn't involve a whole page refresh.
We're not getting a new web page.
It's a different approach.
We're just getting some data or can I use is asking for data from a server.
It comes back and then new elements are added to the page.
If I search for something else, let's go back to transform.
You can see what happens.
I'm not moving.
The page is not changing.
Well, the page is changing.
The contents are changing, at least some of it.
But it's a single page that we are staying on and this is really what Ajax is all about.
The idea of Ajax is using these requests that we can make via JavaScript asynchronously.
That's the asynchronous JavaScript to load some data from a server or to send data to a server to save
something to a database, whatever it is, we're communicating with the server behind the scenes, not
in between page loads like we had here where I search for something else.
In between those loads, in between what a user sees and the page refreshing.
That is when the communication is occurring with the server.
Here, the communication is happening while I'm on this page, it's happening in the background and
the general process is a request is sent based off of, in this case, a keyboard events.
So if I type something else, what's another how about arrow functions?
So I finished typing.
There's some sort of balance on here, so it's not sending a request.
Every single time I hit a letter, it's waiting until I finish a word or something.
It's sending a request based off of my keyboard input.
In the background, it's happening.
We get some response from the server.
The response usually these days is in the form of something called JSON.
In the past it was XML, which is what was most commonly used and where the name Ajax comes from.
But these days almost everyone uses JSON.
So JSON is just a format for sending data.
Imagine you have data representing all of this information we see here.
The elements themselves are not being sent as HTML or the CSS is not being sent.
All that's being sent is basically the text and some information that maybe doesn't show up.
You know what supported, what's not supported and it's being sent as text, but rather than just plain
text, it's turned into this JSON notation.
It's a way of representing data.
It's a protocol for communicating between servers or a protocol for formatting data and sending it to
another server or to another browser somewhere.
So we're going to talk about what it looks like in depth in the next video.
But if we open up our dev tools here and you go to the network tab, I just want to show you that we
can see the requests happening behind the scenes.
Let's search for something else like spread and you'll see some activity over here.
This activity represents different requests that have been sent if we go to X HR, which we haven't
talked about yet, but that's what we'll see next.
X HR here is going to show us the requests that have been sent.
And we can see here is one sent to a can I use server?
If we open this up, this was the URL of a sent to search equals spread and some information was sent
back.
This is the data that was sent back.
If we take a look at it here, this is the data that came back from the server behind the scenes.
So we end up with some information, let's see, MD and CSS properties box shadow spread radius.
So that represents this result right here.
Then we have another one operator spread, spread and de structuring, which is what we see here.
So this information was sent back from the server, but it's not all of the information.
It looks like there was a second request sent.
And if we look at this.
It's a lot more, but this is really the core of the browser support chart that is created.
So we get the titles back.
I guess they split it up maybe so you can get them faster.
I'm not positive, actually.
There's I'm sure there's a good reason why there are two requests instead of one that just gets everything
at once.
But here we can see a representation of the CSS property box shadow spread radius.
That's a title that we have here.
We have, let's see, support.
And under support we can see all the different browsers.
Here's all the support for Chrome and Edge.
There's a lot of information here, so we won't go into detail on what this actually looks like.
But the point is, this is not HTML that's being sent.
It's not JavaScript itself, it's not actually JavaScript.
It looks like JavaScript, but it's actually called JSON.
It's simply a way of sharing data between a server and another server, a server in a browser that we
can then use in JavaScript.
It's really easy to to take JSON and turn it into JavaScript and do something with it.
So we send a request or in this case the website sends a request.
Whenever I type something, we can clear all of the requests we see here.
Just like that, we search for something else.
Like what's another one?
The CSS HTML property.
How is it so hard?
How about text decoration?
Okay.
So there we go.
Some requests for sent.
We've got the first one.
The second one, it looks like it sent two requests.
I had text dash dx and then it sent another follow up for text dash deck.
I must have been very slow and in my typing there and we get information back.
This information is then parsed via JavaScript.
JavaScript takes that information and turns it into elements on the page.
It manipulates the DOM.
So it's all happening behind the scenes.
Some event usually triggers it typing or hitting a button.
A request is sent.
Life goes on in the browser while this request is is gone, or while we're waiting for a response.
JavaScript doesn't just sit there doing nothing.
We talked about that in the last section, how this all works with web APIs.
So the browser is sending that request.
Information comes back, then JavaScript takes the reins and decides what to do.
Display some content in this case, add some classes, make some tables, some whatever.
These are h threes or something.
Add them all in the right order and we end up with this page.
Okay.
So next we're going to talk about JSON in more detail and then we'll start making our own requests.