All right.
So that was a brief intro to the concept of Ajax, asynchronous JavaScript and XML in this video.
The last one, before we actually make requests, we're going to talk about XML and this other thing
I mentioned, JSON, JavaScript, object notation.
So these are two ways of basically formatting data so that you can send it from a server to another
server or a server to a browser.
It's a format for information.
They both solve essentially the same problem.
We have some data that we want to send.
We need to figure out a common standard way of sending that information.
So if we had some data about a user, for example, where we have name would be something like Todd
and then we have email is something else.
Todd at Gmail and age could be a number like 89.
This is information and I'm already formatting it in some way.
This isn't actually JSON, this is an XML, but there's tons of ways we could do this right.
We could just use arrows to represent keys and values.
We could what else could we do?
We could do colons, or we could go with XML, which is one format.
I'll show you what it looks like.
It stands for Extensible Markup Language.
You can think of XML as a very, very broad, almost the parent of HTML.
It looks like HTML, except the element names are very different.
They're not actual elements.
XML is a way of just grouping content and adding meaning to your data.
So if we were to represent this as XML, we actually use tags like name.
And then inside of that we would put Todd and then we could have another tag for email.
And inside of that we put Todd at gmail.com and we could even nest things.
So inside of name we could have first and that would be Todd, then we could have second.
So it's very similar to HTML in the way that we structure things, the characters we use, but it means
something entirely different.
XML can represent any sort of information like first name, last name, what am I going with second
JS I meant last name, email, whatever.
HTML represents the structure of a web page.
It uses similar formatting, but otherwise it's it has a totally different purpose.
They both are encoding information so that it can be transferred from one machine to another across
the internet, little tiny pieces of light or bits turning on and off.
But XML is just a broad way of structuring data.
So XML used to be a lot more popular.
You'll still see it sometimes.
It's actually kind of frustrating when you encounter an API.
You want to use that response with XML.
It's just not very common, at least in my experience.
But in JavaScript we have a way of taking data like this and turning it into a JavaScript object.
Like if this was a JavaScript object, it would be name which has another object.
First Todd would be a string, last would be Smith as a string, and then another property would be
email Todd at gmail.com.
This would be an actual JavaScript object we could use that we structure based off of this XML and JavaScript
has a way of doing that.
We can parse text that is XML and turn it into actual JavaScript so we can use it.
But there is another format we've already mentioned, which is called JSON.
And JSON is extremely common these days.
It stands for JavaScript object notation.
So it is not JavaScript, it looks like JavaScript.
It shares a lot of things in common with JavaScript, but it is not the exact same JavaScript.
Object notation is another format for sending data.
It's another notation, but there are some key differences.
First of all, every key in JSON must be a string.
With quotes we use colons instead of an object.
We also can use arrays.
We can have values like numbers, boolean strings, but we cannot store more complicated things like
functions as an example.
So the bad news is that it's not actually JavaScript.
The good news is that it's very close, which makes it a great fit.
If we are using JavaScript because we can translate between JSON and JavaScript very, very easily,
it's a single function call instead of JavaScript.
So here's one of the APIs we'll play around with later.
This API is called Swap or Star Wars API and we can play around with this on their web page.
Let's look at starships slash nine.
This is just the documentation.
It's a little preview of what you get back.
And if I actually open up the DevTools and I go to network again, let's go to Planet Slash three.
You'll see that a request is sent.
Here is our response.
If I paste this over here, it looks like a JavaScript object, but it's not actually JavaScript at
this point.
But remember, it's being sent as part of a response.
It's not actually JavaScript.
What we would do is then take it once we get it back and translate it into a real JavaScript object,
which is really, really easy to do.
So this is another format of representing information to take this XML and turn it into JSON.
It would look almost identical to what we have here, except we would have quotes around every key.
And actually that's pretty much it.
If we had more complex data, if we had a function from JavaScript, we're trying to turn into JSON
that becomes problematic, but there are ways around it.
So to sum all of this up, JSON is a format for sending data.
So it is XML.
XML used to be very common, hence the term Ajax with an ex.
Nowadays most people use JSON and even though it's called JavaScript object notation, it's name that
because it's very similar to JavaScript, that doesn't mean you can only use it with JavaScript.
So these APIs we see will respond with JSON like the Star Wars API.
I just briefly showed you it sends you JSON when you send a request to it, but you can write a Python
application that communicates with that API, receives JSON and turns it into valid Python.
You could do any you could do a Ruby application and do the same thing.
So the name JavaScript object notation means that it is similar to JavaScript, but it's not something
you can only use with JavaScript.
You can interact with it with any other programming language.
You just have to parse it.
You have to turn it into valid JavaScript.
And there's actually a formatter here.
This, there's a bunch of them.
Here's what I'm looking at, which will tell you if your code is valid json.
So if I try and write some JSON that is not actually valid like person
is the string of Thomas.
And then let's just start with that.
Let's process that invalid.
It tells me immediately.
Strings should be wrapped in double quotes.
Okay, so I use single quotes here that should be double.
And this has no quotes which is valid in JavaScript.
Not valid in JSON.
If I try something like hello or greet.
Which should be a function.
It doesn't even do anything.
It's just a function.
JavaScript wise.
This is totally fine, but if I process it, it tells me string should be wrapped in double quotes expecting
comma, colon or curly brace to close the object, not an opening curly brace.
And it encountered an opening curly brace.
So it doesn't tell me you can't do functions because this parser doesn't really care.
It's telling me you're not following the exact rules of JSON which say after a colon you have to encounter
a comma, another colon, or a closing object brace.
Like this object brace here, which is closed down there.
So all of this is to say, yes, it's similar to JavaScript.
It is not JavaScript.
Okay.
Next, we're going to get practice sending requests a couple of different ways.
We'll get JSON back and we will turn it into JavaScript and do something with the information.
That's coming up next.