Okay.
So now we've talked about Ajax, we've talked about JSON, we've gotten all that stuff out of the way.
We can move on to making our first requests using the Ogg method of sending an HTTP request through
JavaScript.
It's called XML HTTP request.
So these are objects in the browser we can create that have different methods and we can use them to
fetch data from an API to send data somewhere.
Basically they generate an HTTP request and it's confusing.
It does say XML in the name that's just a relic from when XML was the standard.
We can use XML HTTP request, also known as Zeus to fetch any sort of data from an API.
It doesn't have to be just XML, so this is the original way of doing it.
It's clunky, it doesn't support promises, so we end up with a lot of callbacks.
If we have nested requests, things where we want to make one request, get information back, and then
make a second request, which we mimicked back when we talked about promises a couple of videos ago,
we made that fake HTTP request function that we used, so we send one request, we have some callbacks.
Then within those callbacks we could send another one and we end up nesting things.
So no promises are supported.
Also, this is always driven me crazy.
Why is it capitalized this way?
XML is an abbreviation.
It's all caps.
HTTP is two, but it's not capitalized except for the H.
It always trips me up whenever I have to type these myself.
And the most important thing that I don't like about XYZ and nobody really likes is the syntax.
It's hard to remember.
I have to reference it all the time.
I guarantee you in the making of this video, the very one I'm recording right now, I'm going to have
to pause at some point and reference some other code because I can never remember it.
Fortunately, we have an alternative these days, which we'll see very shortly called Fetch, which
arose out of the fact that people hate making czars.
It's just annoying.
But let's see how we do it now that I've made it sound horrendous.
Just remember this used to be the only way.
So it's not like nobody use this ever.
This was the only way of making a request.
What we do is we make a new object.
That object is created by calling new XML http request with parentheses.
Then we provide two callbacks one to run if the request loads, if it's successful, one to run if there's
an error.
So we have once again, once again that branching path, success and failure.
Then what we do is we call the request object, which I called my request open.
We tell it what type of request will make a get request and what URL to send the request to.
We'll come back to the headers in just a moment.
Then we finally send the request.
That request is then sent after this line is encountered.
If it's successful, there's no problem.
This code will run.
If it's not successful.
If there's an error.
This code runs.
You can read more about it on MSDN.
I really like their documentation on it and what I'll do to help myself out probably more than this
actually helps you.
I'm going to copy this over into my file where I'll paste it in as a reference.
Okay, so let's make a request somewhere.
We're going to use this simple Star Wars API to start.
It's free.
You don't have to sign up for anything or register.
There's no authentication.
Let's look at what do we get if we go to slash planet?
Send a request.
This is just a little viewer and it doesn't like that.
Is there a list of planets?
How do we see all planets?
Okay, well, let's go to documentation.
What are the endpoints?
Yeah, we can just go to slash planets.
It should work.
Okay, here we go.
So we'll try making a request to get all of the planets, which is swap eco slash API slash planets.
So I'm going to copy this URL over and we'll try sending a request to it.
So the first thing we'll do is make our request object.
We'll call this first request equals new XML, http request like that.
Then we have a couple of different ways of attaching the callbacks.
We can do what I showed in the slides where we use on load and on error or we can use add event listener.
So either one works in general.
You know, I've already mentioned this when we're working with a DOM and adding click events and other
sort of event listeners, I like to use Add event listener, so I guess we'll go with that, even though
I didn't put it in the slides.
Like I said, I pretty much never use this.
So we'll do an event listener for Load.
This is the code that will run.
Let's just do an arrow function.
If things go well, I will just cancel that log.
It works, and then we'll duplicate this entire thing here.
But listen for the error events.
So in the event that it doesn't work, something went wrong will cancel that log error.
Okay.
So we're just attaching these to event listeners.
We haven't even sent the request.
We haven't told it what you are able to go to.
So that's the next part.
First request dot open and you would think open would actually send to the send the request, but it
doesn't we have to explicitly send it afterwards.
So I'll put my URL in here.
This is the URL I want to send a request to.
Then we'll call first request dot send.
Remember, this takes time, which is why we have to add our callbacks.
If I put something afterwards, just like with a set timeout, all the stuff we saw in the last section
JavaScript moves on.
This request is handled by the browser.
One of the web APIs just like set timeout.
So JavaScript doesn't just pause like it does.
If I put an alert, it pauses and just waits and waits and waits.
That doesn't happen here because JavaScript is not sending the actual request, it's done through the
browser.
So we'll console.log request sent down here and this is what we should see appear first.
And then our request hopefully comes back successful.
We'll see this.
If it does not come back successful, we'll see this.
Who knows what will happen.
So here's my page where I have it loaded request sent.
It worked.
I guess we just have to trust that it worked right now.
But if we put some URL in here that we know does not exist, well, I hope that doesn't exist.
Try it again.
There we go.
Request was sent and we got an error.
So our two branching paths did it load?
Was everything okay or did it suck?
Did it not work?
Was there an error which we just deliberately cause to make sure it worked?
So that is the first part.
Making a request object in XHR xml http request we make it, then we attach our callbacks then.
Well, actually you can attach the callbacks after you open, but before you send, what's most important
is that you send after you've configured that object.
So the object represents an HTTP request.
It's just a JavaScript object.
It has different methods.
It has properties where assigning a load in an error callback, we tell it what type of request we want
to get request telling it where to send the request to telling it to send it.
Now what about the data that's coming back from the API?
The whole point of this is to send a request and get something back.
Right now we're not accessing it.
We don't even know if we get the correct information back.
We just get a console.log.
The way that we access that data is by referencing this DOT response text.
Well, what does this refer to?
It refers to the request itself.
So why don't we just look at that request?
I think we called it first request, right?
So after this finished, which it already finished, we can see that here.
If we look at first request, it contains a response and it contains this response text.
If we copy this response text, see if I copied it correctly.
Okay.
This right here is a whole bunch of JSON.
Everything we see is JSON.
It's not regular old JavaScript, but it's a string of a bunch of JavaScript looking stuff.
You can see it enter the quote.
It begins with a double quote.
So if I save right now in my auto format or tries to run, it's not going to be happy with me.
It's not considered JavaScript.
But we have a way of referencing it.
So I'll get rid of that massive monstrosity down there and let's try referencing the response text on
first request.
So in my slides, what I did was this dot response text.
But that won't work here.
Why not?
Any guesses here?
It has to do with the fact that I'm using an arrow function.
So an arrow function, remember, does not have the same rules of the keyword.
This.
So this will not refer to first request if I use an arrow function.
So I have two options.
I can just reference first request dot text or what is it?
Response text.
We could cancel that log that.
Refresh the page.
Hey, all of our information.
If I instead tried to do this, we will get undefined.
There is no response text because this is not set to the first request.
If I instead rewrite this as a standard function expression.
Now I can use the keyword this.
So in this case, it probably makes more sense to use a standard function expression because we want
the value of this to refer to the first request object.
So this gives me this massive thing of text.
It is not JavaScript, it's JSON.
So the next step is to turn it into actual JavaScript.
So here we go.
We have a special method called JSON parse.
And we pass into that a string of JSON like that.
And we can save that to a variable to call this data and then we can cancel that log data.
Let's see what we get now.
Hey, check it out.
This is now being presented to me as a JavaScript object.
It includes things like Count how many results we got back with the next pages.
So it looks like it didn't give us all the planets at once because there's a lot of them.
Instead, it gave me the first the first ten, and then instead of results, we have all of the different
planets that we got back, ten of them, and they contain tons of information.
And this is an actual JavaScript object.
So I could do something like loop over the results and print out each planet name.
So I would need to access data dot results loop over that.
So why don't we start there?
Data.
So let's do for let Planet of Data Results.
We now have this awesome JavaScript object.
It wasn't JavaScript before we converted it and we want for each one of these to print out the name.
So we'll do a console.log planet dot name.
Refresh.
Awesome.
We are now sending a request, getting information back as JSON, converting it to JavaScript, iterating
over it or doing something with it, somehow manipulating it and then printing data out.
So with what we've seen so far, it wouldn't be a stretch to instead display the information on the
page or do something visual for a user.
It would be the same sort of stuff we've seen before creating an element, appending an element, selecting
elements, styling them with classes, all of that.
Hopefully by now we're pretty comfortable with.
But this, this is kind of a lot of code and it has some drawbacks other than the clunky syntax which
will go into in the next video.