All right, so we saw the loveliness of XYZ, XML HTTP requests.
It didn't seem that bad.
I mean, it's a little extra syntax, but if this was the only way we had to make requests, we can
obviously make it work.
Where it gets kind of annoying is once we start making these requests that are dependent on one another.
So for example, here we're getting all the planets back, or at least the first ten planets.
And if we look just on the API, this is a little dashboard.
If we look at the data, we get back.
It includes residents and films which are actually just references to other API endpoints.
So if I wanted to take the first planet and look at the first resident of that planet, I would send
another request to this URL.
So let's do that through our code.
We need to wait for the first request to come back.
Then we'll look inside results.
We'll get the first results.
The first planet looking residents will get the first resident and send a request to that URL.
Let's see if it works.
So up here, we would have to write our code inside the callback to make a second request.
So we're getting our data.
Why don't we just start by singling out the URL we want to request?
So that's data.
Dot what is it?
Results dot.
We want the first result so of zero.
We can start by printing that.
Refresh the page on my web page.
So that's the first result.
Then we want residents.
Or we could do films that might be more interesting.
Why don't we do films?
So we'll do data.
Results of zero dot films.
That's an array.
We want the first URL that we get from that films array, which is right here.
Swap eco slash API, slash films, slash six.
This is a URL that we can send a request to to get more information.
And it looks like what is this film?
Slash six is Revenge of the Sith.
Honestly, I know almost nothing about Star Wars, sadly.
I love sci fi and fantasy, but somehow I've never seen them.
So let's now send a request to this URL.
So we have the URL, we'll save it to a variable.
We'll call this concert film URL, then we have to do all of this again so we make a new object concert
film request equals new xml http request not capitalized, even though I always attempt to do it the
first time.
Then film request dot add event listener on load.
Put our callback in here.
Let's just cancel that log.
Hmm.
Let's do this just to start.
Then we'll add our other event listener if it fails.
So for the error, that's what the ADD event listener for error.
At our function in here we do have an event object, by the way, that we can use.
Why don't we cancel that log error and then also show the event object, that error event object, and
then we need to actually send the request.
But first we have to open it like we did down here.
So film request, dot open.
We want to get request and the URL this time is this URL right here film URL that we extracted from
the response of the very first request.
So film url then finally film request dot send.
So if it works, we should see this printed out first.
We'll say first request.
Worked.
And then let's add a second console.log here.
Second request worked.
Let's give it a look first.
Hey, second one worked.
Let's take a look at what we get back instead of response or response text.
We've got title.
Let's just print the movie title.
So we need to parse again.
So this references the entire film request object.
We want this dot response text, which is exactly what we did in the first request.
We want to parse that whole thing, so we use that magic method that comes for free with JavaScript,
JSON, parse that turns it into JavaScript.
We'll save this in a variable called film data and we can just cancel that log film data now.
Try it again.
Now we have an actual JavaScript object and it contains information.
So we sent one request to get all the planets and we're just arbitrarily selecting the first planet
and the first film that it appears in.
It also appears, I think this planet, whatever the first planet was, Alderaan or something, I don't
know, I might have made that up.
Whatever the first planet is, it appears in two films we took the first one and we requested information
about that using the URL from that films array from the first result.
So we couldn't make the second request until the first one was successfully completed.
So we have to nest it inside here.
These nasty nested callbacks.
This is just not a good look.
And it's still only, what, two levels deep?
It's not bad.
We're not even doing much with our errors at all.
We're not handling them.
We're not trying to make a subsequent request.
Often you will try and make another request.
If the first one errors, you might try something different, and then that subsequent request needs
to have its own two callbacks.
Things get very messy very quickly, which is really the main reason that I don't like to use XYZ,
why most people don't like them.
It's just difficult.
It gets messy and nested, which is why fetch was created, which is what we'll see just after this
video.
Fetch supports promises which makes it way, way easier to make subsequent requests or to handle failures.
We need one catch.
So if you didn't watch the promises section, definitely go back and check it out.
It will help you really understand what is so amazing about fetch and promises in general.
So that's coming up next.