So that was a quick taste of XML.
HTTP request.
It's a mouthful both to say and also to type, especially once we get working with a bunch of callbacks
and nesting things, it becomes very messy.
So this is where Fetch comes in.
Fetch is the newer way of making requests via JavaScript.
It is something that essentially was created because Xlsx XML HTTP requests were just obnoxious or difficult
to remember.
Clunky things got messy with callbacks.
They don't support promises, so fetch is the solution.
The only problem with fetch is that it's not supported in Internet Explorer.
If you take a look on MD, NW can see under I'm on the page called fetch API down at the bottom browser
compatibility.
What we care about is this part right here.
These are all more advanced features, but this part here fetch in general no support in i.e. the main
thing.
Aside from the cleaner syntax and easier to remember terminology, the main advantage is that it supports
promises which we spend a ton of time on.
I hope by now if you if you made it through the promises section, you can understand why promises are
useful, especially when we're making a bunch of requests.
So let's see an example.
This is what it looks like we call a method called fetch.
We pass in some URL, then that returns a promise.
And then of course the promise is either resolved or rejected if it is resolved.
The value it's resolved with is a response object.
It contains information about the response.
Otherwise we can catch a rejected promise if for some reason the fetch didn't work for internet was
just not connected for some reason.
That would be one example.
This code would run.
So why don't we go back to our app JS?
This is what we had from the last few videos.
Let's rewrite this using fetch.
This is done with creating a new XML HTTP request.
I'm going to copy the URL from the very first request we send right here so we can recreate this and
then I'll comment it out.
So we're going to call, fetch and pass in that URL.
So if I just ran this code in my browser, I'll save it to a variable so we can check on the status
of the promise.
We'll call this.
I don't want to go with promise.
How about prom?
If we look at prom?
No, not promo.
Well, it's now been resolved.
If I just paste it in and run it immediately, it's pending.
But eventually it's either resolved or rejected.
And really, all I want to show you here is that we're getting a promise back from that fetch method.
So in order to run code when it is resolved, we need to use.
Then in order to run code, if it's rejected, we need to use catch.
So we can chain on our dot then.
Dot then.
It will be resolved with a response object.
We can call it response.
And if you want to learn more about the details of the API, if you go to Mdcn, there's a pretty there's
a lot of articles actually about it.
We've got this overview using fetch, fetch, basic concepts, very useful stuff.
But here's the key thing that you should know.
The fetch method takes one mandatory argument the path, the URL that we're trying to fetch, and it
returns a promise that resolves to the response to the request.
So the value that we would have that is passed in to our callback when this fetch promise hopefully
resolves is a response object.
And if we console.log that response object.
You'll see it's a little different than what we've seen from Zeus.
I'll try running this.
Refresh my page.
This is what we get back.
A response object.
It contains a status code 200, which means.
Okay, that's good.
It also has things like the URL that we requested and then the data that we want is located in the body.
But it's not as simple as reading a property from this body.
If you notice what it says here, it's a readable stream without going into too much detail.
If we take a look at the response page, the response reference on MTN, this is a response we get back.
It's resolved with a response object.
You can name that parameter, whatever, but it will be a response object.
If we read a little bit more about it.
Scroll down somewhere on here.
Whereas Body hears body, it is a readable stream.
Now what is a readable stream?
It is a stream of byte data and this is one of the key differences from using XLS.
Aside from the actual syntactical differences, when you make a request, you get a response object
back.
The content of that response is included as a readable stream, and a stream is a way of accessing data
that could be super large, it could be a massive amount of data, and you can access it in, process
it as you go.
Now, for us, that doesn't really matter.
We're not accessing extremely large things.
We're doing simple requests and just to get some data from an API.
So it doesn't really matter except that we have to be aware of how we read that stream.
Fortunately, if we go back to the response object, we scroll down to methods.
There is a nice method called JSON.
It takes a response stream and reads it to completion.
So right now our response is not actually been read to completion.
It's a response object, but the stream has not been read.
Fortunately, we have a very, very easy way of doing it, as I just showed you.
Response JSON.
The only downside to this is that it takes time.
It's asynchronous.
That stream could be very, very large and reading it fully could take a while, relatively compared
to something like JSON parse.
So because of that, this JSON method returns a promise.
If we console.log response json.
This is what we get.
It's another promise.
So we have a promise returned from this and then another promise from this.
So if we actually want the data, we need to do another dot then and it will be resolved with the data
that is read and parsed.
So now we could console.log data.
So it's an extra step if we compare that to what we did up here.
All we had to do was JSON, parse the response DOT response text here.
We call a JSON method and then when it finishes, it's resolved.
We can have access to the data.
And there we go.
Now we have our API data with the results and we can do whatever we want with them.
So why don't we do something simple like print out each planet?
So we would have data inside of this, then callback.
After we've read the JSON data dot and then response.
Results I think is what it was.
And we'll loop over that for let planet of Data results.
We can double check this data is this whole thing results.
We'll do what we did earlier.
Console.log.
Planet Dot name.
Run it again.
There we go.
We're getting every planet's name, at least the first ten planets that we're getting from this one
API call.
Sending a request to this URL.
So this is the first part of fetch when things go right.
We don't have any errors.
Or if we do, we don't know about them.
So let's put a catch in here.
If fetch returns a promise, it's resolved or rejected.
Right now we're not catching it.
So why don't we catch and do something where we console.log?
Something went wrong with fetch and then we can console that log error as well.
Let's see what happens.
Right now, nothing should happen.
We should still see the same result.
But why don't I try fetching some URL that doesn't exist if I visit this URL myself just in the browser.
This page is not the page you're looking for.
This is a 404 error page.
And when we got a 404 with czars with this approach, our failure callback ran this on error.
Callback was executed.
However, fetch is different if we try and send a request to this URL which I am telling you now will
give us a 404.
Let's take a look.
Huh?
We did get a 404, but our catch never ran on.
Caught in promise.
Unexpected token.
So what's happening here is that we're actually getting the HTML four, a four page back, and we're
trying to parse that as JSON, but it's not JSON.
So why don't we start by just constantly logging the response in here?
Because it seems like if the status code is 404, then the dot then should not run.
That seems like an error where our cat should run, but that's not how fetch is set up.
If we look at the response status is 404.
But it still worked.
It's still ran.
Our catch, the promise was resolved.
So what's going on?
Well, this is just how fetch is set up.
If you take a look at this paragraph here on the using fetch overview on MDM, the promised returned
from fetch will not reject on error status or HTTP error status even if the response is a 404 which
is not found or 500.
Instead it resolves normally and it will only reject on network failure or if anything prevented the
request from completing.
So this sketch is not going to run.
The promise will not be rejected just because the server responded with not a 200, not an OC status
code, because we still got a response.
So that's all that this cares about.
This code runs whenever you get a response, whether it's the one you want it or not.
Unlike our HR, where the failure callback would run, the error callback did run on a 400 error or
404.
Excuse me.
So fetch will only return a rejected promise in the event that your internet's not working.
The request can't be made at all.
And we just don't get a response.
And I can show you that if I turn my Internet off.
So that's what I'm going to do.
Okay, it's off.
Let's refresh.
Now, it's actually running that catch callback.
Something went wrong with fetch type error, failed to fetch so it didn't get a response period.
So the then callback was ignored, the promise was rejected.
And this runs so inside of this callback here, if we want to ensure that we actually got a status code
200 in OC before we try and read JSON, before we do anything with it, what we can do is check.
If response dot OC that is a property on the response.
Well, we don't see it here, but we did see it earlier.
If that's the case, then we can run this code.
Or another way of doing it would be if response is not OC, then we could console that log something
error, not status 200.
And then we can wrap this in an else because we only want to attempt parsing if the request came back.
Status 200.
If instead we got a 404, we'll just print this out and we could also console that log response status.
So now if we try it again, here we go.
Error, not status 200.
We got 404 and this code did not run.
So this is one option.
But we also have a way of using this catch.
If I throw an error instead of a dot, then it will trigger the callback in my catch so I could rewrite
it like this.
Throw new error.
If you've never seen how to throw an error, it looks like this will say status code error and then
interpolate using dollar sign instead of a string template.
Literal.
I'll put response status here, so let's test it out.
This URL should give us a for or for.
If we try and visit it in our browser, it gives us a four.
For earlier we saw that we got a404 status code, which means not found.
Then the promise will still be resolved.
This code runs up until this point.
This will be true because it is not OC.
So then we throw a new error which should trigger this callback and the error will be this error we're
passing through.
When we throw an error, we have access to it here in our catch.
So let's see.
There we go.
Something went wrong with fetch status code error 404.
So this is the basics of fetch.
I wish that you didn't have to worry about the status code, but that's where Axios comes in, which
is another improvement upon fetch.
In my opinion.
This is still better than what we saw here, although we were making two requests here.
But as you can imagine with with promises which we automatically get from fetch, it's pretty easy to
chain and make multiple requests in a row, which is what we'll talk about in the very next video.