Next up, we'll see how we can chain requests one after another and avoid the messy callback situation
that we had here using XML.
HTTP request, really the main selling point of fetch that we don't have to use callbacks and ness things
and it just gets messy.
Instead, we can use the promises and chain a bunch of events as long as we return promises from then.
So if we go with the exact same idea what we had here, if we look at each planet, why don't we console.log
the entire planet instead of just the name or in addition to the name, and also make sure we're actually
requesting a valid URL now.
Here we go.
Each planet, as we saw, has films and also residents.
We could request residents instead.
Let's do films and we'll just look at the first film that the planet occurs in.
So we have all to run two films.
We'll take the first one just to match what we did earlier and send a request to this URL.
So with promises, we always have a lot of flexibility.
Do we want to do everything on one level, like one line of events?
Right now we have a dot then that is currently nested inside of this callback, but we could avoid that
if we wanted to.
If we just return the promise, we can actually take this then and move it outside.
Put it here as long as we return.
Response JSON which is a promise.
And doesn't like my semicolon.
There we go.
So now we return this promise and we add our dot then which will be run when this promise is resolved.
And if it's rejected, we have our catch.
So we just moved our code out and made it a little bit flatter, I guess less nested and it should still
work.
Let's check.
It does.
Okay.
So now what we can do is make our request.
We can still print the planet names out if we want, but I think I'll stop that for now.
We're going to take the data results dot films zero, which should give us a URL that we can now request.
Let's console that log and cannot read property zero of undefined.
Let's see dot then data.
Let's console.log data.
I think I did it wrong.
Results are.
That's why I'm not accessing the correct result.
We have to go to the first planet.
If we want the first planet, we could also pick a different planet.
But we'll go with the first one to match what we did here.
So this should work now.
Let's make sure I'm getting the correct URL.
Print it out.
There it is.
So we'll send another request here using fetch.
So fetch of this URL.
I'll save this to a variable.
What should we call it?
Let's go with concert film URL.
And fetch film URL.
Now this is a promise.
So I could put my dot then right here and do all that stuff nested or because it's a promise I can return
it.
So return that fetch and then put another dot.
Then here.
And I'll call this data also.
We could call it movie data and then we can go through this exact same process.
I could actually just copy this entire thing and response is a better name rather than data, because
that's what we actually get.
If fetch is resolved, it resolves with the response object.
We have to check if it's OC, then we parse it.
We call the JSON method, which itself returns a promise so we can add another then.
Data.
Why don't we console.log data?
Okay.
Moment of truth here.
Hey, take a look.
We're getting all of that movie data.
So we requested all the planets, which I guess I can add some concept logs in here.
We'll do a console.log fetched all planets.
Well, it's actually first ten.
Then down here we can console.log fetched first film based off of first planet and then we'll just do
data title.
Refresh.
Fetched planets first ten then fetched first film based off a first planet Revenge of the Sith.
So here we have multiple requests that are happening one after another, but there's not really any
nesting.
It's all very flat.
Yes, we have some repeated logic where we have this, where we are checking for the response being,
okay, we're checking for or we're parsing the JSON.
We duplicate that at least twice.
And if we made further requests, we would want to do the same thing.
But in the next video, I'll show you a way we can refactor it and clean it up even more.
So here, really, if we're making a comparison, the main points I would make is one I can never remember
the syntax.
I can never remember the different pieces.
We need the names, but that's just me.
So that's not a great reason.
The main reason that I think fetch is much better and almost everyone I think would agree with me is
that we have promises that are returned from fetch.
We can use those promises.
We can keep things flat, linear, non nested, even though this code here where we make a request to
get the film based off of this first request, this only runs if this happened.
So if everything was okay here, we got the JSON that finishes, then we make a second request and we
could have ten different requests that are dependent on one another, but we don't have to nest them
ten callbacks deep like we would up here.
So next we'll see a way of refactoring this and shortening it up.
Then we'll move on to my personal favorite, Axios, the crowning jewel of making requests, in my opinion.