Next up, let's do some refactoring.
So first, I'd like to change what we're actually requesting.
Right now, we're getting the first ten planets and then taking the first one of those ten and getting
the first film URL and requesting that if we look at the planets response that we get back, I'm the
docs, the API documentation for Star Wars API.
It gives us a visual little nice representation that's interactive.
There is a property, there's a next that we can access.
It's another URL to get more planets.
So page set to two.
So why don't we get the first ten planets and then when that finishes, get the next ten.
If there are ten from page two, we won't keep going.
I don't know how many pages there are, but we'll just do the first two to start.
So we'll keep this first request to get the first ten planets.
We'll run this code, but then here we'll do fetched planets.
Sure, let's print out each planet again.
So for let planet of data dot results, we'll console.log planet name and then instead of a film URL,
what we'll do is get the next URL which is just at the top of the JSON.
We get back, it's called next.
We don't have to look inside of results.
It's simply data next.
So we'll save that to a variable called next URL.
And then request that instead of film you URL next you are.
Then we have our same logic to check if the status code was not okay, we'll throw an error.
Otherwise we call the JSON method, which takes time.
It's asynchronous, it returns a promise.
We return that promise then.
Then we'll change what we're doing down here.
Fetched next ten planets.
And then we'll just copy this logic right here to print out the name of each planet.
Let's cross our fingers.
Hope it works.
Cool.
So you can see the first ten came back right there and then a split second later.
The next ten.
So fetched.
All ten.
There we go.
And then fetched next ten.
So, yeah, we don't technically need to have this happen one after another.
If we know the pattern for how we fetch the next batch of results, there is a pattern we just pass
in this query string page equals to if we changed it to three or four, we get the next page.
So they're not really dependent.
But let's say that we don't know what this URL is and we want to send the first request and use this
URL.
So we're doing one after another.
Also, it's just good practice with promises.
But now what I'd like to show you is how we can clean this up.
We have some duplicated logic.
First we are doing the same thing twice, checking response that okay, calling JSON, we do it here,
loop right here and right here.
Then we're also doing this right here.
It's pretty much the same where we are fetching planets.
So we could just write a separate function, a standalone function called maybe check status and parse.
It's a bit long of a name, but that will work and we can move this logic into the function, assuming
that we also add response as a parameter.
If we don't want to change this, we could go with Rez and update this to be rows and rows and rows.
What we'll do is pass this in to our dot, then dot, then check status and pass.
So it doesn't matter if we have a named function that we've well, this isn't technically a named function,
but it's in a variable slight difference.
But it doesn't matter if we pass in a predefined function or an anonymous function.
The promise when it's resolved will be resolved with a value this function is called, and that value
will be passed in.
So why not move it out so we can clean up our code, not have to have these long ends with anonymous
functions.
We can replace this here as well dot then check status and pass as long as we return a promise which
we are.
We were already doing that, so I just moved it out.
Let's see if it still works.
Refresh.
We got the first ten.
We got the second ten.
Cool.
So this is a pretty good improvement.
But wouldn't it be nice if we could do something like this then?
Like if we had this here?
Fetch planets, then check status and pass.
Then print planets dot, then get ten more planets.
And then we can just duplicate this as many times as needed.
So what if we had a method or a function to print planets?
That's easy enough, right?
What about getting ten more planets?
Well, it's relatively straightforward, but there is one caveat.
In order for those thens to work, they all need to return promises.
And something like printing a planet or ten planets probably won't return promises.
But let me just show you what we could do.
So I'm going to start by defining a function called print planets.
And we'll just have it expect some data, the same data that we are expecting here.
I'm going to move this logic out.
I'll replace the console log with loaded ten more planets or something like that.
And then for each planet of data results, we still console.log the planet name.
So I should be able to do a dot then print planet.
But then we'll run into an issue here.
But we should see the first ten planets print out.
Let's verify.
There we go.
Then we get here.
Cannot read property next of undefined.
That error is coming from this next URL.
That's where we're trying to get the next URL equals data.
Next.
Well, there is no data that was passed in.
We never called this our self.
Remember how then works?
It's run when the callback is run.
This callback is run when a promise is resolved.
But there's no promise being returned from print planets.
The only way we can chain all of these together is if we return a promise.
So check status and pass that returns a promise.
This is a promise here.
Or this method returns a promise itself.
We return that promise.
Print planet does not return a promise.
However, we can fix that.
It's nice and easy.
We have a couple of ways of doing it.
First, the most obnoxious way would be new promise and go through the whole thing we've seen before.
So we have resolve and reject and we just want this promise to be resolved.
We've printed them.
We're not doing any checking of logic or error handling.
We just want to automatically resolve so we could do this.
Const I don't know.
P equals new promise, resolve, comma, reject.
And then we can just call resolve.
And return P So we have an automatically resolved promise that we're returning.
And what does it not like?
I'm missing a paren, forgot my arrow.
If I'm doing an arrow function now let's see what happens.
I'm returning a promise.
So we get our first ten.
And then the last thing I need to do is make sure I resolve with the data that this then callback is
expecting.
Right.
We need to pass that data along.
So I would just do resolve data.
That's what we have here.
It's being passed in to print planets.
We use some of that data, we print it out.
Now I'm creating a new promise.
I'm resolving it with that same data and I'm returning that promise.
This is kind of clunky, but it does work.
But there's an easier way.
There's a method called promise, dot resolve, and this will create a brand new promise for you that
is resolved.
So we don't have to go through any of that stuff.
We can just return, promise, resolve with data.
So then this returns a promise, which means I can chain on a dot, then afterwards.
And I'm resolving it with some data, the same data we had passed in.
So I'm just passing it through again.
I'm not changing data.
It's being passed from check status and parse to this, then callback, and then we're using it, passing
it along as we resolve this promise, which only exists to keep the chain of events moving.
Then we have this dot then, which we could turn into its own function as well.
So why don't we refactor this?
We're doing the same thing.
We'll just do Dot, then print planet.
Does it work still?
Do we get both sets printed out?
Yep.
Looks good.
So now what we could do is make another function called fetch more planets.
Or how about fetch next planets?
And they will expect a URL to be passed in.
And if we're expecting a URL rather than the entire data, we could just do this data next.
And data next is the URL that we want.
If we go back, that's the URL.
So I'll just resolve with that value.
If all we want is that next URL instead of the next then callback.
That's what I'll do.
And this will simply return fetch of your URL.
So kind of simple.
I'm not doing anything crazy.
I'm just putting a name on this function instead of using an anonymous function here.
So I should be able to just change this to fetch next planet.
And let's see if it works.
We're returning a promise.
We get our first ten.
Hey, and our second ten looks good already.
Very short and neat and easy to read.
Adorable code.
And we could duplicate this as many times as we wanted.
All right, if I want to get three pages, I would print the planets and then fetch more planets, check
their status and print those.
So now I should get 30 results.
Awesome.
First ten, next ten, final ten.
And we could even use fetch next planets here instead of calling fetch if we wanted to.
It's not really going to make a difference for us, but we could start, we could do this, have URL,
default to this URL.
That should be the very first place you look for planets if you don't pass anything in.
And now I can just call fetch next planets with no argument.
This returns a promise.
It's returning fetch of this URL if I don't pass an argument in.
But then all of these other ones right here.
Fetch next planets.
Fetch, fetch, next planets.
They will be passed the specific URL for page two or three or four.
And we should be good to go.
Let's make sure.
Ten, 20, 30.
Okay, so nice little refactor.
Look at how adorable this is.
Super clean and easy.
And if I wanted to fetch 100 pages of planets, I don't think there are that many and the API would
probably get -- at me, but if I wanted to, my code would not be any harder to understand.
It would be longer, but it would still remain completely flat compared to doing it like this.
It would be a nightmare to try and keep track of.
So that is why fetch is so much better than xlsx xml http request.
Also, this is just a mouthful to repeat fetch.
Much easier to say out loud.