Next up, we have a third option for making requests via JavaScript.
This is not a built in option.
It's not native JavaScript like Fetch or XLS.
It is a external library called Axios.
It's one of many a whole bunch of different HTTP libraries that you could use.
Axios is just the most popular and I prefer it over some of the other alternatives, but it is by no
means the one and only option.
It's just the one that I like, and it's one that you'll be using throughout the rest of the course
and a lot of the projects where we need to make requests.
So you can find it by going to GitHub slash Axios.
If you Google for Axios, there is this news website, Axios, which is actually pretty decent, but
that's not what we're looking for.
We're looking for the Axios GitHub.
So you could just do Axios HTTP.
Here we go.
This is the official GitHub repository.
You can see it has a ton of stars.
It's used by almost 2 million people.
Very popular library.
So all that it does is it simplifies the process of making requests.
It uses fetch behind the scenes so it doesn't give us anything we can't already do.
It's not somehow magically adding features to the language of JavaScript.
It just simplifies things through a bunch of methods and objects that it creates that we can interact
with.
It is promise based, just like fetch.
So that means that we don't have to deal with a bunch of nasty callbacks.
You can get a nice overview of the features here, but one of the most important features that people
really like is that you can use it both in the client on the browser side of things, which is what
we're doing right now, but also on the server side using Node.js, the exact same library, which is
not always the case.
So we haven't talked about Node, but in some of the projects we will work with Node and you'll see
how you can include a tool like Axios on the server side using Node and use the exact same syntax.
So one library, one way of fetching data.
Let's say Axios dot get is the name of the method that will work in the browser and in Node.js.
But that's beyond the scope of where we are right now.
So the first thing we need to do if we want to use Axios, is we need to include it in our HTML file
as an external script so you can download it and have the files on your machine.
But the simplest way is to copy this CDN right here.
So a script where the source is set to an external source, it's not one of our files on our machine.
This is a URL and if we visit it right now.
This is what we would be loading.
This is the source of Axios.
It's been minified and compressed into this massive chunk of very ugly text.
But this gives us everything we need to use Axios.
So we'll include that script and we definitely want to make sure we include it before our own files
that are trying to use Axios.
Otherwise, we'll get an error if we reference Axios in our app JS and we have this line down below.
JavaScript won't know about Axios yet.
So that's the first bit.
Next, how do we actually make a request?
There are a couple of different options.
There's actually quite a few.
We can perform a get request like this Axios dot get and then we pass in a URL.
So it's kind of the same thing with fetch where we do fetch google.com or something.
Instead we do Axios dot get google.com.
Why don't we just make sure the library is showing up?
So I'll refresh my page here.
Axios intro.
We'll look at Axios.
It exists if we call Axios get and we pass in some URL.
Let's let's use the Star Wars API again.
This URL right there, the same one we've been using.
Swap eco slash API slash planets.
I get a promise back.
Why don't I save it to a variable?
We'll call this const rez and we look at Rez.
It's now been resolved.
So just like fetch, we get a promise back when we make a request using Axios.
Let's take a look at the value that it's been resolved with.
Inside we have a data property and it's already been parsed for us.
We don't have to parse it ourselves.
That's one of the main advantages of using a tool like Axios is that unlike Fetch, we don't have to
do the JSON parsing on our own.
If we go back to our fetch example from earlier, I'll just uncomment the whole thing.
Every time we make a request using fetch, I've moved these into separate functions.
If you didn't watch that video so I've moved fetch next planets into its own function.
It returns fetch which is going to return a promise.
Then we check the status code and we pass.
So we have to check the status code to make sure that the response is okay because fetch will resolve
the promise.
As long as we get any response.
It doesn't matter if it's a 404, an error not found or if it's 200 status code.
So if we want to weed out those bad status codes, we have to manually do it.
Then we have to parse on our own response JSON.
If we instead use Axios.
Those are not really a problem anymore.
If we do Axios, get this URL, we'll do a dot.
Then it does return a promise as we've seen.
Let's call this rez.
We console.log rez.
Refresh our page.
OC Resort Data.
It's already been parsed as we saw.
We don't have to handle an additional promise.
Right.
Because when we use fetch response, JSON returns a promise.
So we have to use a dot then.
So we end up with chaining multiple events and it's not that ugly or anything.
It's not the end of the world.
But we do have to parse on our own.
We get a string of JSON that needs to be turned into JavaScript.
Axios already takes care of that for us, so it's doing the same thing behind the scenes.
It's getting a string of JSON and it's parsing it, but we just don't write it.
It does it for us, which is pretty nice.
Now let's see what happens.
We add on a catch go with error as our parameter and console.log error.
I'll do this on multiple lines.
So right now, unless somehow my internet went down or the API went down, we still get our dot then
callback.
But if I try and request a resource that doesn't exist, this should give me a 404 error.
Let's see what happens here.
Check it out.
Request failed with the status code 404 error.
My catch is what ran.
We could make that clearer.
Console.log in catch callback.
The promise is being rejected.
So this is another key difference between Axios and Fetch.
When we did fetch, when we used fetch, we had to manually check the response to the status code because
fetch does not reject a promise.
If status code is 400 or something else, that is not okay something other than 200, which is what
we want.
Axios and its developers or developer.
Not sure how many there are.
Axios knows that typically if there's a 404 or some other status code that is not 200, you're going
to want the catch callback to run, which is what we're doing here anyway.
I'm throwing an error which then triggers this catch callback.
So it just simplifies things in two ways, as we've seen already.
One, you don't have to parse JSON.
Two, you don't have to weed out the bad status codes.
Responses with a non 200 status code will be rejected.
Or at least I don't think it's every single non 200 status code, but the bad ones like 404.
So that is it for now.
I'll show you a few more examples with Axios in the next video.
Otherwise it works exactly the same way it returns.
Promise we chain with dot.
Then if I wanted to make a second request, we'll see that in the next video.
We just return another Axios docket just like we did with Fetch.
So to summarize this, so far, Axios is an external library.
We have to include it.
If we don't include it there, we'll run into issues.
We'll get an error saying, I don't know what the heck you're talking about.
Axios is not defined.
Once we include Axios, we can reference Axios dot get, which is the method we've been using.
There are other methods.
If you want to send a post request, you can do an Axios post if you want to send some other request
to put or patch.
If you never heard of those, don't worry about it.
But you can send those requests using Axios.
It's nothing revolutionary.
It's nothing that we can't do without Axios.
It's just a simple, clean syntax that removes some of the minor pain points of using fetch.
All right, so next, we'll get some more practice.