Next up, let's see how we can use Axios to make multiple change requests, just like we did with Fetch
where we refactored our code.
So it's nice and clean, but we're still having to repeat a couple of things over and over.
We start by fetching the first ten planets, which is right here.
Where are you?
Right there.
Then we check the status code.
If it's not 200, we trigger the catch callback.
Otherwise, we continue on.
We parse the JSON that returns a promise.
Then we print the planets afterwards.
And we had to work with this promised resolve right here to print the planets so that we could chain
on a dot, then again, so we could fetch more planets and keep the whole chain of promises going.
Each one of these functions here returns a promise to rewrite this with Axios.
It saves us a little bit of code, so I still have Axios included.
Change the title here.
Axios change requests.
We'll start by running an Axios get call which returns a promise.
We need to put our URL in there, then our.
Then we don't have to parse.
So all we need to do after that is print out the planets.
So we'll go with rez.
Sure.
And actually, if all we want is the data, I'm just going to do rez data.
I can use D structuring right here to grab the data out and we'll consider that log data to make sure
it's showing up.
Refresh the page.
Awesome.
So now we can print each planet for let planet.
Same thing we've seen before.
Planet of of data, dot results console.log planet name or something like that.
Hopefully that works.
There we go.
We're getting the first ten planets.
Then we have that data next URL.
If we look in our data next right there, we make a request to that URL.
So it would just be Axios dot get.
And then in here, rather than passing in a string URL that we create, we'll just pass in data next,
which is a URL.
And if we want to chain on a dot then out here rather than right here, I mean, I can do this.
This is totally fine.
I can just copy this entire thing.
I could make a second request this way, and let's just make sure that works.
And I'll print the data out both times and I'll console.log each planet name.
Does it work?
All right.
So our first ten and our second ten.
But as we've seen, we can change events by returning a promise.
So I don't have to nest the dot then, like I have here.
I could move this out.
If I return Axios target data next, which itself returns a promise so I can put the dot then like this,
which is a little cleaner and simpler.
Refresh.
Same thing.
So that's kind of it if you want to make one request and then another request using Axios.
We don't have to worry about parsing.
We don't have to worry about checking the status code.
Otherwise it's pretty much the same as using fetch returns a promise we put our dot, then continue
the then chain as long as we want to make these sequential requests.
So this happens here, then this, then this.
So the only way we make this request is if the first one was successful and we don't have a catch right
now.
So we could add that in sketch.
Error.
And what should we do here?
Console.log.
Error?
Sure.
Something like that.
So if we want to refactor this in the same way that we created this nice chain of promises where we
just call a function each time and pass in a function name each time to dot, then instead of having
to use these inline anonymous functions, we can do that.
I think I would go with what would we call it?
The same thing.
So fetch next planets and then print planets and then fetch next print planets and so on.
So let's try that.
We can start with const fetch next planet equals function.
It will accept a URL and it will default to this URL.
The first set of planets that we want to fetch, just like we did earlier right here.
And then all we do is return.
Axios dot get URL.
So at this point I should be able to rewrite at least my very first Axios dot yet as just fetch next
planet's.
And I won't pass anything in.
We'll use the default initial URL.
Just make sure that part works.
We should get the first ones.
And it still continues to work because we're not ever calling fetch next planets again.
And then we can replace this with fetch next planets as well if we wanted to.
Although we will update this shortly, we'll pass in data next the same URL that we had before.
Refresh.
It still works.
We get first ten, the second ten.
Now let's make a print.
Next planet, function, print, planet equals.
And as a parameter.
The way that this would work ideally is that we could call fetch next planets, then print planets.
Now fetch next planets is just returning Axios dot get of that URL it returns the entire promise and
that promise is resolved with the entire response as we've seen, and we're extracting the data.
So why don't we do the same thing, the structure data here, and then we can move our console.log,
we can move all of our code right there and then print the name out of each planet in data results.
And then we return.
Fetch next planets again.
So now I should be able to rewrite this.
Then print planets, then fetch next planets, then print planets.
There is one thing we have to pay attention to in order for this to work the way we've written it,
which is that we need to manually resolve our promise, return a resolved promise, just like we did
here.
Back when we did a similar refactor with fetch, we returned promised resolve data next, which then
calls the dot, then that is the ensuing dot.
Then we'll do the same thing, promise, dot, resolve, and then we'll just pass in data.
Next, whatever this value is will be used and passed into the then callback.
So if this is print planets, we'll print out all the planets.
Then we return a resolved promise with the value of data.
Next, which is a URL then that is passed into fetch next planets because it's the next.
Then callback fetch.
Next planet is expecting a URL to be passed in and it is so we don't use the default.
Now we would use that next URL, make sure it works.
And there we go.
Our first ten and our second ten so we could continue to fetch and print as many as we wanted.
We'll do one more round.
So I'm printing.
I should fetch and then print one more time.
You could also move this each pair into its own function called fetch and print, and then that would
return a promise and you could chain multiple fetch and prints together.
But this is pretty clean.
And if we compare it to what we had before, the only difference is that we had to check for a status
code and parse.
But with Axios, we don't.
So it's just slightly cleaner, slightly quicker and easier to use.
We don't have to worry about the fact that we get a stream back when we're working with Fetch and we
have to parse the JSON and that itself takes time.
It's asynchronous, it returns a promise.
We just get the data back when it's ready and it's pre parsed for us.
So that's a brief introduction to Axios.
You will definitely get a lot more experience with it throughout the project.
Part of this course we use Axios in a couple of projects to make requests both on the client and server
side.