One more thing before we really get rolling here, I want to talk about a website called MDM Mozilla
Developer Network.
MDM is just about the closest thing to an official documentation for JavaScript that we have.
If you watch the video where I talked about schema and script and different versions and new features
and how there's not really a official JavaScript that we can just go download that it's really an implementation
of this script spec across different browsers.
That's the same reason we don't have one official documentation.
It's not like a language like Python where you can go to Python or Python dot org and see the docs for
Python two or Python three.
With JavaScript, things are a little murkier, but MSDN is a really good resource.
So this is what it looks like.
Developer Mozilla.
Org.
What I do, if I'm ever googling something and I'm trying to understand how a feature works in JavaScript
or I can't remember the name of a particular method, I'll Google and add in at the end of my Google
search so I get these search results.
So just as a quick example here, we go to references and guides.
There are some tutorials here, but if you go to technologies and you look at JavaScript, this gives
you a whole reference of pretty much everything in JavaScript.
If we talk about arrays, which we will shortly in the course, if you go to the array page here, there's
all sorts of information and tons of links about all the different things that arrays can do.
So you'll see me reference MDM quite a bit in this course and I just thought I should take a moment
to address it, introduce the idea of MD and remember, it's not an official documentation for JavaScript.
It's put out by Mozilla, the company that makes Firefox, and it's just a great resource for learning
JavaScript, but it's also an invaluable reference for existing developers and maybe teachers who are
teaching Udemy courses who need to refresh their memories on certain things.
So you'll see it a lot in the course.