Welcome back.
So far we've only seen one of the primitive types we've been working with, number.
We talked about numbers, how they work, different numeric operators who made variables with numbers,
but there are multiple other primitive types and we're going to address them.
So first of all, we're going to talk about Boolean very quickly.
It's a simple, short and easy primitive type to discuss and then we'll come back to Strings in the
next video.
So Booleans are simply true or false values.
There's only two options if you're using a boolean, true or false, they are very efficient as far
as how much space they take up because there's only two options and we use them all the time.
And the main reason for that will become clearer later on.
And once we talk about logic and how we write logic using JavaScript, so true or false, we can make
a variable with them.
That's it.
To make a boolean.
It looks like this.
If you want to do, you can go ahead and type.
True, that is a boolean and you can type false.
That's it.
No quotes around them if you're familiar with strings.
This is not a boolean.
It says the word true, but it is not the boolean true.
This is special.
As you can see here.
Just like with numbers, we can store boolean values in a variable.
So here are three examples.
Let is logged in equals true.
It starts out as true and potentially it would be false later on if someone logs out.
We have let game over equals false.
So the game starts.
Game over is false.
It's not over.
And then the user dies or does something bad in the game.
And so game over becomes true.
And then const is water wet equals true.
I use const here because is water wet should not change.
Hopefully water should always be wet and that's it.
We can make a variable just like that.
So we'll do one example.
Keep it short.
Let's do is hungry and I'll set that to true.
And we look at it as hungry.
It's true.
Surprise.
And we're using it so we could set it to false.
There we go.
The only other thing I'll talk about in this video.
A very important topic in JavaScript or an important idea is that variables can change type.
If you have experience with any other programming language, well, maybe not any other, but many other
languages.
When you declare a variable and you make it a number, it needs to stay a number.
In JavaScript, there is no restriction on that.
We can change a number to a boolean at any point.
That's not saying it's a good idea at all.
In fact, it's one of the things a lot of people don't like about JavaScript, and it's why things like
TypeScript exist.
If you're familiar with TypeScript, if if you've heard the word or the name, it is built on top of
JavaScript and it adds in stricter rules.
And one of those rules is that your variables cannot change type.
So I could make a boolean variable.
Let is hungry.
I already have that one.
I'll get an error if I declare it.
Let's do let is angry set to false and then I could change is angry to now be 1239 no problem.
So again not something that you usually would do or that really makes a lot of sense, but it's possible
in JavaScript.
And other than that, the main takeaway is that we can have variables of all sorts of types in JavaScript.
We've only seen numbers so far, but now we've covered our second primitive type boolean.
True and false.
That's it.