Next up, let's talk about our third primitive type string.
Strings come up all the time.
Early on, I talked about this form and how we might represent the data in JavaScript.
All of this text information, the review, the name, the email.
We would store that or model that using strings.
Strings are just textual values, pieces of text or strings of characters.
And the most important thing to remember is that we wrap them in quotes, single or double quotes.
So you can see some examples here.
This is a string, Ziggy using double quotes.
Here's another one.
A longer string.
Here's one with single quotes.
This is problematic where we're mixing a double and a single.
We're never closing the string.
You can use either.
What's really important is just to be consistent within a single application or a single file.
You don't want to have some strings that are using single quotes and others that are using double.
It's not a problem for your code.
It won't cause any errors.
It's just confusing for other developers.
So as I said, we can type strings instead of quotes.
That's a string.
We can do it with single quotes.
We could even put numbers in there.
This is a string, not a number.
I haven't shown you this yet, but there is a special operator in JavaScript called type of.
I have no idea why it is not capitalized.
The oh, I'm sure there's a good reason for it, hopefully.
But type of is an operator where we pass in a value like 87 and it tells us that's a string versus if
I got rid of the quotes that's a number.
So strings are text.
They can contain all sorts of characters, not just letters and numbers, but also special characters
as long as we remember to close the string.
So if you do something like this and we don't close it, we get an error invalid or unexpected token.
That means that JavaScript encountered this opening quote.
And thanks.
All right, we're in a string, string, lend, string and string lend.
And then it just ends.
And it was expecting a quote at the end to let it know the string is done.
We can also use quotes inside of other quotes.
So let me show you what I mean.
Let's say we had an example of he said, and then I wanted to use quotes inside of this because somebody
is talking, ha ha ha, this is totally valid.
I have single quotes on the outside and then double quotes on the inside that works and I could do it
the other way around as well, he said.
LOL valid as well.
What does not work is if you tried to use double quotes, she said.
And then double quotes again like that.
What's happening here is that we start a string off and then we close it prematurely and then we have
this just OMG hanging around, which doesn't mean anything in JavaScript.
It will give us an error and then a quote which opens a string and a quote that closes a string and
it just contains a space.
So unexpected identifier it doesn't know what OMG is supposed to be.
So those quotes have to be there, but you can mix them up if you do need to have quotes inside of a
string.
Of course we can make variables with strings.
Let's go with let first name equals.
We'll just use Ziggy as we've already seen in the notes.
So we have first name and then let's also do last name.
So let last name, let's do Ziggy Canary Face.
That's a very unique last name.
And what I want to show you here is that we have some operations that we can do with strings.
We can do something like first name plus last name.
Now, this is very different, obviously, than mathematically adding them.
Even though it's the same operator or the same symbol, it has a very different meaning in this context.
When we're working with strings, we are going to concatenate the strings together, which means shove
them together into one string Ziggy Canary face.
And if we wanted to, we could go further and add in a space between the two like this.
So first name plus a space plus last name.
Now we have Ziggy Canary face and we could save that to a variable like let full name equals first name
plus space plus last name.
And we have full name as Ziggy Canary face.
There are some quirky things.
If you start mixing types like high plus one, one is going to be turned into a string and we end up
with high one.
We're concatenating them.
We don't have similar operators for minus.
So if we try to do high minus H, it doesn't work.
Thinks that we're working in mathematical realms so we get not a number.
Same thing with division.
If we try and do high divided by H, not a number.
There's quite a bit more to talk about with strings, which we're about to do.
But I'm going to leave off here for the.
This video, we've seen that strings are textual value, strings of characters and they need to be contained
within quotes, double or single.
It doesn't matter as long as you are consistent and you close them correctly.
So you have an opening single, you need to have a closing single.
And the same goes for double quotes.