Next up, let's talk about string methods.
So we haven't really talked about methods at all.
Methods are kind of like built in pieces of functionality, built in actions that can be performed on
a certain thing, a particular value, or in our case, on any string.
So we can do things like search for a particular string within a string.
Does this string contain a dollar sign?
We can replace parts of a string.
We can change case from lowercase to uppercase to all caps.
We can remove additional spacing if we want to get rid of spacing.
There's a bunch of these different features that come built in with every single string and they all
follow this format.
So we have a string dot, some method name with opening and closing parentheses.
And to be clear, strings are not the only things that have methods.
There are a number methods that are built in.
They're just not as useful.
So I'm not going to talk about them just yet.
String methods, however, are really useful, so I'm going to cover some of the most important ones.
If we go to MSDN and we look at String, it's under the JavaScript reference built an object string.
On the left hand side you'll see a very long list of methods.
Each one of these is an action we can perform on every single string, so we can take a look at one
of them, like two uppercase or two lowercase, like this one.
Before I do that, I just want to mention these thumbs down mean that you shouldn't really use these
anymore.
They're deprecated.
They still work because JavaScript needs to support older websites.
They still need to work in the browser, even though you're not really supposed to use these anymore.
But those withstanding, they're still quite a few different methods that we have access to.
So here's one to uppercase, and the way that we call it is on a certain string dot to uppercase, open
close parentheses.
So let's make a variable called message.
We'll set it to you are so grounded mister like that and we'll hit enter if we call message dot to uppercase
I'm just going to use autocomplete so oh you tab and then parentheses.
This is what we get.
We get a new version, a new string.
So to be clear, the original is unchanged.
Remember that the strings are immutable.
We can't change the first character.
We can't change any character manually.
Same thing here.
If we uppercase a string, we are creating a new string or we're getting a reference to a new string
that is the same content, just uppercase.
So if we wanted to save that to the variable, we could do message equals message to uppercase.
Or we could just make a new variable called yel or uppercase message or something like that.
Now I have message and it's been updated.
Let's quickly talk about those perrins.
They're really, really important.
If you leave them off, it's not going to work.
It won't throw an error, it won't break your code, but you're not actually executing that action.
You're just sort of asking JavaScript, does that action exist?
So we also have a two lowercase and if I call it we get you are so grounded Mr. Lowercase, remember
message is now uppercase.
But if we do it without the friends just message to lowercase JavaScript just tells me.
Yeah, that's the thing.
There's some code for two lowercase.
It's an action, a function.
Do you want me to call it.
It's not even asking if we want to call it, but that's kind of how I personify it.
And if you do want to call it, you need those prints.
So that's two uppercase and two lowercase.
I have a slide on that as well.
Remember, the original value is unchanged unless you manually set the variable using the return value
from to uppercase or to lowercase.
And then the second method we'll look at for now is called trim.
Trim is very simple.
It just removes trailing, leading and trailing whitespace.
So spaces at the beginning and end of a string.
When you call trim, it returns a string where that space has been removed.
So it's not going to remove all spaces.
Let's do let color equals purple with some spaces in there.
I'll even hit tab a couple of times just like that.
Now if I call color trim with prints, it removes those spaces.
Color is still unchanged, of course, as we've seen before.
And another thing we can do is we can call trim.
And then on top of that, we can chain on another method call like to uppercase.
So Trim will run first, which takes this string and it returns a version with no spaces on either end.
Then we're basically calling purple this dot to uppercase.
So this goes first and then two uppercase runs on whatever this returned.
So we end up with purple, no space and all caps.
A quick note about trim.
If you have spaces in the middle of the word like this, it is not going to remove those.
It only removes the leading and trailing spaces while keeping all other spaces intact.
Those are the first two string methods in the next video.
We have a different batch that works slightly differently, but remember all these methods, whether
we're working with a string, a number or something else, like when we get to arrays, objects, they
all have a set of built in methods, built in actions.
We call them by referencing a thing.
A string.
An array dot.
A method name with parentheses.
Cool.