So far, the string methods that we've seen all follow this pattern.
We call the method name with empty parentheses.
We don't provide any information or values when we execute it.
Now we're going to see a different set of string methods.
They work in the exact same way, the same syntax, except inside of the parentheses we pass in additional
information to modify their behavior.
Methods are just actions uppercase this, trim this, lowercase this.
But some of them like replace require additional information.
What are you replacing and what do you want to replace it with?
Or if we are searching for something, we need to specify what we're searching for.
So those values that we pass in between the parentheses are called arguments we can pass in one argument,
and sometimes we pass in multiple.
As in the case of replace, what are you replacing?
What do you want to replace it with?
So I'm going to show you a couple of examples of these methods.
So they work the same way.
We just pass an information.
Here's the first one.
It's called Index of No Index of will tell you where in a string, a given string occurs a substring.
So here I have catdog as the variable TV show and if I call it index of cat, it returns zero.
Meaning cat comes at the very beginning of the string.
It's not just looking for C, it's looking for cat.
The entire substring, the entire match cat starts at index zero.
Then if we do dog index of dog we get three, which means it starts at zero 1 to 3, index of three
or the fourth character.
Here's a quick example baseball index of let's look for where ball occurs in the string and it tells
us it starts at index four.
If I just did B this one is important because there are two B's.
It only tells me the first instance of B, the first occurrence which is at index zero.
It is case sensitive.
So if I instead had baseball with capital B, it ignores that one.
That's not a match, but this one is a match at index.
For now.
If we're looking for something that doesn't exist in the string like baseball index of entertaining,
which clearly entertaining does not exist, instead of the world of baseball, we get negative one.
So negative one is the representation of not found.
Anytime you call it index of with a value that is not found, you'll get negative one and you'll often
see people use this.
Once we talk about conditional logic, people will write code that checks if index of something equals
negative one.
That means the thing you're looking for is not there.
So that's pretty much it for index of it returns a number always.
Sometimes it will be the index of something you're looking for, and if it's not found, you get negative
one.
The next method we'll take a look at is called slice.
Slice does kind of what it sounds like.
It takes slices of an existing string and it gives you a piece of it, and it works in a couple of different
ways.
If we pass in a single number, let's just keep working with baseball.
If we pass in a single number to slice like maybe four, it's going to take a slice starting at index
four all the way to the end.
So in our case, that's ball.
But remember, strings are immutable, just like all the methods we've seen so far.
This is not altering baseball.
It's not changing the value.
If we had it in a variable, like if we had let sport equal baseball and then we do sport, slice for
sport is unchanged.
It's still baseball and we could save this to a separate variable if we wanted it.
So that's one use for slice if you pass in a single number.
Also, if we tried something like sport slice 40, there is no index 40.
We get an empty string.
When we use slice, we can also pass in two numbers, two indices.
The first one is where we should start the slice and then the second one is where the slice should end.
So let's test it out.
We'll do this on Super Hero and if we do a dot slice going from index zero and then we go into index
five, we'll end up with super notice that it is not inclusive because index five is 012, three, four,
five.
That would be the H right here.
It stops right before that H so it starts at zero and it goes basically to four one less than what we
have here.
So we end up with super.
If I wanted to slice, let's go with he the word I guess it's not a very exciting word but two characters
in the middle.
We need to go from this index which is zero one, two, three, four, five, and then we want to go
and tell seven.
And we get here.
Let's say I had a bunch of prices that people had written, like 50.60 and I wanted to remove the dollar
sign on all of them.
What I could do is slice, so just do slice from one to the end.
And now I get the number isolated, even though it's a string.
I could then turn it into a number, which we haven't seen how to do yet.
But this is a common use case.
If you have data that follows a pattern and you're trying to isolate a certain portion of it, you use
slice.
And then we have one more method that accepts arguments that we'll talk about.
There are many, many others that come with built in and JavaScript, many string methods, but the
last one we'll see is called Replace and it also does what it sounds like.
You specify what you want to replace, what string and what you want to replace it with.
So if I had the string, baseball is entertaining and I called replace on it, I could replace entertaining
if I wanted to with how about OC and now we get baseball is OC if I try it with something like this.
Ha ha ha.
Dot replace and I want to replace ha with.
Hmm.
What should we replace it with?
How about.
Hee hee hee hee!
Let's see what happens.
It only replaces the first one.
So there are ways of replacing all occurrences in a string.
But it involves a regular expression, which is something we have not talked about.
So we're not going to go into it.
But if you want to learn more, go check it out on MD n lookup replace.
So it replaces the first occurrence.
And of course, if it doesn't find the thing that you're trying to replace, like if I tried to replace
ha with Hee, there is no ha.
So it's unchanged.
It doesn't give us an error.
Nothing really happens.
It just doesn't replace it.
So that's replace you pass it in two values.
The thing that all of these methods have in common is that we pass in at least one value.
So we had methods where we pass nothing in like trim or to lowercase to uppercase.
And we have methods where we pass specific values in index of where we specify what we're looking for.
Tell me the index of cats here we have slice.
You can pass in one number in order to go from one index to the end of the string.
Or you can pass in two numbers to get a specific slice.
And we had replaced where you pass in two values.
If we go back to the docs here, I'm on MD N right now, I'm on to uppercase for string.
But if we go to the left again, we can see all the different methods.
If we look at slice, just to give you an idea of how you read these docs, if you look down right here
or it says syntax, the syntax is string slice and then we must pass in a begin index.
So the starting index and then we have an end index.
But notice there's these brackets around it.
This is a way of telling you this is optional.
Slice works if you only specify begin index as we've seen, if we only pass in five, it works.
But if you want you can also pass in an end index.
So if you see documentation like this on MD and whenever you see these brackets under the syntax portion
of a documentation page, this is telling you it's optional.