Next up, we have a bit of an odd operator in JavaScript called type of.
We use type of in some situations to determine the type of a given value.
We simply write type of which always has driven me crazy that it's not camel case like everything else
in JavaScript, it's type of like this.
And then a space and then we specify a value like 99 and it gives us a string containing the type,
like a name of the type number.
If I do type of true, we get boolean.
If I have a variable, we'll call it mystery and close your eyes and you don't have to close your eyes.
But let's say this is our mystery.
I'll clear the console.
If I do type of mystery, it tells us it's a string.
Yes, it contains a number at the beginning, but that doesn't matter.
It's in quotes.
So it's a string type of with undefined.
We'll give us undefined.
Here's a really odd part of JavaScript.
If you do type of null, it tells you object.
This is allegedly a mistake.
A weird quirk that has worked its way into the language over time.
So more of a piece of trivia, I guess than something you need to look out for.
Type of often confuses people because they think you need to use parentheses like you do for console.log
or for what else have we see in math?
Random or these different actions where you pass a value in and you use parentheses to execute it,
but type of is actually an operator just like the plus sign is we don't do plus sign with parentheses
or or minus sign or equal sign.
That's an operator.
When we say const x equals three, we don't use prints.
Type of is very similar.
It's also an operator.
It just has one side.
So unlike the plus sign where we have two sides, a left and a right with type of we just type of a
value and that's it.
So not much to it.
I just wanted to show it to you because sometimes it's useful once we get to writing functions in particular,
if you want to check that a user did indeed pass in a number or a function has been called with a number
and not a string, then you can use type of.