Speaking of types, there are two functions I'll quickly mention called Parse int and Parse float.
You may not use them all the time, but there are situations where you have a string and you need to
turn it into a number.
So the string contains a number hopefully, and you want to extract that number as a numeric value so
you can do math with it or do something numerical with it.
So Parsons is going to give us back and we'll return an integer.
You can see here parse int of the string 24 gives us 24.
If we try it on a decimal, the string 24.987.
It stops at that period at the decimal and it just gives us the integer part.
24.
Parse float does the same thing, except it's going to parse the entire float.
The entire decimal number of the string in the string.
So I can just quickly show you that if we do parse it, let's say we ask the user to enter their age
into a form and they enter in 21.
Pass ENT is going to give us the actual number.
If we had 21 and we wanted to add a year to it to indicate a birthday for that person, that's not going
to work for us.
But if we pass int of the string 21, we can now add one and get 22.
And then we also have pass float which you could see from the slide.
If we pass in something like 33.5, we'll get back a number containing a decimal.
Now there are some weird situations like if you tried to parse int on a price dollar sign 99 is going
to give us not a number.
It does not like that dollar sign.
It's not expecting any non number characters, any non digits in there.
And the same applies for Parse float.
But if your string does contain a number at the beginning, if it starts with a number like $0.99,
if we had the word sense afterwards, we actually will get the number 99 out of there.
So it's kind of odd if it detects a number at the beginning.
If the first character is a valid digit, then it will keep going until it can't go any further.
So if I had this, we'll get all of that, but instead have a non digit character at the beginning it
gets messed up.
Also I can put spaces in there and it will be okay, but as soon as they put other characters it gets
confused.
You probably won't be doing something like this with this particular string, but it's common if a user
enters something into a form.
This is one way of getting that string because form data comes in as a string.
You could turn it into an actual number and do math with it and that's it.
Parsed in parse float.