Hey, everyone, we've made it to one of my favorite sections, Dom events.
So this is where things start to get real.
This is where we can actually make cool applications that do things instead of just running code to,
you know, change the color when the page loads or change the color of something when you type it into
the console.
We need to understand those fundamentals selecting and manipulating.
But we have one missing piece, which is events.
Events allow us to run that code to create a new element or to remove an element or to change a color.
When a specific interaction happens from a user and there are tons and tons of different events out
there, this is a small sampling of some of the events that we can work with in our browser.
If we take a look at any modern website these days, there are JavaScript events everywhere.
Here's an example.
I was just using this website.
Can I use dotcom a couple of videos ago?
And let's see, there's a hover event.
When I mouse over something, we get a pop up that's done via JavaScript.
We've got click events.
When I click, I'm loading new content, or at least showing and hiding different tabs.
We've got other events like Let's see if I come up to the top.
As I start typing, I'll get new search results.
How about color?
There we go.
A whole bunch of new search results that's all happening through JavaScript.
So just on this one page, I have events when I'm typing that causes some code to run.
I can type something invalid like that or I can type, transform and get results showing up.
I've got hovers, I've got clicks.
I'm sure there are others that I'm skipping.
And then here's another example.
I just signed up for a Trello account in a throwaway email and it does a little tutorial for me.
It wants me to make my first board, so I'm going to type a name in here.
My first Trello board will be my life goals and notice what's happening as I type.
Something is changing over here.
That is Dom manipulation.
As I hit these keys, every time I type a single character, this element that's over here, whatever
it is, a span, a paragraph, an H three, who knows?
It's being updated.
Maybe it's inner text, it's changing.
Oh, click.
That click is an event.
So is this one to go back?
I'll go forward though, and here's more of the same.
I can change some titles of these default lists things to do.
I add my exclamation points over here and it's updated here.
So there's an event as I type.
Something is happening over here.
My interaction is triggering something and more of the same.
I guess I can add some titles here.
Things to do in my life.
I would like to explore the ocean in Submarine.
What else would I like to do?
I would also like to release an album I can hit Enter, by the way, which is a different event.
I can click to move forward or I can just hit enter and now I moved a step forward.
All right, then, over here.
Let's see.
I've got some other things I can add to my checklist.
I'm just going to do some gibberish here, and I'm ready to get started.
So those are all quick events and typing events, but now we've got other events I can drag to reorder
things.
This is an event in JavaScript.
It's actually a couple of different things.
There's dragging, there's dropping, there's when I mouse over, when I drag over something, notice
how I get those like this shadow, I guess a little gray background showing me where I would be dropping
this.
I've also got drag and drop within, I think.
Do I?
Oh, I think I just deleted one, so I'll do that.
Let's try this again.
How do I reorder?
There we go.
I can move these around.
I can click.
That's an event.
Click again to undo.
I'm sure there are other events I'm missing, but already we've seen dragging, dropping, hovering,
clicking, typing.
All of these are events that we can listen for and there are way more.
This is a small sampling of some of the more common ones.
I've tried to group them.
On the left side, we have things that are definitely more common.
On the right side, somewhat common so we can listen for clicks in our JavaScript and run some code.
When somebody clicks, we can do something.
When someone drags or drops or hovers or scrolls, that's a pretty common one.
When you scroll on a web page, sometimes there will be like an animation that triggers when you scroll
to a certain position.
We have events for forms being submitted, key presses, focus and blur.
So focus is when you're in an input like this, it's focused right now, and if I click away, it's
blurred.
We can run code in those scenarios.
And actually right there we're seeing that happen live.
If I go to edit it, notice that I get all this stuff over here, I've got this grayed out background
and then when the input loses focus, all of that goes away.
So there are some code that says when that input loses focus, when the user clicks away, then hide
all of that extra stuff or change the colors or whatever happened.
We've also got mouse wheel events.
I don't think I've ever worked with one of those, but they are available double click, not as common.
Then we have copying and pasting.
I maybe used them a couple of times, but these allow you to run specific code when a user copy something
or paste something into an input.
For example, we have events for when audio starts playing or audio stops playing or when audio initially
loads when it completes its load.
We've got screen resize events, even printing events.
I've never used these, but there are two events, one called before print and after print.
I think that's what they're called.
When a user goes to print a website and open up that print dialog before it opens, there's an event
that we can tap into and run code, and after the user clicks the print button, I guess there's another
event that we can listen for.
I've never used them, but they exist.
If you go to MDM, there's a page called Event Reference and this contains all of the different names
of the events in JavaScript that we can work with and they're grouped together.
So we have mouse events when a user clicks or double clicks when they mouse down, which is when you
depress the key or depress the mouse button, but you don't have to release versus a click is a click,
a full click down and up we have mouse leave.
So that's when a mouse leaves an element that it was hovering over.
We've also got things for dragging and dropping.
You can see there's quite a few drag, drag and drag enter, drag start.
We have things for media not as common, at least in most of the apps that I do.
We have audio.
What do we have play playback has begun on a piece of media is playing when the playback rate has changed,
when a user has seeked forward, when they've skipped forward or backwards.
Volume change events time update.
Okay, I'm not even sure what that one does.
The time indicated by current time attribute has been updated.
All right.
I'm sure there's a use for that.
We have things like progress events, storage events, update events, value change events.
And further up we've got view events.
When a user goes to full screen mode, scroll events, resizing, printing, which I mentioned, kind
of obscure stuff.
We've got animation events.
When an animation starts focus and blur network events, there's just so many of them and you're never
going to use all of them.
Well, I'm sure somebody has, but it will be pretty difficult to use all of them.
I'm going to focus on the most important ones.
But the great news is I'm going to show you the pattern you follow where you can use any of these events
with just one method.
It's actually pretty straightforward.
So we've got a lot to talk about here, but it's honestly just one method that we're going to cover
after the very next video.
So I'll see you then in like 5 seconds.
If it auto plays, I'll see you then.