All right.
So we've established that there are tons and tons of different events we can work with in our JavaScript
code.
They range from super common things like clicks and drags and hovers, scrolls, key presses to some
pretty obscure events like a printing event or a before print or an after print or even a mouse wheel.
They all follow the same pattern.
So even though the triggers of the event are different, whether it's a user typing the key enter or
return, versus the user hovering or dragging or dropping, the triggers are different, but the way
we incorporate these events into our code follows the same pattern.
We essentially have a thing.
We'll call it the thing that we're listening for an event on.
We're listening to see when this event occurs on a given thing or with a given thing like a click on
a button, a drag of an image.
Then we have the event itself.
So the event type, I'll call that event type and then we tell JavaScript, here is the code.
I want you to run.
The code to run.
This is all extremely unofficial language, but as an example, you might have a single button.
We want to listen or wait for a click on that button, and then when a user clicks that button, we
could change the color, we could have a text input.
And when a user hits return or types return, what do we want to do?
We have some code that we want to run.
It could be something as simple as clearing the input, or it could be get search results where we're
working with an API or a database.
We could have an image as the thing and the event would be a hover, which is actually called a mouse
over.
When you mouse over a particular image, we want to display the image caption or we want to make the
color image turn black and white as a nice little visual effect.
But they all follow this pattern.
We have to find a thing, an element, an event type, and then code we want to run when that event
actually happens.
So there are multiple ways.
There are three different syntax.
I'll show you for how we can actually achieve this.
But I'm telling you right up front, two of them you should probably not use, but I'm going to show
them to you because they are simple, but you'll also see them in bad tutorials.
You'll see them sometimes, you'll see them on the docs, they have to talk about it, but then we'll
see the third and the best option for how we can achieve this, how we can add events or event listeners
to elements in the next video.
So let's take a look at a very simple type of an event, a click, and we need to start by adding something
to click on right now.
I mean, I guess we could listen for a click on the body, but let's not do that.
Let's add in a button or two.
So we'll have a button that says Click me.
Let's also put in a hmm, how about a form with an input of type range.
So a range input and we'll give it a min of ten, a max of 50.
Okay.
So we have at least two things that we can now listen for clicks on.
And the first syntax I'll show you involves actually putting our code right in the element, which is
not a good idea for the same reason.
It's not a good idea to add a bunch of inline styles.
You end up with super cluttered HTML.
Your JavaScript is spread out all over the place or in the case of style, your CSS is spread out all
over the place.
It's not in a centralized CSS file or a style sheet.
Same thing with JavaScript.
We don't want to do this, but I'm just going to show it to you to run code.
When we click on this button, we can add an attribute called on click and then we need to write some
code in here.
Something as simple as an alert.
You clicked me.
Notice we're having to write our JavaScript in a string, which is bizarre to begin with, especially
if you have to worry about quotes.
Here I had to use single quotes.
This is a very simple one liner, but it's pretty gross already.
Normally what you would see if you were to take this seriously and actually use inline events like I'm
doing here, you would write a function and call the function from right here, but still it's not worth
doing.
But let's make sure it works.
If I refresh my page, I'll zoom in a bit so we can see a bit better.
And I will click.
There we go.
You clicked me.
All right.
So that's our first event interaction that we have going on.
We added an event listener to the button, and we said, when a click occurs, run this code.
And if I have another button without the on click.
Just so we're very clear here, nothing happens.
So we're not adding that to every button.
We're simply registering an event listener for this one button that does this one thing when it is clicked.
As you can see there, if I added a on click to my second button you clicked me to.
And I refresh the page.
This one gives me one alert.
You clicked me.
This one gives me a different alert.
You clicked me too.
So they have nothing to do with one another other than the fact that they're both buttons.
And we can also add an on click to something else like this.
Input on Click Equals Will Alert.
Why don't we console.log instead?
Console.log clicked the input.
Okay.
Once again, I have to pay attention to my quotes, which is obnoxious.
We'll refresh the page.
What happens when I click on this?
There you go.
I'm getting clicked to the input.
Very fancy stuff.
We also have other events, as I mentioned, back in our JavaScript file.
I deleted my little table here.
Right now we are doing one event type which is click, but we have other event types that we can work
with.
You can see them all here.
So we're doing on click.
The event name is just click.
We have other events and if we want to use them in line like we're doing right now, we preface them
with on.
So what's another one with a mouse?
So here are some other mouse events.
Why don't we try mouse over?
So mouse over right here.
It fires when we move our mouse over a particular element in order to make that work.
We need to change this either from on click and adapt it to be on mouse over.
Or we could add a second attribute.
We could have an on click and an on mouse over.
But let's see what happens when I mouse over this.
There we go.
Mouse over.
You can see it's working.
Very annoying to have an alert so often, especially just from a hover.
All of these follow this pattern on and then the event name equals do something.
Okay.
So this is the first example of something that I recommend you never do.
Adding these inline event handlers, it clutters your markup.
It's really hard to keep organized and to understand where everything is coming from.
You just don't want to put all that JavaScript directly into your elements.
So instead there's another way of doing this where we select an element first in JavaScript, and then
we can add an on click or an on mouse over.
So I'll keep one of these.
Let's get rid of, I'll keep both of them.
I guess I'll add a new button here and this button will have an ID so I can select it.
We'll call this clicker and the text will just be clicker.
All right, now let's go to our JavaScript file, which I've included here as a script at the bottom.
And I'm going to start by selecting that button document.
I could do get element by ID, I could do a query selector, I'll do query selector.
The ID was clicker and I'll save that to a variable BTN button clicker, whatever we want to call it.
And why don't we go take a look and our console here, if I look at BTN console that deer BTN, I want
to see all the properties, open it up, scroll down and you've probably noticed this before all of
these on properties on mouse over on selection change on click these now probably make a bit more sense.
These are properties we can set inline, which we've already done or we can add them in.
We can set a function as a value in our JavaScript.
So if we select the first button with that horrible mouse over event, we'll do document dot query selector
button.
And just get the first one, save that to a variable cost first.
BTN And we do our console air first.
BTN Open it up if we find our on mouse over there it is.
Notice it's not null, it has a value and that's coming from our HTML.
So this is one way of adding in one of those event handlers.
This is one way of saying this is what I want to happen on Mouse Over, but we can also do it through
JavaScript.
We just set that same property.
So BTN dot let's do on click first and then we need to set it to a function or give it something.
If instead we just wrote alert right here.
Alert.
Hi.
What do you think will happen?
Let's try refreshing our page.
Ha!
I get alert high right away.
So why does that happen?
Remember that JavaScript is just going to go through this code and encounter.
This will say, all right, we're going to update the property on click.
Set it equal to the result of executing alert.
Hi.
So it runs this line and whatever alert returns which I'm pretty sure is just undefined alert.
Or H what do we get back.
Undefined.
So then it sets on click to undefined when we do it in our inline html.
It seems deceiving, but what happens is that the DOM is just going to take this string, turn it into
JavaScript, but wrap it in a function so that it only runs when you actually mouse over or you on click.
So if we want to make this work through JavaScript, we need to write a function.
We could do a regular function expression function.
We don't have to even give it a name.
And in here we could say alert or console.log.
Let's do a console.log.
You clicked me go away.
All of them are basically saying the same thing.
You click to me, click the input doesn't matter.
This is still not the way you want to be doing this.
Remember, this is educational, but but this is not the approach that we want to take.
So BTN on Click equals this function, we're saying the button that we selected, that's the thing.
When the click happens or a click happens on that button, not just anywhere but on this one button,
this is the code to run.
It will execute this function.
So let's try it out.
Refresh the page, click on my button.
There we go.
You clicked me go away.
And I could instead change this to a different type of event.
Or I could add a second event listener to that same element.
So we have on click.
What about double click?
Is it double or is it double?
It is double click.
I rarely I don't know if I've ever used that, but we can just look it up if we ever need it.
So on double click, let's go double click as our console.log.
Refresh the page.
Here is a single click and a double click.
Okay, so we now have two different events that we're listening for on the same button and it follows
this exact same pattern.
We select something, we select the event, and if we're doing it with these on properties, it's on.
And then the event name on, click on double click.
But we'll soon see a much better way in the very next video that makes it easier.
We don't have to keep track of all of these different property names.
We use one method, so that's kind of it for this video.
Two different ways of adding events, both of which are kind of frowned upon.
And I'm not recommending, but it's a good introduction, so we could do it inline in our HTML using
the exact same names.
So on some event, all lowercase, which is also very confusing.
I don't know why it's all lowercase, but it is.
Everything else in JavaScript is camel case.
So on mouse over on click on Key Press, which will take a look at some key press events later on.
Then in your JavaScript, you could also instead set the property by first selecting an element, adding
in the on click or the on double click or the on mouse over and setting it equal to a function.
And that function will execute when the event occurs.