All right.
So in the last video, we saw that we could add an event listener by using an on click or on some attribute
in line, which I said I'm not a fan of because I don't like writing JavaScript in a string in our HTML.
And then we also saw that we could do it in our JavaScript by selecting an element, I'll call it L,
I haven't actually selected it, and then setting the on click property or the on mouse over or on double
click property, whatever the name of the property is on something.
And I also mentioned this is not great in my opinion either, but I didn't go into a ton of detail why
I'm going to show you quickly why it's not great and then we'll see the alternative, which is called
Add Event Listener.
So if we add in something to select a simple button, we'll do a button, click me and then select it
over here.
So document dot, query selector button, save it to a variable and I set the on click to be some function.
Nice and simple will console.log you clicked me All right so this is review.
It should work unless I mess up any syntax here.
Let's refresh the page and it does work.
Now, if I wanted to have a second click listener, I don't have that option with what we've seen with
on click.
It's a single property.
Just like if we have some object contact thing equals this object.
If I set thing dot color equal to purple, if I try and change things color instead of equal to some
other, it could be a function.
It doesn't matter.
Only the most recent value is there.
I don't have purple anymore.
It's a property and we're doing the same thing here.
So if I were to add another click listener button on click equals function, this time will console.log
second time.
Let's try it.
All we get is second time.
I'm not getting the first event listener or this function is not running because we overrode that property.
Now it seems stupid to do two different council dialogues based off of a click, but there are times
when you might want different listeners or multiple functions to run on a given event.
Sometimes you want them to run dynamically, so you may not have both of these functions running every
single time something is clicked, but you could have it turned on and off, if that makes sense.
So it's possible you could have more than one handler running for a given event.
Now, that doesn't work with the two options we've seen, but we have a third option, which I've been
hinting at a lot.
It's called Add Event Listener.
Now, add event listener is great because for one thing, it's one method and it will attach any type
of event listener you want a click, a double click, a, what do you call it, a mouse wheel scroll.
That's not the official term.
A drag.
A mouse over any of them.
A print before print.
For some reason you needed that event.
And also it will attach as many as we want to a given element.
So if we want to use it, we select our element and then we call the add event listener method.
We have it on all elements that we can select.
So I have my button I have selected I call button add event listener and if I hover, oop, but there's
over 100 different options here.
You can see it.
It's been condensed.
It says 81 more or 91 more.
So what I can do is pass in one of those event names.
Now I don't pass in on click, I pass in click and instead of on mouse over, I would pass in mouse
over as a string.
So let's do click start there.
And then I have a second argument which is a function and this function will execute when this event
occurs.
So I'll do an alert clicked and save.
Let's check it out.
I click the button and we get our alert.
I could add a second event listener if I wanted to to the exact same button, also listening for a click
and I'll console.log.
Second thing.
Let's see what happens.
So we get our alert and I get second thing.
Print it out.
So what we're doing here is not setting the on click property.
If we actually look at button over here, button on click.
It's not set to anything.
We are attaching an event listener which we can have multiple of for a given event on a given element.
So I could attach as many as I want.
It's probably uncommon to do that, at least to do multiple clicks.
So let's try a different type of event.
How about a hmm?
What should we do?
A mouse over.
So button add event listener mouse over again.
Not on mouse over, which is the name of the property we could set, but mouse over and a function.
And you can do an arrow function.
Although I'll show you times or a situation where you wouldn't want to use an arrow function.
It has to do with the keyword this.
But we're not there yet.
When this happens, why don't we change the inner text of the button?
So button dot inner text equals stop touching me and save.
Let me zoom in for you.
There we go.
Now, as soon as I leave, it still stays because I'm just listening for the mouse over and I'm permanently
changing the inner text.
Fortunately, we have another event we could attach, which is a mouse out.
So mouse out and I'll change the text back to what did we have originally we had click me originally,
so I'll do that here, click me and save.
Let's see if it works.
I hover, stop touching me back to click me Stop touching me back to click me If I click it, we get
our first click function running and the second one runs as well.
Add event listener is our Swiss Army knife for events.
We don't have to set individual properties, we don't do it in line.
Instead, we can just use the exact same method, but we pass it in the type of event we want.
We can have multiple of the exact same event on one element and then we give a callback function.
This function will run when this event occurs on this button.
So I've got a mouse over a mouse out, a click, a second click.
Why don't we try one more something that is a little different.
Not a mouse event, so not a click or a mouse over, mouse out.
Let's try a scroll event.
When we work with scrolls, we have a couple of options as far as where we attach the event to.
We can listen for a scroll on the entire window, so that would be a scroll bar over here.
I don't actually have enough content to scroll, so I could quickly rectify that by adding a ton of
h ones.
And if I now do it, I do have a scrollbar on the right side.
We could also listen for scrolls within a single element.
So if you had like a text box that was very large or an eye frame or some element that you could scroll
inside of, then you could add a scroll event to that.
But I'll do it on the entire window.
I'll also move my button to the top so that it's easier if you are just coming to this code and trying
to figure out what the heck is going on.
So to add a scroll event to the window, I have access to the window.
If I just open up the DevTools, I can just type window.
It's the global scope, the global object in the browser and JavaScript window dot add event listener.
And the event is scroll and then I'll add a function.
And in here, why don't we just cancel that log?
Stop scrolling.
Same exact pattern.
Select something or in our case, with a window.
We don't have to select it.
We already have window available and then add event listener.
What kind of event?
What to do in the event of a scroll on the window.
So we will refresh and I'm going to scroll.
There we go.
So you probably notice how many times this is printing out.
One of the most common things to do with scrolls is to do something called throttling.
You may not want to run this function every single time the scroll event happens.
It will fire if you just change your scroll position by a single pixel.
Usually what I've seen at least is there's some position you want to scroll past and that will trigger
something, maybe an animation.
If you get down to the bottom of the page, something will happen.
But you normally don't want something to happen like 100 or 300 times in the course of scrolling from
the top to the bottom of the page.
But that's beyond what we're talking about here.
All we need to know is that we can use an event listener to attach all sorts of different events you
pass in the event name and a function to be called, and that function will run when the event occurs
on that given element on the window, on a button.
And also, remember, not only is this nicer to write, in my opinion, one method, but we can also
listen for multiple events of the same type on one element versus with our old fashioned on click,
either inline or through JavaScript.
We don't have that flexibility.
So Add event listener is your go to way of adding events?
Definitely.
Five out of five stars recommended.