Hey, welcome back.
In this video, we'll make a tiny demo project using ad event listener.
I'm calling it the world's most annoying button.
It's a button that when you try and click it, it moves out of the way and you have to wrangle it.
You have to corner it into a corner or a small space in order to actually click it and defeat it.
So it'll be very simple.
We have a single button element and we'll add some text like try to click me and that's all we need
in our HTML.
Then in our JavaScript we're going to select that button and use the mouse over event.
So when you get near that, as soon as you mouse over that button, it's going to move.
So you can't click because it will be gone before you can click.
So let's do a document query selector to select that button.
We only have one.
We'll save this to a variable called BTN.
And then we'll add our event listener, BTN add event listener mouse over and our function will start
by just console logging, click to me or no mouse over me.
And just make sure that's showing up.
I always like to just test that things are connected the way they should be.
So if we refresh, open up my console, I'm way zoomed in, by the way, your button will probably look
a lot smaller.
Okay, mouse over me.
That is showing up.
Okay, so now what we want to do is when you mouse over, I'd like for it to randomly move somewhere
else on the screen.
And there's a lot of ways of moving elements.
I'm going to go with the very simplest one, which is not really ideal as far as performance.
I'm going to change the style dot top and style dot left.
Not this dot style, but BTN style top BTN style left.
This being a JavaScript course, I don't have time to go into a bunch of complex CSS animations and
optimizations, but you can check out some other courses that are online.
Other people have great courses.
You can check out my YouTube video on animations in CSS to understand why animating top and left and
a lot of different CSS properties is not really ideal.
But for this demo it totally works fine.
So I'm going to start by selecting all buttons.
We only have one.
I'm going to give it a position of absolute.
I'll give it a top of ten pixels and a left of ten pixels.
So now I have a top in the left.
Set and position is absolute.
I can now manipulate that inside of my function.
The callback for my add event listener.
So when mouse over occurs the first time, why don't we just set BTN style dot left equals and we can
just pick some number like 200 pixels and then BTN dot style dot top equals 100 pixels and let's make
sure it moves.
So refresh the page.
I hover and it moved.
Okay, so that's the first bit.
Relatively easy.
I'm still way zoomed in, aren't I?
250%.
So there we go.
It's moving.
Now, what I'd like to do is randomly pick a number and have it move that many pixels.
And ideally, that number would be on screen.
I don't want to just pick some random number between zero and, I don't know, 1000 because some people
might have a screen that's only 900 pixels or they might have a really big screen with thousands of
pixels.
I don't want to limit it.
So how do we get access to the size of the screen?
This is a bit of a side topic here, but it's worth going into.
There's a lot of different ways.
And unfortunately, it does.
It does vary a bit according to the browser.
A user is in especially older versions of browsers, but there are a couple of different options I'll
show you.
The first is on the window.
There is a property called screen, and if you look at screen, it has things like available height
and available width.
Now, this is the maximum dimensions of my actual screen on my computer.
This is not the dimensions of my browser window.
If I were to shrink this or change the size of the window we still end up with.
1200 or what is it, 19, 20 by 1200.
So that is not what we want to use here, because that would assume a user had their screen or their
browser window full screened.
But if we were doing it in a very small window, you want to account for that as well.
So we have another option.
This is just one of the many options we have.
If we look in window, again, there's a property called Inner Height and another one called Inner Width.
So right now my inner width is 818 pixels.
If I resize this, here's my actual window.
For this browser, it's down to 203.
If I bring it over here, it goes up to 1680.
So we want to use inner width and inner height to calculate how many pixels are to use to calculate
where we should move this button.
We'll just multiply a random number by the inner width and by the inner height turn it into pixels.
So I'll do that here.
Why don't we start with math random.
We'll multiply that by window dot inner height.
And we can floor it if we want to.
I think we can just use a fractional number of pixels as well in case I'm actually not positive.
I don't know if I've ever done that, but we'll floor it just to be safe.
So this will give us a height.
Let's make a variable for that const h.
And then we'll get a width.
So I'll just duplicate that.
I'll call it W.
Math flaw of math out random times window dot inner width.
Then we'll use that to set button style left.
So I'll use the width here and I'll do a template literal.
So I'll insert and I don't really like the name w I'll just do width height so with pixels.
And then the same thing for button style top.
I'll change this to height pixels.
Let's test it out here.
It appears to be staying on screen so far.
If I shrink my window down and I refresh again, it still stays within that window size.
Okay, so we have this part done.
What if we add some behavior in?
If the user does manage to click somehow and there is a way to do it, if you zoom way in and you make
your window super tiny, you can click.
So why don't we add another event listener on the button?
Add event listener when a user actually clicks if they can.
What should we do to reward the user?
It won't be much of a reward.
But let's do.
Let's change the inner text of the button.
Button enter text equals you got me.
And then let's make the body the background color turn green.
So to select the body, we can do document body and then style property.
We'll do background color, not color.
Camel cased equals green.
And is there anything else?
I guess that's good enough.
We could do an alert, but I'll leave it at this.
So in order to catch it and show it to you, I'll go into my case file and make the button a little
larger.
So I'll do height is maybe 50 pixels with is 100 pixels refresh.
And I'm also going to resize my window.
So if I resize this as small as I can go in chrome and refresh, it's still going to be tricky to click.
But what I'll do is zoom in.
Make the button really large.
Okay.
So now.
All right, I should be able to click close.
There we go.
I got it.
You got me.
And it turns green.
So I cheated.
I made the window way smaller, and I made the the button way bigger by zooming in.
But it works.
So this is a silly demo, but the point is that we can have multiple events on one element and we have
a mouse over, we've got a click.
It's moving.
So inside of this on click well it's not an on click inside of this event handler for mouse over we
are manipulating the button.
Same thing here.
We're changing the inner text and the background color of the body.
So this is kind of fun, silly stuff.
Next, I'm going to show you how we can add event listeners to a bunch of elements.
So how do we add an event listener to every comment on a page or every button on a page that should
behave in a particular way?
We don't have to do it one by one.
So that's coming up next.