Next up, a very important topic.
How do we attach event listeners to multiple elements?
We've seen how we can attach multiple event listeners to one element.
We had a button and that button had a click listener, a click handler, and also a mouse over.
But how do we take every button on a page and add a click event handler?
Or how do we take every upvote arrow on Reddit and make it do something when you click upload versus
downvote, we don't attach those manually one at a time.
At least we don't.
Hard code it, we use a loop.
So here are some examples.
This game we saw earlier on each one of these cards has some event functionality.
When I click, it flips, I click, it flips.
When I hover.
That's probably done through CSS.
So it's probably not a JavaScript event, but it could be a mouse over.
But each time I click, there is an event that's firing and it pertains to each one of these cards.
And there's no way I mean, there's no I can't imagine that they're doing this manually where they have
a variable button, one button to button three, button four, and they're calling an event listener
on every single button.
That would be disastrous.
Here's another example a simple calendar widget.
It's not that simple, actually.
It's a good amount of code coming from code pen and every single day has some functionality I can click
and stuff happens.
That's about it.
But we have some click functionality on every date on this calendar, so let's see how we do that.
I have my blank HTML page and rather than putting HTML here to start with, let's generate some with
our JavaScript.
So I'll delete what we had before and I'm going to make just some colored boxes.
You'll see why in a bit different colored boxes, using an array of colors, we can just do the standard
boring rainbow colors.
Red, orange.
I have an array of colors.
Red, orange, yellow.
Green, blue, purple, indigo.
Violet.
I want to loop over all of these colors and create a div on the page with that background color.
So I'll do a four let color of colors.
We want to create a div, so document dot create element div save that to a variable.
I'll call it box and I'm going to do a couple of things.
First, I'll actually define a class called Box in my CSS and I'll give it a width of let's start with
200 pixels, a height of 200 pixels, and then let's create a container to insert all of our boxes in
our HTML.
So we'll create maybe a section, give it an ID of boxes, and that's where we'll attach all of these
boxes.
So we'll select that document dot query selector using the ID sign boxes.
We'll call this the container as the variable name.
We want to make a box.
We also want to assign that box, dot style, dot background color, camel cased to be color from the
loop.
So the first one will be an empty div with a background of red and then orange and so on, and we'll
append them to the container.
So container dot append child or just regular append if you don't care about i.e. append child of box.
And I also have that box class, but let's see if it's showing up at all right now.
If we inspect, we should see that we do have Divs in there, but they have no content and they don't
have a height or width because our class is not being used.
So let's add that class box dot class list.
Add box.
Refresh.
Hey, there's our boxes.
I'm way zoomed in again.
Okay, so we've got these different boxes.
I'm quickly going to style them.
So in my case, what I'm going to do is give the boxes ID, which is our container.
A display of flex.
If you're not familiar with flex box, well, we don't have time to talk about that in this video.
It's a relatively easy way of positioning elements on the page and divvying up space.
I'll do justified content center.
Align Items Center.
Let's see if that works for us.
Okay.
Awesome.
So we have this going now.
We have our boxes on the page now for the main event.
How do we add a click listener to each one?
Well, the most obvious answer that you probably came up with is to use a loop, and that's the right
way of doing it.
So we just loop over all those boxes, we add an event to or an event listener to each one.
But if we want to do something unique for each box, if I wanted to print out the color that we're clicking
on, we have to add a little more code in.
But let's start by adding in an event listener for each box.
So we could do a separate loop, we could select all the boxes and using query selector all loop over
each box and do box add event listener.
Or we could just do it right here as we append it or after we append it, it doesn't matter.
I could do box dot add event listener.
Remember this box variable is a new div each time through so it will reference or it refers to the red
box we see here.
And then next time around it's the orange one, then all the way down to the violet one.
So boxed add event listener for click.
We'll add in our function here and why don't we just console.log?
Clicked a box.
So this is simple enough.
We should get a console.log click to box.
Click the box.
I'm clicking if you can't hear that.
But what if I want to print out the specific color that was clicked or do something with that color,
maybe change the background of the entire body?
It's actually not that bad.
In this loop we have box I could just access box I could console.log.
Box dot and then style dot.
Background color.
And print that out.
Let's refresh the page.
Red, orange.
Yellow.
Green, blue.
Purple.
Indigo.
Violet.
Okay.
Anyway, distracted.
Here.
This works.
We have access to the variable box because we're inside the loop still.
But here's where it gets a little trickier.
Let's say that my code is getting really long, and I want to break it into separate functions.
I don't want to have all of this, all my logic contained in one loop.
I want to break it out.
Maybe this function here is 50 lines.
How could I make that work?
Well, if I make a separate function, let's call this function.
Let's do a function expression.
We'll go with print.
Color equals a function.
And in here, what I want to do is print out the background color and I'll update my ADD event listener.
To call print color like this.
So boxed add event listener of click when there's a click on that box print color.
Right now, I don't have a way to access box at all.
I could pass it in, but I can't do that here because the function will execute right away.
If I were to pass box in.
So I guess I could rewrite this as a function like this and then call print color and then pass in box
like this.
Let's see if that works instead of print color.
We'll accept a box.
As a parameter and constant log box style dot background again.
So I have this function that runs and all it does is it calls print color up here.
Imagine we have a lot more code.
So this does work.
We can pass that argument around of box.
But there's another option which doesn't involve having to add a function in here.
I can simply pass print color and I'll have to change it because right now box will be completely undefined.
But what is the magical keyword I can use to reference the item that has been clicked?
It is this.
The keyword?
This.
So if we console.log this and print color, we don't need to pass in a box.
Let's see what happens now.
Red, orange.
Yellow.
This is referring to the individual div that was clicked on.
Remember that this instead of a method which is added on to an object, this will refer to that object.
If you skipped over the section on this, I highly recommend you go back and check it out.
It's not the sexiest thing ever in JavaScript, but it is important.
We also could rewrite this to do something else instead of printing out the background color.
Let's either change the background color of the body or maybe we'll add an h1n up top.
H one say pick a color and we'll change the color of our h one depending on what you click on.
And I'm going to give my h1a text, a line of center, not text decoration.
So it's aligned in the middle.
And then in my JavaScript I'll select that h one.
So const H one equals document dot query selector h one and I'll put it in the function up top.
And instead of calling this print color, we'll go with change color.
We'll call change color down here.
And then what we want to do is update h one dot style dot color to be this dot style dot background
color.
So whichever div we clicked on, we want to take the background color of that, which is what we're
doing right here, get that value and set the H one, which isn't on the page right now.
There it is.
Set the H one to be that color.
Now, change color is not defined.
Let's see.
Change color.
Extra e.
There we go.
Let's see if it works.
All right.
We've got red, orange, yellow, green, blue, purple, indigo, violet.
Awesome.
So we've got this nice little color picker.
Very simple.
But the point that I want to make here is that we can add event listeners to multiple elements inside
of a loop.
I'm not saying that you should use this pattern here where you always need to use the keyword this,
but generally inside of an event handler like we have here, this will refer to the individual element
that the event listener has been added to.
So if I instead had instead of boxed add event listener, if I instead had document body date of add
event listener or I had a button, this will refer to whatever I'm attaching that event listener to.
So let's add one to our H one very quickly.
We have our H one.
I'll just select it up here now and do H one add event listener and we'll listen for maybe a mouse over.
No capital.
Oh, that always gets me.
And we'll add in our function.
Why don't we just console.log this dot in our text and we'll see what happens here.
And now when I mouse over that h one, we're getting pick a color.
This is referring to the H one that the ad event listener ran on or that we attached it to.
So I'll get rid of that.
We don't need to add that mouse effect.
And we'll leave it at this.
No pun intended, but.
All righty.
So we saw that we can add multiple click listeners to or one click listener to multiple elements.
They are separate add event listener calls.
It's not like we have one event that we're listening for.
We're attaching eight or nine or however many different colors we have where it's hatching that many
event listeners.
It's not like we just have one overarching event listener.
We have multiple.
All right.