Next up, we need to talk about something called the event object.
So when this function is called, let's go with the change color function, it's called when we click
on a box or a user clicks on a box, we're never executing change color ourself.
It's being called for us and it's actually passed a value.
It's past an event object.
And this event object sometimes is extremely useful to have access to in our callback, in our event
handler.
So we have access to it.
It's automatically passed every single time.
We're just not capturing it and change color.
We're ignoring it.
But if we were to add in a parameter here, you could call it anything.
Usually you'll see e or event or ev t any of them is fine.
I'll go with ev t.
Why don't we just see what it contains?
Console.log ev t I'll refresh my page.
We click on one of these.
And it's an event object which contains information about the particular event.
So it's a mouse event.
You can see where it occurred on my screen, the screen X and screen Y, we can see what else we have
this property path, which is kind of interesting.
It shows everything that we clicked on.
Yes, we did click on a div with the class of box, but it was inside of a section with the idea of
boxes and that's inside the body, inside the HTML element, inside the document, inside the window.
We clicked on all of those.
There's things like was the shift key to pressed the timestamp for when it happened after the page loaded
all that stuff it contained in this one object.
If we instead had a different type of event listener set up, why don't we do a keyboard event, a key
press or a key up?
A key down?
Let's add in a simple input here.
Or actually, let's even just do it on the body.
So if you type any key while you're on this web page, let's alert the key or do something with it.
So I'll select document dot body dot add event listener.
And we'll do a key press.
We'll talk more about these events, the particular key events and form events in the next video.
But I just want to show this function.
We'll work with the event object.
We'll use it.
And why don't we just console.log?
The event object.
So key press on the body of the document.
So anywhere on this page if I type a key.
Okay.
I just typed the key.
I typed another one.
And the reason I'm showing this key event is that often we need to know which key has been pressed and
that information is contained in the event object.
We don't say key press of a or key press of Z key.
We just say key press.
Any key that is pressed will fire this event and call this function.
So if we want to know, was it the enter key?
Was it the I don't know, w a SD key?
Was it an arrow key?
Then we use the event object which is automatically passed in and if we open it this time it is a keyboard
event, not a mouse event.
And we have a bunch of things like key that is a very important one, if you want to know just the basic
key that was pressed.
Although it doesn't always work the way you might expect.
For example, if I press shift, my event is not firing, but if I instead do shift, ah, it does fire.
But we'll save that for the next video.
All you should know is that we have access to information about the particular key that was pressed
so R or w, p, 0iu and so on.
Okay.
So the event object is very useful part of working with events.
If you need information about the events, whether it's what was clicked on or what key was pressed,
what time after the page loaded?
Where on the screen?
The coordinates, exactly.
There's a bunch of different pieces of information you can access using that event object.