Next up, let's talk more about key events.
So I'm going to start by adding in a simple input.
So we have something to work with here, something that we can type into.
I'll give it an ID of username, give it a placeholder of username, and let's also give it a type of
text.
Okay.
So I've got my input element.
Here it is.
It's a bit small, but it will work.
And we're going to see that there are at least three different options for listening, for a key press
or a key down or a key up in this input.
So I'm going to select it in my JavaScript.
I'll do const input equals document dot query selector.
We used an ID of username and then we'll add our first event listener.
So input add event listener let's do key down and we will want the event object because that object
will contain information about which key in particular was pressed.
But why don't we just start by ignoring it and console that logging key down?
All right, so let's open up our console, refresh the page, and if I type a key in this input, I'm
going to hit P.
It fires.
We got key down.
If I type L, we get key down I what if I hit shift?
That's a key down a number is the key down caps lock.
That's a key down.
You can't tell but I am hitting caps lock tab.
That's also key down.
So it's not just when we're actually typing some character into the input.
It could be the control key.
The command key.
I'm hitting command over and over and over.
Any time I press a key down, it's going to fire and it's firing when the key is pressed down.
Originally, if we duplicate this and add a second event listener for key up and save or replace this
to console.log key up.
I'll refresh, I'll click, I'm going to start typing.
So I'll hit the letter P and you can see key down fires first and then key up if I hit space, same
thing key down then key up.
If I hit the right arrow, same thing.
And if I hold the key down continuously like I'm going to hold, how about shift 3 to 1?
I'm holding it.
And then I'm going to release it.
There we go.
So key up only occurs when the release actually happens, but it also runs just like key down.
It runs for any of the potential keys I could press, whether they actually change the input or not.
I could hold command option control, the function key.
All of these are going to trigger those events which you may or may not want.
So there is a third event that will see input add event listener key press.
Key Press actually differs a little bit from browser to browser.
If you read the docs anywhere online and check out Mtn's explanation, it explains how it's supposed
to work.
The idea is that for something to be considered a key press, there needs to be a character showing
up in this input or a change like space.
I'll refresh the page and just as a fun little demo, it's not fun or a demo, but instead of clicking
in if I hit tab to select the input, what do you think will show up over here?
Only key up because tab when I'm pressing down on that, it's actually moving me into this input.
It's focusing on the key down.
So that tab event did not occur or the key down event did not occur on the input, but then it focused
and then I released or that's the order that things happen in behind the scenes.
So I release the tab key once I'm focused in the input.
So back to key press.
If I type a key like K, we get key down.
Nope, I hid.
I accidentally hit M as well.
We get down and then press and then up.
But if I type something like shift, we only get down and up.
If nothing is showing up in that input, we're not considering that a key press.
What about a capital letter?
So shift and then t.
There we go.
It's hard to see because I have so much going on.
But what's happening is that the key press is only occurring after I hit shift and then t and I get
this uppercase T versus the key down and the key up are firing both for shift and for T.
So those are three different options for listening to events in an input or on the body.
For example, there are three different input events.
They are different.
Generally, I mean, it depends on what you're doing.
If you are making a game, for example, and he wanted to have arrow keys to move something around,
you probably would not want.
Key press.
Key press is not going to give you the the impact that you want.
If I click here and I hit the right arrow, I'm not getting key press at all.
I'm not changing the input.
But if I hit L or some some character that's showing up, that key press event fires.
So that's one situation where you may not want a key press, but if you want to know when something
is actually changing in the input so you don't care if a user is hitting shift, you don't care if they're
hitting return.
You want to know what's in the input.
You could use key press instead.
What's interesting about Key Press interesting might be a stretch, but it's important to note that
when you hit return, it actually does count as a key press.
I just hit return and we got press over here, even though nothing changed in the input.
If I type, clearly that's a key press and if I hit delete, which I'll do right now, that is not considered
a key press.
That's just a up and down.
But return is a press.
So why am I showing you this?
Well, a lot of the time we want to listen for specifically a return press or an enter key press, meaning
that the user has typed something in and they're hitting return to submit or to finish.
So if we wanted to make a very simple, I wouldn't even call it an application, but a to do list or
something, a shopping list where we have an input.
Let's do this down here.
We'll add an H three shopping list and then we'll add in a UL that will start empty.
We'll give it an ID of items.
Sure.
And then we'll also add in an input.
And it will be type equals, text ID equals, what should we call it, add item and we'll give it a
placeholder of enter a food or something.
Okay.
Now from our app JS, I want to select that input.
So I'll do const add item input equals document query selector.
We have an ID that we added, I think it was add item and I'll also select that UL while we're here
const let's call it items UL equals document query selector.
Ah, good friend ID of items.
Now I'm going to add an event listener to the add item input and I'll do an add event listener of key
press.
I want to listen for when a user hits return and when they do hit return, we'll take whatever is in
here.
Let's say fish, I hit return, I'll clear out the input, I'll grab that information and make a new
ly with that data, but only on return.
So we could do it for key up or key down as well.
But I'm not going to because those fires so much, so much more often, for example, if we have shift
t like that, that is two key downs or two key ups versus if I'm using key press, I only get one.
You're not seeing it show up here, but I'm only getting a key press event when the capital T shows
up.
So I'm going to go with key press function.
And then this part's very important.
We want the event object and we're going to start by just console logging.
That event object.
That object, as we saw very recently, contains the information about the event.
So it should contain the key that was pressed.
Here we go.
We've got a keyboard event.
It has a bunch of stuff, but I prefer to stick with key to keep it simple here.
We also have code.
That's a bigger topic we don't have to go into now, but let's see what we get.
I shouldn't have closed that when I hit enter key is set to enter.
Okay.
Also key code I believe is 113 and 13 for enter so we could use either of those.
This key code is standard across all browsers.
I'm pretty sure using key is also standard these days.
The way I learned when I was learning this stuff was key code, but it's just so annoying to have to
use a number as the key that you're typing compared to a key string.
And then in here we can simply check if.
Eventbrite key equals enter.
If that happens, we'll add a new item to list.
Otherwise, we don't need to do anything.
We don't want to do anything.
We just leave a user alone so they can keep typing.
But if they do hit enter, we want to grab the value from that input.
So what would be the easiest way to do that?
Well, we have the input selected.
I could also just say this dot value console.log, this value.
Why don't we start there?
And see what happens.
So I'm gonna start typing in here.
I need cat food.
I'm going to hit enter.
Hey, there we go.
We've got cat food showing up.
I need to get cat litter, and it shows up over here.
So we'll grab that value and save it to a variable cost.
New item, text or something equals this value.
Then we'll select our items UL, which we've actually already selected and we want to append a new ly.
So let's make our new item equals document, create element of an ally, and then we'll set new item.
Enter text to be this new item text that we grabbed whoops from this value.
So we extract the value and then we create a new ally.
We use that value we extracted to set the inner text of that ally, and then we should append it.
So we have items ul append or append child of new item.
Let's see if it works.
So we have a UL down here right now.
It's empty, but I'll add something in like chicken breast.
There we go.
We're missing one thing, which is we're not clearing this input, which is very easy to do.
We can just call this dot value equals empty string.
The input which is this add item input value where we fetched or retrieved the actual value a user entered.
We'll now set it to be empty.
So every time I hit enter.
Awesome.
Very simple example, but this is a really common pattern.
Listen for an enter key or some other key and do something based off of that.
So that's one example.
I'll stop here.
Let's just recap the difference again between key up, keep down and key press.
Key up and key down are going to fire for any key that you touch at all.
One will fire when you press it down.
The other one doesn't fire until it's released.
But it includes things like shift or arrow keys caps lock.
A key press does not the way key press is supposed to work, which is not always the case.
Sometimes there's some weirdness across browsers, but the intended use for key press is that it only
fires when, in the case of an input, something actually shows up like shift k would be one key press
instead of two key downs or two key ups, it would be one key press.
An arrow key does not count at all.
Something needs to show up here or the user hits enter, which now that I'm looking at this, we should
probably add in a quick little check and just return early if this dot value.
How about if not this top value return?
So instead of checking if this dot value is an empty string, we'll just check if it's true or false,
actually.
And there we go.
Nothing happens.
But if I have some stuff, it does work.
But if I hit enter and there's no value, we're ignoring it.
We return early.
We just get out of this entire function.
Awesome.