Next up will make a little tiny game where we have a player, a little sprite of a guy walking in a
coin.
We're going to move the coin somewhere randomly on the screen and we'll use the arrow keys to make our
little avatar walk and pick up the coin, at which point the coin will move somewhere else and you'll
keep moving towards the coin.
I guess it's a commentary on the pursuit of wealth and never being fulfilled, and there's always a
new coin to go chase.
Okay, so to do this, we're going to take advantage of some of the key events we just learned.
We're going to use the arrow keys to move our little avatar.
And I've given you starter code.
There is a folder that you can download called Coin Game Starter.
It has the two images one for the player, one for the coin and in the app.
It also has a function that I've given you just so that we don't have to spend too much time trying
to write this logic.
It's logic that will detect if two elements on the DOM to divs or images or whatever are overlapping.
And we'll use that to figure out when the avatar is actually touch the coin and then we can move the
coin.
So this is straight from I think I found it on StackOverflow and adapted it a tiny bit.
It's just kind of annoying to type ourselves, and it's also the kind of thing that if I had to do this,
I would just Google it anyway, which is what I did.
So I'll be transparent about that.
I didn't write this from scratch, just modified it.
And what we're going to do to start is just make it so we can move our player.
And I'll tell you now that to make a game, a real game that performs well, you would want to use canvas
in the browser, which we're not going to talk about, at least right now.
We're going to just focus on the key events and we'll move the player by adjusting CSS properties top
and left.
So I'm going to start by selecting that image, which has an idea of player.
So we'll do document get.
Nope, we'll do query selector.
We could do get element by ID too.
We want just regular query selector.
The ID is called player const player image or just player equals.
Or how about Avatar?
And we also want to add an event for a key press or a key down or key up.
But we don't want it to be on one of these elements.
We want to be able to just press a key like the left arrow, the up arrow, anywhere.
And to do that, we can attach it to the window.
And key press is not going to do what we need it to do here in most browsers, Arrow Keys are not considered
key presses, so we'll do key down or Key up.
Let's do key up.
For now, we'll add event listener for key up function.
We'll use the event object and why don't we console.log event key.
We'll refresh the page.
I'll open up my console and I'm going to hit the down arrow.
There we go.
Right, left up.
Cool.
So we have those four different arrows that we want to work with.
Those are the keys that we care about.
Event key.
And let's just take one of them.
Let's start with down.
So when you press down, we want to add to the image or the avatar style.
So Avatar dot style, dot top and I could just hard code it right now to be like 200 pixels.
The initial CSS has top at 100.
So if we set it to 200, it will move downwards.
And right now I'm doing this just whenever you press any key at all, I'll refresh the page and I'll
hit down or right.
And it does move down, but only the first time.
Every other time it's just being reset to 200 pixels.
So this is where it gets kind of annoying if you're not using canvas.
What we need to do is figure out the current value, whether it's 200 or 100 or some other value.
But this is a string, so we need to remove the pixels.
We want to turn that into an actual number like 200.
Then we want to add some amount.
Let's say we're adding 50 pixels, then we want to take 250 and turn it into a string.
Then we want to take that and add X and use that to update Avatar style top.
So what I'm going to do is probably make a separate function.
We'll call this const extract.
Mm.
What do we want to call it.
Extract position.
And we'll pass in a string.
We'll call this pause.
And to use it, we would do something like this, extract pause of and then avatar style top and that
would be something like 200 pixels and we want to get 200 back from this function.
So we'll start by getting rid of the pecs and we can use slice to do that.
If I have 200 x dot slice and I go from 0 to -2, I'll get rid of those last two characters.
Even if my string is a lot longer, we'll just remove the last two.
We're not actually removing it, but we're creating a new string, so we'll do that here.
Pause dot, slice zero, comma, negative two.
And then we want to make sure that we turn this into a number.
And to do that we can do parse int.
And let's just copy this over here.
Let's make a variable called pause equals 350 p x and then call parse int of that pause position, we
get 350.
If we set pause to be something larger and run that again, we get a number.
So we want to return this and I think I'll just do an implicit return on a single line like that.
So now we have that function extract position.
And we'll save that to a variable cost current top and then we'll just take a current top, we'll add
in, let's say 50 and then we want to add pixels the string p x.
So what I'll do is set avatar dot style dot top to be current top.
I'll do string interpolation here with a template, literal current top plus 50 and then p x outside
of those brackets.
And that should do it for me.
Let's see.
Now, this is going to fire every time I press any key.
Hmm.
Does not seem to be working the way I'm expecting.
Let's take a look.
So we have our image.
Let's see what avatar dot style dot top is.
Let's console that log.
Avatar, dot style, dot top.
Every time I press a key.
Hmm.
We're not getting anything.
So is this returning?
Avatar style laptop.
Okay, so here's what's going on and figure it out.
Our issue.
Initially on our image, the very first time it loads we don't have an inline top set.
So even though we have it set in CSS, I actually went over this in hopes of preventing these issues
for you guys early on in the DOM sections and then I completely forgot about it here.
So what's going on?
Is that Avatar style top initially is an empty string and when I'm trying to extract a position from
that, we're getting not a number.
And then every time after that we're working with not a number, which is not working.
Well, you might think that we could do this, give a default value if position is not passed in or
if it's empty string or undefined, set it to be ten pixels.
We'll extract ten or we could do zero pixels and turn that into just zero.
The problem is that if I tried out those default parameters don't run.
If I do extract position of an empty string, it doesn't work.
If I passed in nothing.
Oh well, we're not returning anything, so that's a problem.
But if I do return something.
I would get zero.
But if I pass an empty string in, we still get not a number.
So this default parameter won't work.
What we could probably just do.
It's kind of clunky and it's not that bad.
Say if not position because an empty string is still falsey even though it won't trigger a default parameter
value, we'll simply return zero.
So if currently Avatar style dot top is an empty string, then we'll return zero and then use that.
Okay, so that should work better for us.
And then we're setting avatar style that top using that.
Let's make sure though, double check and I'll refresh the page and it looks like it's working one more
time.
Okay.
Cool.
So now let's make it so it doesn't do this.
Every single key that is ever pressed.
Let's make sure it's only if event key is equal to arrow down.
This is moving us down.
I did do some research and figured out that in Internet Explorer, the Arrow Keys are actually just
left, right, up and down instead of arrow left, arrow down.
So we could account for that as well.
We would just need to do if event dot key equals arrow down or event key or e key equals down.
Then we'll run this code where we're adding to the top.
So adding more pixels to the top moves us down.
Let's get the other direction going.
So else if events key equals arrow up or e key equals up for Internet Explorer and edge, we'll do something
similar and we can refactor this later.
We'll just do some very explicit long code.
We'll get the current top and then we'll set the Avatar style up to just subtract 50 pixels.
Let's test it out.
Refresh.
So I'm going to hit down.
I'll hit up.
I'll hit.
Right.
Nothing happens left.
Nothing happens.
So that's working pretty well.
There's one issue with the workaround I added in for the very first time.
We pressed the key I'm going to hit down.
We actually move up.
And that's happening because my initial style for the top is 100 pixels and then left is ten pixels.
So I could either go to my app JS and change this instead of returning zero, we could return 100.
So we're matching what the current top is and let's see if that works.
So I'm going to hit down.
There we go.
So we don't have that issue anymore.
So we've got up and down now.
How about left and right?
Well, it's the same idea, but we're going to have to change it up just a tiny bit.
So let's duplicate our elseif and let's do if the user hits the let's do the right arrow.
So right arrow or if key equals right for those Windows browsers or Microsoft browsers, we don't want
the top.
We'll get the current left.
And we want to extract that number from avatar stylist.
And then this is going to be annoying.
Again, we're returning 100.
Why don't I just say the original left is also 100, so we're in sync and then we'll set Avatar style
left equals current left plus 50.
And then one more.
We want an Elsa if we don't want an else, because we have a million other keys that could be triggering
this.
We only want this group of four so else is not what we want.
This will be a left arrow and we'll check if it equals left.
And then we'll do current left.
That's the same.
We'll just subtract and we'll cross our fingers.
Let's see.
So I'm going to hit the right arrow.
And the left arrow.
It's not working.
So what's going on?
Red dot key equals.
Well, that was one of the dumber things I've ever done.
That's a complete lie.
I've done far dumber things, but this was very silly.
Hopefully you caught it before me.
Arrow down, arrow up.
This needs to be arrow, right?
Not right.
Arrow.
And then same thing here.
We need arrow left.
All right, let's try again.
Okay.
I can move.
I can go down.
I can go up.
All right, so one fun thing we can do is make it so that when we're moving to the left, our image
is facing to the left.
And to do that, I can just show you here, if we do image style, I have it selected transform and
we set scale to be negative one, comma one.
Image is not defined.
Oh, that should have been Avatar.
Try that again.
We're now facing left.
So we've scaled the image on the x axis.
If we pass negative one, it basically flips the image and then to go back the other way, we would
just go scale one, comma one, so we could just copy this.
And when you're moving to the right, well, let's start with the left.
When you move to the left, we'll set Avatar style transform to be scale of negative one, comma one.
And then when you move back to the right, next time we'll go back to one comma, one refresh, I'll
go down to the right and stay the same left.
We're now facing the correct direction.
So obviously this movement kind of sucks.
It's based off of having to press the key over and over and over.
If I just hold one of the arrow keys, it's not going to do it for me.
And that's okay.
This is not really how you would build a game for the most part.
I mean, this could be a little demo, but you would use canvas, you would use some library to help
you out with physics where you had coordinates.
It was it's a lot easier, but this is a good enough demo.
So why don't we figure out now how to move the coin to a random place on the page?
And then when you touch that coin, we'll move the coin again.
So to move the coin, why don't we just make a function to do that?
We'll call it const move coin equals.
We don't need any arguments.
I guess we could pass in the thing we're trying to move, but we'll just do move coin.
We'll select the coin.
Do I have it selected?
No.
So const coin.
And I think I'm going to select this up top with our avatar equals document query selector with the
ID of coin.
Then down here we'll want to pick a random position to move that coin to and then move that coin to
it using top and left.
So we'll pick some random numbers based off of window dot inner height, which we saw sometime in this
course already a couple of videos ago, if I call window inner height or let's do inner width, it tells
me I have 928 pixels available.
I shrink that down more and call it again.
Now it's 175, so we don't want to move the coin somewhere way off the screen if the window is not large
enough because you could have a large screen, we don't want to do what it did.
Body window, dot screen.
We don't want to use this because this is the available width for the window.
On my monitor.
It's 1920, but I might only have 100 something pixels available, so we'll use those windows inner
height and I'll do a math random.
We'll multiply it by windows inner height and I'll floor that.
So we get a whole number and we'll save that to a variable called for doing height.
We'll call that Y and then duplicate it.
Make another variable called x method random window inner width.
So we have those two variables.
Now I want to take the coin and do coin dot style, dot top equals and then I'll do a string or we don't
even have to do a query string.
We could use concatenation and just plus sine pixels at the end, but I'll do a string template literal.
So for the top we want why this is based off of the height.
So height p x and then for the left we'll do x, p x and let's just try calling move coin from over
here.
So move.
Let me make some more space here.
Move, coin.
Let's see if it works and it appears to be working.
Okay, so we're moving the coin around.
I'm sure it's not perfect.
Our logic may end up moving it off the screen at some point, but it's simple enough for now, so that
moves the coin.
Now, all that's left to do is to initially move the coin at the beginning when our code runs.
So we can just put that somewhere, maybe put our function definitions.
So we could just call that early on, so we could just execute that and move coin at the beginning so
that when you refresh the page, the coin is somewhere else and then we'll move to try and go get it.
And nothing's going to happen.
So the last thing to do is figure out when we've collided, which I've thankfully given us a nice helper
function that computes that it's called is touching.
And all we do here inside of this event listener after we've moved the the avatar, if necessary, we
can just check if.
We want to check is touching that function that I gave you.
We'll pass in the avatar and the coin.
And if that's the case, we'll just call move coin again.
So if this returns true, we pass in two items.
It returns true.
If they are touching, then we'll call move coin.
Let's try it.
So, so far it's touching has been called a couple of times, but we're not actually touching it.
But there we go.
It moved.
Let's try again.
And it appears to be working.
So very, very entertaining game.
But it's kind of fun.
It's a little demo here and we get that fancy change of direction.
We're halfway to like a very basic, basic game, except we don't have anything fun.
All right.
So if you wanted to, you could definitely refactor this a bit with the arrow down, arrow up, arrow
right, arrow left.
You could consider making an object to hold the different functions to call.
You could make a function called move left, move right, move up, move down.
That could be kind of fun.
So here's one option.
I'd make a couple of different functions called Move Up.
Or we could even just call this move vertical and then we'll take the thing.
So we'll call it element and then the amount.
And what am I doing?
I want this to be an arrow function.
So we'll do that.
And we would call this, for example, here, if we're trying to move down, we would do move vertical
pass in our element that had moved.
Let's just go with Avatar and then positive 50 and then here to move up, we could pass in -50.
And we would basically move this logic in here.
So four move vertical.
We're going to do instead of Avatar, we'll do element, which is the parameter name.
So this could work for any element that we're passing in, not just the Avatar element style top and
then set element that style top to be current, top plus amount.
And the moment of truth.
Let's try deleting that.
Let's see if up and down still work.
It looks like they still work.
So let's do the same thing.
We'll make another function called move horizontal and you could make one to handle all of this.
But I think this will help keep them a little shorter and easier to understand if you're looking over
the code.
So here we want current left equals extract element dot style dot left element.
That style left equals curr left plus amount.
And then we'll just call it.
If we're moving to the right, we want to add 50.
We'll pass an avatar, make sure we're calling move horizontal.
And then the same thing for the left, except we'll do -50.
Okay.
Let's try it.
It still works.
Oh, except I deleted that one part where we flipped our avatar, so I guess I'll undo that for a moment.
I got too eager there.
We'll do it like this.
So move horizontal avatar, -50 and then set the scale to negative one, comma one.
Here, we'll set it back to one, comma, one.
Does it work?
Now to the right.
To the left.
Down.
Up.
Awesome.
And if we touch the coin, finally.
Pursuit of money.
Uh.
You have to keep going.
Maybe more money.
Maybe I'll be happier now.
Nope.
How about over here?
I think this is the one.
If I just make a little bit more.
Get that treasure.
Oh, man.
All right.
Next time.
Awesome.
So if you want some extra features that you could add, definitely one would be a score count or a scorekeeper.
Just a little chart up top or even just a paragraph in H one that tells you how many times you've collected
this.
Also, you could create a whole bunch of coins, different coins, different values, give them a different
color.
You could do that with a CSS filter.
You can make some of the coins larger to make them worth five.
You could also have the coins move if you wanted to get fancier.
But if you're going to do a bunch of animations, I would look into canvas to make something a little
bit more or a lot more performance.
All right.
So that was mainly just about the arrow keys, but I thought it'd be fun to put something together where
we're using a lot of the stuff we've seen, events we're talking about selecting, we're talking about
style properties, creating elements already.