Next up, let's talk about using forms.
So we saw how we could use the key down key press key up events to run some code when a user types in
a single input.
But what if we want to do something when a user submits an entire form?
So let's start with a simple form that will add in.
Let's do a couple of different inputs.
We'll have an input type equals text.
What should we do for this one?
Let's go with placeholder equals credit card number.
Sure, this is not going to be a real credit card form.
We'll do another input.
This one will be type equals.
Let's do a checkbox and let's put a label around it.
So I'll move it inside the label.
I don't need a four.
If I'm embedding my input inside the label, I'll put some text in here.
Let's do a checkbox.
I agree to sell my soul to your company and we don't need a placeholder for a checkbox.
Let's also do.
How about a select?
A select where we have different options.
If you're not super familiar with a select, it's how you can get a dropdown menu, basically.
So why don't we pick, hmm?
Options.
We'll just do something boring.
Let's do vegetables, eggplants.
And asparagus and carrot.
All right, so I'll put corresponding values and we'll do eggplant there.
So we have a couple of different inputs now, and I'll also add in a button to submit this input type
equals submit.
And let's see what we end up with when I open it up here.
Kind of an ugly form, but we have a couple of different inputs.
We've got a select we've got a check box and we have our credit card input, which it's just a text
input, no validations.
And then our submit.
Now, if you're familiar with forms, you'll know what happens when I click submit the page refreshes.
A form is made to take data that we get from an input and submit it or send it somewhere.
Traditionally, we would submit our data to one for some URL like slash sign up.
So this would be an endpoint on our own server.
The data would be sent to slash sign up and then on our server side we would do something, create a
new user in the database and then respond with a new page that would load.
And so you would end up going to a completely new page.
But with JavaScript and the rise of single page apps and things like React and Angular and Vue or just
vanilla.
JS We can work with forms in a slightly different way.
What we'll do is submit the form or when it's submitted, we'll intercept it and say, Don't send that
request.
Don't refresh the page.
Just to show you right now, if I submit this, I have to refresh to get that new attribute.
If I submit this right now, it takes me to slash sign up, which doesn't exist.
So what we'll do with JavaScript is take the form.
When it submitted, we'll say, stop, don't actually send a request, don't take us anywhere else.
I just want to capture that event.
I want to trigger some JavaScript code.
When the user submits a form, then we can extract the information we want and do something with it,
whether it's simply to display it back to the user, whatever we're doing here, or maybe we'll send
the data to a database somewhere to a server, but we won't actually refresh the page.
We'll do it using JavaScript on the same page we're currently on and we could maintain a single page
application.
So we're not really at the point where we're sending requests right now, but you'll see where we could
easily add that in.
So there is a form event called Submit.
You could attach an on submit, which I don't recommend doing with any of those on events.
Those properties are just not ideal.
But in our JavaScript, if we select our form, let's call this signup form as the ID and then select
it.
So document dot, query selector the ID sign and then sign up form.
Save that to a variable we can add in a form dot add event listener for the submit event.
And we'll use the event object.
Why don't I start by alerting?
Submitted the form and let's see what happens.
So I'll refresh my page.
Click submit.
Okay, so we get that event triggering, but then our page reloads.
I don't know if you can tell that.
If I go back to what I had before where I gave it an action equals slash.
No, let's do that and we'll do method equals get.
This is a traditional form if I submit it now we get our alert from the event handler, but then it
still continues on.
It does what it did earlier.
It takes me to a different page.
So we are capturing that event.
We're doing something when that event is triggered, but we're not preventing the typical form behavior.
And if I want to capture the data but not go to a new page and not send a request, we have a way of
doing it.
There is a method on the event object.
It's called prevent default.
So e if I'm calling my event object e dot prevent default.
And what this will do when we execute it is prevent the default behavior.
And the default behavior in this case, with a form when it submitted, is to continue sending on your
data, sending a request to whatever URL we specified in our case, slash know as a get request.
So now if we try it, let's see if it works.
I click submit, we get the alert and we don't go anywhere.
Our form has not actually submitted the submit event has run, but we haven't actually submitted data
anywhere.
And this leaves us free to now extract data.
If we wanted to get all the data at once and send it to an API using Ajax using a client side request.
Again, something we haven't learned yet, but the point is we have the flexibility to do something
with the data and we can still capture these submit event.
And what's nice about doing it this way as opposed to capturing each input as it changes every single
time.
Like we could have a key down or key press on here and any time this input changes, we could create
a variable in our JavaScript that is in sync with that.
And any time you select a different option, we could immediately update that variable or a second variable,
but that means attaching a bunch of event listeners.
We need to attach one here, one to the checkbox, one here, and then one for the submission as well.
But by adding a submit event listener, there's just one event we're waiting for.
We tell it not to behave the way it normally behaves, and then we can extract our data in here.
So why don't we take a look at the event object for just a moment.
I'll open up my console.
We'll click submit.
Let's put some data right there.
Let's select carrot, submit, we get our alert, here's the event.
Notice it has type set to submit and then we have the target here.
Target is the form that was submitted and we also have this property called Default Prevented, which
is set to true because we did prevent default.
All righty.
Now that we have the submit event and we're preventing default, let's extract the data from the form
and do something kind of trivial with it.
So to extract the data, we need to be able to select the individual elements.
So we've got an input, another input with type equals checkbox and then these select.
So why don't we start with the text and put that one to easy enough, I'll select them all.
So const what we call it credit card number, let's go with credit card equals, document dot, query
selector.
And did we give IDs to these inputs?
It will be easiest if we just do an ID.
Let's do credit card or CC for the checkbox.
Let's go with.
Hmm.
I agree to sell my soul to your company terms check or something or just terms.
And for our select, let's go with ID of veggie.
Okay.
And then we'll go into our app, guys.
We'll select based off of that ID credit card.
We'll also select the other options.
So we had credit card, then we had terms check or what do we want to call that terms checkbox, credit
card input, maybe just to be more descriptive.
And this was the ID of terms, and then we have the VIJI select with the ID of Fiji.
So now we have our three inputs.
What we would do in here is probably just access each one of those input values, although they do differ
a little bit because we have a regular input, a text input, so why don't we console that log credit
card input value and maybe we'll just add CC comma so we can see both of them.
So we can see what we're printing out.
Then to get the checkbox, how do we get the value from a checkbox?
Well, why don't we start with just doing terms checkbox?
We'll print out terms.
And then for the last one we have vegie select, veggie select.
And then here we'll do vegie select dot value.
Let's see what we get.
So I'll refresh.
Let's fill something out in here.
Credit card number.
Just make up a fake number.
Then we'll do.
Let's do.
Agree and go with asparagus.
Submit.
And here's what we have credit card.
We got the value out correctly for terms we got on, which is the checkbox here.
I submit again we still get on even though it's not checked anymore.
So value maybe isn't what we want to use.
I'll show you the the better attribute in just a moment or the better property and then vegie select.
We did get asparagus notice we're getting the value we set.
So it's eggplant with a capital E, but the value I gave as an attribute was eggplant lowercase E.
So this is what we're getting.
We're not getting this here.
And if we go back to our app, JJ's, instead of printing out terms checkbox value, there is a property
called checked on inputs with type equaled check or type equal to check, and it's a boolean property.
So we've got false.
Now we've got true.
Cool.
So we have our data.
We could put it in variables.
I won't spend too much time here doing that because it really just depends on what you're trying to
do with it.
But we have access to the data from that form.
But the point here is that we can stop, prevent default from a form submission and then tap into the
form or to the inputs, get the values we want, and then do something else.
We could send form data to database or append something to page using form data.
It's totally up to you, but the process looks like this.
We have a submit event on a form.
We prevent the default which I like to put up top.
Just so it's clear, you can see it's still working the way we had it written, but it makes it very
obvious what we're doing.
First, we're stopping default submission behavior for a form and then we're extracting the information
we want.