Next up, two very similar events that are pretty useful.
They're called input and change on input on change are the respective properties.
They have to do with inputs like we have here, a text input, a select, a checkbox.
And what I want to show you is that we can actually listen to changes across all three of these different
types of inputs or different form controls using a single event type.
And our goal here is to, let's say, create a data structure that looks like this.
It's an object that will automatically stay in sync or we'll stay updated with whatever a user is typing.
So instead of waiting for a user to hit submit like we did in the previous video where we grab the data
from each input after they submit the form, we could instead just keep in sync and know exactly what
is happening in each input.
So we would have an object with maybe a key of credit card and it would be equal to whatever is in that
input.
We could have the checkbox of terms and then that could be set to true and Fiji could be set to carat.
And then as soon as one of these changes, if the user checks the checkbox, we want it to go to false
immediately.
We don't want to wait for a submission event.
So to do this we can use the input event.
The type of the event is called input.
I'll show it to you now.
We'll do an event listener input and then we'll do an arrow function.
This time let's console that log.
E Well, let's start with credit card changed and then we'll print out the event.
I'll refresh and you'll see as soon as I change this input here, anything which is basically whenever
I type a character in here, we get a new console.log.
So the input has changed.
We also have input target, which tells me what the input actually is or what what triggered this event,
what the object is.
And if I wanted to create this data structure, I could have const form data, set it equal to an object
and then update form data of let's go with credit card, maybe all lowercase CC equals and then to get
the value it's event dot target dot value, which is the target element, the input itself.
Scroll down, we'll see the value.
Where are you?
V Keep going.
I got carpal tunnel already from that scrolling.
Here we go.
That's the value.
Or I could have just hardcoded it as credit card input value.
But I'm going to go with event target value because you ll see in just a moment that we could actually
refactor this into a single callback.
So I'll type something in here.
Let's look at our form data and it's up to date now.
We could do the same thing, duplicate this for the vegie select.
So vegie select add event listener for the input event which will trigger whenever we change the value
of that select.
So instead of credit card changed, we'll say veggie changed and let's add to form data under the key
veggie.
So I'll change this value and we get our console.log.
If I look at my form data object, it has veggie of carrots, but as soon as I type something in here,
we look at form data.
Now it has the credit card value from that input and it has the selected veggie.
So it's staying up to sync, staying up to sync, staying, staying up to date or in sync with what
we have.
And we can do one more for the checkbox, which is a little bit trickier.
Not really, but we can't use the value.
We'll use the checked attribute or the checked property terms checkbox that add event, listener input
event and we'll do console.log checkbox and then we'll print the event and for form data.
If we want to update the form data, let's go with agree to terms maybe and set that equal to event
target.
We can't do value because it's a checkbox we do checked which we saw very recently.
So let's try it.
I check it, let's look at form data.
Agree to terms is true.
I change this.
We'll look at form data.
Vegie is carrot.
I type something in here.
We look at form data again.
And there we go.
It's staying up to date.
So now we have this object that is staying in sync with whatever is going on in the form.
So we don't have to wait for a user to click submit.
We could wait for them to submit to send the data off or to do something with the data.
But we have a live representation.
Well, it's not live, but a in-sync representation of what's in the form.
And this is how we could achieve something like this.
Credit card form from code pen.
As I type, the numbers are updating up top, although they're also being obfuscated.
So they're not fully showing.
But whatever I type is being affected and displayed live so it's not waiting for me to submit and I'll
add in a cardholder name that's updating up there.
I can put in the security code and that's showing on the back.
It's a pretty cool form, but what I'm trying to illustrate here is that these events are all being
triggered before a user submits the JavaScript, knows what's going on in these inputs as I type, which
is what we have here.
It's just there's no functionality and nothing pretty to look at, but we're doing the same thing.
So I did mention there's a better way of writing this.
This is three separate event listeners, which is fine.
We need to attach an event listener to each one.
What is not great is that we're hard coding these in.
It would be nice if we could have one where I could say something like in the event listener in the
callback where I could figure out which input we were working with, take that input, get its value,
and then just store that in the form data dynamically, which we can do.
And here is the simplest way of doing that.
Uncomment these out.
So we have them.
We'll add a name to each input.
So the first one will have maybe credit card as a name.
The second one will have a name of agree to terms, and the third one will have a name of selected veggie.
So we have three names now in our JavaScript.
We can loop over all three of these, so I'll make an array with credit card input terms, checkbox
and veggie select and I'll loop over that for let input of.
And then I'll do an input add event listener for the input event.
We have our event here an arrow function and on this event object we have event target, which we've
already seen.
There's a property called name.
So why don't I console.log that?
We'll try running it when this changes.
Selected veggie was the name here agree to terms.
So the name here credit card is the name so we can use that name to add to our form data object.
So it would be something like this.
Form data of event target name equals event dot target dot value.
We're taking whatever that value is and adding it in under the name that is on the input.
There's still a minor problem because our checkbox doesn't have the value we want it to have.
But if I do asparagus change my credit card number to lol.
We'll look at form data over here and look at that.
Selected veggie is asparagus credit card is low lol and I didn't have to actually reference any of those
manually so I could have ten different inputs and automatically, as long as I give them a name, their
input value will be added to my object under their name.
Now as far as the checkbox, this one is kind of annoying.
Unfortunately, there is no value on a checkbox.
It's just set to on whether it's on or off.
We still get on, which is pretty obnoxious, but we can write a little bit of an edge case into this
function where we can check if the type of the input is a checkbox.
So if we console.log ea refresh my page, I'll check this.
If we look at event target, scroll way down.
Every input here has type of checkbox.
Not every input, but every input has a type.
In this case, it's a checkbox.
Here if I do the text input, which is for credit card and we take a look, where are you, target,
scroll down, we can find type.
It's set to text so we could write a little bit of a conditional to check what type is equal to.
And what I would probably do is de structure target.
That's the only thing we care about from the event.
So use a parameterized de structuring.
I don't even know if that's the right term for that, but the structure in the parameter definition
and then I'll structure even more, I'll grab the name, I'll grab the type, the value and the checked
property out of target, which is event target.
And then I can update this to B form data of name equals event target value.
But I want to check first if type is equal to checkbox.
If that's the case, then we'll store the value of checked.
Otherwise we store value.
So this is kind of a maybe hacky one liner, but we're taking the name, whatever the name is, credit
card input or credit card I think is what we went with.
And then we have a type which should be set to text for that input.
We have a value which is whatever is in the input and checked won't exist for that input because it's
not a checkbox.
So then we're taking form data, we're updating the property credit card, which is the name, and we're
checking if type is equal to checkbox.
It's not, so we'll use the value.
But then if we change the checkbox checked, we'll have a value.
True or false and type will be checkbox.
So this is true and we'll store the boolean true or false from checked.
So let's console that log form data here.
Extra se refresh.
I'll check it.
Agree to terms true.
Check again.
False.
Now we have selected veggie is carrot type something in here it's updating automatically, which is
pretty cool.
You have one function, one callback that we are using and it's working on three different inputs.
And I could have more if I had four or 510 different inputs here.
I could use this same code if all I wanted to do was create an object containing the form data.
The last thing is that I mentioned we have input and change to different events.
If I just switch this over to be a change event, it will still work pretty much the same way we've
got selected veggie asparagus.
This is updating, but here this won't update until I lose focus.
So I just clicked away or if I hit enter.
So just typing in the input doesn't trigger that event.
But focusing or losing focus, which is called blurring the input or hitting enter, will change it.
Otherwise these two are the same.
You can't really incrementally change the checkbox or the select.
It's just yes or no.
But with a text input there is a difference between the change event and the input event that we had
earlier.
So input will just always update whenever this updates or whenever the input itself has any new characters
in there, it triggers the event.
All right.
So two different events and a new pattern.
This is pretty common, especially if you get to something like React and some of these other frameworks
out there in other libraries, you'll see code kind of like this where we use the name of an input as
a key to store the value from that input under to create a nice object that contains all of our form
data at once.