In this video, we're going to discuss the first application we're going to build.
The goal of this application is to practice your JavaScript skill set.
We're not going to be covering a lot of new features of the language.
Instead, we're going to be focusing on a lot of the stuff that we've already learned and really practicing
our skill set.
Let's take a look at some mock ups to help you get an idea of what we're going to try to build.
So we're going to be making an application called Movie Fight.
The idea here is that a user is going to search for a movie on the left hand side of the screen and
a different one on the right hand side of the screen.
So a user is going to type in some movie title and then once they search for it, we're going to fetch
some information about that movie and show information about it on the left hand side of the screen.
So in this case, a user might have searched for Dark Knight.
And so I would pull up some information about the movie The Dark Knight.
This little box right here with an X represents the image or the movie poster for The Dark Knight movie.
So we're going to show the poster for the movie right there and then some stats about the movie underneath
it.
So, for example, how much money it made and its critical, critical rating and so on.
Once a user searches for a movie on the left hand side, they're then going to repeat that same process
on the right hand side.
So we can imagine that a user might type in a different movie over here like The Avengers, and we will
show some information about The Avengers in a very similar fashion on the right hand side.
Now, here's what makes this application an actual like movie fight application.
For every different stat that we fetch about every different movie, we're going to compare them between
the two.
Whichever movie has a higher statistic we're going to highlight in Green, in whichever movie has the
lower statistic we're going to show in yellow.
So in this case, The Avengers made a lot more money at the box office than The Dark Knight.
So we would color that statistic as green and we would color the Dark Knight statistic as yellow.
However, the Dark Knight might have a higher critic rating, so we'll show that as Green and The Avengers
one will be displayed as yellow instead.
So that's the application.
There is one last thing I want to mention here, kind of a very specific thing, because we actually
are going to be spending a pretty good amount of time on this when a user searches for a movie.
Like in these two inputs right here, a user might not know exactly what movie they're looking for.
They might have some kind of idea of what the title is, but they might only be able to remember that
like has dark in the title if they are trying to find Dark Knight.
So these two inputs right here are not going to be normal inputs.
Instead, we're going to make them into kind of autocomplete inputs.
So whenever a user types in something like Just Dark or even Dark Knight, we're going to have a little
pop up listing right here that shows a couple of different movies related to the search term that they
just entered.
So to actually select a movie and start the comparison, a user would have to click on that entry right
there, and that would select The Dark Knight that was made in the year 2008.
On the left hand side of each of these movie titles.
We're also going to show the poster for the movie as well.
This is going to be a separate little autocomplete widget that we put together as a part of this project.
We're going to build that autocomplete widget from scratch, and as a matter of fact, everything you
see in this application is really going to be from scratch.
So we're going to get a really good idea of how to approach this app, how to build it, and eventually
we're going to deploy it.
Okay.
So I hope you're as excited as I am.
This is going to be a really fun application.
So let's take a quick pause right here and start working in the next video.