Now that we have a better idea of what we're trying to build, let's get started working on this application.
Before we write any code, however, I want to go through a couple of different steps here to make sure
that we've got a really solid plan on how we're going to tackle this application.
The first thing we're going to do is set up a little boilerplate for our project.
So attached to this video there is a zip file that has some starter files inside of it.
If you haven't downloaded that zip file already, then pause the video and download the zip file.
Right now I've already downloaded that zip file and I've extracted its contents onto my computer.
So inside of that zip file are three different files the indexed HTML file, a JavaScript file, and
a CSS file.
Once you get those files on your computer, make sure you also open them up inside of your code editor.
So I've already done that right here.
Here's the HTML file, the JavaScript file, and the CSS one.
And then finally make sure you open up the indexed HTML file inside of your browser.
Once you do so, you're going to see a initial screen like this right here.
Okay.
So once we've got that all set up, I want to very quickly just mention exactly what this term boilerplate
is referring to.
When we talk about a boilerplate package, we're talking about some essentially starter code for a project.
Usually a boilerplate will have a little bit of setup already done inside of it, and usually it's going
to have some code or HTML or styling that is generally kind of repetitive between different projects.
So it's really just a good starter point to begin from.
I know that sometimes using a starter package is kind of annoying and you might prefer to write out
everything from scratch so you really understand what is going on.
Just so you know, the only real setup that I've done inside of this little boilerplate package is,
for the most part, just some styling.
So just some CSS to make sure that the end product that we end up with is going to look really nice.
This is a course about JavaScript and not CSS, and that's why I did all the CSS for you up front.
You can't, of course, review that CSS file at the end of this application and get a better idea of
what's going on inside there if you want to.
Okay.
So now that we've got a little bit of setup done, let's take a pause right here and then identify some
challenging aspects of this project in the next video.