Whenever I start working on a new project, either a personal project or a professional one, I really
like to sit down and identify some of the big problems that I anticipate that I'll run into as I'm working
on that project.
So I want to do that right now.
Really quickly, we're going to identify some of the more challenging aspects of this application and
get an idea on how to solve each one.
I've already gone through and thought up some of the big kind of challenging things that we're probably
going to have to wrestle with as we build this app.
So we're going to talk about some of these big challenges and then go over some possible solutions to
each of them as well.
So the first thing we need to think about is where we're going to actually get some information about
different movies.
I want to show real data inside of this application.
I don't want to just like make up movies or anything like that.
There's probably two obvious ways that we could handle getting some information about movies into our
application.
The first obvious way, and this is probably not a good one, would be to write in or hard code some
information about a bunch of different movies right into our JavaScript file.
So we could create a really big array and write in some movies like maybe the hundred most popular movies
out there directly into that array.
That's not really a good solution, however, because it means that any time that we wanted to add in
more movies, we would have to make a change to the source code of our application.
In general, that's not really a good thing to do.
So instead, I think that we should attempt to fetch some data about movies inside of our JavaScript
code.
When I say fetch, I mean let's make a network request to some outside API.
So we should try to find some outside API or essentially a server that will give our application a list
of movies that we can search over or show details from.
So for that, we're going to be making use of an API called the IMDB API.
This is a free API that we can use to get information about different movies.
I'm going to open up a new browser tab and it navigate over there right away.
Okay.
So you can read over the documentation here.
This API essentially exposes two different endpoints for us to use.
If we scroll down a little bit, we can see parameters right here and this will describe the different
ways that we can access movie information.
We can either search for movies.
So that would be reading from this by search category right here.
Or alternatively, we can look up very specific movies if we know the ID or the title of a movie.
So these two operations match up with our application really, really well.
Just think about it for a second.
If we go back over to our mockups over here, there's really two different operations that are going
on around these movies inside of our application.
The first distinct operation is when we do a search with the autocomplete.
So when a user types in there, we need to essentially try to find movies that match a given search
term.
So that's really a searching operation.
We want to find a big list of different movies that match that particular term.
When a user finds the appropriate movie and clicks on it, we then want to fetch some additional information
about that very particular movie right there.
And then we're going to take that additional information and show it on the screen.
So again, it's really a two step operation.
We first are going to do a search and then we're going to do a very distinct lookup.
Now, you might be curious why we have to do both a search and a lookup and not just a search by itself.
In other words, if we're already doing a search for a bunch of movies and getting information about
like ten different movies as we are putting in results into that autocomplete, can't we just use that
same data that we just fetched to put on the screen?
Well, as a quick side note here, the way that a lot of API's work is to give different sets of data
depending upon whether you're doing a listing action or a show action or trying to get information about
one record.
Let me tell you more about what I mean.
So in this diagram, I've got some imaginary search results from two different operations on an API.
On the left hand side is the set of information that we might get back if we do a search or a listing
or what we refer to as an index operation.
So this is what we would see if we tried to get a list of different movies.
We might just get a very limited set of attributes about every movie, like just the ID of the movie
and just the title.
So when we do an index or a search operation, we very frequently don't get the full listing of information
about every individual record.
Instead, if we want to get the full listing and we want to understand every attribute that a movie
has, we usually end up having to do a follow up request where we say, Hey, give me some details about
the movie with ID number one, and then the API will probably respond with a full set of attributes,
essentially everything that it knows about that particular movie.
A very easy way to understand this is to just think about Google search results.
When you do a Google search, you don't see an entire Web page.
Instead, Google just shows you some high level attributes of every Web page that it founds that excuse
me, that it finds that matches your query.
If you want to actually get some details about any given Web page, you actually have to click it.
And so that would be like a selection or a show operation.
So it's going to be the exact same thing with the API we are using.
We're going to have to do initially a search to find some records that match the user search term and
then a follow up request to get information about the very particular movie that a user selected.
Okay.
So that's big challenge.
Number one, don't worry.
The other challenges are a little bit easier to understand.
So the second big thing that we're going to have to do is to build an autocomplete widget from scratch.
There's definitely some pre completed or pre-built widgets out there online that we could download and
use inside of our code.
However, it would be a really good learning opportunity to put together our own autocomplete, so I
think we should do that inside of our project.
Now, I don't really have a lot to say about this challenge until we really start tackling it and writing
code.
But I think that at least at a minimum, you and I should really sit down and really agree on how an
autocomplete widget works in general.
If we just try to write out some autocomplete logic right away, well, you and I might have really
different ideas about how an autocomplete works.
And even like you personally, you might have some idea about how an autocomplete works, and then you
might start writing some code and then realize that the code you're writing doesn't really match up
with what you thought personally about an autocomplete.
So in other words, I think that we really just need to sit down and say, this is how an autocomplete
widget works.
So we're going to do that in a separate video.
Okay.
Last thing here.
The app would definitely look a lot better with styling and CSS.
Like I mentioned, the starter kit that we're using has a CSS, a little bit of CSS written into it,
and it also makes use of a CSS framework called CSS.
So this is stuff that has already been wired up for you.
We're going to have a quick discussion or two about CSS as it pertains to this application.
In particular, we're going to take a little look at MOMA, CSS, just really as a side topic.
Again, this is a course about JavaScript.
Nonetheless, you might be curious about it.
So we'll do a little quick aside just to understand what's happening with this thing.
Okay.
So that's it.
That's our big challenges.
So let's take a pause right here.
Now that we have a better idea of what we're trying to build, we've identified some of the hard things
about this project.
We're going to get started writing code in the next video.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.