All right, my friends, in this video, we're going to start writing some code.
The first thing we're going to do is to make sure that we can reach out to the IMDB API and do a search
for some different movies.
That's a very core operation inside of our app, so we should probably make sure that we can get that
working right away to make use of this free API.
I'm going to first navigate to IMDB API inside my browser.
Once here, we first have to sign up for the API and get what is called an API key.
The API key essentially identifies us to the API whenever we make a request.
We can think of it as like an email and password that our code is sending over to the API.
To get an API key, we're going to go up to the very top menu and find the section that says API key.
It is free to generate an API key.
All we have to do is enter in our email address.
So I'm going to select the free option right here.
And then I will enter in my email.
It does have to be a valid email because they're going to email us our key.
So I'll put in my email, my name and for use right here, we're just being asked to enter a description
of what we are building.
So I'm just going to say that this is API practice.
It doesn't really matter what we put in there.
I'll then submit this and then I'll be told that.
There we go.
I'm going to be sent a verification link to my email.
So you're going to now open up your email account and you're going to find an email that was just sent
to you.
So I'm going to pull up my email really quickly.
Here it is right here.
You'll see that I am given my API key.
That is essentially my password right there and it identifies me to the API.
Before we can use that key, we do have to click the link at the bottom of the email, so make sure
that you do click that link right there.
Now I'm told that Mikey has been activated.
Okay.
Very good.
So make sure you keep that key up on your screen.
We're going to use it in just a moment before we use the key.
However, let's take another look at the documentation for this API and get a better idea of how we
do a search operation.
So I'm going to go back to the main page and then scroll down a little bit.
So to access the API, we're going to make a request to that URL right there.
When we make the request, we have to include the API key that we just signed up with.
In order to customize the request, we're going to also pass in some number of different query string
parameters.
Remember, parameters are essentially added on to the very end of a URL.
We're going to be using a library that is going to add in these different parameters for us automatically.
But to do a search operation.
We'll scroll down to the search section.
And we are being told right here that if we add in a query string parameter called SW and assign it
some string, that is going to be interpreted as the movie title that we are trying to search for.
So this documentation is not the most clear in the world, but that's okay.
Well, let's go back over to our code editor and we're going to start to write out some code to make
a search request.
And this documentation will very quickly start to make sense.
Okay.
So back inside my code editor.
I've already opened up my index JS file.
So I'm going to delete that console log that was inside there by default.
We're going to be making a network request here.
Remember that with JavaScript there are many different ways that we can make a network request.
We can use the built in fetch function that is included inside the browser, or we can make use of third
party libraries like the Axios library that makes making requests just a little bit easier.
In this case, we're going to be using Axios.
Again, just because it makes our life a little bit easier than using fetch directly.
Axios has already been wired up to this project.
You can find it referenced in a script tag inside of the indexed HTML file.
So in order to make our request, I'm going to first define a helper function that I'm going to call
fetch data.
I'm going to want to use the async await syntax with this thing when we make our request.
So I'm going to mark the function as async.
And then inside the function body I will write out Collins response is await Axios dot get.
So remember, the first argument to the Axios target function is going to be the URL that we want to
retrieve whenever we make a network request that is an asynchronous operation and we essentially have
to wait before we get some kind of response to continue running the lines of code directly underneath
that.
And that's why we have the await keyword right there.
We're going to eventually get back a response object that is an object that represents all the information
related to this request in response that we just made.
And inside of that response object is the data that we should be getting back from our API.
So as the first argument to Axios Doggett, I'm going to go back over to the API documentation.
I'm going to find where it says usage and I'm going to put in this URL right here.
Now, really important.
We're not going to copy in the API key part just yet, so I'm just going to get HTTP oh IMDB API.
So I'm just going to copy that and then put it in as the first argument.
So again, make sure you only have dotcom inside there like so.
Then to specify all the different parameters here, like our API key or the search string that we want
to use.
We're going to use some automated functionality inside of Axios.
So we could manually type out question mark, API key, blah, blah, blah right there.
But instead using Axios, we can write this out a lot more neatly by putting in a second argument of
an object.
Inside the second argument, we're going to put in a property called params.
And inside this thing, we're going to list out all the different query string parameters that we want
to pass along with the request.
So we can imagine that this object right here is going to be turned into a string and appended to the
end of that URL.
Inside a params, we're going to first list out our API key.
A really important notice that we have a lowercase key on here.
It is not uppercase, so everything is lowercase.
And then I'm going to put in the API key that I just got from my email a moment ago.
So here's the API key.
Right there.
I'm going to copy it and paste it in.
I'm also going to specify that SE property se essentially stands for search.
That is the property we just looked up on the API documentation.
So this is going to be a string of the movie that we want to search for.
I'm going to first try looking for The Avengers, so I'll put in Avengers like so.
Okay.
And that should be it.
That should be all we need to make our request.
Now, if this params object right here is a bit mysterious, don't sweat it.
As soon as we make the request and look at it inside of our browser, you're going to very quickly understand
what that part is all about.
Okay.
So after we make the request, I'll then do a console.log of response data.
Again, remember that whenever we make a request with Axios, this is an object that has a lot of different
properties inside of it that describe the request in response we just issued.
The only property that we usually care about is the data property, and that's the actual information
that we just got back from that API.
All right, so I'll save this one last thing.
Let's make sure we call fetch data at the bottom.
So I'm going to save this now flip back over to the browser.
I'm going to go back to my indexed HTML page.
I'm going to open up my console.
And then refresh.
And sure enough, right away I see a response from that API.
Now, if you do not see a response right here, if you instead see some kind of error message, make
sure, first off, that you have in fact activated your API key so that you went into your email and
clicked on that link.
Secondly, make sure that you've got a lowercase API key right here.
Make sure that you've got the correct URL right there.
And essentially just do a direct comparison of this file.
So in sight of this response object that we got back, we have a search property and inside there are
all the different movies that match the search string that we just provided.
So I'm seeing a lot of different movies with the word Avengers in the title.
One thing I want to point out here is that you'll notice that we are just getting back a couple of different
properties about each movie.
So I'm only seeing the title, the type, whether it is a movie, a TV show or something similar.
The year that it was released, the idea of the movie and then very interestingly right here, a link
to the image for the movie as well, if I copy that and throw it into my browser really quickly.
We'll see the poster.
So this is what we're going to eventually show for each individual movie.
Now, one last thing I want to show you inside of my network request log.
If I open that up, I can search by air requests and this will show me only the request that my JavaScript
code have issued.
So there's the request that we just made to the API.
If I click on headers right here, it will show me the full request URL.
So you'll notice that Axios took that params object that we passed in to that configuration object.
It took the API key property and its value and the SW property and its value and it stuck them automatically
into the URL as a query string.
So again, this is what is kind of nice about using Axios.
If we were using fetch, we would have had to form that string by ourselves, by hand.
Not the worst thing in the world, but again, just a nice little benefit to using the Axios library.
Okay.
So now we've got some data.
I know this is a long video.
Don't worry.
Future videos will definitely be shorter for the most part.
So let's take a pause right here, and we're going to start to investigate our data that we just fetched
a little bit more.