I'm taking a look at the search results that we just got back from the IMDB API.
Inside of here, I'm looking at the very first result and I'm noticing that we've got just a couple
of different properties that represent this first search result.
One thing that's kind of interesting is that I don't see any information related to a lot of the stuff
that we need to actually make this application work correctly.
So for example, we want to make sure that we eventually show a short summary of the movie and the box
office take the critic rating and so on.
But none of that information is visible inside of this search result right here.
This goes back to a discussion that we had just two videos ago.
Usually whenever we make use of an API like this one, we got a one endpoint for doing a searching or
index operation and we are just seeing a very limited set of information about every search result that
we just got.
So if we now want to get more information about a very particular movie and get like the revenue or
the rating or whatever else, we have to do a follow up request.
So this would be referred to as a show action or a show request or something similar.
When we do this show request, we should hopefully be able to get a lot more information about one particular
movie at a time.
So let's take another look at the OMP API documentation and figure out how we can do a request like
the one over here on the right hand side and get all that extra information that we know that our app
is going to need.
So I'm going to once again go back to the documentation we were looking at by search previously.
This time I'm going to go up to buy ID or title.
So if we do a lookup for a single movie at a time, which is essentially this section right here, we're
going to get a bunch of information about just one particular movie.
To do this request, we're going to add in a new parameter called simply I lowercase I.
That is going to be the ID of a movie that we've already found through our search request.
So to do this request right here, we're going to go back over to our code.
I'm no longer going to pass in that string anymore.
That was if we wanted to do a search operation.
I now instead want to do a lookup operation.
So I'm going to put in I like so and then I have to put in the ID of the movie that I want to look up
to get the idea of a movie.
I'm going to go back to the search results that I was just looking at inside of my browser.
It looks like the ID of the movie The Avengers is TX zero eight.
Blah blah blah.
Right there.
So I'm going to copy that string.
And then paste it in as I like.
So.
So we no longer have an SE.
Instead we just have an AI that indicates the exact movie that we want to get information about.
So now save this.
I'm going to go back over to my browser once again, refresh.
And now I get information about just this single movie.
And inside of here is way more information than what we got before.
And inside of here is definitely all the information that we really need to make our application work.
So remember, we need to eventually get the.
And a search story or excuse me, synopsis right here.
We need to get the box office value and the critic ratings and so on.
And so inside of this result, we can see plot right here.
That is the kind of plot summary of the movie.
We can see the box office take right there.
So that's the amount of money the movie made.
And I can also see a rating right there.
So that's essentially the critic rating.
There's also a Metacritic METASCORE right here, which is another critic rating as well.
So again, this is the request that we're going to have to do.
Once a user selects on an individual movie or clicks an individual movie and we want to show a lot of
information about that single movie on the screen.
Okay.
So now that we understand the two different types of requests we have to make, let's take another pause
right here and we're going to start working on our UI in the next video.