We've now got a good understanding of how to make requests to that outside API and get some information
about some different movies.
So we're now going to turn our focus a little bit and start to think about how we're going to put together
that autocomplete widget.
Once we understand the autocomplete will then be able to just about go straight from start to finish
on writing out the code for this project.
So just one last little video here.
I put together a diagram on the behavior of this autocomplete widget.
This is a kind of confusing diagram, so we're going to go through it step by step.
But my intent here is to really clarify exactly how this autocomplete widget is going to work.
Once again, I really recommend that on your own personal projects, you go through a kind of process
like what I'm about to show you to make sure that you personally are 100% aware about the requirements
of the different things that you need to build inside of your application.
Once you start building diagrams like this, or you even have to make a diagram, just to be clear,
once you just start thinking through it, I can just about guarantee you that you're going to very quickly
start to realize there are quarter cases that are a lot easier to solve upfront, as opposed to if you
were just start to write code and then kind of run into some issue along the way.
Okay.
So we're going to start off this diagram on the very top left hand side, and we're going to think about
all the different ways that a user can interact with this widget.
So this is what the widget is going to look like when a user first loads up the page.
We're going to show them just a simple empty input.
We would refer to this as the default state.
In other words, this is what it looks like by default when the application first starts up.
At some point in time, the user is then going to start typing inside that input.
As soon as the user enters in some kind of full string and stops typing.
We're going to take that search string and make a request off to the API.
We're going to do a search request, get back some list of results like we just saw a moment ago.
We're going to take all those search results, open up a little menu underneath that input and render
out all the possible movies that the user might have been looking for.
As a quick reminder at these boxes with an X in them represent an image.
So that would be the movie poster for the movie The Dark Knight made in 2012.
Right away.
There is one other case we need to be aware of here.
It is entirely possible that a user user will enter in a search string, will do a search and not find
any results whatsoever.
So if we don't find any results, we're just going to say that we're going to close that menu entirely.
It might be a little bit better to show us some kind of error message to the user and tell them, Hey,
sorry, but we couldn't find any movies with that search term, but right now we're not going to worry
about that right away.
So we're going to say if we don't find any results, just hide the menu.
So that's kind of like step one, understanding what happens in the instant that the user starts to
type stuff in.
So now I want to kind of go further along the flow and think about the different ways that a user can
then interact with the widget.
After we show them that menu, the first thing they could do is press enter, thinking that that will
select some kind of record or something like that.
In this case, we're going to require a user to actually click on an element here to select it.
So we want to see a user click on like that movie or that movie or that movie to indicate which one
they want to select.
So we're going to require them to click on a movie and pressing the enter key is not going to do anything.
This is another one of those scenarios where you kind of have to sit down and think these things through
because otherwise you might build the widget and then press the inner key, expecting something to happen
and see that it does nothing and be kind of surprised.
So I'm saying from the get go that I don't want anything to happen if a user presses the enter key.
The next possible interaction is that a user does what we want.
They might click on an entry.
So if they click on an entry, that means that they have made their selection.
In that case, we're going to update the text inside of the input to the exact text of the title of
the movie that they just clicked on.
So, for example, if the user had searched for Dark Knight and then they clicked on The Dark Knight
with proper capitalization, we're going to take that full movie title right there, just the title,
not the year it was made.
We're just showing the year for convenience sake, for the user.
We're going to take that full title and stick it back into the input so that it's crystal clear exactly
what movie they were looking at.
Now there's one last possible way of interacting with this thing that we need to be aware of after a
user enters a search term.
If they enter a term and we open up that dropdown menu and show them all the options, they might decide
that they don't want to pick any movie.
They might decide, Yeah, I'm kind of done with this.
I don't want to select a movie.
I want to work on some other part of this application or something.
If that's the case and they click outside of the menu after it's been opened, then we're going to make
sure that we close the menu and do nothing else.
So this is one more of those scenarios where we really have to think through the lifecycle of the entire
widget, and it's helpful to do so before we start writing any code.
Okay.
So that's it.
That's the entire life cycle of this little autocomplete.
These are all the different scenarios that we really have to be thinking about now.
There definitely are one or two kind of other corner cases inside of this widget that we need to be
aware of that I kind of purposely did not add into this diagram because I want us to kind of run into
these little mysterious scenarios and point them out as kind of a learning experience.
So we might see one or two unexpected things crop up along the way.
All right.
Now that we understand what we're trying to do here and we understand the interaction with this widget,
let's take one more pause and then start writing some code in the next video.