Well, I think that we both understand exactly how this autocomplete widget is going to work in general,
at least how we're going to interact with it.
So let's start writing out some code.
The first thing we're going to do, or the first step is to just show a plain text input to the user.
Any time a user types inside there, we're going to initiate a search of our API and try to find some
corresponding list of movies.
So to get started, I'm going to go back over to my code editor and find my indexed HTML file.
At the very bottom.
I'm going to find a dive inside of here with the class of container.
You and I are going to add all of our HTML inside of this div.
The other HTML that you see right above it is responsible for just showing the header and we're not
going to have to mess with any of that stuff at all for this entire application.
So inside of that container, I'm going to add in an input element.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it.
That's all the HTML we have to add right now.
So I'll then go back over to the indexed JTS file.
And inside of here, we'll add in a little bit of code to select that input element.
Then we'll add in an event listener and we'll say that any time a user types inside there, we're going
to run our fetch data function and try to search for some particular movie.
So at the very bottom of the file, I'm going to delete the fetch data function call because we no longer
want to search the API automatically when our application first starts.
Well then select my input and assign it to an input variable.
So I'll say document query selector.
Input like so.
I'll add on my event listener.
So I'll do an input dot add.
Event listener and we're going to watch for the input event.
The input event is triggered any time that a user changes the text inside that input.
And that's exactly what we want.
Then as a second argument, I'll put in my callback function that's going to be called with some event
object.
So now remember, we can get access to the change text by referencing event target value.
That's going to be whatever the user just typed into that input.
So now if we want to try to search the API, we can take that variable right there and pass it as an
argument into fetch data.
We can then do a little bit of work on fetch data to make sure that it receives an argument and uses
that as the query string or as the query first search of the API.
So inside of my event listener, I'm going to call.
That's data.
With the value from the input.
Well, then make sure that I receive that as an argument to this function.
So I'll call that.
How about search term like so?
And then we will make sure that we pass that in as a parameter.
And right now remember that we refactored this params object to look up details about a very specific
movie.
If we want to look up a collection of different movies or do an actual search, then instead of an se
param right there or something that I premium, we will replace it with an s and that's just straight
from the documentation that we were looking at.
We can go back over really quickly if you want to and look at the search documentation.
If we want to do a search, we're going to add in an S parameter.
So then instead of searching for that very particular movie, ID will instead search for search term.
And that should be it.
So let's save this file.
I'll go back over.
I'm going to refresh the page.
I see my search input.
I'm also going to open up the network tab inside of my chrome console so that I can see all the different
requests that we're making to the API.
If I want to see only the request that our JavaScript code are issuing, we can click on the X Air button
right here, and that's going to filter by just requests that are being created from our JavaScript
code.
Well, then start to type inside of here and we'll see what happens.
So I'm going to search for Avengers a Venn.
Jr's like so.
Okay.
As soon as I started typing, I saw a collection of different requests being issued.
If I go to the very last request that was made, I can click on it.
I'll see the query string right there inside the URL says S equals Avengers.
All right, that's definitely good.
And if I click on Preview, I'll see that I definitely get some search results for The Avengers movie.
Perfect.
Well, it definitely looks like it's working out pretty well so far, but there's just one little issue.
We're doing a search of the API for every single key press.
Is that a problem?
I would say yes.
This is not really ideal.
The reason this is not ideal is that you and I only get to access the API 1000 times per day.
So we've got a hard cap on the number of times we can reach out to search for The Avengers.
I made a total of like 12 requests or so.
I even made a little typo in there, which means I had to make an additional three requests or so as
I fix the typo.
So I just ate up 12 out of my 1000 possible requests that I get to make for the entire day with that
one single query.
So what would be kind of nice is if we said, okay, as soon as the user stops typing for a little bit
of time, then let's go ahead and do the search automatically.
So in other words, if I type out Avengers and then just sit here for like half a second and don't type
anything more, let's make our request then, as opposed to doing a request for every single key press.
That's going to be a little bit of complicated logic.
Let's take a quick pause right here and figure out how we will implement that in the next video.