In the last video we saw that we were making search requests to our API way too often.
So in this video we're going to figure out how to somehow fix this behavior.
Just make sure it's really crystal clear what we're going to try to do.
Let me show you a couple of quick diagrams.
So this is our current behavior right now.
Every single time there is a key press, we do a search to our API.
And this is not ideal.
This is not what we want.
So instead, this is a little bit closer to the experience that we want to have inside of our application.
We want to allow the user to press the key inside that input as many times as they want.
And only after we go through about 1/2 or so of nothing happening do we want to eventually call the
search function.
So in other words, let the user press as many times as they want.
If they then stop for 1/2, then go ahead and call search.
There's two ways that we can implement this functionality.
We can add either add in a JavaScript library that will do this for us automatically, or we can write
out some code where we will just figure out how to do it ourselves.
And I bet you can guess which we're going to do.
We're going to figure out how to implement this from scratch on our own.
It's actually a little bit simpler than you might think, but to implement this, we first need to get
a little bit of background on the set time out function.
Chances are you've already taken a look at the set timeout and function in JavaScript before.
But I just want to give you a quick recap on how set timeout works in general.
So I'm going to write out a little bit of test code inside my console.
Back over here.
So inside my console, inside my browser, I'm going to use the set timeout function.
I can use it by calling set timeout.
I'm going to pass in an arrow function to it as the first argument.
And inside of that arrow function, I'll do a console log of.
Hi there.
Like so.
The second argument to the set timeout function is a delay.
That's going to specify how long we want to wait before we run that function right there.
The one with console.log.
So as the second argument to set time out, I'm going to put in 1000, which means that I want to wait
1/2 or 1000 milliseconds before executing that function.
So if I run that, I'll wait for about a second and then I see hi there appear I can adjust it up to
5 seconds and that will wait 5 seconds before that function is invoked.
The important thing to keep in mind around set time out is that any time we call it, we get back an
integer value.
So in the first case we got out of set time out a value of one.
In the next case, we got out a value of two.
These numbers are essentially identifiers and they identify the timer that we just created.
If we want to, we can call the clear timeout function to stop that pending timer and prevent that function
from being called.
So I'm going to set up another timeout and I'm going to give it a timeout of 10 seconds.
Like, so that's going to give me more than enough time to write out some code very quickly to clear
the timer that I set up with this line of code.
So I'm going to run that.
And then very quickly write out clear time out with three likes.
So.
When I call clear time out of three, that means look at the timer that was created with the idea of
three.
So the timer that was created with an idea of three was this one right here.
So I'm saying stop that running timer and don't call that function ever even after 10 seconds pass.
So that's just a quick reminder on how set timeout and clear timeout work.
Now that we understand or have a quick reminder on that, let's go back over to our code and we're going
to add in a little bit of code to add in this behavior right here.
Okay.
So back inside my index file, I'm going to go down to where we added that event listener.
So the function that we kind of want to prevent from being executed is this whole function right here.
We want to stop that from ever running.
If a user is pressing on the keyboard too often.
So to add that in, I'm going to first assign that function to a new variable.
I'm going to cut the function out right above.
I'm going to create a new variable called on input and assign that function to it.
I'll then pass that variable.
As the second argument into the event listener.
So on input like so.
So what we have right here is 100% equivalent to the code we had before.
Now we can add in some logic to actually make sure that we don't call it input too often.
So to do so inside of an input, I'm going to first write above the function to clear a variable that
I'll call a timeout ID like.
So we're eventually going to take one of those IDs so we get from calling set timeout like the ones
we saw back over here, one, two and three.
And we're going to assign one of those IDs to this variable.
Then inside this function, we're going to wrap the fetch data call with a set timeout.
So I'll say set timeout.
Like so.
I'll move my call to fetch data into the timeout function.
Then as the second argument to set time out, I'm going to put in 1000 milliseconds.
So if we ran our code right now, the only effect would be to make sure that we introduce a delay of
1000 seconds, 1000 milliseconds between typing something and actually calling fetch data.
That's the only change that would occur right now.
But we want to make sure that we don't run any code until the user stops typing for some amount of time.
So to implement that behavior, I'm going to take the timer that gets returned from calling set timeout
and assign assign it to timeout.
ID like so.
Now here's the magic line of code right above that.
So between on input and where we assign that timeout ID, I'm going to add in an if statement.
I'm going to say if.
I married.
Then clear.
Timeout.
Timeout ID.
That's the magic part right there.
Now you can kind of imagine what is going on behind the scenes here.
We're going to be calling on input many, many times in a row.
Just imagine a user typing in to the input like the word Avengers.
However many characters that is, we're going to call on input that number of times.
The very first time that on input is going to be called, we're going to enter this function.
We're going to take a look and see if timeout ID is defined.
The very first time that we call this function timeout ID is going to be undefined.
So we're going to skip over this if statement entirely.
We're going to go down to set timeout and set up a timer and say in 1/2, call fetch data.
So that's the very first key press.
We're then going to assign that timer to time out ID.
The users, then going to press on the second key on their keyboard.
The second time they press the key, we're going to once again enter this function.
And now when we hit the if statement, timeout ID will be defined.
So we're going to enter the if statement and we're going to stop that pending timer.
So we're going to stop the existing one and we're going to set up a brand new one.
But the brand new one is going to have a new value that it's going to call fetch data with.
That process is then going to repeat itself over and over and over again until we eventually go for
a full second before calling on input again.
In that scenario, we're not going to call a clear timeout.
This timeout is going to execute and fetch data.
We'll be called.
So let's save this and test out our code and see how it's doing.
I'm going to go back over to the network tab over here.
I'm going to search for Avengers again, so I'll put in Avengers like so, and I have to wait for about
a second after my last key press before I actually see a request being issued, which is exactly what
we want.
So now a user can be typing in here, they can make as many typos as they want, and we're not burning
through all of our credits on our API.
That looks pretty good.
Now, last thing I want to mention is that we can very easily make sure that we execute the search a
little bit more quickly by just adjusting that 1000 milliseconds right there so we can instead go to
500.
And now we are going to do the search twice as quickly after the user stops typing.
Now I can put in Avengers and I'll see the search up here right away.
So this looks pretty good.
Let's take a quick pause right here and continue in the next video.