In the last video, we added in some code to make sure that we only call our search function after the
user stops pressing on their key inside that input for about 1/2 or so.
This entire process right here is referred to as D bouncing an input.
So this is when we are going to wait for some amount of time to pass after this last event before we
actually run some function.
There's actually many different scenarios in which we might want to d bounce some event inside of a
web application, not just for text inputs.
So there might be some other scenarios that we want to limit how often we call it in order for performance
reasons.
Exactly like what we just did for our API.
Because of that, I think that it might be useful to think of some way to refactor the code that we
just wrote right here and make it more reusable in nature.
Because like I just said, it might turn out that we have to balance other things inside of our application
at some future point in time.
And I don't know about you, but this code right here is kind of hard to read and hard to understand.
So it would be nice to make this more reusable and kind of hide the complexity or hide the implementation
of the actual bouncing logic.
So that's exactly what we're going to do.
We're going to refactor this into some more reusable fashion so that we don't have to think about these
like really complicated set time out and clear time out calls and whatnot.
Now, before we start to write this code, I want to show you a diagram to just help you understand
how this refactor is going to work, because it is going to be slightly complicated.
So here's what we're going to do.
Right now, we are essentially trying to de bounce the on input event or the on input function.
We're saying that we don't want to receive any notifications of a change to that input after until after
some amount of time occurs.
So we kind of want to guard access to the on input function.
So to make that happen, we're going to create a new helper function called the D bounce function.
This D bounce function is going to be a little bit complicated for exactly one reason.
We're going to pass a callback or a function into this D bounce function.
The thing that makes it complicated is that the bounce function itself is going to return a function
as well.
That's what is complicated in my opinion.
Maybe that's really easy to understand, but I think it's kind of hard to grasp the very first time
you see it.
Now, like I said, we're going to pass a function into the bounce function.
That is something that is probably not going to be a big shock to you throughout this course.
We've seen several times already where we pass callback functions to other functions and heck, we're
already doing it.
Back over here we are passing a function into add event listener so that on input can be called at some
point in time in the future when the user inputs something into our text input.
So that part passing a function into another function, not that bad.
The only hard part to understand here is understanding that the balance is going to return a new function.
So this green box right here represents a new function.
It's like a wrapper of sorts that's going to restrict calls to the original on input.
So this input input right here is the same function as that one.
So again, this green box, it just restricts access to on input.
It might be better to visualize this using a slightly different diagram.
So in this diagram we still have the green box that represents kind of like a wrapper function of sorts
that restricts access.
So you can imagine that the green function, this wrapper kind of has like a shield of sorts, and it's
going to guard against repetitive, instantaneous calls to on input.
So if we start to call on input very quickly several times in a row, the shield is going to step in
and say, sorry, you can't get through.
You have to wait some amount of time before I'm actually going to execute your call.
So we can imagine that maybe 1/2 passes and we end up like down here.
And at that point in time, the shield is going to say, okay, you know what, most recent call to
on input, I'm going to actually let you through because 1/2 did pass and you were the last person to
call this.
So I'm going to let you through.
So again, we can imagine the green function right here as being like that little shield that's going
to deflect all those other calls.
So that's the idea.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to refactor our code and build out this balance helper
function.