In this video, we're going to define our D bounds helper function.
So right above the timeout ID, I'm going to make a new function called bounce like we just discussed.
This thing is going to take an argument of a function.
I'm going to refer to that as an argument called func short for function.
You could just as easily call it KB for callback or just callback itself, but I'm going to call it
func.
So then inside of here, we're going to return a function like so.
So this function right here, that is the wrapper.
That is the thing that is going to implement a little shield and guard.
How often func can actually be invoked.
So what you have right here, this is kind of the hardest part to understand.
All we have to do now is to finish up the implementation of the bounce is essentially take all the same
code that we have down here and stick it into the bounce.
So let's go through that step by step.
The first thing we're going to do just above the return statement is to fine, let timeout ID.
Then inside of our function.
So this is the function that we are going to be calling possibly many times in a row.
We're going to first check to see if timeout ID is defined.
And if it is, we're going to clear that timeout.
We're going to say sorry, previous execution.
Turns out you're not going to be actually running, so we're going to stop that thing in its tracks.
Then immediately after that, we're going to queue up a new execution of our underlying function, which
we can do by calling set timeout, passing it the function to run inside there we will call func like
so.
And then as a second argument to set timeout, we'll put in the delay that we want to have.
And then we're going to make sure that when we call set timeout, we take the timer that gets returned
and assign it back to timeout ID.
Like so.
And that's pretty much it.
There's just one less thing we have to take care of.
This function right here that we pass in might need to receive some kind of arguments.
So we essentially need to make sure that if we ever pass any arguments to this green wrapping function
that we intend to get over to on input, we essentially have to take the arguments that are being passed
to the green function and forward them on to on input.
So to do so very simply, like a real straightforward way of doing it, would be to say, okay, I'm
going to take in that first argument right there that I'll call simply ARG short for argument.
I'm going to take whatever that argument is and I'm going to pass it through to that func when it finally
actually gets called like.
So that's a very simple and straightforward way of doing that.
However, this approach right here will only work if we are passing in one single argument, and that's
possibly not always the case.
So to make sure that this works in all cases, we're going to use a little bit more fancier code.
We're going to say dot, dot, dot args, plural.
So this is going to take all the different arguments that are passed to the function.
Then down here when we call funk.
We're going to do funk apply with NULL and ARGs.
Remember what the apply function does?
Essentially says call the function as we normally would and take all the arguments or whatever is inside
of that array right there and pass them in as separate arguments to the original function.
So this right here, like the code that you see right here is 100% equivalent to if we had.
Instead, I'm going to make it very quick change here like argh!
One, ah, two, argh, three.
And then inside of here called func with arg one are two arg three 100% equivalent.
The only difference is that the apply way is going to automatically keep track of however many arguments
we need to actually pass through.
Only difference.
Okay.
So I'm going to go back to that point right there.
So that is the entire balanced function.
So now we can use this anywhere inside of our code, any time that we need to introduce some rate limiting
essentially on how often a function can be invoked.
So in this case, we want to limit how often on input gets invoked.
So let's take out all the time out code that we have inside of here right now, and we're going to instead
use our bounce function on it.
So I'll first begin by deleting timeout ID.
I'm going to delete the if statement.
I'm going to delete the timeout ID with set timeout.
And the closing brackets on their.
Then fix up the indentation a little bit.
And now we're back to a very simple, plain and easy to read on input function.
So now we can apply the D bounce function right on this thing right here so we can say I want to pass
in.
That function like so.
Now we can imagine that this thing right here is going to be received into bounce as funk and we're
going to rate limit it essentially on how often it can be invoked.
We're going to wait until some amount of time has passed before we actually invoke it.
And then the important thing to keep in mind here is that we are returning a new function so we can
take whatever gets returned from de balance and still continue to assign it to on input.
Now we just have a version of an input that can only actually be invoked once every second.
So we can still continue to pass that directly on through to our event listener like we were doing before.
Just you know, there's one other way that we could have applied de bounce.
We could have defined on input normally like we did before.
And instead applied to bounce when we pass it off to the event listener.
So we could have used the bounce.
Down here as well.
100% equivalent.
Same exact thing is just a question of where we are actually applying the de bounce logic.
We would want to apply it in this way, like when we actually use the function or pass it off somewhere
else.
If we expect it to call on input multiple different times from multiple different places and we only
want to to d bounce it in some scenarios.
Okay.
So let's save this and go do a quick test.
So I'll flip back over.
I'm going to search for Avengers.
I'll wait for a second and then I see the response appear.
So it looks like it's still working as expected.
Okay.
So one last little, little improvement we could add inside of here.
At present, we've got a hard coded delay of 1/2.
And chances are we would want to allow other developers who might be using this function to adjust that
more easily.
So an easy way to do that would be to say that we're going to take in a second argument to our bounce
function.
That second argument might be called something like delay, and that will be the number of milliseconds
we want to wait so I can use that delay argument in place of 1000.
Right there.
And now whenever I make use of de balance, I would just have to make sure that I pass in the number
of milliseconds to wait, like in this case, maybe just half a second like we had before.
So that would definitely work.
One last very small optimisation as well.
We could say that maybe we just want to have like a default delay amount and to do so we can use a defaulted
argument right up here.
So we could say something like equals 1000.
So now that means that if we ever make use of de balance without passing in that second argument, we're
going to get a default delay value of 1000 milliseconds.
But I'm going to go with 500 because I felt like that was pretty responsive when we tested it out inside
the browser.
Let's save that one last quick test here.
I'll search for Avengers and looks like we're good to go.
So that's it?
That is the bounce function from scratch.
Now, I want to say really quickly here, if this is really confusing and chances are it is, don't
sweat it.
Honestly, if you're going through this course right now and you're having a hard time with this function,
I honestly really expect you to have a hard time with this.
I really, really do expect this to be some challenging stuff.
The reason I'm showing it to you is that seeing hard code like this is how you get to be a better engineer.
If I just continue to show you a bunch of like Baby Easy code, that's really easy to understand.
You're never going to be a better engineer.
You have to look at the harder stuff like this.
It is what is going to make you into a better engineer.
So if it is hard, good, that is a good thing.
You want it to be hard if it's easy.
Hey, congratulations.
You understand what's going on?
So either way, don't feel bad.
If this is some hard stuff to understand, I really, really do expect it to be challenging.
Okay, so this all looks great.
We've got a great working D bounce function, so let's take a pause right here and continue working
on our app in the next video.