Our demon's function is all done.
But there's one last, very quick thing I want to do with it.
Our index file is already getting a pretty good amount of code inside of it.
Right now we're at just 29 lines of code and we've barely really begun to start our application.
So I think that we could be well served to move this bounce function out into a separate file.
Inside of my root project directory, I'm going to make a new file called Utils.
JS The idea behind this file is that I'm going to place any utility functions that I create inside of
here.
So this is just so I can better organize the code inside of my project.
I'm going to go find the bounce function.
I'm going to cut it, move it over to utils eggs and paste it.
I then need to make sure that I include the utilized JS file inside of my HTML document.
So I'm going to open up the HTML document.
I'm going to go down to the very bottom of the file.
I'll find the existing script tag for indexed JS and I'm going to copy it and paste it right underneath
itself.
I'll then find the first script tag and change the source to utilize JJ's.
So now whenever we load up this HTML document are going to first load up and execute all the code inside
of utils that will define the bounds function well then load up and execute indexed JS which has a reference
to bounce.
So we need to make sure that we define UTILS first or include that file first so that we can define
the bounce function before we run it inside of indexes.
Okay.
So let's save all these files and make sure all three are saved.
I'll then go back over to my browser, do a quick refresh.
I'll search for Avengers again, and I'm just going to make sure that I still see my data getting fetched.
And yep, I definitely do.
Okay.
Quick little change.
All good to go.
Let's take another quick pause and continue with our app in the next video.