Let's continue working on our autocomplete inputs.
At this point we are calling fetch data inside of the on input function.
Let's make sure that we return some useful data from fetch data.
Once we get some usable data back, we'll then make sure that we iterate over it.
And for every movie we fetch, we'll try to render out some content onto the screen.
After that, we'll then start to think about how we can select a video and by actually clicking on it.
So to make sure that we actually get some data back from fetch data.
Let's take a look at the fetch data implementation.
Here it is right here.
Right now, at the very end of the function, we're just console logging out our data, which is not
very useful.
Instead, we should probably return all the data that we have fetched, but more importantly, we need
to make sure that we only return the actual real data that we care about.
Let me show you what I mean by that.
If I go back over to my browser right now and do another search.
I'm going to see a council log of all the data that we get back inside of our request.
So this is the console data property.
It is an object that has a search property inside of it that is an array of objects.
So you and I don't really care about the response property.
We don't really care about total results.
All you and I really care about is the search property.
So from fetch data, we should really only be returning the search property and nothing else.
So I'm going to go back over.
I'm going to find fetch data.
I'm going to remove that console log and I will I will replace it with return response data search.
Now notice I'm using a capital S right here.
That is definitely not standard.
Usually in JavaScript we always have every variable preceding with a lowercase letter like.
So the only reason I'm using an uppercase s right here is that the response that we actually get back
from this API has a capital S in it.
And that's actually true with many of the different properties that we're going to see coming back from
the API.
This is very much non-standard in nature, so it is way more standard on any API to see all these different
property names with lowercase letters.
So in general you should expect to see lowercase letters at the start of every property name.
It just happens that this API author decided to use uppercase instead.
So unfortunately we have to follow that same convention at some locations inside of our code.
Okay.
So now whenever we call fetch data, we're going to get back our array of different movies we fetched.
So inside of on input, let's make sure that we take whatever comes out of fetch data and assign it
to a variable.
So let's say cost movies is.
That's data.
And then right after that, I'll do another console.log log of movies.
If we save this and run it, we're going to very quickly see something unexpected.
So, of course, let's do that right away.
I'll flip back over.
Refresh.
I'll run it again.
And now I see a console log of a promise.
So what's going on here?
I'm seeing a promise instead of an array of movies, which is what I kind of expected to see.
Well, remember, fetch data is an async function.
We marked it with the async keyword.
So whenever we call fetch data, it's going to take some amount of time to actually process this request
and then eventually return the data that we get back.
Right now, when we call fetch data, we are treating it as though it were a synchronous function.
So if we want to somehow wait on fetch data to actually get some data and get access to the response,
we have to treat it as though it were an async function.
So in other words, we need to put the await keyword right in front of it.
And now because we are using the await keyword inside the on input function, we have to mark that function
as being async as well.
So let's save this and try to run it again.
Buy Refresh and put in Avengers.
Now I can see my list of different movies being printed out.
Okay, so that's definitely better.
All right.
Now that we've got our data inside of on input, let's take another quick pause.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to start to iterate over our list of movies and turning
each one into a snippet of HTML and then throw it onto our document.