Now that we have all of our data inside the on input function, let's make sure that we can iterate
over this list of movies right here.
And for every movie that we have fetched, we're going to try to create a div element that kind of summarizes
the movie.
In particular, I want to take every movie that we fetch.
I want to get the poster printed out as an image on the screen, and I want to show the title for every
movie as well.
So let's get to it.
I'm going to remove that console.log and I'm going to replace it with a four of loop.
So I'll save for let movie of movies like so.
Now we can use a four of loop right here.
We could use a normal for loop.
We could use a while loop a for each map statement.
It's really up to you personally.
I rather enjoy using four of loops because they're really easy to see and pretty easy to understand
as well.
So as we start to iterate over this list of movies right here, we're going to get the movie variable
inside the loop.
So that movie variable is going to be the same objects that we're looking at inside of our console right
here.
So that right there is going to be the first movie variable and then we're going to go over the second
movie and then so on.
So now inside of my loop.
I'm going to create a div.
And then going to set the inner html on this div.
So I'll say div inour html.
I'm going to use a set of tactics here.
Like so because I want to have a multi lined string so I can nicely format my html though.
I want to write out make note that you are supposed to use back here.
We cannot use single quotes to form a multi-line string in JavaScript.
That would be a syntax error, so make sure you have a back tick character instead.
Then inside of here, I'm going to display an image that's going to show the poster for my movie.
To get the URL for this image or the CRC property.
Let's take another quick look at the movie object that we are working with.
So again, this is the movie object that we are currently working with right here.
Notice that it has a poster property and that is a URL to the poster image for this movie.
Also take note that it's poster with a capital P, so we'll need to make sure that we spell the property
with capital P inside of our code as well.
So back over here.
I'm going to set the Z on the image.
And remember to inject a JavaScript variable into a string formed with back ticks.
We use a dollar sign curly braces like so and we'll say movie dot poster with a capital P.
Now, this right here is not quite correct.
There's a very small gotcha in there.
In order to write out a correct image tag, we're supposed to write Z a set of double quotes and then
our link inside of there.
To whatever it might be.
Right now, if we ran this code right here, it would just take whatever the URL is and stick the URL
directly in without any double quotes.
So in other words, we would end up with something like that, which is not quite what we want.
Again, we want to have some double quotes around it.
So to make sure we get double quotes around, well, we have to put them in ourselves.
So I'm going to put double quote right there and a double quote on the other side.
Next up, I'm going to put an H one right after it.
Inside that one.
I'm going to try to show the title of the movie so we can get the title of the movie by referencing
the title property.
And again, notice that it has a capital T.
Inside the one.
I'll do dollar sign curly braces with movie title.
Okay.
So it looks pretty good.
So now the last thing we need to do is take the div we just created and insert it into our DOM somewhere
so that we can actually see it.
Let's go back over to our index.html and we're going to make sure that we create some element inside
there that's going to list out all these different divs that we are creating.
So I'll go back over.
I'll find where we have our class container and I'm going to add in a div with an ID of target.
This is not a really good practice right here to use an ID of Target because, well, we might end up
with many different targets, so to speak, or things that we want to render content to inside of our
application.
But to be honest, we're going to very quickly replace this div with something else like very, very
soon.
And that's why I'm just going to use it here very temporarily.
So now back after we create our div, we can use a query selector to select that element with ID of
target that we just added.
They'll do a document query selector.
I'll look for pound target.
And I'll append child the div we just created.
Okay.
And that should be it.
So I'm going to save this.
I'll go back over.
I'll refresh the page.
Then I'll do a search for Avengers.
And there we go.
So I can see my first poster right there.
I can see a title, the next one, and so on down the list.
So we can definitely at least show some content now.
However, I want you to notice that while I was typing this out, I also got an error over here, which
is kind of unexpected.
So let's take a quick pause.
It looks like everything worked but didn't quite work out quite as expected because we got an error.
So we'll come back in just a moment.
We're going to figure out why we're seeing this error message.
Then we're going to try to fix it.