I was able to successfully search for some videos at the very end of last video and then show them as
a list on the screen along with the title of each.
However, as I was typing out Avengers, I saw little air up here at my console right here.
So this is an error that you might or might not be seeing right now if you're not seeing it.
Let me show you how you can get that same error very quickly.
Try refreshing your app and select your search bar right there and then enter in a long, random string
of characters.
And as soon as you do, you're probably going to see an error just like that.
So what's going on here?
We are successfully making our request.
You can see that if you still have your network tab open.
But we definitely are seeing something around movies not being iterable.
Well, let's take a look at the actual response that we're getting back inside this request and we can
figure out why we're getting this error.
So if you select that, you're going to see a response object that looks like that right there.
It has an air property and a response.
So essentially we entered in a search term for a movie that has no results whatsoever.
So rather than giving us some kind of response that says, hey, here's the list of movies that we found
zero, like an empty array.
This API chose to tell us inside of this kind of inner message right here that no movies were found
whatsoever.
So we need to make sure that we go back over to our fetch data function or somewhere inside of our code
and handle this case in which we make request and don't get any results whatsoever.
One other thing I want to mention at this time as well is that the search functionality with these API
is not quite as great as you might expect.
So for example, we've seen several times that we can put in Avengers and get the correct result.
But if I only put in the word like a VPN, a VPN like so unfortunately.
Well, that one happened to like actually turn out.
There we go.
So if I do AV E and G, it's only part of the word Avengers on any normal search engine or search functionality.
I would still expect that to give me some results of like The Avengers, because that's part of the
word.
But unfortunately, this API doesn't really consider partial terms like AV, E and G, so it doesn't
match that with the movie Avengers.
And so when I put that in, I still get the same kind of response.
It says Movie Not Found.
So that's just something we need to be aware of.
As we are testing out our application, we really do have to put in a reasonable title of a movie in
order to see any kind of results whatsoever.
Okay.
So let's go back over to our code and we're going to figure out some way to fix up our code and handle
the case in which we don't get any results at all.
So back over here.
I think the most reasonable way to handle this would be to go to our fetch data function.
So inside of fetch data right here, right after we make our request, let's try to look at the response.
We're going to inspect response to data and we're going to see if there was an error that we're getting
back when we made the request.
One thing I want to kind of mention here is that the errors that we're talking about right now are not
like actual request errors.
A real request error would be like if we typed in an incorrect URL and we didn't get any kind of response
whatsoever.
That's not what is happening here.
In this case, the request is being issued successfully.
We're getting back a status code of 200, which means that everything with the request went A-OK.
So this is not really an error in the strictest sense of the word.
So in my opinion, this is not the best designed API.
Nonetheless, it's what we're working with.
So rather than handling an error in a classic sense, we're just going to check to see if the response
has an error property.
And if it does, then we're just going to return an empty array and say, well, turns out we didn't
find any results whatsoever.
So back over here.
I'm going to say if response dot data dot air like so.
And again, notice that we have a capital E because that is what the response is giving us.
So if there is an error, let's just return an empty array and essentially say we didn't get any movies
whatsoever to show to the user.
Okay.
So now let's try this again.
I'm going to refresh and I'm going to put in a very strange search term here.
So just a bunch of characters.
Now, I don't see anything on the screen and I don't have an air either.
So this is definitely what I would really expect.
If I don't get any results, I don't show any content whatsoever.
That might seem a little bit odd.
But remember, this is kind of the.
And a system that we agreed with right here.
We had said that if a user finishes typing and we find no results, we're just not going to show any
content.
In a perfect world, we would show the user some kind of error message and tell them that, or like
a warning or something like that and tell them, Hey, we didn't find any content, but right now this
is definitely good enough.
Okay.
So that we got that ear fixed up.
So another quick pause right here and we'll continue in just a moment.