We can now show a list of movie posters and the title of each respective movie.
So now all we really have to do, believe it or not, is kind of work on the styling a little bit.
In particular, we need to make sure that all these images are small, that they show up next to their
titles, and that they all appear in a kind of menu directly underneath that little input right there.
So to do so, we're going to use some CSS that is included inside of this project.
Remember, at the very start of this section, we downloaded a boiler plate project wired up inside.
This project is a CSS framework called Boma CSS.
Oma CSS has a collection of different CSS rules that allow you to very quickly style an application.
We're going to take a look at a component or essentially a set of CSS rules that are going to allow
us to very quickly turn the content that we have right here into what we're really looking for.
So I'm going to open up a new browser tab and navigate to this documentation.
Okay.
So if we go down on the left hand side just a little bit, we'll see a demo of what they call a dropdown.
Now, you might look at this and say, Stephen, we're not making a dropdown.
We're making kind of an autocomplete thing.
Yes, that's correct.
But we can kind of use some of the CSS that's been implemented to make this dropdown to kind of leverage
it for what we are trying to create.
So the only effective difference between what you see right here and what we are trying to make is the
fact that we want to show a text input right there instead of a button.
They have a button.
We just want to have a text input so we can very easily swap that out to get something like what you
see right here.
All we really have to do is replicate the HTML structure that they have over here on the right hand
side.
Now, I'm not going to ask you to like read over all that CSS and memorize it instead.
Let's go back over to our project.
We're going to write in some of the CSS that you see right here directly to our HTML file, and I'll
show you how quickly and easily we can replicate something that looks like that.
Okay.
So back over.
I'm going to find my index.html file.
I'm going to go down to the very bottom.
And I'm going to find my input element.
Right above that input element.
I'm going to add in a new div.
With a class of dropdown and is dash active.
I'm going to put the closing div on the other side of the input.
So this div right here is going to wrap our input element.
Then immediately after that I'm going to create another div with a class of dropdown menu.
I'll close it off.
Inside of there.
I'm going to create another diff with the class of dropdown dash content.
Close that one off.
And then finally I'm going to make a couple of anchor tags.
So an anchor tag like so with a class of dropdown item.
I'll then close off the anchor tag and inside the anchor tag I'll put in movie number one.
And then I'm going to copy paste that anchor tag twice like so and just update the text.
So all I'm doing here is using the same HTML that we just saw inside the Bouma documentation by using
the same HTML, the same class names, all the Boma CSS rules that are included inside this project
are going to kick, in effect and try to style this block of HTML right here.
So even though we are not trying to create a dropdown per se, we can still leverage that set of CSS
rules for styling our application.
Yes.
I'm going to save this.
I'm going to flip back over.
Refresh.
And now I see at least what kind of looks like a menu right here.
Of sorts.
I know.
It's, like, pushed up against the left hand side.
But it kind of looks like what we're going for.
I've got a list of items I can kind of hover over them.
When I hover over them, I get that nice little pointer cursor thing, like with the hand, with the
little finger.
And so it's very evident to a user that I can click on this.
So all you and I really have to do now is instead of showing these anchor tags that say movie number
one, two and three, we need to just take our movie images.
So like the poster and movie title and stick it into this anchor tag.
And then everything should essentially show up correctly and nicely styled in our application.
So now we understand what our goal is in the short term.
Let's take a quick pause because there is something to kind of think about on how we approach this problem.
So quick pause and we'll discuss a little interesting side topic in the next video.