We just added in a bunch of HTML directly to our indexed HTML file.
So now in theory, we could go back over to our JavaScript code, try to select these different anchor
elements, and then update the content inside them to show the movie poster and the title.
In theory, that would work, but before we do that, we kind of have a choice to make here about how
we're going to implement this autocomplete widget.
Let me show you a diagram to help you understand the decision that we have to make.
Okay.
So this is option number one right here.
And this is kind of what the path is that we're walking down right now.
So right now in this kind of option, we would write out all the HTML that is required or at least as
much as possible inside of our HTML document.
So in other words, we would write out that div with class dropdown, we would write out the input inside
there, then the dropdown menu, the content, and then eventually render out all the dropdown items
inside there.
And then inside of our next JS file, we would write out some code that looks like this.
It would try to select probably like that div with class dropdown or some like autocomplete class or
something like that, and then set up an event listener on the input inside there.
And then whenever a user does a search, we would then take the results, generate all those options
and throw all the different results, like all the different anchor tags into that dropdown content
div.
And this right here might seem like a really obvious way to do it.
Right.
Like, what other way is there?
Well, there actually is another way to approach this problem.
One thing I want to highlight about this is that we are making some really big assumptions between the
contents of our HTML file and the contents of our JavaScript file.
In other words, our JavaScript code is not going to work correctly if our HTML file doesn't have exactly
the correct structure.
In other words, this code, this entire setup, would not work correctly at all if we did not have
that input element.
If we accidentally delete it or move that input element, our JavaScript code would probably not work
correctly.
Likewise, if we did not have the correct spelling on this class right here, have dropdown content,
which is where we want to put all of our anchor elements that represent each individual video.
If we misspelled that class name or moved it somewhere else inside of our project, that's pretty much
it.
Our JavaScript code is no longer going to work correctly either.
So in other words, we've got a very distinct coupling between our HTML document and our JavaScript
file.
The two of them work very closely together, and if we change either we might break our entire application.
So then means let's take a look at another way of approaching this.
This would be option number two.
Okay.
So an option number two, we are going to have way less HTML inside of our indexed HTML file.
So to represent our entire autocomplete widget, maybe we could get away with only creating one single
element, a div with a class of autocomplete or something like that.
So in this scenario, we would create just the bare root of our widget inside of our HTML document.
And then instead of putting all the HTML inside there inside of our HTML document, we would instead
rely upon our JavaScript code to go through the process of creating all the HTML that was required for
us.
So in other words, we would try to maybe select this div right here, and then we would run some code
to create an input in there for us.
We would then handle the input, like, in other words, deal with change events.
We would run our search on the API and then we would add in all the different HTML required to show
that dropdown.
So add in all the HTML for the dropdown menu, dropdown content and so on.
So in this scenario, we're essentially dumping all the responsibility of producing HTML off to the
JavaScript side of our application.
That might sound like a lot more work on our side, but in reality, it kind of makes life a little
bit easier because no longer are we going to have a strong coupling between our index.html file and
the JavaScript file.
Now all we have to do is make sure that we have got one div inside of here with a class of autocomplete,
and then we should be able to just run some code inside of our indexed JS file that will find that div
and set up our entire autocomplete widget inside there.
So no expectations whatsoever about the HTML that's inside of that div.
This right here is a way more flexible approach, because with this approach, you and I can much more
easily create reusable widgets that we can re-use between different projects.
It also makes it much more easy to share our code with other developers.
Imagine sharing both these options with some friend of yours who wants to implement the same kind of
autocomplete widget.
If you were using option number one up here, you would have to tell your friend, okay, first you're
going to go over to your HTML document.
You're going to put together this div and it has to have an input, make sure it has input and it has
to have these two divs and they have to be nested in this very particular way.
Just imagine trying to communicate that to some other engineer.
You know, maybe it's as easy as just copy pasting them some snippet of HTML, but at the end of the
day, that's definitely a decent amount to communicate over to them.
However, if you were using option number two, you could tell your friend, Oh yeah, just create this
diff with a class of autocomplete and then run this JavaScript function, run like some function called
create autocomplete and boom, that's it.
Everything will be set up for that other engineer automatically.
So throughout this course, we've largely been using option number one.
But as we move forward, we're going to be moving towards option number two.
We're going to try to limit the amount of coupling between our HTML document and our JavaScript file.
And again, the entire idea here is that it's going to lead to greater use of the different widgets
we put together, and it's also going to lead to less coupling between our different files of our project.
Okay.
So now we understand, like, why we're going to take this kind of approach.
Obviously, it's going to require us to add in a pretty good amount of additional JavaScript code,
and we're going to have to make a couple of changes to our HTML document.
But I just want to kind of set you up and get you to understand why we are about to write all the code
that we're going to write.
So a quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.