We just spoke about the differences of creating a bunch of HTML to support a widget inside of our HTML
file versus our JavaScript code.
Now, one thing I want to mention here is that this discussion is really about the creation of JavaScript
heavy reusable widgets.
They're still going to be many times where you're going to want to create some HTML inside of an actual
document, and that's totally fine.
We're really just thinking about moving HTML generation over to our JavaScript code when we are thinking
about widgets that we want to make easily reusable between different projects or even on the same project.
For this autocomplete.
We know that we need to show two different auto completes on the screen.
And so our options are to either write out all that code like one time, all that HTML structure one
time inside of our JavaScript file or write it out twice inside the indexed HTML file.
So definitely the easier thing to do is create some JavaScript code that can create this widget for
us as many times as we want.
But there's definitely going to be some other elements that we're going to throw directly into our HTML
file.
For example, that header element that's already visible right there, that's not something that is
quite appropriate to try to display from our JavaScript code.
So because that thing is like just there's only one, there's not really any interactivity.
I don't expect to use it totally appropriate to create that inside of our HTML file.
Okay.
So back over.
We're going to do a little bit of a refactor and move some of this HTML generation to our JavaScript.
So that involves essentially deleting a lot of the HTML that we just wrote out here.
I know it's kind of a pain to delete some of the HTML that we just wrote, but I wanted to write this
out for two reasons.
First off, so you understood the difference between option number one and option number two.
And secondly, so that you just understood that if we use this HTML structure right here with these
very particular class names, well, my CSS would kick in and style that stuff for us automatically.
So I apologize to the delete stuff we just wrote.
But again, that's why we did it.
Okay.
So I'm going to find everything inside of class container and delete it and we're going to replace it
with one single element instead.
I'm going to do a div with the class of autocomplete like so.
So now we can go back over to our JavaScript code.
We're going to select that element.
So back over right above where we get that input, I'm going to add in some code to select that thing.
I'm going to call it root because it kind of represents the root element of our autocomplete widget.
So we'll do a query selector with dot auto complete.
And then immediately after that, we're going to do a routine or HTML and put in all the HTML that we
need to make our autocomplete widget work.
So essentially we're talking about adding in all the HTML that we just deleted from the HTML file.
So it might seem like we're just kind of shoveling HTML creation from one location to another.
That's totally accurate.
That is what we're doing.
Again, the point is to reduce the coupling between these different files.
The HTML still has to be created somewhere.
We're just moving it over to the JavaScript side.
Okay.
So inside of this thing, we're going to add in pretty much the same structure we just had.
But I'm going to put in one or two more elements in class names that's just going to kind of represent
the final styling of this widget that we're going for.
So I'm going to put in a label that has a B element to bold the text in here.
And for the text I'll say Search for a movie.
I'll then close off the B element and close off the label.
After that, I'll put down the input.
We still need an input.
I'm going to give this one a class of input like so.
And then after that, I'm going to start to show that dropdown.
Now, previously we wrapped up the input with a dropdown.
This time for like no great reason, we're going to do things slightly differently.
So I'm going to put the dropdown right after the input element.
It's also a div with the class of dropdown.
We're going to close that off.
Inside there I'll do a div with the class of dropdown menu and close it off.
And then finally I did with the class of dropdown content.
And this time around I'm also going to put in a class name of results that is just for some additional
little styling, just some CSS.
No other special reason for that class besides a little bit of styling.
Okay.
So now we are creating all of our HTML on the JavaScript side and that means we can create as many of
these autocomplete widgets as we want eventually.
So now we're going to go through this and we're going to select a couple of the different elements inside
of here that we know that we're going to need.
We already have a selector for that input.
We're going to make sure that we also get a selector for that div right there that says dropdown content.
Because remember, that's where we're going to eventually show all the different search results that
we get.
We're also going to get a selector for this div with class of dropdown as well.
The reason for that is that we can hide and show the dropdown menu depending upon whether or not this
element has a class of is active.
This is not some like magic JavaScript thing.
This is another little bit of styling from Hbomax.
If we actually go back over to the documentation over here.
You'll notice that the root element in their example has is active.
If that element has the class is active, then the dropdown is going to be displayed.
Otherwise, if the class is not there, the dropdown will be hidden.
That is normal CSS behavior.
They just have a little CSS selector to say either apply a display of block or none to this thing to
show and hide it.
So we're going to leave off is active because by default we want this thing to be closed.
But like I said, we're going to get a selector to that element so we can add that class on eventually
and open or close the dropdown.
So next to our input element right here, we're going to add in some more selectors to get those two
other elements we just discussed.
One, to open the thing up and one to eventually render some contents inside there.
So I'm going to add in a selector for dropdown and that will be document query selector.
That dropdown.
And I'll also get a we'll call it How about results rapper.
There'll be a document query selector.
Or DOT results.
And as you would guess, that's that element right there.
I'm calling it results wrapper because essentially it's going to wrap all the rendered results that
we're trying to show to the user.
Okay.
So this looks good.
This video is going a little bit long.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to update some of the code inside of our on input function
to make sure that we render some input or excuse me, some output into these particular elements.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.