All right, let's continue working on our widget here.
The last thing we have to do is make a couple of updates inside of on input to refer to the elements
that we just selected instead of some elements that we just deleted, actually.
So like, for example, right now, as we loop over all of our different movies and create some divs,
we're trying to append them to document query selector ID of target so that element doesn't exist anymore.
Remember we said that we want to take all these different elements that we create and put them inside
of that div right there.
So we just have to update a couple of different references, that's all.
Okay.
So to get started right before the for loop, we're going to take a look at the dropdown element, as
we just discussed in the last video, to make sure that we open up the menu, we have to add the is
active class to that element right there.
So right above the for loop, I'll say dropdown dot class list add and we're going to add on the class
is dash active.
So we're going to do that right after we fetch all of our data successfully.
So we're going to fetch all of our data, open up the dropdown, and then add in all of our movies to
it.
So then inside of our for loop.
As I just mentioned, this element right here doesn't exist anymore.
Instead, we want to apply or append all these different divs that we create to the results wrapper.
And the results wrapper is that thing right there?
So on the query selector, I'm going to delete the query selector and I will replace it with results
wrapper.
All right.
Just one or two more changes.
If we go back over to the Burma documentation, you'll recall that as we show each individual item inside
the dropdown, they're supposed to be anchor elements with a class of dropdown item.
Right now, as we loop through all of our different videos or our different movies, we are creating
a dive element.
So that's not quite correct.
We need to update that to be an anchor element instead.
So to do so, I'm going to update the document create element to make an anchor tag or a instead of
div.
And then to be complete, we should probably update the div variable name since we're technically not
creating a div anymore.
A name for this could be like anchor because we are creating an anchor element, but that doesn't really
convey the context of the code we're writing here.
I personally kind of like the name option.
Option might seem a little bit weird, but the idea here is that we are creating like a dropdown or
in autocomplete.
And inside there we're going to show a lot of different options of movies that users can click to select
one of these.
So I think the term option kind of makes sense in that context.
So I'm now going to go through and update div right there and right there as well to refer to the option
variable since Div doesn't exist anymore.
They'll change that to option and on append child.
I'll change it to option as well.
Okay.
Just one or two more quick changes inside of the option element.
We currently have the image, which is definitely good, but we have the movie text inside of an H one,
which might be just slightly too large.
So I'm just going to take off the H one, the opening and the closing tag.
All right.
So there should be just one last little thing to do here.
Right above the option element.
As we were just looking at the Wal-Mart documentation, remember I just said that we have to add in
a class of dropdown item to get everything to style nicely.
So right above where we set enriched HTML.
I'm going to also do an option class list add.
Drop down item like so.
And that should be it.
So I'm going to save this and we should be ready to flip back over to our browser and test this out.
So I'm going to go back over, I'm going to refresh, and right away you're going to see that this looks
a lot better than how it looked before.
We've got the nicely bolded label and the input looks a lot better as well because we added in a class
of input to that thing.
So now inside of here, I'm going to do a search for Avengers.
And as soon as I do so, I see this nice dropdown open and so I can kind of hover over each of these.
I get the nice and a hover effect.
I got the nice finger right there.
All the styling that you're seeing here is coming from Boma.
And so I know that working with Boma and having to understand this dropdown stuff was kind of probably
annoying.
But I think you can agree with me that this looks pretty awesome right here.
Like this definitely looks really good.
Now, as good as it looks, there's definitely still some things we have to do to make our widget work
as expected.
In particular, you might recall that we spoke about all the different ways in which our.
Dropdown is going to behave.
Remember we had said stuff like, Oh yeah, if a user clicks outside the dropdown, close the menu.
Well, right now, if I click outside the dropdown, that thing stays open.
So definitely not appropriate.
In addition, if I do another search, so let's say that I look up Dark Knight.
I'm going to see as I scroll down that all those results get appended to the very end of the list.
So we still have a little bit of work to do.
So let's take a quick pause right here and continue solving a couple of these little issues in the next
video.