Okay.
So our autocomplete definitely looks great.
But like I just mentioned, there's a couple more things we need to do for it.
So first off, we need to make sure that whenever we fetch a new list of videos, we clear out the existing
ones inside there.
That's going to be pretty straightforward.
So let's take care of that task first.
So the big question here is when should we clear out the existing list?
Well, remember, inside of On Input, we are making a request to fetch our data right here.
After we fetch some data, we should probably clear out any existing items before we attempt to add
any more in.
So right above where we have dropdown class list add, let's add in some code to take a look at our
results wrapper.
Remember, that is the thing that is going to eventually contain all the different rendered results
that we get.
So right above dropdown class list add, I will add in results wrapper and to clear the thing out we
could do a simple inner html is empty string like so.
So let's save that.
I'm going to flip back over.
Do a refresh.
And I'll search for Avengers.
And I'll do a search for Dark Knight.
And there we go.
That's much better.
Now, one thing you might notice as I search for Dark Knight and you might see this or you might not.
It looks like the last result in here has a broken image.
And inside my console, I also see an error as well.
So you might not see that it really depends upon the movie that you are searching for.
Let's take a look at the API response that we're getting inside of our network request tab and try to
understand why we are seeing a broken image there.
So I'm going to open up my most recent request to the API.
I'm going to take a look at the list of results we get back.
I'm going to select Dark Knight right there.
So you'll notice that in this case, we have a poster property of an A, which means that there is no
poster image available.
Normally that poster is going to be the link to the actual image.
So the reason that we're seeing this error is that we're essentially throwing in the string and a as
an image source, and we can actually confirm that by inspecting that element, inspecting the image,
and you'll see that the image very plainly has an CRC of an A, and that's why we're seeing this nasty
error down here.
So to get this fixed and again, you might not be seeing this yet, but you probably will eventually.
We just have to add in a check for an A essentially, and make sure that if we ever see it, well,
we probably just don't want to show the image at all.
So to do so, I'm going to go back over.
I'm going to find where we create the inner HTML for each individual option.
So that's where we create the image right there.
So all we have to do is add in a quick check beforehand to decide whether or not we want to show this
image.
To do so right after we create the option, I'm going to say const image CRC like so.
And I'm going to use a little ternary expression here.
So I'm going to say if item dot poster remember it, the capital P is equal to N slash a.
Then I want to assign a value of empty string to image z.
Otherwise, if it is not equal to n a, I want to you assign item capital P poster to image z instead.
So again, this is a turner expression.
We're going to first evaluate that expression right there.
If that is a true expression, then we're going to return whatever is between the question mark and
the colon.
Otherwise, if that is falsely, we will assign item poster over to image z.
So now we can use image Z in place of movie poster.
If we show an image element with an empty string, it's essentially just not going to show up inside
the DOM Well, it's going to technically show up on the DOM, but it won't show up on the screen, which
is going to solve this issue.
So I'm going to put Image Z inside there like so.
All right.
So I'm going to refresh I'm going to look for Dark Knight again.
And it looks like I probably made a typo inside there.
Sorry, I called it item.
It is not item.
It is movie.
That is better.
My mistake.
Yeah.
That's better.
So I'll do dark night.
And the last one down here don't have an image.
Totally fine.
I mean, that's life.
There is no image to show.
But we are not trying to show some, like, non-existing image and showing a broken image or anything
like that.
So this definitely looks good.
So I think the last big thing we have to take care of is to make sure whenever a user clicks out of
the input, like, I'm clicking over here right now, we need to make sure that we close this thing
up.
So let's figure out how we can do that in the next video.