The next little fix we're going to add in is to make sure that if a user searches for something and
then decides they don't want to select a video and click somewhere else, we want to close the menu.
So essentially, we need to really detect when a user clicks anywhere on the screen that is not inside
of that menu.
Now, believe it or not, adding in some code for this is not the easiest thing in the world and it's
actually kind of deceptively challenging.
There is a little trick to it.
However, this trick is going to seem a little bit weird, but it's probably the best and easiest way
to handle this.
To understand the trick, I'm going to first write out a little demonstration in my console.
So inside of my console with my devtools open, I'm going to right click on the label right there.
Search for a movie.
And I'm going to click inspect on it.
That's going to open up my Elements panel and select the B element.
Whenever I click an element in this element's panel, you'll see right after the HTML snippet, I get
equals equals dollar sign zero.
And if you hover over it, you can type in dollar sign zero in the console to refer to that element.
So if I open up my console at the same time, which by the way, you can do by hitting escape, we can
write in at dollar sign zero and that will print out the reference to that element.
Just, you know, dollar sign zero is a valid JavaScript identifier that is not some like magic operator
or something.
It is a normal, completely valid, totally legal JavaScript variable name.
Okay.
So now that I've got a selector to that element, I want to show you the little trick.
I'm going to get reference to the entire document and I'm going to call document contains and then pass
in dollar sign zero.
So what this checks is to see if the element that I currently have selected in this case that label
right there is contained within the document element.
If it is contained because remember we view the DOM as a sort of tree, then we're going to get back.
True in this case, the element inside the document definitely is contained.
But if we try to check the reverse relationship so dollar sign zero contains document we're going to
get back false.
Oops.
Typo.
We're going to get back false like so.
So that means that the label does not contain the document.
So I just want you to keep that in your head for just a moment.
Keep in your head.
We're going to go back over and write a little bit of code to handle closing that input menu or the
dropdown menu.
Okay.
So back over here.
I'm going to say document dot, add event listener.
So this is kind of the crazy part.
We are adding a global event listener to our entire document and we're going to watch for any time that
anyone clicks on any element whatsoever.
Now remember how events work in JavaScript events bubble, which means that if some element contained
inside the document like let's say the container right here or even the text inside of it, if someone
clicks on that, that's going to trigger a click event on that element.
If it doesn't get handled right there, then the event is going to essentially bubble up until it gets
to the top level of our entire HTML document.
In this case, the document.
So this event right here, we can look at console.log event target.
And as we start to click around, we're going to see that this is going to print out a variety of different
elements, essentially whatever element we click on.
So I'm going to go back over again, I'm going to refresh and now if I start to click around like on
the label, I'll see the label text.
I can click on the H one, the icon right there, the header anywhere else, the input, whatever else.
And whenever I click on it, I see the console log up here.
Okay.
So now here's the real final conclusion of all this.
So we know that event target is going to tell us what gets clicked.
We know that we also have that contains element as well or something that contains method.
So the whole big trick here, the whole kind of conclusion to all this is that we can take a look.
At our roots element.
Remember, the root element encapsulates everything having to do with our autocomplete.
So we're going to check to see if the element that was clicked on is contained inside of root.
If it is contained inside, that means that the user clicked on the label, the input or the dropdown.
And in any of those scenarios we want to keep the dropdown open.
But if the click is not contained inside of the root, then the user clicks somewhere else in the document
and so we should close the dropdown.
That's the whole conclusion.
I apologize in coming to it in a roundabout way, but that is the trick.
That's how we're going to do this.
So inside of our event listener down here, we're going to say if.
Not Route DOT contains event target.
So that's saying if the root element for our little autocomplete doesn't contain the element that was
just clicked on, then we need to close the dropdown and remember to open or close the dropdown.
We can get a reference back to the dropdown element right here, which is essentially that thing right
there.
And we can add or remove the class is active.
We just added in some code a little bit ago to add in the class is active, which opens it up.
So to close it, we're going to remove that class and that will close the dropdown.
Yeah.
So down here I'll do drop down class list.
Remove is.
Active like so.
And I'll save.
Flip back over.
Refresh.
I'll go for Dark Knight.
Now I'm going to click anywhere else and the dropdown closes.
If I do another search for, let's say, Avengers, I can click on anything inside here so I can click,
click, click, click, click on the input, click on the label.
I click on anything inside of the entire Autocomplete widget, and this thing stays open as we would
hope.
All right.
So that definitely looks like it's working correctly.
So just one last little fix I want to take care of in the next video.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.