There's one last fix I want to take care of very quickly right now, if we do a search for something,
so I'm going to search for Avengers.
Oops, I accidentally lost it.
There we go.
And then I delete this.
The input stays open or excuse me, the dropdown stays open, but with nothing inside of it, which
is definitely not appropriate.
So we just need to make sure that we do a little check inside of our code and we say that if we get
back no results at all from our fetch data function, we should probably close the dropdown.
So we just spoke about how we open and close the dropdown.
So this should be pretty straightforward.
Back up right after we check to see if we are assuming it right after we get some data.
Let's take a look at movies and we're going to say that if there are no movies whatsoever, if we didn't
fetch any data, let's just return early and not run anything else inside of here.
So I'm going to say if.
Not movies, not length.
So if there are no movies, then let's make sure that we close the dropdown.
So I'm going to do a dropdown.
Class list dot remove is active and then we're going to return entirely from this function because we
don't want to try to render anything or even open the dropdown back up or anything like that.
So that's pretty much it.
Let's do a quick save and a test.
I'm going to once again search for Avengers and I'll delete it.
In the drop down goes away.
All right.
Well, I'd say that's looking pretty good.
So our autocomplete widget is now in a really good state, and there's really only one last major interaction
we have to add.
We need to make sure that a user can actually click on a video to select it.
Right now, we can click on a video all day, but nothing is really happening.
So let's take a quick pause and handle that last major interaction in the next video.