Our autocomplete has a couple of things fixed up now, so we get to now start to think about adding
in some additional features to it.
The next thing we need to do is to make sure that once a user searches for something and then clicks
on an option right here, we have to somehow handle that click.
We spoke about what to do whenever a user clicks on an entry a little bit ago.
So remember we had said that we want to update the text inside the input.
So we want to update the text from whatever the user had just typed, like Avenger's right here to the
exact title of the movie that the user clicked on.
So instead of saying Avengers, it should say The Avengers inside of that input.
In addition, we need to make sure that we also close the menu.
Finally and this isn't really in this diagram right here, but the last thing we need to do as well
is to make sure that whatever movie a user clicks on, we need to essentially render it out really large
on the left hand side of the screen because that is the end goal of this application.
But right now, let's just make sure that whenever we search for something and click on it, we update
the text and we close the dropdown.
So what we really need to do here is to detect a click on an individual option.
To do so, I'm going to once again find my on input function.
Inside of there, we've got our four of loop where we create a bunch of different anchor elements.
We then add on some classes and set some inner HTML and whatnot.
So to detect a click on one of those options, we can add in a click event handler to that option variable.
Remember, the option variable is an anchor element.
To add in a click event handler right underneath where we set the inner HTML.
I'm going to do an option dot add event listener and we're going to watch for a not a click event,
but a click event.
So then inside of here, we can do the two things we just discussed.
We want to update the value of the input, and we also want to make sure that we close the dropdown
as well.
Let's see, the dropdown is something that we've spoke about several times now.
Remember to toggle whether or not the dropdown is open.
We add or remove.
The class is active to the dropdown element and the dropdown element is that one right there.
So let's take care of that first.
Inside of my event listener.
I'll do a dropdown class list.
Remove.
Is Daesh active?
So let's save that and do a very quick test.
I'll refresh.
Avengers.
So now I'm going to click on The Avengers and the entire dropdown closes.
Very good.
So now the next thing we need to do is to make sure that we update the text inside of the input.
Once again, remember that we've got a reference to that input on the input variable right there.
So we can update the value of that text input by going back down to our event listener.
And we'll say input.
Dot value.
That's how we can change the value inside of an existing input.
And we're going to update it to the title of the movie that the user just clicked on.
We can get the title of the movie that the user just clicked on by using the closure scope of this function
right here.
Remember, the closure scope is essentially everything outside of that arrow function.
So right outside that function, we've still got a reference to the movie variable, and that is the
object that has all the information about the movie that the user just clicked on.
So we could do movie title.
And as I've mentioned many times, remember title with a capital TX because this API property names
are just a little bit strange.
So we're going to take that title, shove it into input value, and that should update the text on the
screen inside the input.
So let's do another save here.
I'll flip back over, refresh, I'll search for Avengers.
And now if I click on any of these right here, I would expect to see the text inside of the input update
as well.
And there we go.
Very good.
Okay.
So this looks like we've got something pretty good put together now.
I would say that our autocomplete element is just about done.
So now the last thing we have to do is think about how to take the movie that the user just clicked
on and render out some details about it on the screen, just like we said we would do with the original
mockups of this application.
So like this right here, we want to show the image title, some statistics and so on.
So another quick pause and we'll start to address that in the next video.