Like we said at the end of the last video, we now need to take the movie that the user just selected
and show some details about it right here.
There's just one or two things to be aware of.
First off, I want to remind you that the open DB API that we're using has those two different endpoints
that we're making use of.
Right now, we've got some results coming back from the BI search method right here, and that only
gives us some very limited pieces of information about every movie.
So when a user selects an actual movie, that means that we need to do a follow up request to the API
and we need to then attempt to fetch that movie by ID.
Once we do the request by ID.
That's going to give us a very much expanded set of information about this particular movie.
And it's going to give us stuff like the critic ratings and the box office take and the plot summary
and so on.
So in other words, once a user clicks on the movie and we detect it right here, we need to make a
follow up request, get some more information, and then use that to update some content on the screen.
We could definitely add all that code right here inside of our event listener, so we can add in a ton
of code and say, okay, do another request.
Get data, render data and so on.
But I bet you could very quickly imagine that that's going to be a fair bit of code.
This file, the indexed JS file that we're working on already has a lot of code inside of it, and it's
all kind of a hodgepodge of different stuff right now.
And so if we start to add in all this additional code directly into this event, listener well, this
file is going to get even more challenging to read and understand.
So instead of tucking all that logic in right there, I think that we should make some other helper
function inside this file, maybe something called like on Movie Select or something.
And inside of that helper function, we can make sure that we attempt to do all that extra logic, do
the extra request, render that additional content onto the screen.
So I'm going to imagine that we're going to define another helper function inside this file called On
Movie Select.
And I'm going to call that with the movie that the user just clicked on.
So now let's go to fine this helper function and then we can put all that additional logic inside there.
So I'm going to go down to the bottom of the file.
I'm going to define on movie select.
It's going to be called with some movie object.
And right now let's just do a console.log.
Now, I'm sure I don't need to prove to you that we're going to call this function successfully.
Like, Hey, that's definitely going to work.
I don't have any reason to suspect it won't work.
The reason I just want to do a console.log right here is to just remind you some of the properties that
we currently have access to and the properties that we're going to need to make the follow up request
to our API and get that additional amount of data.
Okay, so let's save this.
I'm going to go back over.
I will refresh.
All once again, do The Avengers, click on it and I see that console.log.
So again, I just want to remind you that inside of the current data set that we have right here about
this one very particular movie, we've got that property called IMDB ID and notice how ID is capital
for both letters.
So that is the ID that we're going to use to make our follow up request to the API.
We're going to do the follow up request.
We're going to pass that ID in as a parameter called I.
And that is what is going to give us all that additional data about the movie.
So inside of here, I'm going to make this into an async function so that we can then go ahead and use
the await syntax and Axios to make our follow up request.
So I will write out consent response is await Axios get.
I'm going to go back up to the top of the file.
And get the URL from the first request we made up here.
So I'm going to get that URL right there just to save myself a little bit of typing.
And you know what?
I'm just going to go ahead and copy the entire Axios get function because we need that params and the
API key as well.
So I'm just going to copy all that stuff.
I'm going to go back down to the bottom and put it in like so.
Then inside of here we just need to make sure that we update the params object rather than passing along
a pram of TSS, which is what is used for doing a search.
We instead want to do an individual lookup so like we just saw, we need to provide a parameter of the
letter I and that is going to be the movie IMDB ID, so I'll put an I.
And we want that value to come from the movie that we just selected.
Dot IMDB.
Capital I.
Capital D.
So then after that, we'll do a quick.
Console log of the data.
So response data like so.
Yes.
Let's try this out again.
Just make sure we still have the data we expect.
So I'll do a search for The Avengers.
I'll click on it and there we go.
We do the follow up request and get all that additional data about this particular movie.
Well, now that we've got all the data, we can now start to think about taking that information and
rendering it out.
So we're going to essentially just have to write out a lot of HTML to build up this kind of structure
right here.
So as you probably would guess, a quick pause and we'll start to write that stuff out in the next video.