Like I just mentioned, now that we've got this expanded piece of information about the movie, we're
going to start to write out a lot of different HTML to get that kind of structure right there.
We're going to end up printing out several different properties about the movie that are not shown inside
this mockup.
So in reality, we're not going to only show the box office taken critic rating.
We're also going to show stuff like the awards that the movie won and the number of votes that it's
gotten on IMDB, the rating on IMDB and so on.
So a couple of other elements besides what is just pictured inside of here.
Now I'm going to tell you right up front that we're going to write out a lot of HTML to get this structure
inside this video.
All the HTML that we are about to write in, all the class names are essentially taken directly from
the Boma CSS framework.
Remember, we discussed that this project is using this framework a little bit ago.
So essentially I went through, I took a look at all the documentation and I figured out some HTML structure
and class names that would give us something that looks like this right here.
So I'm not making up all these class names and whatnot off the top of my head.
Instead, these are all corresponding to styling sets that are included inside of Boma.
So let's go back over.
Yours on Movie Select right here.
That's where we just got our response with all the information about one particular movie.
So we're going to take that object right there, pull off a ton of different properties from it and
stick it into some big HTML snippets.
This is going to end up being a lot of HTML.
So rather than stuffing it all inside of on Movie Select, I'm going to instead make another helper
function called Movie Template.
I'm going to receive an argument to this function that I will call movie detail.
I'm calling it movie detail right here.
Just to be clear, that argument is going to be this really big object with all the specific properties
of a movie, just to distinguish between the movie object that we had back up here.
This movie object right here is more like a movie summary.
It just has the title, the poster and like yea and one or two other properties, that's pretty much
it.
So I just want to have these two different variable names, movie versus movie detail, to indicate
that this is just like an abbreviated object of all the different movie properties.
This is like the detailed object about all the different movies properties.
Then I'm going to Inside of here movie template.
I'm going to return a multi-line string.
So once again, set it back ticks.
And inside there we're going to write out a whole bunch of HTML.
And again, this is all about getting that content right there on the screen.
So let's get to it.
A lot of writing.
So we're going to write that out rather quickly.
Please triple check your spelling as you're going through this.
So I'm going to do an article with a class of media.
I'll close off the article.
I'll put in a figure with the class of media left close off the figure.
I'm going to do a paragraph element with a class of image.
And inside there is an image with a Z.
I'm going to put in the double quotes because remember, we need those when we are trying to stick some
image source inside of this tag and then we're going to get the poster property of the movie detail.
So here's that object that we're working with right now.
We want that poster property right there with the capital P.
So for the sauce I'll do dollar sign, curly braces and then movie detail dot poster with a capital
P.
Then I'll close off the image tag like so.
Okay.
So that's the first block.
Now we're going to add on something after the closing figure tag.
So after the closing figure tag, I'll do a div with the class of media dash content.
Was off the div inside there.
I'll do a div with the class of content clothes off the div and inside there I'll do an h one.
I'm going to reference once again a JavaScript variable.
So dollar sign, curly braces, I'll get movie detailed title.
So that's going be the title of the movie as usual.
Notice the capital T for title.
I'll then do an H for and inside their movie detailed genre.
So that's going to be the genre of the movie.
So is it an action movie, a mystery, horror, suspense, drama, whatever else?
And then after the H for a paragraph.
With dollar sign curly brace and you want just to be consistent.
This really should be on the same or a single line.
So dollar sign, curly braces, movie, dot plot.
That's going to be a plot summary of the movie.
I want to remind you that all these movie detail properties, so poster titles, genre and plot should
all have starting capital letters.
Let's save this really quickly.
We're going to try to call movie template.
We're going to pass in our movie detail that we just got back from the API up here and then we're going
to append that somewhere into the DOM.
So we're essentially just going to test out just that snippet right there.
We're not done with all the HTML that we need, but we've got enough that we should just do a very quick
test to make sure that we don't have anything too crazy.
Okay.
So the first thing we need to do is to make sure that we have somewhere to render this template inside
of our DOM.
So I'm going to go back into my index.html file.
Right after my autocomplete element, I'm going to put in a div with an ID of summary.
We are going to eventually replace this element, but we're just going to leave it here for now for
testing purposes.
And then back inside of indexes I will find on movie select.
I'm going to delete the console log.
I'll do a document query selector.
And we're going to do a selector of pound and get that element that we just put in there.
Summary.
And then I'll say iner, each HTML will be essentially that string right there.
So to get that string, we're going to call movie template.
And we'll pass in response data, which is that big movie object that we just saw at our console just
a moment ago.
All right, so let's save this.
We'll go back over and just do a quick test.
Again, this is just to make sure that we don't have any errors in the HTML that we just wrote out.
So I will again go for Avengers, click it and I think I've got a typo somewhere because it says here
movie is not defined.
So I definitely accidentally wrote out movie instead of Oh yep, right there.
My mistake.
I put movie instead of movie detail.
That's better.
It's going to save that.
Let's try it again.
Avengers.
Click it.
There we go.
All right, so we've got something on the screen and it looks kind of reasonable right now, kind of
looks very similar or somewhat similar to what we said we were trying to build right there.
So this is good progress.
Let's take a quick pause right here.
When we come back, the next video, we're going to start to write out another block of HTML to show
all the stats about the movie underneath what we have so far.
So quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.