All right, let's keep writing out some HTML to show all the stats underneath this movie.
So back inside my code editor, I'll find the movie template function.
We will go down to the bottom and we're going to add in just a little bit more HTML here.
So after the closing article element, I'm going to place another article.
I'm going to give it a class of notification.
And then a space is dash primary.
I then close off the article.
And inside of here, I'll do a paragraph tag.
But the class of title.
Was it off?
And inside there, we're going to reference movie detail about awards.
So this is going to be a string summary of all of the different awards that this movie has won.
We'll see exactly what it looks like in the dorm in just a second.
After that, I'm going to put in essentially a label for this statistic, so I'll do another paragraph
element with the class of subtitle.
And inside of there, I'll say simply awards like so.
Okay.
So this right here, this article element, we're going to essentially duplicate this down several times.
And inside of every duplicated version, we're going to be referencing a different property off of movie
detail and B, giving each of them a different label as well.
So I'm going to take this article element, I'm going to copy it, and then I'm going to copy it down
four times.
So here's one to.
Three.
And for now, we'll go through each of these and update some of the different properties.
I'm going to go up, find the first one.
I'll go to the second one and I'm going to change the second one from awards right there to box office.
I'll change the label right underneath it to box office as well.
Next up, we'll go to number three.
I'm going to change that one to awards to Metascore.
I'll change the label to Metascore.
So again, this is like a rating essentially of the movie.
The next one.
So second to last one IMDB rating.
Notice how in this case I has a lowercase as opposed to all the other property names that start with
the capital.
The label will be IMDB rating.
So this is the rating of the movie according to the website IMDB.
And then finally on the last one, we'll change it to IMDB votes.
And IMDB.
Boats.
So that's the number of votes that this movie has gotten on IMDB by different users of that platform.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it.
Let's save this.
We've got five different properties here.
Like I said, a couple added beyond just the two that we had mentioned over here back in our original
mockup.
So I'll save that file.
I will refresh.
I'll look for Avengers.
Look at and there we go.
So now I see The Avengers.
I see the awards that this movie has won box office, take the METASCORE, the rating on IMDB, and
the number of votes that the movie has gotten on IMDB as well.
That's pretty much it.
That's like stage one of our application.
We now have the ability to search for a movie.
We've got some autocomplete functionality in there.
Once a user selects a movie, we show a lot of information about it on the screen.
So now we essentially just have to do a lot of duplicate work.
We essentially need to duplicate everything we just did and show a second auto complete on the right
hand side of the screen.
And then once we have all the same functionality for that autocomplete, we'll then just need to make
sure that when we search for two different movies, we compare all the different statistics and highlight
the higher ones in each category.
Yes.
That's some pretty good progress.
Let's take a pause right here and start on this next phase in the next video.