At the end of the last video, we discussed how the phase one of our application is pretty much complete.
User can search for something.
See some statistics.
So normally we would now move on to phase two where we would show a second autocomplete on the right
hand side, allow a user to do another search, and then compare some statistics between the two movies.
But before we do, we're going to take a look at our current code base.
It turns out that the code that we've written so far has some kind of serious issues inside of it.
So I want to take a look at the code we've written so far.
I want to point out some really big issues with our current implementation, and I want to figure out
some ways that we could fix that stuff before we move on to phase two of our app.
So in other words, we're going to start to do some really big re factors in the goal of these three
factors is to help you get an idea of how to write some more reusable code.
Naturally, at the start of this application, I could have just shown you the right way to build this
application from start to finish, but I think that you can learn a lot more effectively to see kind
of the wrong way, so to speak, to build out an application.
Which is kind of what we've done so far and then see a better way to write it.
Now, don't think that everything we've written so far is awful.
Don't get me wrong, the code we've written so far is 100% A-OK.
And if you went to some job or like an interview or your first junior position as a JavaScript engineer,
and you wrote code like what we've done so far, this would 100% be A-OK.
There's not anything that's like inherently wrong with the code that we have.
I just want to show you some quick changes we can make to our code base to make it even better than
it currently is.
And it's all themed around making our code more reusable.
So that in mind, let's take a look at some issues inside of our current code base.
Okay.
So here's the current overwhelming issue with just about everything inside of our project so far, I
would say that just about all of our code touches everything.
In other words, just about every function, every block of code, everything kind of reaches around
to other variables inside the file and other functions inside the file.
Let me give you some practical examples of this, mostly focused around the autocomplete widget, and
you're going to get a better sense of right now how our code is just reaching around, referencing a
ton of different variables all over the place.
So a good example of that is the autocomplete widget.
Remember, the autocomplete widget was supposed to be reusable.
We spoke a little bit ago about how putting a bunch of HTML inside of our HTML document would lead to
making it more challenging to reuse the autocomplete logic over time.
Because if we ever wanted to reuse all this autocomplete stuff on another project, we would not only
have to copy over a bunch of JavaScript code, but we would also have to copy over some HTML inside
of our HTML document.
In other words, if we had all the autocomplete HTML inside the HTML document, we had that really strong
coupling between those two files.
And again, it just made it more challenging to use.
So as we start to think about how to make the Autocomplete widget actually reusable, it's going to
involve the process of making sure that the code inside there doesn't touch everything.
Again, let me give you some practical examples of this.
The first way in which our autocomplete knowledge excuse me, the first way in which the autocomplete
widget kind of touches everything, is that it has knowledge of exactly what a movie object is.
So let's go back over to our code base and let me show you that inside of the on input function right
now.
We have a for loop right here and inside that for loop, we have a couple of different lines of code
that take a look at that movie object right there.
And in doing so, specifically on line 43, it is very clear that the current implementation of our
autocomplete stuff knows exactly what different properties a movie object has.
So on this line of code, it's clear that the autocomplete stuff knows that a movie object has a poster
property.
The Autocomplete logic is going to behave very differently based on the presence and value of that poster
So I would say that if we consider all of our autocomplete stuff right now, like everything from Const
Root right there all the way down to our add event listener right there for the document, if we look
at just this code block, we would say that this autocomplete widget knows exactly about the structure
of data that it is working with.
Now.
Why is that bad?
Well, it's very simple.
Again, imagine that you wanted to reuse all this code on another project.
And let's imagine for just a second that maybe you did not want to try to have to, like, go into all
this code right here and change a bunch of different variables or property names in order to get this
code to work on another project.
So let's imagine that in a perfect world, we could just copy, paste all the stuff, reuse it right
away.
If that were the case, then, well, having these direct references to properties inside the movie
object would not be good at all because maybe our other project doesn't work with movie objects.
Maybe instead it works with, say, like recipes.
A recipe probably would not have a poster property.
Instead, maybe a recipe object like a cooking recipe would have some property called like, I don't
know, recipe image or something.
So if I wanted to use all this code on that other project, I would have to go through it first and
update all these property references.
That's sign number one that we don't have reusable code just yet.
The next instance of this is that our autocomplete has knowledge of exactly what to show for each option.
So again, inside of our for loop right here, we are setting the inner HTML on option.
So this right here, this image that we're placing and the title of the movie once again means that
our autocomplete code has perfect knowledge and perhaps too much knowledge of what to render or what
to display for every option.
Maybe once again, if we were searching for recipes on some other project, maybe we don't have any
images to show at all.
And maybe we would not want to show that image element.
Instead, we would want to show something just like recipe, dot name or something.
So if that were the case, again, we would have to come into all this code.
We would have to find where we set the inner HTML for the option, and we would have to update that
stuff right there.
So that again, is another sign that our code is not reusable.
In order to change the way in which each option looks, we have to modify the source code of our widget.
Finally, the autocomplete stuff has knowledge of what to do when a movie is clicked.
So again, if we go back over, take a look at the four of Lupe, take a look at the Click Event listener
that we set up on each option.
You have a direct reference right here to some function called on Movie Select.
Again, for the third time, imagine that we took all this code and moved it to a new project.
This code would not work correctly if we did not have a function inside of our file called On Movie
Select.
So again, if we were working with recipes, we would have to go into the source code.
We would have to find that function call and change it to on recipe select or something.
And then we would have to have some function inside this file called on Recipe Select.
If we moved all this code to another new project after that that worked with maybe, I don't know,
blog posts, we would have to change this to on blog post select.
So again, the overriding point here, the point I'm trying to make is that if we wanted to re-use all
this autocomplete stuff on any other project, we would have to copy, paste all the code and then go
around to all these different lines and update each one of them to work with this new kind of resource
that we wanted to use the autocomplete with.
The other big issue with our code right now and specifically around the autocomplete as well, is that
we have have many different global variables that are referring to specific elements.
Now the reason this is a big problem is that it's going to be really, really hard right now to show
a second autocomplete on the screen.
So let me show you why that is the case.
If we go back up to the top of all of our autocomplete code.
So about right here, remember, we have a query selector for some element with a class of autocomplete
and then just about everything else inside this file after this is working with this root element.
We have many references back to the root variable.
So what would we do now if we wanted to show a second autocomplete on the screen?
Well, to be honest, we would probably I'm going to zoom out for this just so you can see this little
refactor I'm about to do.
Don't make any changes.
I'm just going to give you a very quick example here.
In order to show the second autocomplete, we would have to take all this autocomplete related code.
Just about all of it, I think all the way down to like right here or so, we would have to copy all
this.
But another code section here for like autocomplete number two, do a duplicate all that stuff and then
go through here in Autocomplete number two section and update all these references so that the variable
names wouldn't conflict with the earlier autocomplete that we defined.
So for example, for Autocomplete number two, I would have to do a query selector for a totally different
element like Autocomplete Dash two or something.
And then because I have all these variables that are inside of the same scope, I would have to change
root right here to like root two and root to enter HTML.
And then for these variables right here, again, they're defined earlier up inside the file.
So we'd have to do input to drop down to results wrapper too and then repeat that entire same process
with all the other variables inside of here.
And so I bet you can imagine really quickly that this is a really, really bad way to approach this
problem.
And there's got to be some better way to tackle this than having to duplicate all the code and then
just arbitrarily change all the variable names in order to just show a second autocomplete.
Okay.
I'm going to delete that copy paste I just did very quickly.
And go back to what I had before.
And there we go.
Okay.
So again, that is the big issues with our current implementation.
It's essentially all revolving around our current autocomplete widget.
It is not at all reusable, and the reasons for that is that it knows exactly what properties a movie
has, which means we can't reuse this with a different kind of resource.
It knows exactly what to show for each option, which means, well, if we ever want to change that
representation, we would have to mess around with the internal source code of the Autocomplete.
The autocomplete knows exactly what function to call whenever a movie is clicked.
And that means, again, that our source code would have to have a function called on movie select or
something similar.
And then finally, if we ever want to show multiple instances of that autocomplete, well, we would
have to duplicate all that code and change a bunch of different variable names.
Yeah.
So that is the big issues with our project right now.
Now, I want to repeat one more time that the code we've written is not the worst in the world.
And we did not just waste like an hour of our time putting together the first implementation of this
project.
I am just suggesting that perhaps there is a better way, even better than what we've written out so
far.
So with all this in mind, now that we understand what is wrong with our project, we're going to start
to refactor all this stuff in some very significant ways.
So quick pause right here.
We're going to come back the next video and discuss how we can essentially solve all these issues in
some really nice fashion.
So I'll see you in just a minute.