Now that we understand what is going wrong inside of our project, let's talk about the absolute distinct
steps that we're going to undergo to actually fix each of these issues.
So here's the idea.
Right now, we've got a lot of unreviewable code inside of our indexed JS file.
We're going to start to refactor this into two separate files inside of our index DOJ's file.
We're going to have some not reusable code, so code that is very specific for our project.
Examples of code that is specific to our project is the process of fetching movies or the process of
deciding what an individual movie should look like inside the autocomplete and the code related to deciding
what to do when an option is clicked on.
Then we're going to have a second file called Autocomplete.
JJ's inside there.
We're going to have some extremely reusable code that is all related to getting an autocomplete to display
on the screen successfully.
That file should be 100% reusable between different projects.
And so because of that, we need to make sure that everything inside that file has zero knowledge of
exactly what a movie is or what a recipe is.
If we were building something around showing recipes or what a blog is, and so on.
In addition that, we want to make sure that the code in this file can be executed several times successfully.
The idea there being that we want to have the ability to show several different auto completes on the
screen at the same time without having to do that crazy renaming of variables or anything like that.
So to make this happen, we're going to create a function inside of autocomplete.
JS That's going to take a configuration object.
It's going to process the options inside that configuration object and then render an autocomplete out
onto the screen.
So inside of that configuration object that's going to be created inside of index dogs, we're going
to have to provide all the code that is like customized for the very specific application of this autocomplete.
So let me tell you about what our config object might look like.
I think that our config object is going to have three different properties inside of it.
It's going to have a function that is used to find movies, a function that is used to render out an
individual option inside the autocomplete.
A function that says exactly what to do when a user clicks on an option.
And finally, an element that designates exactly where the autocomplete should be rendered to inside
of our final HTML document.
So because we are passing these three very or four very critical options inside of a config object,
that object right there is essentially wrapping up all the customized code specific to our application
and it's going to pass it off to Autocomplete JS.
Autocomplete JS is then going to call some of those very specific functions whenever it needs to say
get some data or decide how to render out each option or what to do whenever a user clicks on an option.
So in other words, all the not reusable code gets defined inside of indexes and all the reusable code
is inside of autocomplete.
JS.
And if we ever want to re-use all this stuff on another project, we're going to take Autocomplete.
Add it to the new project.
Come up with a new config object that has the exact same options inside of it and pass it into the same
function.
So that's the idea.
That's how we're going to make our code reusable.
Now, if I am explaining this right now and it makes zero sense, that is totally okay and really very
much expected.
I really do not expect you to like look at this diagram and know exactly what is going on right away.
This is just your first taste of what we're going to be doing and how we're going to make all this code
reusable in nature.
So now that we have a vague idea of what we're going to do, let's take another pause right here.
We're going to come back the next video.
We're going to start to create these two separate files and then split apart all of our code into these
separate, different implementations.
So I'll see you in just a minute.