Now that we have a better idea of how we're going to make our code more reusable, let's start writing
out some code.
Now, understanding this entire flow from the get go is kind of challenging.
So rather than trying to do this entire refactor all at once, we're going to set ourselves a little
bit more immediate goal.
We're going to try to say that rather than defining all these different options right away inside of
some config object, we're just going to try to pass in some root element.
So this is going to be some element that the autocomplete should be rendered into.
So the immediate goal that we're going to focus on is just having the ability to show multiple different
auto completes on the screen at the same time.
So we should be able to create multiple different config objects and pass each of them into some autocomplete
function.
The autocomplete function should then create the autocomplete in those different route elements.
So again, that's the immediate goal.
That's what we're going to try to do from the get go.
So to get started, I'm going to first go back over to my editor inside of my route project directory.
I'll create a new file called Autocomplete JS.
Inside of here, I'm going to define a function called create autocomplete.
So we're going to call this function multiple different times and eventually it's going to have a bunch
of reusable code inside of it.
Whenever we call this function, we're going to pass in some kind of configuration object, and that
config object is going to have all the kind of custom functions that specify how the autocomplete should
work inside of our specific application.
So that config object is essentially where we put all of our references to movies and how the movies
should be rendered and what to do when one gets clicked and so on.
And then going to make sure that I wire up that autocomplete JS file inside of my indexed HTML file.
So inside of here, I'll go down to the very bottom.
I'm going to duplicate one of the script tags and then change the Z to autocomplete.
So now that file will actually be executed.
You make sure that you've got utils and then autocomplete and then index dogs.
If index dog's is listed first, then the code inside there will run first and it will try to call the
autocomplete function before it has been created.
Okay.
So I'll save that file and we're going to start to do the big refactor.
So the big refactor, we're going to go into indexed indexes.
And I'm going to take as much of the autocomplete related code as possible that is supposed to be reusable
in nature and move it over to the autocomplete JS file.
That's going to start from about line 16 or so where I have construit right there.
I'm going to go from that line and I'm going to select everything down.
To the end of document ad event listener.
That's about line 65 or so for me.
I'm then going to cut all of that.
Go over to Autocomplete JS.
And paste it into the function.
Okay.
So now all we have to do is start to repair the code inside of here.
We're going to make sure that some of the stuff that is application specific is being taken from this
config object instead of being placed directly inside this file.
So the first and best example of that is going to be the root element right here.
Normally, when all this code runs, it assumes that our document is going to have a diff or some other
element with a class of autocomplete.
If that were the case, then we would only be able to call create autocomplete exactly one time, because
there's probably only one element that we're going to be able to select with this statement.
So instead of trying to figure out what element we should be rendering into inside of this reusable
function, we're going to instead accept this as a configurable property.
So we're going to make sure that our config object has a root property, and that's going to be the
element that the autocomplete should be rendered into.
So in other words, this config object right there, I'm going to expect to have a root element.
So I'm going to de structure.
Out a property called root like.
So make sure you get those curly braces because we are structuring that property out.
So now, because this is being provided as an option, the create autocomplete function no longer on
its own has to figure out where to render the autocomplete so we can now delete that first statement
right there.
All right.
One or two other quick changes inside of here on lines 12 or 14 or so.
We're we've got all those different references to input dropdown and so on.
Those are trying to find just some input in the document or some element with the class of dropdown
and so on.
We don't want that to be the case.
Instead, we want to try to find the input, the dropdown and results that are inside of that root element.
In other words, that one right there, that input and that results element as well.
So to make sure that we get those elements, we can update the query selector right here.
Instead of looking at the entire document, we're going to look specifically inside of the root element.
So root, root and root.
All right.
That's probably just about everything we have to do inside of create autocomplete for right now.
So now we can go back over to our indexed JS file and we're going to try to call it create autocomplete
multiple different times.
Every single time.
We're going to form up a different configuration object that has a different root element to render
the autocomplete into.
So back inside of indexes, I'm going to call create autocomplete and I'll pass in my configuration
object.
This thing is going to have a root element.
Let's first go back over to our indexed HTML file and make sure that there are different elements so
we can render these separate autocomplete into.
Inside of indexed HTML.
Right now we've got that one div with the class of autocomplete.
I'm going to duplicate that down twice, so I'm going to try to render three different autocomplete
into my application.
One into that one.
That one and that one.
I need to make sure that I give them class names just to make sure that they are easier to select.
So on the second one, I'll do Autocomplete Dash two and Autocomplete Dash three like so.
We'll eventually get some better class names than this.
But for right now, that's good enough for testing purposes.
So finally, we can go back over to indexes.
And I'm going to say that I want to create one instance of an autocomplete widget.
At a root element of document query selector dot autocomplete.
Then I'm going to duplicate this down twice.
So one and two.
And I'll change the query selectors for those two other divs that we just added in.
So the second one right there is going to get autocomplete dash two.
So Autocomplete Dash two and then dash three.
And that should be it.
Yes.
Let's save this.
We'll test it and then do a quick wrap up on the changes we made.
So go back over refresh and now I see the three different inputs.
I'll first go down to the bottom one, I'll search for Avengers.
There we go.
And I can click it and select it and it gets selected on the screen.
Well, then go to the second one.
I'll try searching for Dark Knight.
Yup.
That one works as well.
That one gets selected on the screen.
Now, why is it getting selected here?
Well, remember, right now our create autocomplete function has a reference to just one single element
to show the output in.
It's that summary right there inside of on Movie Select.
So that is the only location right now where we can render some output to whenever a user clicks on
an element.
And that's why we are seeing essentially the same summary element being overwritten every single time
that we click on a movie.
So obviously that's something that's definitely going to eventually have to be fixed up.
But again, for right now, we were just worried about trying to make sure that we could show the same
root element or show the same autocomplete in different root elements.
So finally, one more test here.
On the first one, I'll look for Avengers.
It and that works as well.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it.
We can now clearly show multiple different autocomplete widgets on the screen, whereas before we definitely
could only show one at a time.
So the big summary here and the process that we're going to start to duplicate again and again in the
next couple of videos as we continue this refactor.
Is that we are trying to be able to create multiple different auto completes and we're going to centralize
all the logic around creating each one inside of index dogs and inside of autocomplete dogs.
We're going to have just the logic inside of here that is reusable between different projects.
So it will not have any references to movies.
It will have no idea what a movie object is.
We'll have no idea of the different properties it has and so on.
So let's take a pause right here and continue our refactor in the next video.