Our first test worked out pretty well.
So let's continue on with this refactor.
I'm inside of my indexed JS file.
Inside of here we've got the three create autocomplete function calls in a row.
We don't really need three different auto completes.
I just did that for testing purposes, so I'm going to delete the two.
Right there.
And we're going to go back to just one call to create autocomplete.
I'm also going to go to my index.html file and remove those two extra divs.
All right.
So let's continue on with this refactor.
I want to continue to add in some additional functions to that config object that we're passing to the
create autocomplete function.
We're then going to refactor the function to make sure that it uses the functions we had provided instead
of locating all that logic directly inside of the create autocomplete function.
So I think the next one we should try working on is render option.
So this is going to be a function that is going to be called with each different option or each kind
of object that we're getting back from that API.
We're going to pass it into this function and that function needs to return some kind of string.
That's going to be the HTML that shows up inside of the dropdown.
So in short, if we go back over to autocomplete JWs.
Here is create autocomplete.
And if we go down to our four of loop right now, right about here essentially where we're setting the
inner HTML of the option, remember we had said that this is assuming 100% that we always want to show
in image and then the title right next to it.
But we might decide that we want our autocomplete to work in some very different way.
Like, for example, maybe we won't have an image at all.
So right now this would be really challenging to customize because this is code that is located inside
of our autocomplete file, which we want to be as reusable as possible.
So instead, I want to extract the logic that decides what this thing looks like to a helper function
on that config object.
We're going to assume that that helper function is going to be called with each movie object that we
are iterating over.
Now, I know you see the variable movie inside of here quite a bit still.
And like I'm still using the term movie, we are going to eventually refactor the terminology inside
of here to not refer to movie anymore.
I just want to throw that out there really quickly.
Okay.
So back inside of our index case file, I'm going to find where we create the autocomplete.
I'm going to pass in a second property into this object.
I'm going to call it render option.
We could make this a function like, so we could also assign it as an arrow function.
No difference whatsoever.
We can really use either syntax.
So passed into this function, I'm going to expect to receive some object like each individual object
that represents some possible movie or whatever else, and I'll just refer to it as movie.
Then inside we're going to generate some HTML and return it.
And this will be the HTML to get shown for each individual option.
So we're going to have to extract all the logic we had around that.
It's not only the HTML right there, we also have to extract that line where we got the Image CRC as
remember in some cases the poster link was an A and we needed to make sure we handled that as well.
So I'm going to take the Image Z line right there.
I'm going to cut it.
I'm going to go paste it back inside of render option.
I'll then go and get the inner HTML that we had created right here.
I'm going to cut it.
Go back over to render option.
I'll paste it in here and return it.
So now we have extracted all of our rendering logic into this render option function, and it's going
to be called many times automatically with each movie that the autocomplete fetches.
So now we just need to make sure that the create autocomplete function references this function to figure
out what each option should look like.
So to do so, we'll go back over to the other file.
We're going to go up to the very top.
We're going to make sure that we structure off the render option function.
Then we'll go back down to that same four of loop.
Here it is right here.
I'll find where I left the option in or HTML.
So to generate the HTML to show for this option, we're going to call render option with the movie that
we are currently iterating over.
And there we go.
So now, once again, we've extracted some custom logic that is only appropriate for this movie related
stuff.
And if we ever decide that we want the autocomplete to look very different.
So if you want to generate some HTML for each individual option, we only have to update the render
option function back inside of index js.
So I'll now save this and do a quick test.
Back over here.
I'll refresh.
I'll look for Avengers and I still see the same thing.
Let's try making a change to the render option function just to see how easy it is now to make a change
and get something that looks slightly different.
As a quick reminder inside of the data that we get back from our API, it contains the year that the
movie was created.
So let's try printing out the year that the movie was created next to each option as well.
So to do so, I no longer this is the entire key right here.
This is the part to like listen to.
In other words, I no longer have to go hunting through and searching through all the source code of
the create autocomplete function to figure out how to change what each individual item looks like.
Instead, I can look at my render option function right here, which is very appropriately named.
If I see that name, chances are I would think to myself, Oh, this is where we decide how to change
what each individual option looks like.
So then inside of here, right after the movie title, I could put down like maybe a set of parentheses
and then inside there print out using dollar sign and curly brace movie dot yea.
So we can save that.
Go back over, refresh.
Look for Avengers again.
And now I see the year on there.
So hopefully this change is a little bit more meaningful when we start talking about all this refactoring
and kind of reusable logic stuff.
It is the presence of this function right here that will make it really clear to other engineers how
to customize and get some version of the autocomplete that works for their particular application.
I'm sure you can imagine that if we wanted to make even more changes to how each individual option looks,
we would just make some more changes to render option.
And that's it.
Okay.
So hopefully now you're starting to get a little bit more sense of the purpose of this whole refactor.
So let's take a quick pause right here and continue in the next video.