The next refactor we're going to do is for on option select.
So in other words, we're going to pull out all the logic that decides what function to run whenever
a user clicks on an option.
So to do so, I'm going to go back over to Autocomplete JS and we're going to find inside of here the
code responsible for doing something whenever a user clicks on an option.
So I'm going to scroll down a little bit inside of on input.
Inside of there is our for loop once again.
And then inside of there, after we create our option, we attach that event listener.
So this right here, this function is what's going to run after a user clicks on an individual option.
Now.
Something to be aware of inside of here.
The first line, like removing that is active class.
That's something that we want to have happen, irregardless of what goes on.
In other words, no matter what, whenever a user clicks on an option, we always want to close the
dropdown.
So we don't want to just kind of extract that function right there or somewhere else.
Instead, we only want to extract some parts of it.
I think one part that we very definitely like probably very clearly want to extract would be on movie
select right here because that is what actually decides what really happens or what goes on whenever
a user clicks on the button.
But the line that is kind of questionable about whether we need to extract or not is where we set the
inputs value with the movie title.
Half of this line.
In other words, like that half right there is very much appropriate for keeping inside of this autocomplete
file because it is related to how the autocomplete works.
And we probably want it to work the same way regardless of whether we're showing movies or recipes or
blog posts or whatever else.
But the source of it, in other words, movie title, that part of that line or that expression is very
much customized for the type of resource we're working with.
If we weren't working with movies, then instead this line should probably be something like blog name
or something like that or recipe name.
But in every scenario, we definitely want to take whatever that value is and throw it back into the
input value.
So this is kind of a more challenging refactor and we're going to have to think about exactly how to
handle that.
Right now, it's probably pretty obvious that we definitely want to extract the callback right there.
So at a very minimum, let's make sure that we create and pass in some function called like on options,
select on our config object and inside there we'll make sure that we call on movie select.
So back inside of indexes here is create autocomplete.
I'm going to pass in another function called on Option Select.
I'm going to expect that this is going to be called with whatever object that the user just clicked
on, and I'm going to call it movie.
So then inside of here, we can do the same exact thing that we did before where we call on Movie Select.
So I'll call on.
Movie Select.
And pass through the movie.
So then we can go back over to Autocomplete JS.
At the very top.
Once again, we can structure off that new function.
Which we called on Option Select.
And then back down at the event listener that we were just looking at instead of calling on Movie Select
right there directly.
Instead it will be on Option Select.
Now, this might seem like a very insignificant change right here.
Right?
Like what?
We just changed the name of the dropdown or the callback function.
Who cares?
Again, the entire point here is that if we had some scenario where we wanted to call a different function
right there, if we were using our autocomplete on another application, we would have had to open up
the source code for our autocomplete and change that line of code, which 100% not good.
We don't want to have to edit the source code of autocomplete JS.
So in doing this change we've extracted deciding what to do when a user clicks on something into this
configuration option over in indexed JS, which is going to contain all of our application specific
code.
So I know this seems like a smaller change, but it still is pretty meaningful.
Okay.
So now the other thing we need to be aware of that we discussed this line right here.
So again, the left hand side, it needs to happen for every instance in which we use an autocomplete,
but the source of information is really well, that's kind of application specific.
So I think that we need to pass in another helper function to our config object and I think that we
need to use that to decide exactly what value to assign when a user clicks on something.
So back inside of indexes, I'm going to add in another helper function.
I'm going to call it input value.
The goal of input value is going to be to take a movie.
And after a user clicks on the option, we're going to call it input value with the movie and we're
going to return whatever value it should show up inside of the input.
So I'm going to return movie title.
So this is how we're going to extract the logic out of Autocomplete JS.
So now to use that, we'll go back over to Autocomplete JS again.
Rather than directly referencing movie title, I will instead call input value.
But the movie.
Up inside of our config object up here at the very top of the file.
I'll make sure that I also extract input value from the config.
Object.
All right.
Now, one last thing I want to repeat really quickly here.
We still have many references to movie inside this file.
And so it might seem like we're making no progress in actually making this thing reusable.
Again, we are going to eventually come back through and replace the term movie with something else
that will be a little bit more consistent.
So we got one more step forward.
Let's do another test.
I'll refresh.
I'll search for Avengers a click and it looks like the input value still gets updated correctly.
So that's very good.
Let's now take one more pause and try to finish up this refactor in the next video.