The last thing we need to extract is fetch data.
So fetch data is being used inside of our Autocomplete JS file right now directly.
So if we go to Autocomplete JS, find our on input callback right here.
We're calling fetch data when we call fetch data right here.
That is a reference back to the fetch data that gets defined inside of indexes.
So this means that we have a direct link between these two files.
Autocomplete JS is directly referencing this function right here.
So if we ever deleted this function or renamed it or even just commented it out, our autocomplete would
no longer work correctly.
So we definitely do not want to have such a tight coupling between these two functions.
So we're just going to essentially take this function right here and we're going to throw it as another
argument or another option into our create autocomplete config object, or then going to update our
autocomplete file and make sure that it references the fetch data that is passed on that config object
instead of over this like direct global scope between the two files.
So to do so, I'm going to take just the function.
I'm going to cut it.
I'll delete the function name at the very top.
I'm going to add in a new key value pair to my configuration object.
I'll call it fetch data.
I'm going to put a set of parentheses and then paste the function.
Now.
I definitely have some mistakes on syntax inside of here, so I'm going to make sure that I fix those
up.
First off, we need to make sure that we mark fetch data as being async.
So I'm going to delete the async keyword right there and put it right in front of fetch data.
Well, then make sure that I take the search term.
And as the argument to fetch data.
And then finally I can remove the fetch data right there and the arrow and it should be good to go.
So make sure you triple check your syntax right there because definitely very easy to make a little
typo.
I'm also going to do a quick change or fix to the syntax or indentation.
There we go.
Okay.
So now we are passing the fetch data function as an argument into our create autocomplete configuration
object.
So now if we go back over to Autocomplete at the very top, once again, we will structure out the fetch
data function.
So now there is no direct kind of window scope access between these two different files, which is definitely
a good improvement.
All right.
So I think there's just one last thing for us to take care of.
We need to go through our autocomplete file and we need to find any reference to a movie in order to
actually make this code generic in nature and reusable.
We need to not make any big assumptions about the kind of data that we are working with.
So we just have to go through and change the words movie or movies to some other kind of appropriate
term.
So inside of here, I first see a movie on our label, says, Search for a movie.
I'm just going to change this to just a search.
I'll then go down a little bit.
So inside of on input, after we made a request, we called what came back movies.
So again, not appropriate to have the term movies inside of Autocomplete jars anymore.
So I'm going to change the term movies throughout this file to items.
So this kind of reflects that we have a collection of different items that we want to show inside that
dropdown.
So now we can go through and update every reference to movies, to items instead.
So the first one is inside the if statement.
I'll change that to items.
The next one is right here on the for loop.
And I think that is about it inside of here.
Let me do one more search.
Yep, that's it.
So now inside of the four loop itself, we'll change the term movie to item singular.
So on the for loop, I'll do item.
On render option.
I'll change it to item input value right here.
I'll change it to item.
On Option Select, we'll go to item and I think that is just about it.
I'll do a search for movie and nothing.
So make sure inside of Autocomplete JS you do a search for movie and if you see the word movie inside
of here, that is wrong.
We should not have any references to movies anymore.
All right.
And that's pretty much it.
Let's save this and think we're ready for one last test.
So I'm going to go back over to my index.html.
I'll refresh.
All search for Avengers again and everything works correctly.
The search occurred and I should be able to click on that and still see something appear.
If you see any errors inside of your console, I can just about guarantee you that you still have a
reference to movie or movies somewhere inside of Autocomplete.
JS So make sure that you find that remaining reference and update it to the appropriate term.
Okay.
So at this point in time, we now have a fully reusable function called Create Autocomplete.
We can take this function right here and we can use it on any other project we can think of, and we'll
get the exact same behavior as the one that we currently have inside of our application.
All we have to do.
Is called a function and pass in these appropriate different properties.
So we need to specify where to render the autocomplete to how to show an individual item.
What to do when someone clicks on one, what to kind of backfill inside of the input after a user clicks
on one, and then how to actually fetch the data.
As long as we put all that code inside there, then we're going to get a fully functioning autocomplete
ready to go.
So I know this last bit of the refactor is a little bit of a pain, but I hope that at this point it's
a little bit more clear why we went through this pain.
And I hope you can recognize that the code that we now have is quite reusable in nature.
So let's take a pause right here and continue with our application in the next video.