Just to make sure it's really clear why this refactor was so significant.
I want to show you how quickly we could change some of the code inside these different options that
we're passing in and get an autocomplete that works with a very different source of data.
So just as a quick example, you don't have to change your code here because I'm going to change my
code right back.
Again, this is a very quick example.
I'm going to go to JSON placeholder type ICLOUD.COM.
This is a fake API that can be used for testing purposes and just generally kind of messing around.
If I scroll down a little bit, I can find a section called Resources.
And inside there is an endpoint that will serve me up a photo's collection.
Inside there is 5000 different photos, so I encourage you not to click that link because it's going
to load up a ton of data and might make your browser hang.
Nonetheless, I'm going to go ahead and do it myself, so if I click on it after a second or so, I
will see that if I make a request to this endpoint, I'll get back an array of objects where each object
represents one photo.
Each photo has a title and a thumbnail URL.
I'm going to try to make a request and get just 50 of these photos inside of my code, and I'm going
to try to render each of them into that autocomplete that we just put together.
If I want to only get 50 photos instead of the 5000 that it just fetched, I could add on to the URL
question mark album ID equals one and that will give me only the first 50 photos inside of here.
So if I scroll down, I'll see that I only get 50 photos total.
Okay.
So to change my autocomplete to work with this source of data, instead I would take this URL and again,
you don't have to make these changes.
I'm going to change my code back very quickly.
This is just a fast demonstration.
I would then go and update my fetch data function, so instead of making a request to the IMDB API,
I'm going to instead just paste that URL in directly.
So slash photos album id equals one.
These params are technically not going to be used, but I can still just leave them in here.
The request is still going to work.
Actually, I'll take them out.
Just be sure.
Just to make sure it's really clear.
So I'll take those out.
I'll then make sure that when I get the response there is no longer a search property.
So I'll take out the dot search.
So this should work correctly to fetch the data.
Now, all we would have to do is make sure that we update how each of these gets rendered that is controlled
inside of render option right here.
So instead of the current code I have.
I would instead say, maybe just return.
An image element with the source of.
Movie Dot and let me double check the name of the actual image thumbnail URL.
And then I'll do the title, which is title.
So movie title.
Notice I'm still calling this argument movie.
It now technically is like an image object, but it's just not a good use of time to change the variable
name.
Okay.
So now I can save this.
Flip back over, refresh.
And now I should be able to just type anything inside of here.
Technically, there's no longer any searching operation going on, and I'll see this very different
source of data being used.
So now I've got each thumbnail, which is the colored squares you see along with the title of each image
showing up next to it.
And I've got all 50 being rendered out right now, so that's pretty much it.
That's all we would have to do to make a significant change to the autocomplete.
We just go back to these functions that we understand exactly what they do perfectly.
You know, this one fetches data, this one controls how each option gets rendered, make those various
few changes, and that's it.
We now have a widget that works in a totally different context.
Okay.
So that's just all I want to show you.
I'm going to very quickly undo the changes I just made and go back to working with movies and there
we go.
So now I'll do a quick test just to make sure I'm back and still works with movies.
Cool.
So again, just a quick examination of how you would change things out.
So let's take another pause here.
Continue the app in the next video.