Our Autocomplete widget is working out pretty well.
So now the last thing I want to do is to actually go back to the original application that we're working
on.
We need to make sure that we essentially have two different auto completes being displayed and they
need to kind of show up next to each other in like two separate columns.
We should also make sure that when the user first loads up the app, we show some kind of tutorial message
on the screen as well and tell them exactly what to do.
So in this video, we're going to change our HTML structure a little bit to make sure that we get these
two different columns and that tutorial message.
So we're going to do a lot of typing inside of our indexed HTML file.
So I'm going to open that up right away.
Once again, a lot of the different classes that we're going to add in here are taken directly from
the Boma CSS library.
We're not going to focus too much on the class names or the styling because again, class about JavaScript
that's we're here for.
Okay, so let's get to it.
Inside of here, I'm going to first begin by deleting the two elements we have inside of class container.
So we're going to essentially just rewrite all the structure we have.
Inside of class container and then going to create a class or a div with class of columns.
Inside there.
I'm going to do a div with the class of column.
Notice there's no se on there.
The one before had an se.
This one doesn't.
Inside of this one.
I'm going to show a div with an ID of left dash autocomplete.
So as you would guess, we're going to eventually use this as the root element for the autocomplete
that we're going to show.
On the left hand side.
I'm using a div here just to 100% identify this thing as a very unique element inside of my application,
and I only ever want to have one with that ID.
Okay.
I'm going to close off the div with class column right there.
And then after it, I'm going to put another div with the class.
Of column.
And inside there I'll do another div with an ID of right dash autocomplete.
And I'll close it off.
Yes.
That's a good place to get started.
Now, finally, after the div with class columns, the closing element for that or the closing tag is
right there.
So it's going to find the closing tag for the class columns.
And after it, I'm going to put in some markup to show a tutorial of sorts to the user.
So I'm going to do a div with a class couple of class names here.
So we're going to have column.
Is dash half.
Notification.
There we go is dash primary and tutorial.
I'll close off that div and we're going to show some message to the user inside of here so they understand
how to use our application.
So I'll do an H one with the class of title.
And I'll say something like Search for a movie on both sides.
And then after that I'll do a paragraph element with the class of subtitle.
With some texts like we will tell you which is best again, just to help our user understand what's
going on here.
Now, two things here.
Please double check your spelling of the word notification.
Very easy to misspell.
In addition, overall, just do a double check of all the HTML that we just wrote because very easy
to make several typos inside of here.
Make sure you've got columns and then column, column and column down there as well.
Yes.
I'm going to save this.
Now, we're not going to see any autocomplete appear right away because we remove the div with the class
of autocomplete.
So in fact, we're probably going to get a JavaScript error.
I just want to do a quick refresh and make sure that we see the tutorial on the screen.
That's what I really want to see right now.
So I'm going to go back over.
Going to refresh and yep, I definitely see that appear.
So now we can go back and we can start to wire up the two different autocomplete.
So we want to have one that's going to be rendered into right there and the other two right there.
So quick pause and we're going to make sure that we render both these auto completes in the next video.