All right.
Now that we've got this better HTML structure, we're going to go back over to our indexed JS file and
make sure that we show two separate auto completes, one that's going to use left autocomplete as a
root, the other is going to use write autocomplete as a root.
So back inside of my indexed JS file at the very top we are calling Create Autocomplete and we're passing
in a reference to a div with a class of autocomplete which doesn't exist anymore.
So I'm going to change that query selector to LB Right.
Dash actually, let's do left first left dash autocomplete.
I'll go ahead and save this.
So now if we flip back over and refresh, we see one autocomplete on the left hand side.
So now we need to essentially do the exact same thing to create the autocomplete on the right hand side
as well.
So you might be thinking that that means that we essentially have to duplicate all of this code right
here just to have a second call to create autocomplete with a different route.
We don't have to we don't have to duplicate all of this config.
So let me show you what we're going to do.
At the very top of the file, I'm going to create a new variable called auto complete config.
And I'll make it an object and we're going to go into our current autocomplete config.
So like this object right here and we're going to take out every option inside of here.
So every key value property, every function that is reusable between our two different auto completes,
we want to show.
Well, if we look through here, every single function inside is reusable except for the root element.
Maybe that maybe we'll go down the line and realize that it's not 100% reusable.
But for right now, I think that we definitely can reuse just about everything except for that root
element.
So I'm going to take render option.
I'll go down to the bottom of fetch data.
I'm going to highlight all that.
I'm going to cut all of it.
So now the only thing that's left is root.
I'm going to paste all of it inside of autocomplete config.
Like so.
So now inside of the create autocomplete function call right here.
We're going to essentially say create a new object, take all of the properties inside of autocomplete
config that we defined at the top of the file and then add in this new property of root and then take
that whole object and pass it off to create autocomplete.
So to do so, we're going to write out inside of here, dot, dot, dot.
Auto completes config and then a comma.
So the dot, dot, dot right there means make a copy of everything inside that object or essentially
take all the different functions inside there and throw them into this object and then add in this root
property as well.
And that's it.
So what we have right here is 100% equivalent to what we had just before.
But now, since Autocomplete config is its own separate object, we can repeat this process as many
times as we want and create additional auto completes with the same configuration object.
So to do so, I'm going to make a copy of create autocomplete config or simply create autocomplete just
the function call.
Well, paste it.
Now all we have to do is update the query selector.
So instead of saying left, I'm going to say, Right.
And that's pretty much it.
So I'm going to save this.
I'm going to go back over refresh and now I see the two separate auto completes.
I'm going to make sure I don't have any errors.
Nope, nothing inside my console.
Now, if I do a search for Avengers, it looks like the left hand side is working.
And if I do a search for Dark Knight on the right.
Yep, that's working as well.
I can click that Avengers click that.
Yep.
Looks good.
Now if I click on those, I probably going to see an error down here because we deleted the element
that showed the actual summary.
You're only call just a second ago when we were updating the HTML file.
So I think that the next obvious thing we have to do is make sure that once we search for something,
we need to hide this kind of tutorial element right here and show a summary on just the appropriate
side of the screen.
So let's take care of that process in the next video.