The next thing we have to do is to make sure that whenever we click on a video inside of our autocomplete,
we should hide this tutorial right here and start to show some summary information about that movie
on the appropriate side, either the left side or the right side.
So let's first take care of making sure that we just hide this thing.
To do so, I'm going to go back over I'm going to go up into my config object and I'm going to find
where we have the callback of on option select.
Here it is right here.
So I'm going to replace on option select or excuse me, I'm going to add to the code inside of it.
I'm going to get a selector for that kind of tutorial window that we just added in.
So inside my HTML file, here it is right here.
So I'm going to get a selector for a div with the class of tutorial and then we're going to add a class
to it that's going to hide that thing on the screen.
So inside of on option select, I'll do a document.
Where he selector.
With Dot tutorial.
I'm going to look at its class list.
I'm going to add in a class of is dash hidden like so.
This is another one of those classes that is coming from the Boma CSS framework.
So by just adding on that class, that div that is containing the tutorial should be hidden on the screen.
Let's do a save and a quick test so I'll flip back over.
Refresh.
Look for Avengers click and the thing is gone.
That was an easy one.
Another quick pause right here and we'll continue with showing the two tutorials on both sides in just
a moment.