All right.
Last thing we really have to do here is to make sure that when a user selects one of those movies,
we show a summary on the appropriate side of the screen.
So the first thing we have to do is to make sure that we have some developments to render the summaries
into.
Remember, at the bottom of the indexed JS file, we still have the movie template function, so we
essentially know what content we want to show.
We just need to make sure that we have some place to put it.
So inside of indexed HTML, I'm going to find where my div of left autocomplete is.
And right after it I'm going to add in a div.
With an ID of left Daesh summary.
And close it off and then I'll do the same thing right after the right autocomplete as well.
So it div with an ID of right dash summary.
Like so.
So now all we need to do is to make sure that whenever on Movie Select gets called, we render the summary
into the appropriate element either the left side or the right side.
So to make this happen, we're probably going to have to have two versions of either on Movie Select
or two versions of on option select up here.
Remember, right now we're using the same version of an option select between both the left hand side
autocomplete and the right hand side.
So I think that we should probably take on options, select and then throw it down into each individual
call to create autocomplete, and that will allow us to make a customized version for each one.
So to do so, I'm going to go up to my autocomplete config.
I'm going to cut on options.
Select out.
I'll then go down to my calls to create Autocomplete one and two.
And I'm going to paste that thing in so paste and paste and I'll make sure that I get a comma on the
line right above.
Otherwise, I'll see an error very quickly.
So now this one right here is for the left hand side, and this one right here is the right hand side.
So to make sure that we actually render the summary into the appropriate element, let's make sure that
when we call on movie select in both cases as a second element, I'm going to pass in a reference to
an element of where to render the summary to.
So on the first one, which is responsible for the left hand side, I'll get a document where he selector.
Or LB left dash summary.
And I'll do the same thing for the second one as well.
Document.
Query selector.
LB right.
DASH Summary.
So now inside of On Movie Select, we can receive that second argument.
So in addition to movie.
We received that other argument as like, how about summary target or something like that?
How about summary element?
I think that makes sense.
So then we're going to do that request to get more details about the selected movie.
And then instead of throwing the render template inside of some summery element that doesn't exist anymore,
instead we're going to throw it into the inner HTML of that summery element.
So going to replace that query selector with summary element.
Okay.
So let's save this and do a quick test.
Go back over.
I'll look for Avengers once again for the millionth time, click it and there's my summary on the left
hand side and I should be able to do Dark Night, look it and see the summary on the right hand side.
Now I should be able to go between both these and just make sure that they've got the appropriate values,
or I should just say different values to make sure that we're not accidentally leaking data from one
side to another.
So I'm looking through and yep, it all looks good.
Okay.
So now the very last thing we have to do here to really complete our application.
Remember, the last requirement of our project was to compare both the different stats and we need to
make sure that we color the greater stat on each side of the screen.
This is going to be a little bit more challenging than it seems because in some cases comparing these
things is actually kind of challenging.
For example, how do we really compare this string right here with this string?
How do we compare this number right here?
This is a string when it comes back from the API.
We know it's a string because it has the dollar sign and the commas in there.
So how do we compare that string versus that string?
It's pretty clear, I think, that we're going to have to figure out some ways to really compare these
different statistics.
And in some cases, it might require some special logic.
So one last pause and we're going to figure that stuff out in the next video.