Last thing we have to do is make sure that we get a comparison going between all these different stats.
So back inside of my index file, I'm going to find where we were just working on on Movie Select.
We're going to eventually do a request inside of here, remember to get some follow up details about
a particular movie.
Now, one thing we should probably do inside of here is get a reference or story, a reference to that
response that comes back so we can hold on to that reference, that movie, in all those different statistics,
so we can do an easy comparison later on.
So right above on Movie Select, I'm going to define it two variables with the keyword.
So I'll say let left movie and right movie.
Then inside this function, after we get some data back from Axios, let's make sure that we store the
movie that we just fetched on the appropriate variable.
To do so, we're going to need to make sure that we pass in some additional argument here to indicate
whether we are receiving the movie on the left side or the right side.
So inside of both the functions where we call on Movie Select, I'm going to pass in one last variable
here of left as a string and right as a string.
So now we know the context in which on movie select is being called.
So inside of here, I'm going to receive that as variable that I'll call simply side.
And then right after we set that in our HTML, we can say something like If side equals left, then
let's update the left movie variable.
So I'll say left movie is response dot data.
Else we must be working with the right side.
So I'll say right movie.
Is response data.
Then after we update both those variables, we should add in a check to see if both the left movie and
right movie are defined.
If both these variables are defined, that means we have a movie on both sides of the screen and it's
time to run the comparison.
So after those if ll statements, I'll say if.
Left movie.
And Wright's movie.
Then let's run the comparison.
I'm going to stick all the code for doing the comparison into a helper function called appropriately
named Run Comparison.
And I'll define that as a helper function right after.
So then inside of here we can iterate through our two different movies, run all the comparisons, and
then update the appropriate statistics on both sides of the screen.
So inside of here, I'm going to do a quick console log for right now and say time for comparison just
to make sure that we are running this code at the appropriate time.
I'll then go back over, refresh, get that console open.
And then I'll do Avengers.
Here we go.
And Dark Knight.
And after I click this movie, it would then be, in theory, time to run the comparison.
So I'd expect to see the console log up here at that time.
So I'll click there and I do, in fact see time for comparison.
So it looks like we're off to a good start.
So now another quick pause.
We'll come back to the next video and figure out how we're going to actually compare all these different
statistics.