All right.
So in this video, we're going to implement our run comparison function.
Now, as I mentioned just a moment ago, implementing this function is going to be just a little bit
challenging because the metrics that we're comparing here aren't always just plain numbers.
In this case, we've got some strings, so we need to figure out how to compare these different values.
But there's actually another reason that this is kind of a challenging little problem.
Let me tell you exactly why I want you to think about the exact logic or kind of ordering in which we
would run the comparison inside this function.
The first statistic that we print out down here is the number of awards or that whole award string and
then the box office and then the metascore.
So it's clear that we need to somehow reach into the DOM.
We need to select this element on both sides of the screen because remember, there's really two of
these elements on the screen, one for each movie we search for.
So we need to find this first element.
Like the first element with the class of notification is primary and a article tag.
And we're going to essentially assume that that is of type awards or displaying the award stat.
So we might end up running some code inside of here that looks like this.
I'm just going to give you a very quick example.
Maybe something like find the first article element for each movie, then run a comparison on the number
of awards, then apply some.
Styling to that article element.
The key thing here is that we're just looking for the first article for each movie.
Then we're assuming that that first article element represents the number of awards statistic.
If we start to write some code like this, we're going to very quickly end up in a bad spot.
Let me tell you why.
If our code just looks at the first element and assumes it is awards, we could break our application
super quickly by going back down to our template and just changing the order of statistics.
So in other words, I could take this first statistic block cut it and move it underneath that first
one or the second one.
So now the award statistic is second in the list.
So if I ever wanted to reorder the different statistics that I'm showing here, I would also have to
make an update to the run comparison function.
Because now the first article in the list represents the box office amount.
So we'd have to update this code to run a comparison on the box office value instead.
And then it kind of follows that.
The second comparison I would have to update from box office to instead take a look at number of awards.
So in other words, we don't really want to encode the order of statistics here and try to read it out
of our HTML to figure out what order we're going to compare these different statistics in.
So that kind of throws that approach out the window.
So how are we going to like actually fix this?
How are we going to actually approach it?
Well, I've got one kind of crazy idea.
That's going to kind of solve a lot of the different issues that we're going to run into up front,
particularly that other issue around, like comparing strings versus strings.
I think that when we run the movie template function, we should add in a data property to each of these
different articles.
And we should make the data property a number version, like an easily comparable version of each of
the different statistics that we want to show.
So in other words, I think it would be awesome whenever we run movie template for each of these different
articles on the article itself, I want to put in like a data value property and maybe set it to for
this first box office value something like 623 million.
So I'll say something like data value is 623 million or so.
Then later on, when we decide to run our comparison, rather than trying to look at the order of articles
and figure out that we first have like box office, then awards, then metascore or whatever, we can
just read that data value property and compare it against the data value property for the first article
on the other side of the screen.
So in other words, we're throwing the idea that this is like the box office statistic out the window
inside the run comparison function.
The only thing run comparison will care about is that data value property.
So we can just take a look at the data value property on each pair of articles and then take a look
at which one is greater and apply the appropriate class to each one to color that notification as either
green or yellow.
Now, this is yet another scenario where I know, as I explain this, it probably sounds crazy and a
little bit complicated.
So let's once again write some code.
As soon as we do, I think you'll get a good idea of why we're doing this so quick pause and we'll start
to implement this approach in the next video.