All right.
So like I said in this video, we're going to update our movie template function.
We're going to take a look at some of the different properties inside that movie detail object.
Remember movie details, an object with some expanded properties that describe a particular movie for
each of the different properties or statistics that we're printing out.
We're going to turn each of these into some easy to represent number value, and then we're going to
add each of them as a data property to each of these different articles.
And so that will make it really easy to compare these different values later on without having to worry
about the order in which they're being presented or anything like that.
So inside of here, the first thing we're going to do at the top of the function is take a look at some
of the different properties on movie detail and then turn them into a easy to compare number format.
So this is unfortunately going to be just once again a little bit challenging.
So the first number that we're going to try to generate is a number representation of the box office
value.
So I'm going to assign that to dollars because that's essentially how this is being represented.
So I want to take a look at the box office value, which currently is like that string right there,
number 623 with commas in it or 533 with commas in it and whatnot.
And I want to turn that into a normal integer that we can compare very easily.
So back over inside of here, I'm going to say that dollars is movie detail.
Box up Capital B box office.
So this right here is a string.
And once again, it's going to look something like this, maybe 629, blah, blah, blah.
So we want to remove the dollar sign and we also want to remove any commas in there as well.
So to do so, we can use some normal string manipulation methods.
On box office, I'm going to call replace.
I'm going to find any dollar sign character.
And replace it with an empty string, which essentially just removes it out of that string.
Now because I'm using a dollar sign inside of a regular expression right here.
I do have to escape it.
Remember what we spoke about earlier on inside the course about regular expressions.
Dollar sign is a protected value, so we just have to put a kind of backslash right in front of it.
So that's going to take the dollar sign out and just remove it entirely.
Now we need to repeat that same step for all the commas in here as well.
So once again, call, replace.
I'm going to find all the commas.
And replace them with empty string.
That's going to take out all the commas.
Now I just need to take this string and turn it into a number to do so.
I can call parse int on that entire expression.
So that's going to parse an integer out of that string.
Now as a quick test as usual, I'll just try to do a console log of dollars.
So I'll save that.
Flip back over.
Refresh.
I'll look for Avengers and I see a number version of 623 million appear.
So now we're going to repeat that same process.
For all the different values on here, we're going to essentially run some custom logic on each of them
to turn them into some number that we can insert for each article element and then compare later on.
The next one will do is the Metascore.
You might think that Metascore doesn't need any work whatsoever because it looks like it is a actual
number.
Well, if you go back to your network request log and look at the expanded detail requests that we're
making, metascore actually is a string.
Just about everything inside of here is a string.
So for every one of these different values, we need to parse them into a number and then throw them
into the DOM METASCORE.
IMDB rating and IMDB votes all included.
So the next one I'll do, I'm going to delete that console log and I'll do metascore.
That's going to be parse int out of movie.
Detail dot meta score.
Next one I'll do is how about IMDB rating?
This one's a little bit more challenging.
Notice how it can possibly have a decimal on it.
So in JavaScript there's a difference between parse int and another function called parse float.
Parse int is going to prevent us from having a decimal.
But if we use parse float, that can take a string that has a decimal on it or in it and turn that into
a full number with a decimal.
So for IMDB score or is it called rating?
Where is it?
Yep.
IMDB rating.
We're going to do a parse float with movie details IMDB rating.
Then we could do the same thing for the number of votes as well.
This one can use a parse int because there is no decimal on it.
However, we do have to remove all the commas in there.
So I'll do IMDB votes is PA's int.
Movie detail dot imdb votes.
It's going to double check that property name.
Yep.
That's it.
And IMDB votes.
We need to make sure that we go through that thing and replace.
Any comma we see with an empty string.
Yet as another quick test, lets console log out.
Metascore.
IMDB rating and imdb votes.
So I'll save this refresh.
I'm going to once again look for The Avengers.
I don't actually like The Avengers, by the way.
I'm a way bigger DC fan, but I figure everybody out there probably knows what Avengers is.
That's why I'm using it here.
Just a quick side note.
Okay, so we've got the numbers 69, eight and blah, blah, blah.
So it looks like we've got all of our values out of here appropriately.
The last one we have to take care of is the actual value right there, the number of awards.
Now, parsing a number out of here is going to be a little bit more challenging.
So, as usual, a quick pause and I'll see you in just a minute.