The last statistic we need to parse is the number of awards.
So how are we going to reduce this down to something that can be easily compared between different movies?
Well, we're just going to take all the different awards or the total number of awards here.
So we're going to find all the different numbers in here, add them all together, and we'll say whoever
had the most numbers inside the statistic wins.
So technically, one movie that has like one win but 100 nominations will beat out a movie with ten
wins.
In theory, the movie with ten wins and like zero nominations would be better.
But for our purposes or the purposes of this application, we're just going to say whoever had the most
numbers in this thing is the winner.
So let's write out some code that's going to take a look at that string and extract the total number
out of it.
Back over here inside of movie template are going to delete that comment up top.
I'm going to delete the console log.
And then we're going to declare a new variable called.
Awards.
So for this one, we'll take a look at movie.
Detail.
We're going to look at the awards property, which is that big long string.
We're going to first begin by splitting it on space.
This right here is going to give us an array where every element in the array is one of the different
actual words or numbers in here.
So essentially all the spaces go away and just the element words we get inside of an array.
So then we're going to iterate through that array and we're going to say that for every actual number
in there, we're going to keep some running total and then eventually return it.
And we're going to write this out in two different ways.
We're going to write it out first with a for each, and then we're going to refactor it to use a reduced
statement instead.
This is a perfect location to do a reduce, but just as some quick practice just to get familiar, because
we're already doing some hard enough things here, we'll first do a four each.
So right above I'm going to declare a variable called count and start it off with zero.
This is going to track the number of award values.
So in this case, we would have like about what, 118 for this movie right here.
That's one plus 79 plus 38.
So on split.
Remember that gives us an array.
So call for each.
And then I'm going to take each word.
Inside of that sentence.
And I first need to see if I am working with a number or not.
The first time that function gets called, it's going to receive the word nominated.
That's obviously not a number.
So to check to see if we're working with a number or not, we're going to first try to parse this thing.
So I'll say value is pass int with word.
If we try to parse an int on a string that doesn't contain any number whatsoever, we're going to get
back a value of not a number.
Let's do a quick test of that inside of our console over here very quickly, just to get a reminder
of of that behavior.
So over here, I'll do a percent of not a number and I get back n a n, which again stands for not a
number.
So if I do parse int on, say nominated.
Yeah, we definitely get back.
Not a number.
So that's how we're going to tell if we're working with an actual number or not.
Value is going to be not a number.
So to check to see if we have a number or not, we will say if is nen n a n like.
So that's how we check to see if a value is not a number or not inside a JavaScript.
That is a function that is built into the browser.
So we don't need to define it or anything like that.
So we're going to say if this value is not a number, then we're just going to stop.
The return statement right here is just going to return from the inner function.
So in other words, we're going to say don't try to add anything to count or anything like that.
Otherwise we'll do count is count plus value like so.
So now at the very end, I'll do a console.log of count and we'll test this thing out for that first
movie.
I'll refresh.
Look up, Avengers, click it.
And there we go.
I get the 118.
So again, that is the one plus 38 plus 79.
So we could stop there and just say, Oh yeah, count is our variable.
But instead, like I said, let's try to refactor this for each into a reduced statement instead because
this really is a perfect place to make use of reduce.
So with reduce remember we're going to change the for each to reduce.
Then the second argument to the reduced function.
The first is the actual function we want to run.
The second is going to be the starting value for our reduction.
So in our case, our starting value is zero.
Then the first argument to that inner function is going to be the previous value and the second will
be the word that we are currently iterating over.
So then inside of this function body, we need to make sure that we return the next value for the next
iteration through this loop.
So right here in the return case, rather than just returning nothing, we're going to instead return
previous.
So at the value that we just are iterating over right here is not actually a number, then just return
whatever our current count is.
Otherwise, we're going to return the previous value that we got, plus this new value.
Okay.
So now we can delete the count up here.
And just to make sure this works correctly, again, I'm going to do a console.log now of awards.
I'll save that.
Another quick test.
So refresh.
Look up Avengers.
Look at.
And I still get the 118.
All right.
So that is it.
We've now extracted some meaningful values out of all these different statistics.
So now the last thing we have to do is take these different values and inject them as data properties
on each of these different articles.
Once again, once we do that, we can then pull those values out later on when we decide that it is
time to compare these different statistics.
So a quick pause right here, and we'll take care of that in the next video.