All right, now that we've got all these statistics, let's make sure that we add each of them to the
appropriate article elements inside of our template.
So down here I have my first article right there that is meant to show the number of awards.
So on that article element, I'm going to add in a data value property and I'm going to inject the value
awards to it.
And we can repeat that same process for the other articles as well.
So the next one is supposed to show box office.
I think we called the relevant statistic dollars.
Yeah, there it is right there.
So I'm going to go back down.
There is the box office statistic on the article.
I'll do a data value.
Of dollars.
The next one is a data value of metascore.
And we've got our IMDB rating.
So data value of IMDB rating.
And then finally, data value.
IMDB votes.
And that should be it.
As usual, we'll do a quick save and a test.
So the test in this case is to inspect our DOM elements and just make sure that we are assigning some
reasonable values to each one.
So I will refresh.
I'll look up Avengers.
Whoops.
I accidentally typed dollar instead of dollars.
My mistake.
There we go.
Dollars on the second one.
Avengers again.
I like it.
That's better.
So now I can inspect my Dom.
I'm going to look at each of these elements and just make sure that they have the appropriate value
property.
And there we go.
So I can see the list of articles.
There's the first one.
It has a data value of 118.
Then I've got the number value for the dollars, then the METASCORE, the IMDB rating, and finally
the number of votes.
So that's pretty much it.
We can now repeat that same process for this stuff on the right hand side as well.
So over here I'll look up Dark Knight.
I'll do an inspect of that element right there.
And I get 309 awards.
Wow, that's pretty crazy.
Then I get the about 533 million, then 84 METASCORE and nine IMDB rating.
And finally, 2 million votes.
Okay.
So that's it.
Now, the very last thing we have to do inside of our compare run comparison function right here.
We can now iterate over all those different article elements.
So we're going to iterate over both them at the same time.
Basically, basically get this collection on the left hand side and this collection on the right hand
side, and then we'll compare each of them one by one by looking at their data value properties, whichever
one is greater.
We're going to apply some classes to to colored as yellow.
Otherwise we'll leave it as is and just leave it green.
It's that's the idea.
One more quick pause and we're going to wrap this thing up in the next video.