All right, let's get to it.
Let's run our comparison on both sides.
The first thing we have to do is select all of these different articles, and we need to make sure that
we keep the two different sets separate.
As a quick reminder, if we open up our element, Inspector, again, the entire summary on the left
hand side is enclosed inside of a div with an ID of left summary.
So if I want to get all the articles that have a statistic inside of there I can select.
So document query selector.
I'd left a summary that's going to give me essentially the entire left side, and then I can find all
of the elements inside there with a class of notification.
So I'll do inside of that a query selector of dot notification.
I don't want to do a query selector.
My mistake.
I won't do a query selector.
All that will give me all of them.
So there we go.
There's my list of five.
I've got all five on the left hand side.
Just to be clear, we don't actually have to run the two separate query selectors.
We could actually reduce that down to just one.
So I could do document query selector all and then say inside of the left summary element, find all
the elements with notification.
And that will still give me all five on the left hand side.
So that's how we're going to make sure that we get all five on the left and all five on the right.
Okay.
So back over here inside of run comparison, we're going to get all the elements on the left and right.
I'll say, how about left side stats?
So that's like the statistics being rendered out on the left hand side.
Will be document query selector.
Paul.
And then we want ID.
Left side.
What would we call it?
Left or left?
Summary.
My mistake.
Dot notification.
Then we can do the same thing for right side stats and that will be document query selector all.
Right.
Dash summary.
Dot notification.
All right.
So now we can loop over either one of these and at each step we can take the corresponding element from
the other pair or essentially like the right hand side.
And we can do our comparison by retrieving the data set values.
So I'm going to try to iterate over each element inside of left side stats.
So I'm going to do a left side stats for each.
So I'm going to get my callback function right here.
I'm going to receive each article element.
I will call them left stat.
So again, that represents an article element that is going to have that data set value that we really
care about.
And I'm also going to get the index of that element inside of left side stats as well.
The reason I'm getting the index right there is that I can retrieve the appropriate corresponding stat
from right side stats.
So I'll say right.
Stat is.
Right side stats at index.
And then again, just to make sure we're doing everything correctly here, I'll do a console log of
left stat and write stat.
That's all safe.
Go back over.
Do the refresh.
I'll look for Avengers.
Dark Knight.
And there we go.
We've got our console logs.
So we can see that each of these console.log pairs are the two corresponding article elements that go
with each other.
So like that one and that one.
And then the box office.
Box office.
Metascore.
IMDB rating and so on.
So then inside of here, we're going to do first get the actual value property off of each of these.
So I'm going to say left side value is going to be left stat.
And to get a data set property, remember we referred to data set and then the name of that data property
on that element.
So in our case, we call the data properties value.
So we would reference that value property.
With data set value.
And then we can get the right hand side.
With the right side, value is the right side or the right statcast data set value as well.
So now inside of here, we can do our comparison directly between the two.
Again, take note that this comparison process right here, because we assign the stats up front inside
of our movie template, we don't care about the order in which these different stats occur.
They can occur in any different order.
We can have the box office value, then the rating, then the METASCORE or the totally opposite, and
it just doesn't matter.
All we have to do is make sure that we are iterating through the same properties on both sides at the
same time.
So in other words, we could not show like first awards over here and then first box office over here.
That's the only thing that we could not do.
So inside of here, I'll say if right side value is greater than left side value, that means the right
side is greater.
And that means that we want to add a class to the left hand side that's going to turn it yellow instead
of the default green.
So to make sure that we turn the left side yellow, we would run left stat which remember is the actual
article element.
I'm going to look at the class list.
I'm going to remove the is primary, which is what makes it green.
Again, this is some class names coming from Boma CSS.
And then on the left stat class list, I will add in is dash warning.
And that's what's going to turn it yellow.
So now we can repeat the same process for the opposite case as well.
So I'll say else.
Right.
Stat class list remove is primary.
And it writes that class list ad is warning.
All right, so that should be it.
So here it is.
This is our moment of truth.
This should be like the entire application all put together.
Let's do our final test.
So I will do a refresh.
I'm going to look for Avengers.
We'll look for Dark Knight.
There we go.
And.
All right.
That is it.
And it's looking pretty good.
So we can look through all these different stats.
And we should see that the stats that are in green are greater than the ones in yellow.
So first off, we've got like 118 wins versus the like 300 and change.
So definitely the correct one is green.
While The Avengers had a higher box office value, so that definitely won out.
However, Dark Knight has a better METASCORE, better IMDB rating and more votes as well, so that's
pretty much it.
That is the whole application.
Well, I hope you enjoyed putting this thing together.
Let's take a quick pause right here when we come back.
The next video, we're going to do a quick review on some of the important points around this application.