All right, my friends, in this video, we're going to do a quick wrap up of this application.
There's just a couple of things I want to point out really quickly that were really important to understand
or none.
The most important thing about this application was to understand the create autocomplete function.
The entire goal here was to create a widget that was entirely reusable in nature.
And we saw a little bit earlier how we could very easily swap out a source of data with the fetch data
function and the render option function as well to customize what the autocomplete looked like and that
was done very easily.
Think about how we would customize this widget if we didn't have access to this options object.
We would have had to go through all the code inside of here and customize each line one by one to change
the source of information or change how each option was displayed.
So by extracting all this logic into the separate file, you can now take this file right here, add
it to any other project that uses the Boma CSS framework and ta dah!
You've got a working autocomplete.
That's pretty much it.
The other big thing we learned about was that whenever we wanted to create a reusable widget, it was
kind of important to locate all the HTML for that inside the widget itself as opposed to our HTML file.
Again, if we had tried to keep our HTML inside of the HTML document around the autocomplete, you and
I, for every autocomplete we want to show, would have had to put something inside of here of like
input and then a div with a class of dropdown.
And then inside there another one with dropdown menu and so on.
And that would have had to have been done every single time we wanted to show an autocomplete.
So we got around that by instead saying, You know what?
Inside of our HTML document, we're going to show just the absolute minimum.
Kind of like a placeholder to display the autocomplete.
It was then up to the widgets code to initialize the HTML inside there.
And so again, this is what made our widget very reusable because now we don't really care about what
has to be displayed inside of it.
We can just say create autocomplete and the widget is going to set itself up automatically.
The last thing we really focused on while we focused on a lot.
But definitely one of the bigger items was to really figure out how to run that comparison appropriately.
So in this scenario, we realize that trying to pull stats out after the fact from our different movie
objects would probably be really challenging because we would be limited to being to how often we could
reorganize or reorder the different statistics.
So instead inside of our movie template, we decided up front to extract all the relevant values and
store those values inside of our DOM.
So then we could easily pull those values out later on from the run comparison function by just finding
those elements and then referencing the appropriate data set value.
Then we could do a very easy comparison without having to worry about what we were actually comparing.
Imagine what we would have had to write in here if we were trying to throw in like the entire awards
string into each DOM element.
We would have had to say something like left side value right here, and then we would have to do some
code.
Like if left side value contains awards or something like that, we've had to write some code like that
to determine or try to figure out whether or not we were working with the award string.
So doing that after the fact would have been really challenging.
So instead we just did all the processing up front and that made our life down the road way easier.
Okay.
So that's pretty much it for this application.
So let's take a quick pause right here.
We still have a ton to learn.
We'll continue in the next video.