Next up, we'll see one of my favorite new features in JavaScript.
Async functions.
So async functions.
And this entire section depends extremely heavily on promises.
Make sure that you are comfortable with promises.
And if you're not.
Go through the previous, I think two sections ago, the promises section because at their core async
functions are just a nice syntactical sugar for promises.
It's a nice, clean, easy syntax to work with promises, but you still have to understand promises.
All right.
So let's start with a quick intro to the main idea behind async functions.
If we have some regular old function, let's call it get data.
And get data makes a request using Axios.
I already have Axios included.
Or we could use fetch or even an XR if we are a bit psycho.
Let's do Axios dot get i have a URL.
It doesn't matter.
We're not building anything with this, but I'm fetching some information using Axios in a regular function.
If I tried to console.log something afterwards, let's say I wanted a variable called data and I want
to set it equal to the result of running Axios.
Get this URL and then console that log data.
What will we see when I run?
Get data.
Okay.
Let's try it out.
It's not going to work to give us the data.
All that we see is a promise.
So X don't get returned to promise.
And we console.log that promise.
The promise was pending.
Now it's hopefully resolved, but it doesn't matter.
We don't have access to that resolved value anyway because we're not waiting.
We're not using.
Then, as we've seen with promises in order to run code when the promise is resolved.
So it would be nice if we could write code like this where we could just write one line and act as if
JavaScript was synchronous, meaning that this code would not run until this finished.
But instead we've got to do this then as we've seen data and then we console.log data.
So we'll see our first console.log of data which should print out a promise if I run it.
There we go.
And then we see what we get back.
So nothing new here.
Just reiterating the fact that we can't write code like this where we expect this thing to be done first.
If we have code that relies on an asynchronous operation like an Axios get method call we need to use,
then assuming it returns a promise which Axios don't get, does otherwise we would pass in a callback.
So this is nothing new.
This does not work.
But it would be nice if it did right.
It's kind of obnoxious that we have to worry about callbacks and then and that is the entire point of
the async and await keywords.
So there are two new keywords to pieces to making this work.
Two pieces of the puzzle.
And by the end of this section, you'll see how we could write a function that looks pretty much like
this, with no doubt.
Then really no explicit mention of promises or callbacks, and the function will look like it's a synchronous
function.
Like this happens first and then as soon as it finishes this runs.
But behind the scenes there will be promises involved and thens and promises being resolved.
Thanks to the magic, the syntactical sugar of async and await.
So that's the whole goal.
Doesn't give us anything we can't already do with promises.
It just makes it easier and cleaner to work with promises and create synchronous looking asynchronous
code.
So let's see how it works in the next video.
We'll start with the async keyword.