All right.
So there are two pieces async and await two separate keywords.
We're going to start with async.
So we use async in front of a function declaration or function expression.
We use it to designate a certain function as an async function.
And the key thing to understand about this keyword is when you put it in front of a function like I
have here, this function behaves differently.
It's now going to return a promise.
So even though I never write new promise, I don't explicitly say, Hey, return a promise.
I'm simply saying return a string because I put async there.
The function now returns a promise and I can show this to you.
Let's make a simple function.
We'll just call it greet, function, greet, console.log.
Actually, that's not console.log.
Let's return.
Hello.
Okay.
No surprise if I call greet.
Right now it's not an async function.
We get a string back.
JavaScript 101 return a string.
We get a string.
Now, if I duplicate this and put the async keyword in front of my function declaration, now when I
call greet, what I get is a promise.
Promise that was returned and resolved with the value of hello.
So whatever the value that I'm returning is, the promise that will be returned from greet will be resolved
with that value.
So I could do something like greet dot then and we'll just call this value and then we can cancel that
log promise resolved with and then we can add in value.
So I can chain on a dot then because greet is now going to return a promise.
Test it out.
There we go.
Promise resolved with hello.
Let's say we have another function.
This one will be trivial as well.
Let's go with ADD and it takes in x and y.
It returns the sum of x plus y.
Right now, if we don't make it async, it just returns a number, assuming we pass in two numbers.
If we make it async by putting the async keyword first, if I call ADD, we get a resolved promise with
the value that it's resolved with set to nine.
So I could use a dot.
Then these two simple functions make kind of no sense at all to use promises with or to make async because
they're not doing anything asynchronous.
Why use a promise?
But the next thing I want to mention is how do we return a promise that is not resolved?
So if things go well, we return a value.
Return the string.
Hello.
That promise returned from greet is going to be resolved with hello or with a number nine in this case
if we add four and five.
But sometimes we want to make promises where they might be rejected, they might be resolved.
And instead of an async function, if we want to return a rejected promise, all that we do is raise
an exception.
So if we throw an exception, we throw an error.
That promise will be rejected.
So if we use this add example, let's check if X and Y are actually numbers.
If they're not, we'll throw some sort of exception.
So we could just check if x let's do type of x equals number or if it's not equal to number, let's
do that.
Or type of y is not equal to number.
Then we can throw x and y must be numbers.
Okay.
So let's not make this an async function for a moment.
Just a regular old function.
If we run it and I call add with E and I don't know five.
There we go.
Uncalled exception x and y must be numbers.
So the logic works.
No promises involved whatsoever.
We call it with numbers.
Instead, everything is good.
Now if I make it async, try it again.
Add four and five.
We have a return value.
This code was running and so the promise is resolved with that return value.
If I call it with a string, something that's not a number, we still get a promise back, but it's
been rejected.
X and y must be numbers so I could call add on E and R.
Sure I can put on my dot.
Then let's go with val console.log.
Why don't I just copy this here.
Promise resolves with val and I could put a catch as well and promise rejected with.
And then we'll print the error.
So I'm just calling ADD.
But ADD is an async function, which means it returns a promise.
It may be rejected, it may be resolved.
I can handle it either way.
And if we take a look, I run my code, we get promise rejected with X and Y must be numbers.
So at this point, async functions are with what we've seen.
They're a nice way of returning a promise.
Take a moment and think of how you would write this yourself.
So without using an async function, but by manually creating the promise and resolving slash rejecting
it, here's what I would do.
It would look something like this function add x, comma y.
Then we would return a new promise.
We have our resolve, function, parameter and reject.
And if none of this looks familiar to you, make sure you check out the promises section.
I can't say that enough.
It really helps.
So we have our new promise.
And then in here we can move this logic.
But we're going to change it a bit.
If type of X is not a number or type of y is not a number.
Instead of throwing, we're going to reject the promise.
Like that.
And then here we would resolve with X plus Y.
So if I comment out my async version and we take a look at our manual promise creation, it's called
ADD.
This code should still work fine.
So I should be catching this error, the rejected promise and we get the same output.
If I instead do two numbers like I don't know why keep doing four and five.
How about six and seven?
Refresh promise resolved with 13.
All right.
So an async function on one level is just a shortcut syntax to make a function that returns a promise.
If you return a value like we do here, that value will be the value the promise is resolved with.
If you throw an exception instead, that promise will be rejected with this value.
So our then callback or catch callbacks still work.
But this is not all there is to async functions.
That is the async keyword.
And shortly we'll see the await keyword, which makes things even more magical.