Next up, we move on to part two.
The second key word await.
So we have async, which we use to declare an async function.
It basically is a fancy way of wrapping that function in a promise.
But a wait is really magical.
We put the await keyword inside of an async function and it will pause the execution of the function
while it waits for a promise to be resolved so it will await something without having to use a dot.
Next, we can run code after an asynchronous operation without having to nest things with callbacks.
So here's an example.
Let's use Axios, which I already have included.
Just do the same old dumb planet API from Swampy and I have Axios.
As you can see here we have get that returns a promise instead of returning a promise myself from a
function let's call this get planets return Axios dot get like that and then doing get planet dot.
Then let's say I want to cancel that log the planet's after the fact.
So get planet dot then rez.
Console.log Rez dot data.
So hopefully this works.
No async function involved.
There we go.
We get the data so we return a promise.
Then we have to use dot then and wait until the callback is actually executed and our code gets broken
up.
It's a little harder to read.
It's still much better than passing in a bunch of callbacks to a function since we're using promises.
But the easier way is to declare an async function, get planet.
We'll do our Axios dot, get pass in the URL.
And the craziest part right here is await Axios dot get and we'll save the value that the promise is
resolved with to a variable.
I'll call this rez.
And then I'll put a line after here console.log rez dot data.
Same thing I had here.
So this looks like it's synchronous.
This is going to happen.
It doesn't matter how long it takes.
We'll get some response value.
We'll call it Rez.
Then this will run after that promise is resolved.
Only after it's resolved.
So we don't have to use dot then it looks like a nice, cute synchronous function.
One thing happens, it finishes, the next thing happens and it finishes.
And that is what the awake keyword does.
But let's verify that it actually does.
So let's do get planet refresh over here.
Awesome.
So this returns a promise, as we've seen before.
If I just run it over here, we get whoops, copy the wrong part.
If I just run the Axios, get that, returns a promise.
Normally without a wait, we console.log data.
We'll get an error.
Now, while we don't get an error, we get undefined.
There is no data property because this is a promise that is returned and it's not yet resolved when
this runs.
But by putting a wait here, JavaScript will wait.
It will not move on until this promise is resolved.
So the promise will be resolved.
That value is resolved with that's normally passed to.
Then we'll just be stored in this variable and then we have access to it on the very next line.
It's important to know, though, you can only use a weight instead of an async function.
This will not work.
I get a nice error.
A weight is a reserved word.
I cannot do it unless I'm in an async function.
So even for just one single request like we have here, this is still much easier to read.
We don't have to do dot then we don't need an extra callback.
It's not horrible to do that and to work with promises.
But this is so nice, right?
It's just syntactic sugar.
So it still uses promises behind the scenes.
It just kind of hides it from you and it makes it look synchronous.
But it's still easier to read.
It's easier to write.
And as you'll see, when we start making more requests or doing more asynchronous operations, it's
very easy to see what happens first, then second and third and so on.
So we'll get some more practice.