All right.
So this is great, very short and easy way to wait for an asynchronous operation to complete before
running the next line.
But what if the asynchronous operation, if that promise is not resolved?
What if it's rejected?
Right now it's working out.
I have Internet.
I'm not requesting an invalid URL, but if I change that, this endpoint should give me a 404.
Axios is going to reject the promise.
I don't have a catch.
I don't have any sort of error handling what happens.
Let's see.
Hmm.
Anchored in promise.
Error request.
I don't have any code that I'm running either to catch that error.
Maybe to make it different.
Request to tell the user something went wrong.
I am not handling it at all.
We have a couple of options.
The first is to chain on a catch to my Get Planet to call.
Remember Get planets is an async function.
It returns a promise if I catch get planets.
Error.
Console.log in catch.
And then let's console that, log the error as well.
Let's see what happens now.
Och.
There we go.
In catch.
Here's my error.
I caught it.
We have another option, though.
If you don't want to have to use sketch and pass in a callback, can comment that out in my async function.
I'll keep this original one.
I can add a try and catch block which looks like this.
Try something.
Otherwise catch the error.
So here's what I would want to try.
And if something goes wrong, if an exception is raised, if there's an error, don't freak out.
Just run this code and I'll console.log in catch comma or e not error.
Let's see what happens now.
I need to call.
Get it still.
Get planets.
Great.
Let's try it out.
Same output.
Well we said in catch I think what we have before in catch with three exclamation points this time we
have one so we get the same behavior.
But these are technically different.
They're different because this is going to catch any errors, any issues within this one async function.
Here, I could have multiple functions that are returning promises I could have thens.
And as we've seen before, the callback in our catch will run for any of them if the promise is rejected.
So when we have one function we're calling, it doesn't really matter.
We're just doing one thing.
There's one place, one promise where the error could be raised.
So it's not a big difference, but there is a difference.
This is more of a backup to catch multiple potential errors here.
It's more specific to what we're trying to do, and we can be more detailed in how we handled it, but
I'm not going to deal with that right now.
Next, what I'd like to show you is how we can make multiple requests or multiple asynchronous operations
in a single async function using await and async async await.