Welcome back.
Next, we'll get a bit more practice with async and await.
So I'm using code that I wrote back in the Promises section.
I know I've said this in pretty much every video so far in this async section, but if you did not watch
the promises section, highly, highly recommend you go back and check it out, or at least look at
the code in more detail.
Remember that everything we're seeing here with async and await, it's all promises underneath there,
behind the scenes.
It's just a little wallpaper on top or makeup on top or paint or who knows?
It's something on top to decorate it, to make it nice and pretty.
So this function that we created a couple of sections ago is called Move X, Move X, Returns a promise.
And in this promise it will move an element, a certain number of pixels horizontally or along the x
axis, left or right, depending on the number you pass in positive or negative.
And then it uses a delay.
So it waits 1/2 or 3 seconds before it actually does that operation.
So it returns promise set time out with a delay.
I'm using 1/2 for all of them and then it moves some element that number of pixels using transform unless
we don't have enough room to keep moving.
So at that point the promise is rejected.
If we do have enough room, the element is moved and the promise is resolved.
So we end up with something like this.
If I shrink my window down.
We can move a couple of times.
And then the promise is rejected.
We caught it with our catch down here and we concealed that, logged some information about the error.
This is what we had before.
This massive mess of callbacks, success and failure, callbacks, promises really helped us clean it
up.
Now we'll see how we can continue to clean it up using async functions.
We won't have to write any of these events.
So what we'll start with is calling move x.
I guess I'll just comment this out.
We'll keep the button.
We do need that.
I'll duplicate it just so we have a record of the original.
We need to select the button and we'll call Move X, but I'm going to do it from inside an async function,
so I'll call this function.
How about animate?
Right.
It's not really a nice animation because it's so choppy, but we'll call it animate, right?
We'll make it an async function.
And we'll pass in an element.
Then inside of here we will call move x, which returns a promise.
I'll pass in that element.
I'll pass in an amount.
So let's just hard code this as 100 pixels at a time every second 1000 milliseconds.
This returns a promise so I can await it.
And if I want to wait for this to finish before I run the next move x I don't need.
Then I can just await this first one and then do it again.
Fingers crossed.
Hopefully we move twice as long as we pass in the correct button to animate.
Right.
So we'll call animate.
BTN.
Refresh.
One jump to jump.
Awesome.
So if we wanted to move this many times, we could do the exact same thing.
We just duplicate this every time and we await.
We say wait and tell.
That promise that is returned from Move X has been resolved, and if it's resolved, then move on to
the next one.
However, right now we're not catching any errors.
So if we do hit that boundary and the promise is rejected, you'll see we get an error.
We'll take a look.
Good.
It's waiting every time for that promise to be resolved.
And then, boom, uncut error.
We did not catch this anywhere.
We just talked about how we can catch errors.
We could add a try catch in our function.
What I would probably do is right here.
Just add a catch for that error and then we could just console.log.
All done.
Let's see if it works.
Okay.
Continue.
Awesome.
And all done.
Perfect.
So if we take a look at this compared to what we had here, I mean, it's not a massive improvement.
We don't have to write all the dot then.
So we don't need these unnecessary callbacks anymore, which I think is definitely worth it.
And all we have to do is add in a weight in async.
Now, this is relatively simple logic we're doing.
It's not much logic at all.
It's the same thing every time.
So it maybe isn't as clear.
But when we talk about making sequential requests, which is what we'll see next, making Axios or fetch
requests one after another where they depend on each other using async await makes it much easier to
read and understand what's going on.
Not to mention shorter.
So why don't we wrap this up instead of just animating to the right?
Why don't we also, once we hit the end, animate back to the left?
So we could change this, animate right to accept an amount.
And then any time I'm passing in 100 there, I'll replace it with amount.
And then here, when we get that error, when we've hit the edge, why don't we consider that log and
move the other direction?
So console.log.
All done.
And then we can call animate, right?
Same element.
BTN.
This time here we need to say we're moving 100 pixels.
This time let's move -100 pixels.
Let's see if that works.
So we move to the right and we're going to hit that edge.
We get all done and now we're moving back to the left.
Now, we don't really have any error handling for the left side, so we're just going to keep moving
off the screen because our logic right now in animate or in Move X is just checking the right boundary.
So I guess that's a bit of an oversight.
But we now have this async function here that we can call it returns a promise within it.
We can await any other thing that returns a promise and mimic synchronous code.
So next we'll see how we can do this with requests, how can we have sequential requests?
And we'll also talk about parallel requests, which is another way of sending multiple requests where
we don't have to wait for one to come back first.