Next up, I'd like to talk about an important distinction that has to do with using a weight within
an async function.
So to illustrate this concept, which I haven't even mentioned yet, I'm going to use Axios again to
make some requests asynchronously.
It takes time.
We'll use an async function.
We will await the request.
I have async JS, I have Axios included and we're going to work with a different API this time and other
free API pokie API.
Kiko, if we go to the endpoint API slash V slash pokemon and then we pass in a Pokémon number like
one, we get a ton of information about that Pokémon.
So let's request a couple of different Pokémon.
It's going to copy that URL.
We'll do something like Axios, get Pokémon Slash one, and let's make sure that we create an async
function to help us.
Instead of having to add a dot, then we get a promise back.
So we'll make our async function, async function get.
How about three Pokémon?
So we'll move that in there.
We will await save that to a variable.
We'll call this pokey.
It looks like poke one.
So we've got that, we're awaiting it.
Now if I just want to verify everything worked, why don't we console that log pokey one data.
Go to my page.
Refresh.
Uh oh.
I never calling my function.
What a moron.
Get three pokemon.
Try again.
Okay.
So now we get a ton of data about that one pokemon.
Where is name?
Its name, not even included.
There we go.
Bulbasaur.
I should know that.
Pokémon one.
So if I wanted to also request three other pokemon, I could do something like this.
Pokémon two equals await get Pokémon two.
This could be Pokémon Slash three.
Make sure I use the correct name and then we can that log Pokémon one, two and three data.
So we're awaiting each one.
We're going to make this request.
When it's finished, we get something back.
If it's resolved, we keep moving on.
We're not catching any errors.
But I assume these are going to work my internets up.
The API is up and there we go.
It looks like it's pretty much instantaneous anyway, but it's important to note they are happening
in sequence, so this has to finish completely before this.
So this runs, we get data back, then this line runs, we get data back, then this line.
So they're not going in parallel.
They're not being sent off at the same time.
Like three passenger carrier pigeons.
Carrier pigeons, I think.
So what I mean to say three pigeons are Harry Potter owls in the night with their own letters and packages.
No, it's one going and returning.
Then the second owl leaves and returns.
The third owl leaves and returns.
They are in sequence.
And this isn't a huge deal for something like this, although we don't need them to be in sequence because
these don't depend on one another.
We're not using information from this first request to make our second request.
We could, if I wanted to get some URL from the response, the actual data we get back, I think is
there something instead of species?
Here we go.
Species has its own URL.
I could request that we've got forms and then yeah, I guess there's a URL there and then each ability
has its own URL to get more information about.
So I could send a request to this URL for example, and it would have to be in sequence.
We couldn't send them off at the exact same time because we're waiting for the first request to come
back before we make the second request.
But here they have nothing to do with one another.
They are independent endpoints.
They're are not related other than the fact that they're with the same API.
We're not depending on this one.
First, in order to make this one so we can rewrite this to have a request, go in parallel.
I'm going to duplicate this.
I'll just write sequential requests.
And then this one will be parallel.
I'm not going to await.
I'll get rid of those awaits here.
I still need to await at some point, but I'm not awaiting there.
Then down here I can await pokey one, await pokey two and await Pokey three.
So this may not seem like a big distinction, but it is as far as the way these are actually happening
behind the scenes.
It's a pretty massive difference.
So here we're not we're not using a weight anymore when we actually send off the request like we were
here.
So this means that we're sending off the request.
It returns a promise.
So Pokey one will contain a promise.
If I were to console.log it here.
Console.log.
Pokey one.
Refresh.
We see that we get a promise here and it's pending at this point.
All three of them are probably pending, unless it's an incredibly fast request, which is highly unlikely
that it's going to beat JavaScript speed.
By the time it gets to this line, they probably won't be back.
But then we're saying, All right, await the response that comes back.
Await the response and wait the response.
But the requests are being sent roughly at the same time.
I mean, as fast as JavaScript can send them off or the browser can send them off versus here we're
fully waiting for this response to come back from the request.
We're waiting for the promise to be resolved before we move on.
Same thing.
Same thing here.
So I'm going to illustrate the difference with something that is slower.
So you can see it in just a moment, but let's make sure we can actually use the data right now.
What I have will not work.
I'll wait.
Pokey one await Pokey to await pokey three.
We are awaiting the promises.
We're making sure they're resolved.
But Pokey one data does not exist.
Pokey one is the promise if I look at what I got printed out.
Three Undefined, undefined, undefined, undefined.
Up here.
Pokey one, pokey two and pokey three are not the promises.
This is a promise.
But when you put a wait there, it waits for a resolved value and stores that resolved value in the
variable.
So pokey one is an actual response.
It's the value we get back here.
Pokey one is a promise.
So poky one should be resolved by the end, but it doesn't actually have.
It's not a variable storing the value.
So we could do this.
Maybe promise one.
Just give them a different name.
Prom to prom three.
And then we can await prom one, two and three and save those two variables.
So we would do something like this.
Const pokey one.
I need to change those numbers to.
And three equals a weight.
That promise.
A weight.
This promise.
That promise.
So the three requests are sent off independently.
They're not in a sequence.
They're not depending on one finishing before the next sense.
They go off on their own into the night.
They come back.
We are awaiting for a resolved value.
That resolve value will then be stored in pokey one, two and three.
Fingers crossed.
Hmm.
Cannot access pokey one before initialization.
Oh yes, we changed the name.
If we look at prom one, it's a pending promise.
Then down here, if I were to look at prom one again for some reason console.log.
Prom one.
It was pending.
Now it's resolved.
The value it was resolved with is this object.
This object here that is stored inside of Pokey One now.
So the promise was not resolved.
It was pending.
Now it's resolved because we awaited it.
Then we have access to all three of those pieces of data.
We can do something with them.
So these were sent in parallel, which is a big distinction.
If you do not care, that one request must be finished before the next is done.
But in a case like this, it doesn't matter.
It's better to do them in parallel.
So now let me illustrate the difference for you, and I'm also going to show you another way to clean
this up so we don't have to have all these variable names.
But first, I'll show you a much easier to see visualization of the difference between a waiting in
sequence versus awaiting in parallel.
These responses or the requests are coming back so lightning quick that it's actually almost impossible
to see with your own eye that they are slower if we do them in sequence versus parallel.
It just happens in a split second.
They all show up at once, so I'm going to do something slower.
Let's make a function called change body color, which will accept a color and a delay.
It will return a promise, and after this delay, it will change the body color.
So our promise is going to have our resolve, reject parameters, standard stuff.
Then we'll have a set time out where we have a function to run after a delay.
So that delay will be passed in.
So I would call this like change body color to teal after 1/2.
So that will be 1/2 there.
Set time out after that 1/2 is up, we will set documents, dot body style, dot background color to
equal color and then I'll resolve the promise.
I won't worry about rejecting it.
I guess we could reject if someone passes in a non color or an ugly color, but we won't bother.
It's not really the point of this demo, so let's make sure it works after 1/2.
Hopefully the body changes to teal.
There we go.
Okay, so now let's make an async function and we'll call this one light show.
And all we're going to do is called change body color and await that.
Then we'll do it again.
Change body color to pink after 1000 milliseconds.
We'll call Late Show and see what happens.
So async await await this promise when it's resolved, then move on to this line.
So we go to Teil after a second and then pink.
So I'll add a couple more colors here.
Let's see.
Teal.
Pink.
How about.
Indigo and violet.
So right now these are happening in sequence.
The first thing finishes, then the second, then the third, then the fourth, which is probably what
we would want.
But if these were requests taking 1/2 and they are not related, we may not want that, which is what
we saw up here.
So now let's see how this would work in parallel.
I'll comment out this version in parallel.
I would save each of these to a variable.
So I'm just going to select all of those and save it to a variable.
Or I could put them in an array.
I'll show you something called Promise at all in the next video.
I'll just go with P one, two and three.
I don't know the shortcut to do those numbers easily, so I have to manually type them and then we'll
do a wait p one, wait p two, await p three and p is just standing for promise.
So awaits p four.
What do you think?
We'll see.
So all four of these functions are going to run roughly at the same time.
This one will run first, then this one, then this one.
They all take a second and they change the background color and they resolve that promise that is returned.
So we await them down here rather than waiting for the full second to be up to, then run to the next
one.
These will happen pretty much at the same time.
So this is what we see.
1/2 straight to what was the last color, Violet?
We don't see those pauses along the way.
So this took only 1/2, maybe a little tiny, tiny bit more than 1/2.
This took four plus seconds, very different.
And here we get a different light show effect.
This is probably more desirable if either of them is at all desirable.
This is more interesting.
But with requests, if you don't need them to happen in sequence, do it in parallel.
It makes way more sense to just have them go at the same time and await all of them at the end.
Speaking of which, I'll show you an even simpler way of doing that in the next end.
Final video in the section coming up after this.
I think this is a good place to stop.
So we saw how we can make requests in sequence, which is useful when you need one thing to come back
before the next, especially if they are dependent.
You're trying to use some data from the first request to then send off your second, which I wasn't.
So then I showed you doing it in parallel where you don't await them at the same time that you are actually
creating the promise and sending that request off.
Instead, you send the request off.
You await them afterwards.
And then we saw an illustration of visually the difference using this light show function.
So next I'm going to show you one last tweak and we'll be done with async functions.