All right.
The last thing we'll take a look at is a nice and clean way of what we did here, sending requests in
parallel and just waiting until they were all back before we did something.
This code down here won't run until we have a resolved value from this first promise, second one and
third one.
But the requests are still being sent at roughly the same time.
So if I don't want to have to type all of this stuff, it's kind of annoying having to make these different
variables.
What we can do is use a promise helper method called promise with a capital P dot all and promise that
all accepts an array of promises.
So these are all promises that we get back.
So I could just pass those in to promised all prom one, prom two, prom three and then await that I
could call this concert results equals await promised all I'll get rid of the original one.
Now let's take a look at results afterwards.
Console.log results thanks to the magic of async functions and await I can just write it directly beneath
even though this may take a while.
If my internet sucks, if the internet's not on or if the API is down, I'm not catching the errors.
But we could also do that as we've seen earlier, so I wouldn't spend time on that.
So this is much cleaner than what we had before.
Assuming it works, let's make sure it does.
I refresh.
This is what we get back.
Another array containing three response objects, which is the values that those promises are returned
with thanks to Axios.
So if I was awaiting something else, I would get whatever the resolved values were in a results array.
So this returns a promise itself.
This promise is resolved when its own promises in this array are all resolved.
Then we're awaiting promised that all to be resolved.
Take that resolved value.
It's now stored in results and then we move on.
As soon as this is done, this code runs, so then we could print out something for each one, you know,
how about just make a separate function print pokemon and pass in results?
Then I can just define a regular function called print Pokémon.
It doesn't need to be async.
This will be past results.
So in here I would just do four let pokemon of results and we want the data dot.
I think it's name.
Why don't we just do that.
Data.
Name.
Console.log data.
Pokémon data name.
Let's test it out.
There we go.
Bulbasaur.
I've saw Venusaur.
So not the most useful actual request that we're making.
But this is much nicer than what we had before, where we were awaiting each promise individually.
A weight from one, a weight prompt to a weight from three.
Here we put them in an array and then we can await that entire promise at all and then move on.
This code will only run when all of these promises have been resolved.
So that's kind of it for async functions.
We use async to declare the function as an async function and then we use a weight to await a resolved
value within an async function.
We can't use a weight outside of an async function only inside, but the combination of the two helps
us write code that looks like it is synchronous, but it still is behaving asynchronously.
It's just much easier to read.
Remember, it's all built on top of promises and it's just syntactic sugar.
So we'll get tons of practice later in the project portion of this course, we'll work with Axios and
make a lot of requests and write our own async functions and use a inside already.