In the last section, we talked a lot about passing functions as arguments to other functions with the
expectation that the outer function will call your argument function, which we call a callback.
And I said, I'm showing this to you because callbacks are central to JavaScript.
In fact, tons of built in methods expect you to pass a callback function.
So in this section we'll see some of those methods, some of the most useful builtin methods that expect
you to pass a function in.
And these all have to do with arrays.
That's not to say there aren't other types of callback methods in JavaScript, but this section is focused
on array methods that expect you to pass in a callback.
So there's tons of them.
We saw a bunch of built in array methods early on, but we didn't cover these because we haven't talked
about functions at that point.
We didn't know what a callback was.
It's a lot to throw at you at the very beginning when you're still wrapping your head around arrays.
So we saw things like dot reverse or includes index of these methods we'll see are different.
They're quite a bit different.
We pass in a function and the general pattern here is that we're going to run a function once per every
element in an array, but we'll have different goals.
Maybe we want to filter out certain values from an array.
Maybe we want to create a new array from an existing array.
Maybe we want to check if every single element in an array meets a given condition.
What they have in common is that we are trying to run a function once per element in the array.
So these functions we're about to see are extremely useful.
I know I've said that a million times, but really the methods we'll see here are used all the time,
far more often than things like Index of or Reverse.
So our goals are pretty straightforward.
We want to talk about the built in methods for arrays that require callbacks for each map filter, find,
reduce some and every.
And our gameplan here is to cover a couple of the easier ones, then take a break to talk about a different
function syntax we haven't seen yet called arrow functions.
Arrow functions are a new ish way of writing functions that are just shorter, cleaner, easier when
you need to pass a function in as an argument.
So we'll use them a lot for the rest of these methods that we'll cover.
So we'll cover a couple of these arrow functions and then the rest of these methods.
So in the next video we'll start off with for each.