The first of this new group of array methods we'll talk about is called for each.
For each accepts a callback, it accepts a function, and it calls it on every element in a given array.
It's an array method.
So we call it on the array.
Here's my nums array.
We do nums for each, just like we would do num index of or num stat reverse.
Both of the examples here are using anonymous function expressions.
They're just one time things that I'm trying to do.
I could also create a function.
I could define it first and then pass the name of the function in.
But again, the goal of for each is that it takes whatever function you give it and it calls it on each
element.
It passes each value into that function.
So let's try a simple example.
I have an array called numbers.
Not exciting.
I know.
20, 21, 22, and so on.
If I call numbers for each and I pass in a function, we'll start with an anonymous function here.
I need to give it a parameter.
I can name this whatever I want, but it is going to store.
It will represent one element at a time.
So the very first time for each run is the first iteration.
It will call whatever I have here this function and we'll pass in the value of 20.
So I'll go with numb or NW it doesn't matter element l something descriptive and then I'll use numb
in here.
We'll start really simple.
We'll console that log numb.
And if I run this code, there we go, 2021, all the way to 27.
So for each calls this function, however many times it needs to, and it passes each element in one
at a time.
So we could also do console.log num times two.
Just as a quick example here and we get 40, 42, 44.
Great.
We could have also written a function ahead of time.
Let's do print double.
Let's do triple.
Just to have something a little different.
And it will accept a single number.
We'll call it DN and it will console.log and times three.
So now I have a standalone function called print triple and I can call numbers for each and pass in
print triple.
Just like that.
So this is accomplishing the same thing.
Well, we're tripling here instead of doubling, but it's the same idea.
Numbers dot for each.
This function we're telling for each.
Here's the function.
I want you to call for each element.
So internally it would call print triple with 20 and then afterwards 21 and then afterwards 22.
And it does it until it hits the end of the array.
So if we double check this one now, we get print triple.
I'll comment this out so we can just see it on its own.
There we go.
60 down to 81, 20 times 360, 27 times three is 81.
So two different ways of using for each JavaScript doesn't care that are both functions.
The main difference is that this is a function we can reuse if we needed to, which is great, but a
lot of the time with for each and a lot of these methods we'll see in this section, you're just trying
to get some code to run.
You don't care about having a name for that function, being able to reuse it.
It's just a one time thing.
So in that case, you would use an anonymous function or it would make sense to at least you don't have
to.
So we pass in that function.
It's called let's do another example here.
I have a more complex array where each element is an object.
Let's say I want to print out every title.
We'll just start with that.
I want to print each title using for each I would call books, which is the name of the array for each
function.
And we'll call this placeholder, this parameter B or book.
It represents one element in that array, which in our case happens to be an object.
And then to print the title, I would just cancel that log book title and let's do dot to uppercase.
So if I refresh, we now get four different book titles in all caps, so for each is going to pass in
each element.
In this case, the element is an object.
It's not a single number like we had earlier, it's a whole object.
And then we can do whatever we want in here.
Now you might be thinking this doesn't seem that useful because we have things like for loops or for
of.
I could do the exact same thing using a four of so I would do four let book of books console.log and
I'll just copy that line over.
We'll comment this one out, we get the same output.
And you're right, this works.
It is different.
This is not identical.
Obviously the syntax is different.
But the key difference as far as JavaScript is concerned is here we have a function that's being called
this is just a block.
That doesn't really mean much in this example, but I just want you to understand there is a difference.
So yeah you could use a four of loop for each has been around much longer than for oth.
So we used to not have this option at all.
We had a regular for loop for let i equals zero.
I is less than book book length plus plus.
And then we would console this out.
But we don't have book.
We would have to do books of I title to uppercase and this would give us the same thing.
But it's just nicer in my opinion to do a for each or a four of where we don't have to use I if we don't
care about the index, we're not using the index except to access each element, then why use it?
So for each was the alternative we use for a long time.
People still use for each, but we also now have four of you can use it to achieve the same end.
So here are all three versions doing the same thing.
Now there's one other thing to know about for each.
We can also add a second parameter to our callback to the function here if we want to use the index.
So if I wanted to print out each actually let's do it up here instead of books.
Let's go back to numbers.
If I wanted to print out the index and then the number using a for each, I could do numbers for each
pass in my callback.
We'll call this num.
And then the second parameter.
This is how for each works.
The second parameter will be the index which we can call I id x index and we'll just do a simple console.log
index comma num.
We run it and there we go.
Zero element is 20 element 121 all the way down to element 727.
So this is nice.
If you need the index, sometimes you do, you could use a for each.
There's not an easy way to get an index if you're using a regular four of although if you use a regular
four loop, you definitely can get it.
You have to generate it yourself using I and I less than whatever I plus plus with for each you get
the index for free.
So what's happening here is that this function is being called each time for one element and for each
is passing in not only the element, but it passes in the index.
And if you don't use that index, it's still being passed in for each is just saying here's the number
or here's the element and here's the index for that element.
You can ignore it.
You don't have to accept it or do anything with it, but it's going to be passed in.
And so if you want it, you can capture it as a parameter.
All right.
So that's for each.
Again, it's the simplest of these methods.
We'll see.
It accepts a callback and it runs that callback once per element in the array where that element's value
will be an argument to the callback.