Next up, we have the array method that I probably use the most out of all of them.
It's called Map.
Map is used to create a new array from an existing array.
It could be used to simply duplicate an array, though there are easier ways of doing it, but it can
also be used to extract portions of an array or to somehow transform an array into a new array, double
every number in this array, or reverse every string in the original, and make a new array with those
reverse strings so it accepts a callback.
Just like for each.
It calls that callback with every element in the array, but it builds a new array with those values.
So here's a simple example here I have an array called text.
We have rofl lol omg t l for strings lowercase and I'm calling texts dot map.
I'm passing a callback function in the parameter name I settled on was PT represents each one of these
strings and I'm returning from this function PT to uppercase.
And what this whole map does overall is it generates a new array and I'm storing it in a variable called
caps, so it does not alter or update texts.
Its original values are still unchanged, but I've mapped them over to a new array called Caps, so
we'll take a look at a bunch of examples.
I have to sample arrays to start nice and simple ones.
Let's work with numbers.
Let's make a new array called doubles.
Doubles will be an array where every value is double this value, the corresponding value in numbers.
So we'll call numbers dot map and we'll pass in a function.
Usually we use anonymous functions unless you have a pre-defined function that does exactly what you
need.
Usually these are one time use things and the callback parameter I'll go with is just numb.
That makes sense.
It represents each number.
Now what I need to do from this function is return a value.
This is how map knows what values to add to the array.
If I don't return anything, it won't work.
So let's return num times to.
And if I run this right now, we don't get anything or we don't see anything.
Numbers is unchanged because MAP does not mutate the original array.
It maps the values to a new array.
So I need to capture that value.
If I run this code in my console, you can see that it returns map itself, returns this new mapped
array.
So I'll capture that in a variable const doubles.
I'll try it again.
And now, if I look at doubles, it exists.
And it's a double of this original array.
So if I don't return something, I just cancel that log.
Or I'm simply writing this expression here.
If we look at doubles, it's an array full of undefined.
Because Mab doesn't care what the return value is, it's going to take whatever is returned from our
function and add it into a new array eight times because it ran our function eight times.
There's eight elements here and each time nothing was returned.
And when a function returns, nothing, the value you get is undefined.
So it created an array of eight undefined.
So we need to return a value here.
There we go.
Next, let's do another example with numbers once again.
But instead of simply doubling the value, let's decide if the number is even or odd.
And we're going to map them into a new array where the array will contain.
Let's have it contain an object for each element and we'll have the number set to 20 and then we'll
set is even to true or false.
And we'll do that for every single element in numbers.
So to do that, we need to call numbers map pass in our callback function.
I'll go with PN as the parameter of this time instead of NUM.
And then we know we want to check if the value is even.
And we want to return an object so we can return an object here.
We can do it all at once.
We don't have to make it in a variable first and then return it and we'll set value to be n.
And then we'll set is even to be a boolean true or false based off of PN mod two equals zero.
So this if the remainder, once you divide by two is zero, that will return true.
If not, it returns false.
So we'll end up with the is even property being true or false?
And then value is just the number itself.
RN.
So if we try this and save it to a variable, we'll go with const num detail.
I don't know.
It's not a great name.
Let's look at what we get.
Num detail is an array of objects and each object has a value and is.
Even so we have value.
21 is even false value 22 is even true.
So there's one example.
Now let's work with the array of strings.
I have all of these abbreviations and let's say I wanted to format them different.
I want an array where each string is all caps and separated by periods like a.s.a.p should be formatted
this way instead of ASAP.
So I want to map them into a new array.
What I need to do here.
Well, what I can do at least is use map.
If I didn't want to use map in all of these examples, I could do this manually.
I could make a loop for let word.
Let's go with numbers just to do this doubles example for the num of numbers I need to make a results
array so we'll make our array.
We'll call it doubles to const doubles two equals an empty array.
And then I need to push into doubles to push.
Numb times, too.
So I'm doing the same thing.
Effectively, there was no function involved, but I'm iterating over numbers for each number.
I'm multiplying it by two and pushing it into an array.
I'm actually doing the push one at a time versus when we use map, all we do is write a function map
calls.
That function takes the result and it puts it into a new array for us automatically, and it gives us
that array.
But if we verify that this works, doubles, too.
There we go.
But again, this is not calling a function for something simple, like multiplying by two.
This is easy, but map is really, really useful, especially when we start to combine it with other
methods that we'll see.
So I don't want to give you the impression that you should do this, that this is easier because it's
usually not.
I just wanted to kind of recreate the basics of what it's doing, so it makes that array for us.
It starts empty and then it calls this function, it gets a return value, it pushes that into the array
and then it does it again for the next element.
So back to our words.
We're going to call map words, dot map.
I'll call this word the parameter here.
Now, the logic to get this to be an abbreviation where we have all caps and a period after every letter
is a little tricky.
It's not hard, but we're going to use a couple of different methods.
We're going to capitalize it first.
So we're going to call word dot to uppercase.
Then the easiest way, in my opinion, to add a period after every character is to split the word into
an array.
So if we do it over here, if we had a.S.A.P, dot to uppercase, dot split, split wants to know where
it should split.
And if we give it an empty string, it creates an array with each character from that string.
So each element is one character.
So now I have an array.
Then I can call Dot, join on that array and tell it what to join those characters together with.
So take each element in this array that we just created using Split and join it together into one string,
separated by a period after each character.
And there we go.
So we can use that logic right here.
Word to uppercase split on the empty string, which means split on every character that gives us an
array and we can call join on a period.
So this is not going to work.
What am I missing?
I'm missing return.
We have to return this from our function and then let's capture the variable.
We'll call this abbreviated abbreviations.
If we run it, we look at a believes.
We now have this array that we mapped.
We took this array of values and we map them into a new array.
The originals are unchanged, but we now have a new array.
Remember, for each is similar, but we're not building an array with those values.
For each is like half of map.
It calls a function on every element, but it doesn't store them in an array.
It doesn't return a new array.
Map does map takes that function, it calls it, and it takes the return value and puts it in a new
array, which is how we end up with this.
Here's one more common use case for map.
If we have a slightly more complex data structure like this books array, we have a bunch of properties,
we have title author's rating.
If I wanted to create a new array that contained all the book titles in my library, I could use map
if I want to just extract or isolate the title.
I don't care about authors.
I don't care about rating.
I can use MAP to do that.
I would map over books.
So books map I pass in my callback and I'll call the parameter here.
Let's go with B for book and all I want to do is return the title.
So B title, return B title, and that's it.
So I'm saying create a new array based off of this array and the value I'm going to return that you
should use to make that new array is only the title.
So I'm whittling down this array of objects and turning it into an array of strings, turning it into
a strong term.
I'm creating a new version based off of it.
The original books is unchanged.
I'm mapping it.
So let's go with titles.
Let's look at titles.
And there we go.
I have whittled down the pieces I need.
I've extracted them.
I didn't change the original.
But this is a really common thing to do.
Sometimes you have complex data structures and you want an array of just one piece or just a couple
of pieces.
You want a simplified form.
We can use map to do that without impacting the original.
We just return the piece or the pieces that we want to form a new array using.
So that's map.
Like I said, it's very useful.
It helps us take one array and map it into a new array.
We provide a callback function and that callback is executed once per element in the original array.
And the return value of our callback is what is used to generate the new array.