Next up, a quick break from the built in array methods like forage and map.
We'll get back to them shortly.
But first.
Arrow functions.
Arrow functions are a new ish syntax in JavaScript, an alternative way of defining a function expression.
Notice up here, Internet Explorer is crossed out.
Arrow functions are not supported in IEEE, but pretty much everyone uses them these days, and there
are many solutions to make sure code will run in all browsers.
You can write an arrow function and then if it doesn't work in IEEE, it will be turned into some other
code that does work, but that's out of the scope of what we're talking about.
Now let's take a look at arrow function syntax.
We write function expressions all the time, an anonymous function like this one here we pass it into
map or one that we pass into for each.
We do this so much in JavaScript that it was decided that there should be a more compact syntax for
defining function expressions.
So it's another way of defining a function.
We don't have to write the function keyword.
Instead we write our function like this parentheses and the arrow that's for the name comes from arrow
function and then curly braces, although we'll see that sometimes those braces are actually optional.
So in this video, we'll just take a look at a couple simple arrow functions.
Let's try them out over here.
If we wanted to write a function expression without an arrow function, we would do something like const
square equals function, which accepts some number and it returns x times x to do the same thing with
an arrow function.
I'll comment that one out.
We would do const square equals parentheses, no function, keyword x or whatever our parameter name
is, and then our arrow return x times x.
And if I run my code and I call square of four, we do get 16.
You can compare the two syntax is here already.
This one is shorter.
We don't have to write function so much and this makes a big difference when you look at some existing
code bases or some libraries where you pass a lot of functions around, you use a lot of callbacks.
If you have function all over the place, especially if you have nested callbacks, you see function
everywhere.
It's like 90% of what your code is versus when we use arrow functions, it's a lot cleaner, slimmer
and easier to understand.
Now, arrow functions were not introduced exclusively because they are more compact or they're easier
on the eye.
There is another difference aside from how we write them, there's a difference in how they behave around
something called the keyword.
This.
Now, we haven't talked about this in JavaScript yet.
We will.
And when we do, we'll address arrow functions.
But with what we know right now, arrow functions work exactly the same way as any other function we
can write.
They're just shorter.
So let's try one more.
I'll define a function.
Let's go with is even.
It accepts one parameter, we'll call this num.
We write our arrow and then we'll return num mod two equal equal equal zero.
Let's call it doesn't like that.
I have two squares.
Refresh my code is even of four.
That's true.
Is even a 47 is false.
There we go.
One more error function with multiple parameters.
Let's do.
This is so boring but let's do multiply equals.
We write our parentheses x and y just like we would with a regular function x, comma y.
We just don't write the function keyword and we instead add the arrow and this will return x times y
we run multiply of four and seven, we get 28.
The next video is going to be all about arrow functions and how we can sometimes make them even slimmer
and cleaner.
But first, I'm just going to show you two rules.
When you write an arrow function, if you only have one parameter, you can actually leave the parentheses
off.
So I could rewrite any of these.
Not this one, but square.
And is even like this.
Those parentheses are optional.
Only when we have one parameter.
So if I run my code is even still works.
Is even of seven is false is even of eight is true.
If we have more than one, we have to have those prints.
Otherwise JavaScript gets confused.
It doesn't know what I'm trying to do here.
And you can see my auto formatter here formatted it oddly and I get an error as soon as I run the code.
It doesn't know what's going on.
We have to add prints if we have more than one parameter.
If we have one parameter, they're optional and it's a matter of personal preference.
I like leaving them off.
But some style guides, some companies you may work with will expect you to add them in.
And then if we define a function with no parameters whatsoever, like const greets which will just console.log.
Hello or hi there.
What do we do here?
We have to have empty prints.
We can't just leave it off.
We need empty prints and it will console.log.
Hi.
I'll run my code now.
I call greet.
And we get high.
So to wrap up the basic rules of an arrow function are that one, it behaves just like a function expression
where we declare it with a function keyword, but we don't have to do that.
This arrow function has no name.
We're simply creating an anonymous function expression using an arrow function.
So we have the arrow, we have our curly braces.
We return just like a regular function.
We have our parameters, but we have a couple options.
If we have no parameters whatsoever, we have to have empty prints.
If we have multiple params, we have to have the prints there.
But if we have one parameter and only one, then we can optionally leave them off.
So this or what we had before both are valid.
Next we'll see some nice optimizations how we can actually write an arrow function without these curly
braces and without having to write return.