The error functions we've seen so far are already pretty compact compared to a regular function expression
where we have to write the word function.
But there's an even more compact way of writing some arrow functions.
This only works in certain scenarios.
It's called implicit return.
Adding an implicit return to an arrow function means that you don't have to write the return keyword
itself, and in some scenarios you can write a one liner arrow function.
So let's talk about when you can use this and how it works.
If I have a simple arrow function whoops typing in the wrong area called Square.
I know it's a boring one.
It accepts a single parameter.
We'll call it N, we return end times n.
This arrow function consists of a single expression that we're returning.
We're not doing some other logic.
First, we're not making a variable, we're not adding a conditional.
We're simply returning an expression in scenarios where you have one expression that you want to be
returned.
You can rewrite this arrow function using parentheses instead of curly braces, and if you do that,
you can leave off the return keyword.
So we could rewrite this as const square equals NW and then parentheses end times N and that's it.
You'll see if I even try and add return in there.
It gets highlighted with the red squiggly of death telling me expression expected, not a return statement.
It wants just the expression and this value will be computed and returned.
So if I run it, we'll do square of 864, square of two is four.
But we can make this even shorter by putting it on a single line, and we can do that in scenarios where
it fits and it makes sense to put on a single line.
We can leave off the friends.
I'll comment that version out and we can just do this right here.
So this is equivalent to what we had right here.
We're writing an arrow function except a single parameter.
N And it returns end times.
NW It's an implicit return.
We don't need those per ns if we're putting it on one line.
But that doesn't mean we should always try and make everything on one line.
If it's super long, if it's hard to read, put per ends and just put it on a new line.
So if instead of returning end times NW we had some array that we were trying to return based off of.
NW Let's just say it was a long array like this.
This won't make sense to JavaScript.
None of those are valid identifiers or existing identifiers.
But if I had this, this is a bit long for a single line.
So we add those prints.
It's just a way of making it clear that this whole thing is the expression, not just this one line,
but let's go back to what we had before and times.
NW Make sure it still works.
Square of two square of 749.
It's working.
So this is a really nice feature when you need a simple arrow function, which a lot of the time we
do need when we're using all of these callback methods, we've seen four arrays for each or map.
A lot of the time we just want a single short expression to be returned so we can use this one line
or syntax one less thing before we see some examples using array methods.
I'll just show you what happens here.
If we had some additional logic, let's say we wanted to check if NW is positive.
So if NW is greater than or equal to zero, or let's just say it has to be greater than zero, then
we'll return something.
Return.
Let's do it the other way around.
If it's negative, we'll return false.
This is a problem.
I have multiple expressions, multiple lines.
It's not just multiple expressions.
I have statements, I've got a conditional.
Then I have this expression at the bottom.
This function does not know what it's supposed to return.
JavaScript does not know what to return.
There's multiple things that it could return and this is an invalid arrow function.
We can't do this if we're trying to use an implicit return.
We only get one thing, one expression to return that way.
There's no doubt in JavaScript mind it knows this is the one thing to return implicitly.
Okay, so let's see some examples now.
All right.
So I have a simple array of numbers.
If I wanted to double every num and map it into a new array, I would call nums dot map and without
an arrow function it would look something like this function for PN.
We want to return end times two, and if we save that to a variable, we'll call this nums.
How about doubles one?
We look at doubles one.
There should be review.
Oh, I didn't run my code.
Try that again.
We get to four, six, eight and so on.
If I wanted to use an arrow function instead I can do doubles two equals nums dot map.
And if we use a non implicit arrow function, a regular arrow function, we would have MN and then return.
Urn end times to refresh our code doubles to.
The same.
But we can make it even shorter with what we just saw.
Doubles three equals nums dot map.
We'll go with the parameter name of pn pn times two.
And that's it.
Much, much shorter.
We don't have to add curly braces.
We don't need to add return.
We simply write an arrow function on one line.
When we have a single expression, this works great.
Let's look at doubles three.
It looks identical.
So this is really nice.
And this is one of the main reasons arrow functions were added in.
We use callbacks so frequently that there needed to be a nicer, more compact syntax.
Remember, later on there is another distinction between arrow functions and regular functions.
We'll talk about that.
It has to do with the keyword this, but we're not there yet.
Let's do another example where we map these numbers into an array where we have the values even in odd
the string.
So we would have odd and then even then odd.
As you can see here, we would just alternate if I wanted to write that function or that map.
How about const parity list?
Parity is the term referring to if a number is even or odd.
I'm pretty sure that's what it's called anyway.
Nums dot map.
Let's use a regular function first function for PN if PN is mod two equals zero.
If NN mod two is equal to zero, we will return.
Even otherwise we return odd.
If we look at parity list, we get odd, even odd, even all the way down.
Let's rewrite this with an arrow function so it will be similar.
We'll have num stop map and then NW with our arrow and we could leave it like this and it still works.
We look at parity list, but if I wanted to use an implicit return, no dice, at least not with this
version.
We could rewrite this to be a one liner.
We're really just doing a simple if and in else one condition.
If that's not true, do this instead even or odd.
And we can use the ternary operator to do this in one line.
Remember, we only get one expression here.
We have multiple.
This will not work if I try and rewrite it using perrins.
We're out of luck.
If I replace those curly braces with parentheses, JavaScript still does not like it.
It tells us expression expected so we can rewrite it like this with the ternary operator.
If you remember this syntax dn mod two equals zero.
Question mark.
So if this thing we want to return this value even colon, that means otherwise we'll return odd.
And this is a one liner.
This works.
Refresh.
Look at parity list.
We're good to go.
And if you wanted to, you could put this actually on one line.
Instead of using parentheses, we just bring it up like this.
It's a little long, but I also have my font zoomed in a bit.
It's up to you if you want to do it on one line.
I think sometimes people go overboard trying to fit something onto one line just so they can say they've
done it.
It's easier to read this, in my opinion, but in a simpler example, like this one here, it makes
a lot of sense to put it on one line.
There's no reason for the extra lines and extra characters.
Okay, so this pretty much concludes our little arrow functions.
Interlude arrow functions are really, really useful.
They don't do anything that you can't do with a regular function, at least with what we've seen, they're
just a replacement that is more compact.
So even in their most verbose form, it's still shorter.
If you compare this to a regular function expression, we don't have to write function, we just write
our parameter optional parentheses around it.
Remember that from the last video you can put parentheses there.
It's up to you.
And then the arrow curly braces return something.
Or we can use an implicit return where we don't have to write return, but we can only have a single
expression in the body of the function.
And if it doesn't fit on one line, like I don't think this one fits very well, you can use print to
wrap it, but it still needs to be a single expression.
So that's arrow functions.
Now we'll pick back up with more of those built in array methods.