The next one of these array methods that expects a callback is called Find.
Find does pretty much what it sounds like.
It finds an element.
It retrieves an element from an array based off of a function that we pass in.
So this function needs to return true or false.
And each time find we'll call that function with one of these elements.
And if that function returns true, then it's done.
It will return to you the value of that element.
So it only returns one value, one element that matches.
Even if there are ten matches in a given array, it stops after it finds the very first one.
So here's an example.
I have an array called movies.
It has four strings.
Every movie has either Mr. or Mrs. or both in its title.
If I want to find the first movie that has the string Mrs. in it, I could do movies that find I'll
do an arrow function, I'll call the parameter movie and this needs to be a Boolean function that returns
true or false.
So how do I figure out if movie contains?
Mrs..
I have a couple of ways, but I'll do movie dot includes Mrs. and I need to make sure I return this
if I'm not going to use an implicit return and then I'll save this to a variable, I'll call this concert
movie.
Let's see what happens.
We'll look at movie and it contains Mr. and Mrs. Smith.
Now movies is unchanged.
All we're doing is a simple find a search.
We're not removing or updating movies in any way.
So this function right here again has to return true or false.
And the first time it returns true for a given movie, a given element find is done and it returns that
movie.
So the fantastic Mr. Fox was movie the very first time through it was plugged into this function.
It does not include Mrs. so it returns false, which means find moves on to the next element.
Mr. and Mrs. Smith that became movie movie includes Mrs. now is true this returns true so then find
stops everything and it returns this string right here.
If I wanted to instead find the first movie that starts with Mrs. not just includes Mrs. somewhere I
could write it as concept.
I'll just do movie two equals movies dot find.
We'll do an implicit return this time.
M I'll do parent to start m index of Mrs..
I do need to pay pay attention to capitalization or down case everything.
I want that to equal one.
That would mean that Mrs..
Actually, what am I saying?
I want two equals zero.
That would mean that Mrs. comes at the very beginning of the string and that should match Mrs. Doubtfire,
but not Mr. and Mrs. Smith.
So let's see if it works.
I run my code movie too.
We get Mrs. Doubtfire again.
This first one was looking for anything that contained Mrs. anywhere.
We do have two matches, but this one doesn't matter.
It's never found because find is going to stop after the first match it returns.
Mr. and Mrs. Smith, the other movies.
There could be 1000 other movies.
They don't get looked at.
They're passed over.
This error function we wrote here, we could just do on a single line if we wanted to.
Huh?
For me, it's a bit long with my editor zoomed in, but it's not too bad.
So this works if you want to do it that way.
Now let's do another example with a different data structure.
Here I have that box array we've been using for a couple of examples.
Each book is an object.
It has a title author's, which is an array and a rating.
If I wanted to find a book that had a rating greater than 4.3, I would do books that find error function.
I'll just go with B as the parameter B rating.
I can spell rating is greater than or equal to 4.3 and we'll save that to a variable concept.
Good book.
Let's take a look.
Good book is Bone The Complete Edition.
Great graphic novel.
By the way, rating is 4.42.
It gave us the first match.
We could also do something like find the first book where Neil Gaiman is an author.
So contact Neil Book.
Equals books don't find be.
We want be authors.
DOT Includes Neil Gaiman.
There we go.
And I think that one is good enough for one line.
It's not that long, but just to have a little variety.
Let's do it with parents.
There we go.
Let's take a look.
Nail book.
And it gave us Good Omens, the first book where he is listed as an author.
So this one doesn't matter because find only gives us the first match.
So find is really useful when you're trying to, for example, find something based off of an ID if
you have a list of comments and or how about a list of posts that a user has created and they've clicked
a button to delete one of those posts.
If it's a web app, they want to remove it.
When that button is clicked.
Most likely you'll end up sending an ID you'll call a function with an ID of that post.
It will be something like delete post with ID of two.
It would be something like this.
You would have a function called delete, maybe delete post you'd pass in two and then you would use
to to find the post with that ID.
So you might do post find for the post parameter p p dot id equals two and maybe instead of deleting
you want it to update.
So you would find the post and then update the post based off of that id we used find a lot, especially
when we're looking for something based off of an identifier, a username.
But remember, it only gives us the first match.