Next up, we have yet another array method that expects you to pass in a callback.
It's called filter.
Filter allows us to filter out subsets of an array.
Basically, we we pass in a function which returns true or false, a test function.
And if an element passes that function, it will be added into the returned or the result array.
So if we had an array of a bunch of numbers, we want to create a new array with only the event.
We could filter the evens out.
It doesn't update the original, it doesn't mutate it.
So filtering it out makes it sound like we're removing them.
We're really just creating a copy with specific targeted information or elements.
So let's do a couple of examples.
We'll start simple with numbers.
I know it's boring.
Const nums equals and I'll just type some random numbers in here.
That's good enough there.
And if I wanted to filter so that I get a new array only with odd numbers, I could call numbers or
nums dot filter and I'll use a single line arrow function.
Implicit return and is my parameter and mod two equals one.
That's how we know if something is odd.
So this function right here is a boolean function.
It's what's called a test function.
At least if you look at the docs for filter, it returns true or false.
So filter is going to start with an empty array and it's going to try 34 and pass it into our test function.
Does that pass?
Do we get true?
No, we do not because this is even so it goes to 35.
That does pass this test.
It returns true.
So 35 is added to the result and then 67 would be added and then 54 would not be added.
And then as soon as it hits the end of the array, it returns this result.
So I can save this to a variable called ODS.
Let's check it out.
There's odds it contains the four odd numbers.
If we look at nums, it's not altered in any way.
So we're not removing them.
We're simply creating a new array with those values.
We could do the same thing for evens.
It would be very simple change.
Name the variable evens and then say num mod two equals zero.
There is no remainder when we divide by two.
So now I'm just unchanged.
But now we have evens containing the even numbers.
If I wanted to get large numbers, I'll call them big numbers.
I could do num stop filter with the parameter name of and again where NW is greater than how about 50?
So this will give me an array of numbers where each number is larger than 50.
Let me just save my code.
Run it over here.
We'll look at big numbers.
And now we have 67, 54, 109 and 102.
So we write a function that returns true or false.
If that function returns true for an element, it's added into the result that we get.
Otherwise it's ignored.
Let's do a few more complex examples.
I've updated this book's array to include more books, but also each book has some new properties.
We have a genre or genres property, which is an array of genres.
We have more books that each have a rating and that's pretty much it.
There's what, ten or so books in here?
Maybe eight.
Now imagine that we're actually creating a ecommerce bookstore or a website like Goodreads where you
can search for books, add them to your reading list, and it's a social network for books.
A lot of the time we want to give users the ability to search for things, to search for a book based
off of a title, or to narrow down search results so that they could check a box that says rating,
I don't know, four star or greater rating or only fantasy books we would use filter to narrow down
the results that we're showing.
So let's do a couple of examples.
Let's start with a simple one.
Let's select the ratings or the books that have high ratings so their rating is greater than maybe 4.3.
So that would be content.
Good books equals books filter for B, we want B to be greater than 4.3.
Let's see what we get.
Good books.
All right.
Well, that's my fault.
I'm comparing the entire book.
This is an object I need to compare.
B rating.
Try that again.
And now we have four books, Bone, which has a rating of 4.42 gentlemen in Moscow.
Great book 4.36.
Name of the Wind 4.54.
And The Way of Kings 4.65.
So we just grabbed the highest rated books.
But again, books is unchanged.
It still has nine books in it.
If a user then wanted to pivot and look at, let's say, only fantasy books, let's filter where genre
includes fantasy.
So we have a couple of them here.
In order to do that, we'll use filter.
So const fantasy books equals bookstore filter.
This one is probably going to be a bit long for a single line, so I'll do for each book or that would
be the name of the parameter.
I'll use an implicit return with parentheses.
We want book dot genres.
DOT includes.
Fantasy.
We could do this on one line, but whoops, no semicolon in there.
And let's see what we get.
Run it over here.
Fantasy books.
We get five books each.
One should include fantasy as one of its genres.
So this one has fantasy.
This one has fantasy.
American gods bone has fantasy, and good omens does as well.
Okay, let's do another example where we filter for short form books where basically it's either essays
or short stories.
I don't know what you would call those small books made up of smaller pieces, anthology books.
We'll call it short form.
So short form equals books.
Filter book is our parameter name.
And then I'll do another implicit return.
We want to check if book dot genres dot includes either short stories.
Let me just make sure it was short stories, plural or I want essays so I'll do or book genres includes
essays.
Let's see what we get for short form, we have two results.
The first one is Changing My Mind by Zadie Smith.
In genres we can see essays.
The second one is by Richard Powers called the Overstory really cool book.
Short Stories is in genres as well, so a whole bunch of different ways to filter just this one array
of books.
Think of any e-commerce website you can filter by rating.
You can filter by searching for something.
So let's try that.
Let's search through a title and find books that contain, I don't know, the in their title.
So to mimic a search box, let's make a variable called query.
And this will be coming from a user.
We don't know what it is, so I'll leave it blank for now and then we'll do books.
Dot Filter.
I'll save this to a variable called results and we'll filter where the book title includes that query.
And to be extra sure, we'll also down case everything.
So it's case insensitive.
So book we'll do book dot title dot two lowercase dot includes.
And then I want to make sure I'm lowercase doing the query as well.
Query to lowercase.
To give us a bit more room.
And honestly, in this scenario, this is fine as a one liner, but just for some variety, I'll break
this up.
So I'll use a regular arrow function where I need to explicitly return something.
So I'll extract this to a variable.
I'll call it title equals box title or book title to lowercase, and then I'll just do return.
Title dot includes query, not local lowercase, regular lowercase.
All right.
So whatever the user searches for, let's say they're searching for, is there anything we could get
multiple results with?
I guess we've got the it's quite boring, but if a user types the we're going to down case this right
here and we're going to compare it to every book title by down casing the title so that we don't care
about casing at all.
Then we'll just check.
Does each title include that lowercase query?
If it does, this returns true.
It gets added to our results.
Let's run it.
Let's look at results.
We get five.
They all contain the phone.
The complete is a complete journey.
Complete Story, Complete Edition.
The Name of the Win The Overstory The Way of Kings and Lord of the Flies.
Here we don't have an uppercase.
The here we do have uppercase though so those are some examples of using filter.
It's a great method.
There's so many applications where you need to narrow down an array to smaller a smaller portion.
Remember, you're not actually updating or mutating the original, but it gives you a return value that
you can save and then work with.
So I use Filter all the time and it's relatively simple.
You pass in a test function that you write, it returns true or false.
If it's true for a given element, then that element is added to the filtered result array.