Next up, I'm grouping two array methods together.
They were called every and some.
So both of these methods are boolean methods.
They return true or false at the end of the day.
After they run, you get true or false.
So every is going to accept a callback which itself needs to be a boolean callback.
It returns true or false.
It's a test and it runs that function on every or with every element in the array.
And if it gets true for every element, then the whole function, the whole method of every returns
true.
So it's a way of verifying or checking.
Does every element in this array have three letters or does every element end with the letter G.
So as an example, let's try this out.
We have a word array over here.
If I wanted to check if every word has a length of three, I would do words dot every.
And then I pass in my boolean function.
This function, also called the test function, needs to return true or false.
So I'll say for every word.
Does that word length equal three?
And I'll save this to a variable called all three letters or something.
Not the most graceful variable name.
Let's run it and see what we get.
All three lets is true, but as soon as I change one of these to be four letters or two letters and
I run it again, it's false.
This function has to return true for every single element in order for every to return true.
So let's go back to what we had.
We could do another test if they all end with the letter G.
So that would be words dot every and I'll do this on multiple lines just so that we have some diversity
here for every word that will be our parameter, let's calculate the last index so we'll go with last
equals and then word length minus one that gives us the last index.
Remember, length is always one more than the last index and then we'll use that to return.
Word of last triple equals G.
So we're getting the last index which for all of these there are only three letters, so the last index
will be two.
And then we're saying is word of two equal to the letter G and save that to a variable.
Let's go with const all g, all end in G and if we check over here, all end in G, it's true.
But of course if I change one of them to be backed with a T, it's no longer true.
So that's every it takes a boolean function.
It runs it on every element in the array.
And if it always gets true for the entire array, then every itself returns true.
Next we have some some is similar.
It does kind of the same process, but it only cares if any of those elements pass the test.
So if there's at least one element in the array that passed the test that returned true, then the entire
method of sum returns true.
So with this example array of words, if I wanted to check if some of the words start with D, it would
be words some and then word will do word of zero equals D.
So this is a boolean function we pass in.
It has to be a true or false returning function and some will call it once per elements and as long
as it gets one.
True, that's all that matters.
Words, not some will return true or the sum method.
So we'll go with.
Oh, I don't know.
These variables are really hard to name const some start with D.
That is quite the lengthy name.
Let's check it out.
Some start with D.
Yes, that is true.
We have two elements that start with D.
If I instead did words dot every word starts with D we'll call this every or all start with D we get
false.
As you can see here versus some start is true.
So the only difference here was some in every sum needs just one element to return.
True, every needs all of them to return true.
Let's try one more.
Every we'll do words dot every.
Actually, let's bring our books back and let's try a couple more examples with our good friend, this
book array.
Let's write some code to check if every book is at least 3.5 stars or 3.5 whatever rating or higher.
So we would call books dot every for each book.
We want to know if book dot rating is greater than 3.5.
And we'll save this to a variable.
All good books.
Let's take a look.
All good books is true.
If I instead did 4.5 and higher.
That's false because we have plenty of books that are not 4.5 or higher.
So let's go back to let's leave it at four.
At 3.5, I think all of these books are good.
I would feel bad saying that one of them is not good.
Some of these older books, Lord of the Flies, people always rate them lower.
And let's write one more to see if any of these books have two authors.
So that would be KONST.
Let's go with any two authors.
Equals books.
DOT some.
Book book authors dot length equals to.
So we're passing in our function, the test function.
It will return true if a given book has exactly two authors.
Author's length is two and we're using some, so we just need one of them to be true.
We'll run it.
Any two authors is true.
So that is some.
And every.
They follow a similar pattern, but they behave differently.
Every needs, every element to pass this test.
Some just needs one to pass.