Next up, we have another array method we've actually seen before, but when we saw it earlier, it
didn't really behave the way we wanted it to.
So the method is sort.
Here I have an array called prices and it's full of numbers representing prices on a website or who
knows what.
When we called array sought or prices sought early on, when we talked about array methods back when
we were covering index of or reverse those sort of methods, we didn't know about callbacks, we didn't
know about functions.
Even so, when we call prices that sort the default sort in JavaScript, it's very weird.
I have no idea why this decision was made, but the default, as we've already seen, is to convert
all of these numbers to strings and sort them as strings.
And that leads to some very odd behavior.
If I run this code, prices sort just do it over here.
You can see it ends up sorting them by the first character.
So one before three and it's sorting them based off of strings rather than sorting them by actual value.
So we end up with nine at the end of the array.
I know that's 99.99.
Okay.
Well, we end up with 99.99 at the end when we have 3000 and 9500 and 405 or 400.5, those should all
be greater, but the sort doesn't really work the way we want it to.
So back then I said, once we talk about functions, we'll see how to use sort and how to customize
its behavior.
This is how we do it.
We pass in what they call on the docs a compare function.
Now this function has two parameters.
You can call them A and B or first and second, and we need to return a value a number from compare
func.
If that compare func returns a negative number, the function will sort a before B if it returns zero,
it does not change the order, and if it returns a number greater than zero, it will sort B before
a So this is always kind of confusing to explain when you look at it this way.
It may not make a lot of sense, but let me show you how we would use it here.
So if we do prices sort and we write our function a compare function, it needs to have two parameters
A and B is fine.
Then the standard sort would be A minus B.
And let me just show you what we get first.
I'll save this to a variable cost sort one.
Let's look at sort one.
We end up with 12 35.9 999 403,000 9500.
We are sorting in ascending order from smallest to largest.
If we come back to this chart, remember that if the compare function returns a negative number, it
sorts A before B, where A is the first element, B is the second, if it's a positive number instead,
it sorts B before a.
So if we walk through this with a simple example, the first time this callback is executed, we have
400.5 and 3000.
So if we have A and B, we have I'm just going to do 400.5 and then 3000.
And the way our compare function is set up is that it returns A minus B, so 400 -3000 is going to be
a negative number.
So what does it do with a negative number?
It sorts A before B, so that means that it's going to sort 400 before 3000.
Then let's say we were comparing 35.9, nine and 12.
At that point, a would be 35.99 and then we have 12.4.
B, when we subtract A minus B, 35, -12, that gives us a positive number.
And when we have a positive number, it sorts B before A so that means 12 would go before 35.
And if we had two numbers that were equal, then they would be treated as equal.
We wouldn't put one before the other.
We'd keep the order unchanged, at least between those two values.
So if we wanted to sort the other way, let's call this constant ascending sort.
If I wanted to do a descending sort and the idea is here we would do prices dot sort, we have A and
B, let's do instead of A and B, this time X and Y, and then we want to return Y minus X.
So this is the other way around.
And I kind of just made a horrible decision to name it X and Y from a educational point of view, because
now you can't compare these as easily.
So I'm going to redo that.
So A and B, same order here, but now we're returning B minus A, so if A is 1000 and we're comparing
it to B, which is 4000, in this case we're doing B minus A, so 4000, -1000 gives us a positive number.
And when we get a positive number, sort B before A, so that means moving the larger numbers to the
left side of the array, sorting them in descending order.
So this one change A minus B versus B minus A or first thing, minus second thing versus second thing.
Minus first thing makes a significant difference.
So we look at descending sort.
It's going from 9500 all the way down to 12.
So the greatest number is first, the smallest number is last.
There is a problem, though, if we look at ascending sort, it looks like I mean, it is exactly the
same thing, but that's deceiving.
Remember, that sort is one of the few array methods, at least one of the few callback array methods
that actually mutates the original array.
So we sorted it one way in place.
We're actually updating prices and then we sorted it another way here in place.
So we lose this effort.
It's gone.
We're just making another reference to the same array.
So we have three variables pointing to the exact same array.
If we look at prices, it's also updated.
It's just one array in memory.
So if I wanted to just have two clear different results where I was not sorting the same array, I could
either declare two variables prices one and then make a duplicate of prices to with the same data.
Or I could use a method to copy the data into a new array.
So something like slice right here.
If I slice first and I don't pass anything in, if I call Price's slice, it makes a copy of that array.
We saw this behavior earlier when we first talked about slice.
So this is not something you would normally do unless you really did not want to sort in place.
It's pretty rare that you're going to sort ascending and descending at once.
Maybe you'll allow a user to toggle between them, but then you can just have one array that is going
from ascending to descending.
But when I'm teaching, I want to show you both so that you can take a look at both of them at the same
time.
Let's make another variable here called bad sort equals prices dot slice.
So I'm just making three copies.
Each one of these variables now is not connected to the original prices.
They have the same data, but they're not the same reference.
And let's see what we get.
So we have our bad sort first.
This is the one based off of strings.
I shouldn't call it bad sort, but it's bad when you're sorting numbers.
Then we have our ascending sort, where we go from smallest number to the greatest number that was using
A minus B first, minus second.
And then we have our descending sort, which goes the other way, B minus A, so it returns a positive
number when this version would have returned a negative number and vice versa.
So 9500 down to 12.
Okay.
Now, the last thing I'll show you is how to sort something that is a little more complex rather than
a single array of numbers.
Let's go back to our books array.
I've copied the books array back in.
We have nine books that each have a rating.
I think that's the logical thing to sort by.
So we'll write our sort and we'll do this one in place.
Books sort.
I mean, it always happens in place, but we won't make a copy of the array.
We don't care about the original order.
Let's just mutate this array so books sort we pass in our callback.
I'll go with A and B again, but this time we can't do something like A minus B because A and B are
both objects.
They're referring to one element in the array at a time.
That's one element, that's another.
How can we compare or how can we run one object minus another object?
We can't.
So what we need to do is compare based off of rating, which is easy enough.
It's just a DOT rating, minus B rating.
And let's take a look at books now.
Before the first one was 4.25 for Good Omens, 3.83 for changing my mind.
If we look at books over here, not book O's, but books we end up with First Lord of the Flies 3.67
Then We Have Changing My Mind 3.8 American Gods 4.11 All the way down to the way of Kings 4.65 And we
could reverse it if we wanted to by going the other direction.
If we wanted highest rated first, we would do B rating, minus A rating.
Now you can do more complex sorts instead of just comparing based off of one value here we're only sorting
based off of rating.
You could write a more complex function that sorted based off of rating and also sorted based off of
I don't know the genre or if you had different types of ratings like for audiobooks, you have ratings
for the book itself and the story and then ratings for the performance quality of the person narrating
it.
So you have two different ratings and if you want it to sort descending based off of primarily the story,
but then secondarily also the performance, you could write a more complex function, but this is good
enough for now.
Let's look at books now and what do we have up first, let me expand this.
We've got Way of Kings 4.65 and that is sort so we saw the very, very basics of sort back when we covered
arrays and array methods before we talked about callbacks and it wasn't that useful.
I guess if you need to sort strings, it's, it's fine.
But if you need to sort numbers, you need to pass a callback in a compare func and it needs to return
a number.
If it's a negative number, one thing happens.
If it's a positive number, something else happens.
Okay, so that is sort.