Last but certainly not least, we have reduce.
Reduce is a built in array method.
You pass a callback to it and just like all the methods we've seen in this section, I saved it for
last because reduce is a bit different.
It's really useful and versatile, but it also is a little tricky to explain.
So this image is not here for you to be afraid of reduce.
It's here showing you my own fear of teaching.
Reduce.
Every time I teach it, it goes well enough.
But I always feel like I could have done that better.
And I'm always worried not actually stressing about it, but it's always something that I worry about
making better because it's just not that easy to teach.
Reduce is something that you just need to practice in order to get good with it.
So what is reduced?
Why is it even named reduce?
We have seen many like for each.
That seems like a pretty standard name.
It does something for each element we've seen.
Every awe filter or sort reduce is maybe not as intuitive, but here's what it does.
It takes an array of values and it reduces them down to a single value, which is what this little diagram
is.
I spent a long time working on this.
It's all just clip art, but I couldn't find the right stuff.
The idea is each one of these is maybe representing an element in an array and they're being combined
and reduced down to a single droplet of liquid.
So applications for reduce include things like summing every element in an array.
That's probably the simplest one we'll start with, but it's not always about summing or multiplying
or accumulating data in one number.
It could be finding the maximum value in an entire array.
We're reducing this array of 100 numbers down to one maximum.
It could also be tallying votes or tallying data in an array or in an object.
So I'm going to split, reduce into a couple of different videos.
We're going to start with the basics here.
We're going to talk about how it works with the simplest example of summing every element in an array.
So reduce is an array method we passed in a callback and that callback needs to follow a particular
format.
That format looks like this.
It's a callback with at least two parameters.
Now, the documentation calls this first one accumulator.
Other people will call it total.
But this is the variable where the parameter that will store the end result of reduce.
And then we have current value or val or element.
This represents each individual element in the array as reduce works its way across.
So it doesn't matter what you name them, but the first thing, the first parameter here will store
the total or the accumulated value that we're reducing down to.
And then current value or just the second parameter here stores each individual element.
So this example sums all numbers in this array.
If we take a look at this table, I think it helps explain how it works.
The accumulator variable is going to start as the first element in the array and current value starts
as the next element.
And if you look at what we're returning, accumulator plus current value.
So take the current total, which is initialized to the first element three.
Add it to the next value five.
Current value that gives us eight.
So we return eight that is then used as accumulator in the next iteration.
So Accumulator now remembers the last time, the last sum, which was eight.
So now Accumulator is eight and current value is the next element seven.
So we add them together and return that which is 15 and now reduce runs again or the callback rather
runs again.
Accumulator is now 15.
It remembers the value from last time.
The sum or the total and current value is nine.
So we add 15 and nine.
That's what I'm reducing or how I'm reducing.
We get 24, it goes one more time.
Accumulator is 24 on the fourth call.
It holds the sum of all of these elements before it.
And now current value is the last element.
11.
So we return the sum of 24 and 11, which gives us 35, and we've hit the end.
So reduce returns 35, that is the total accumulated value.
So we end up with 35 as the return value.
So again, think of it this way.
We're taking a bunch of values and we're reducing them down to a single value.
And the function that we pass in has to follow this format where the first thing is a total or the accumulator
or just the place, the value that you are reducing.
And it will hold a value each time that changes or it can change.
So every time this function runs, it's past the previous return value of the function.
And then current value is whichever value we're working on.
So let's try it again.
Let's do something slightly different.
Let's do a simple array.
We'll go with nums just to keep it easy.
Let's go.
How about three, four, five, six, seven?
And then if we call nums dot reduce and I want to multiply all numbers together and end up with a product
of all of these numbers I need to pass in my callback which follows that format.
You can see here I'm actually getting the autocomplete or the preview where the first value or the first
parameter, they call it previous value in vs code and current value is the second parameter.
Let's call this one total instead of accumulator.
Accumulator sounds a little intense, so total and then cur curve l.
I guess current value is fine and then I'll do an arrow function.
So I need a set of prints around the two parameters and then my arrow and I won't do this one on one
line.
We'll return manually.
I want to multiply total by the current value.
And then let's save this to a variable cost product equals what does product equal?
We get 2520.
I guess that's probably right.
Let's see.
Three times, four times five times, six times seven.
There we go.
So if you feel like you understand how it works, you can go ahead and stop watching this video and
move on to the more advanced ways of using Reduce, which is the next video.
But if you want to step through this step by step, let's go ahead and do it.
So the very first time reduce calls, our callback total is going to be initialized to the first element.
So I'm going to make a little table here.
We'll go with total and then all the way over here, we'll have current value.
So the first time through it initializes total to three right there.
Then current vowel is going to be set to the very next element, which is four and we are returning
total times current value.
So we return 12 and reduce remembers that if to if we want to personify it, it remembers the previous
return value which was 12.
So it uses 12 as total the next time through it passes 12 as a total and then current value is going
to be five.
So we get 12.
And then all the way over here, I don't know why I made it so far away.
We have five now.
What's five times 12.
What is that, 60.
Is that right?
Yeah, right.
Okay.
So the return value is 60 this time and 60 is now the new total and current value is going to be six.
So we have 60 and then six and then the callback is called one more time.
60 times six is 3600.
No.
360.
Excuse me.
So that is the new total that is returned from this iteration here.
Return total 60 times six.
That's 360.
That is the new total and the final value in the array is seven.
So we end up now with 360 times seven, which gives us 2520.
So that is a step by step walk through.
Remember that the first parameter is the total.
It is the thing you are boiling down to.
You're reducing down to and you're keeping track.
It persists.
You can think of it as having a memory throughout this whole iterative cycle, and then current value
changes every time, depending on which iteration we're on, which element we're actually using.
So this is a simple example of multiplying everything.
We saw how we could sum all elements in an array.
Next, we'll see some more advanced use cases for reduce.