All right.
So we saw how we can use reduce to sum all elements in an array or multiply them all together.
And that's one use for reduce.
But there are many other things we can do with it.
We don't have to be accumulating a value through math.
We don't have to be multiplying or adding or subtracting or dividing.
We can also do things like finding the maximum value in an array where the accumulator is really just
tracking the max.
It's not being added to or multiplied or anything like that.
It's simply referring to the current maximum value.
And then we potentially update max if we find a larger value.
So let me show you a quick example here.
We have grades, a list of grades in array.
If I want to find the max, what I could do is grades dot reduce.
I'll save this to a variable called max grade and we need to pass in our callback, which follows the
format of accumulator first and then current Val next.
But instead of calling this a cume or accumulator, I'm just going to call it Max.
Then I'll add my arrow function syntax.
And what we need to do is check if the current value is greater than the current max.
So the first time this runs, we'll have Max start at 87, just like when we summed an array together.
The first total started as the first element, so Max will be 87 and then current Val we'll go with
let's do curve out here cur val we'll start at 64 and then we do a comparison.
Is current Val greater than Max?
If curve out is greater than Max.
If it is, then we will return curve out.
And if this is not the case, we'll return Max.
So whatever is returned from this function will be used as the next max.
So the first time through Max is 87.
Current Val is 64.
This is not true.
Curve L is smaller, so we return max.
So if we add our return here, I should comment this whole thing out so we don't get syntax errors.
That return is going to be 87 return max.
When we return that value Max then uses that previous return.
So we returned 87.
Max is 87 once again, but next time Cavell moves on to 96.
So now Cavell is 96.
We do the comparison.
Cavell is now greater than Max.
96 is greater than 87.
So we return Cavell, which is 96, and that return value is then used to set the new Max Max.
The third time through is going to be 96.
And then we're comparing it to Cavell, which is 92, and I won't waste your time going through this
entire thing, but this time through we return 96, we just return max as is, because this is not true.
And eventually we go all the way through the array and we find the max.
We return that max, which eventually is 99.
Then we compare it to 73.
We keep returning 99, 99, 99 and then reduce returns that final return value, which is 99.
So let's run it and just make sure I'm not crazy.
Let's take a look at Max Grade.
It is indeed 99.
We could also rewrite this in a pretty different way.
There's a couple of different approaches using reduce.
If I comment this out instead of returning Cavell or returning Max, we can use the built in math.
Max So math out.
Max You pass in two numbers like three and five and it will tell us the maximum number three and ten
is ten, nine and one.
We get nine.
So we could use that and replace this whole line with return math.
Max of the current max and the current vowel that we're looking at if we run it, max grade is still
99 and we could also write a min grade.
Keep this exactly the same, although I would rename this to be min.
This represents the minimum value that we are keeping track of as we go through.
As reduced calls are callback over and over and over, it will pass in the current min.
So return math dot min.
And if you wanted to, you could even use an implicit return, since we have a single expression there.
Get rid of the return keyword.
Let's look at min grade.
Max is not defined.
I need to update that to be min as well.
So min grade is now 64.
Max is 99.
So same logic.
Just wrote it in a different way.
Here we're doing the math ourselves or the comparison.
Here we rely on math, Max.
But what really matters is the way reduce works.
So we're not summing things together or not multiplying them into a accumulator variable.
The term accumulator or total kind of makes me think of something that is growing or getting bigger,
but that's not what happens here.
This parameter, which we're calling Max, is simply pointing to one value and then potentially pointing
to a different value instead.
As soon as we find a new max, it updates to be that max.
So it's not accumulating so much as just keeping track of the max.
And before we move on to our third video on Reduce, which I'll show you some even some more interesting
or different use cases for Reduce.
That's coming up next.
But before we do that, there's one extra argument I haven't mentioned.
When you use reduce, you can actually pass in an initial starting value.
So after your callback, the format would be something reduce.
So we'll do array, reduce you pass in your callback and then initial value.
Now this callback is usually an inline anonymous function, so it ends up being kind of long.
But at the end, after your function, you can add a comma and then an initial value.
So if we write a simple reducer function, let's just go back to to adding numbers together.
So we'll do how about ten, 20, 30, 40 and 50?
Dot reduce add in our arrow function.
We'll go with some and then let's go with cur val.
Right now if we return some plus curve ball.
And let's store this in a variable cost sum.
Let's look at some.
It's 150.
Is that correct?
Let's see.
I think that makes sense.
Right?
50.
100 and then 40 plus ten.
Yeah.
150.
When we don't specify an initial value, it will just use the first element, which we saw a couple
of slides ago.
Here.
Nope.
Where the accumulator starts as three.
That's the first element and the current value starts at five.
But you can initialize with a custom value.
So I can say I want some to start at zero, which is going to give us the exact same result.
We start with zero, then we add ten, then 20, then 30, then 40, then 50.
That's exactly the same number at the end of the day as starting with ten, 20, 30, 40, 50.
But if we instead pass it a number like 1000, here are some will start at 1000, then add ten, then
20, then 30.
And we end up with.
1150.
So you probably wouldn't do this right here specifically where you want the sum and you want to start
at 1000.
But there are other use cases which we'll see in the next video where you can specify an initial value
and it won't even be a number.
We'll see that we can specify an object if we're trying to accumulate data into an object.
And that's what we're going to see next up.
So to wrap this up, we saw that you can use reduce not just to multiply or to some things together,
but also to keep track of the max or the min or some piece of data.
It doesn't have to be max or min.
It could be the longest string in an array, the highest rated book, whatever it is.
As we iterate over each element in an array, we are keeping track of some piece of data.
And then the second thing we saw is that we can pass in an initial value as the second argument to reduce.
So this whole thing is the first argument right before that comma.
And then the second argument is right there.
All right, we're almost done.
We've got some other cool use cases coming up next.