In our final video on Reduce.
Yes, we've almost made it to the end here.
We're going to see a completely different way of using it where we can tally up results from an array.
We can group different values in an array using an object.
So here's a simple example.
I have an array of votes which I'm storing as Y and N.
It could also just be true and false.
It could be yay and nay.
We could have multiple votes.
We could have yes, no and abstain.
We could have ratings.
But what we're going to do is use reduce to produce an object where we have y and we count the number
of y's like 12 and then the number of nodes like eight.
Now I don't think that's accurate for this exact array, but this is what we're going for.
So what we're going to do is a little different.
Our accumulator, the thing that will actually return and add into or update is going to be an object.
So we're going to have votes reduce, we'll have some function, I'll just call it func for now and
our initial value will be an empty object.
So I'll call this concept results maybe equals votes that reduce our function, which we have yet to
fill out.
And the initial value is an empty object.
Remember, we specify an initial value like 100 accumulator.
The first parameter to our reduced callback starts at 100.
In this case, we're using an object, so a little bit different, but the same idea.
The initial value will be this empty object.
So I'll draw it out down here.
Then we're going to write our callback.
I'll use an arrow function.
The first piece is the accumulator.
This is the, the piece of you can think of it as like a memory from last time, from the last iteration
of Reduce.
I'm going to call this one tally because that's what it represents.
It's not really a sum or a total.
Total would be okay, but tally is it makes sense here.
And then we'll have current item or current vote or let's just call it Val.
All right, then.
An arrow function.
And what we want to do here is add to this object using whatever key we have.
So let's say it's why we want to check.
Is there a why in this object?
Because the very first time we encounter why, there won't be a key for why it's just empty.
So if we encounter y, we'll want to say y is one.
Then the next time through.
We're not going to set Y to one.
We're going to check.
Is there a Y already?
Yes, that was the first time through.
So add one to it.
Then we'll get to N and we'll check.
Is there an N in this object?
No, there's not.
So set it equal to one.
So we'll have y two and one.
And then next time we get to an end, we'll increment it.
So our logic will look something like this if.
Tally of Val.
Meaning if we already have that key in the object, we're going to want to increment it.
So tally of val plus.
Plus.
That means there's already something in there.
So not this case.
The very first time through this code does not run because there is no value in tally.
There is no.
Yes, there's no.
No.
So otherwise that's the if part.
I'll do this some more verbose way first.
So we'll do tally val plus equals if it's already in there.
If it's not in there, we'll write tally of val equals one, we'll set it to one.
And then at the end we'll return tally.
Okay.
So Talley starts the very first time through.
It's an empty object.
Our vowel is why.
The first element is their tally of Val.
No, it doesn't exist.
This does not run here.
But this does.
So we set Tally of Val to be one and we return that.
So the next time through we have y one.
So now Italy is equal to this object.
That's what we're returning.
Just like we did when we some things together or when we found the max or the min, same pattern.
We're just changing tally in a different way.
We're not accumulating in the same format, but we are persisting this, we're returning it.
And then next time through that return, value is used as tally.
So we get to another why?
Why one?
This is our object.
If Tally of L well, there is Y in this object.
So that means we're going to increment it to be two y of two.
And you can see where I'm going with this.
We'll eventually hit RN.
There is not an RN in here, so this part here does not run and we instead set tally of RN equal to
one and then we keep going.
So let's see what we end up with.
We'll run this.
What do we get when we call results?
It looks like seven yeses and six nos.
I guess we can count that or count the Ys.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven and the Nos.
One, two, three, four, five, six.
Great.
So if we had instead added some other types of votes in here, like, I don't know, nay or how about
absent?
Let's just leave it like that.
We'll run it again.
Results.
Now we have yeses seven absent one and Nos.
Six.
Now, there is a shorter way of writing this, the logic itself that we have here.
And I'll show that to you right now.
Instead of doing this if and else where we're checking if Tally Oval exists.
And if it does, we'll add one.
If it doesn't, we'll initialize it to one.
We can rewrite this slightly differently.
We'll say tally of val equals.
And bear with me for a second.
Tally of Val or zero plus one.
Okay.
So how does this one line work?
Well, it all hinges upon this right here.
Tally of val or zero.
So if our object is empty at the beginning, there is no.
Why, there's no.
We don't have any keys.
The very first time we encounter y, for example, we're going to set tally of Y to equal the current
tally of y, which doesn't exist.
So that gives us undefined or zero which results in zero.
So we're doing zero plus one, which is going to set it to one.
But the next time through, if we encounter y again, the very next element is Y, we'll set tally of
y equal to tally of y, which right now is one.
So then this becomes one, one or zero gives us one.
So then we end up with one plus one, which is two.
So it's kind of a sneaky way of doing what we're doing up here.
If something exists, add one to it.
If it doesn't exist, set it to one.
We're just doing it in one line, taking advantage of this boolean logic.
So I need to reset that to tally.
Oh Val, run this code again.
Results.
It still works.
So just a shorter way of writing it.
Okay.
So this is equivalent to this.
We get the same result.
One more example of using reduce.
I have the same books array we've been working with.
I added in a new book Where are you?
I truly horrible book.
I wanted to give one a bad rating, but I didn't want to call out a real book and give it a bad rating.
So this is a truly horrible book written by Save Your Time.
Save Your Time.
Hi.
Got it.
Save your time.
Very funny.
So what I want to do is group all of these books in a new object and I want to group them by rating.
So all books that have a two star review will go, whoops, it will be an array.
Then we'll have all books that have a three star.
So three point something, not just exactly three, but 3.6, seven and 3.0.
Where are you?
3.83.
And then all the four star books will go into the key of four.
So I'm going to use reduce for this books dot reduce and we're going to add our accumulator function
here.
Just put gibberish and we'll set the initial value to be an object as well, just like we did up here.
We initialize it right there or we give it an initial value.
Okay, so our function is going to look like this.
We'll have our accumulator parameter first.
I'll call this grouped books and then after that we'll have each book.
Aero function, then we need to get the rating from the book.
So book rating.
But I want to eliminate the decimal.
I don't want to use this as the key because that's far too unique.
I only want three.
So I'm going to do a math dot for math floor.
We'll just chop the decimal point off.
Right?
Math floor of 5.4 gives us five.
5.9 still gives us five.
So it's not rounding, it's just chopping off the decimal.
So I'm going to save that to a variable we'll call this key.
Key equals that rating.
So this will give us two, three or four off the current data set at least.
And then we want to check does grouped books.
Of key dates that exist.
If not, we're going to make it an empty array.
So I'd probably just do this if.
Not grouped books of that key.
Meaning there is currently no book with rating of three or rating of four or whatever rating we're working
with.
Then I'll set grouped books of that key to be an empty array.
Because remember, our goal here is to create an object where we have three, which is an array of books.
So each one of these would be a book with a rating of three point something.
So if key is four, if there is no grouped books of four, it's empty.
Then we're going to say grouped books of four is equal to an empty array.
But then we also want to push in.
So that will be grouped books.
Of key dot push the entire book.
So let me make this a bit bigger.
And then finally we'll return our grouped books.
Okay.
So this one's a bit longer, you could definitely shorten it up again.
But just to summarize how it works, we have an empty object at the beginning.
We encounter our first book, which is all the way up here.
It has a rating of 4.25.
So we get that rating, we chop the decimal off.
Now key is four.
We're going to check is there a key of four in grouped books?
There's not.
It's an empty object.
So we're going to set it equal to an empty array.
So we end up with four empty array.
Then we say grouped books of four dot push the entire book.
So that's when we add the whole book into that array.
And then the process starts again, this time for three.
And let's say we get to another four star book like this one.
We're going to get the key which will be for chop the decimal off we have for this part is false because
grouped books of that key does exist now.
So we only push.
We don't do this.
We don't set it to an empty array.
We only push in a new book.
So now we have two books in there.
Let's make sure it works.
Save it to a variable context.
Grouped by ratings.
It's kind of a long variable.
Let's see.
Grouped by ratings.
We have our two star book just as one book, a truly horrible book.
We have two, three star books.
And then we have our four star books.
So this was, uh, a little bit more complicated.
Definitely.
This is why I saved these examples for the very end after we got maybe a little comfortable with reduce.
If you're at all struggling with this, I don't blame you.
This is a weird one.
And why?
I kind of said I was scared to teach it and why I always worry a bit about teaching reduce.
It's hard to teach because there's so many uses for it.
It's not as straightforward as the other built in array callback methods, but don't feel bad.
If you are struggling with it, you'll get more practice.
It will come more naturally with time.
Hopefully it always trips beginners up, so that's reduced lots of different ways of using it.
But it boils down to pun intended, this diagram here where we take multiple elements from an array
and we turn them into one result somehow, whether it's a sum, a product or a min, a max, or we're
tallying them into an object, or we're grouping them by rating or by genre or whatever.
We end up with one result at the end, multiple values into one value that's reduced.
We made it and we're done with this section.
Congratulations.
This is a very meaty section.