Well, I may have just lied to you.
We're not quite at variables.
We have one more very quick topic to discuss with numbers.
Something called Nan.
It is a special value in JavaScript.
It stands for not a number and it is a number in JavaScript.
It's considered a numeric value that represents something that is not a number.
So there's a couple of different ways you could arrive at not a number.
Here are two simple ones.
If you try and divide zero by zero, you'll get not a number.
If you try and take not a number and add a number to it, the answer is still not a number, which makes
sense.
You couldn't take not a number and add five to it.
The answer logically would be not a number.
So you can type, not a number like this.
It is capital n a n.
If you did n a n like this, it's not really going to work.
It needs to be capitalized correctly.
It's a very special value in JavaScript and it is a number, as I mentioned already.
If we do zero divided by zero, we get not a number.
If we take not a number, we add five.
It's still not a number.
There are two other values I mentioned.
We have infinity, which we can generate by doing something like one divided by zero.
JavaScript just has a way of representing a value of infinity.
There's no way to store that as a number, an actual number that you could see.
So we have a special value called infinity.
There's also a negative infinity, as you can see here.
And we also have zero and -0, which sometimes throws people off.
-0 is its own value in JavaScript as well.
But the point here is really about not a number.
If you do encounter not a number, it is a value that means this is not a number.
It doesn't necessarily mean something went wrong.
Sometimes you have code where you're expecting not a number or it could be a possibility.
So it's not an error necessarily, but it means this is not standard math or JavaScript is going to
have a hard time representing this number or this value as a true numeric value.
So that's nine, not a number.
Now we're actually going on to variables.