In the last video we saw that we could have a variable like score.
Let's say it starts at zero.
We're making some sort of board game or a Tetris or something in the browser.
We have a score variable to keep track of the user score and we could update it by doing this score
equals score plus let's say ten if the user scores ten points.
Now score is ten.
There's also a shorthand for changing the value of a variable without having to reference the name again.
So instead of score equals score plus ten, we can do score plus equals.
Let's go with one.
This is the same as saying score equals score plus one plus equals.
Is just going to update score by one in this case.
So score is 11.
Now we could also do it by something other than one.
We could add ten again, score plus equals ten.
Score is now 21.
Now we can also do the same thing with subtraction and other operators like score minus equals.
Say that the user did something bad in the game.
They lose points, minus equals 100.
Now score is -79.
Let's reset it to let's go with 150.
And then let's say we had another variable like bonus, which we call multiplier.
That's kind of long.
How about bonus mult instead of multiplier?
And this will be three.
So if we wanted to multiply the score by three or by whatever this multiplier is, you get a star in
the game or something that multiplies your score.
We could do score times equals.
And then I just wanted to show you can use other variable names to do this score times equals bonus
moult.
We now are just saying take score and multiply it by whatever this variable is, which is three and
then save that new value to score.
We also have divide equals or slash equals.
Most of the time you'll see plus and minus, and a lot of the time you just want to increment by one
or decrement by one.
And there's another shortcut and even shorter way of doing that because it's done so commonly.
Often we're doing things where we have a variable, a number.
You need to add one to it, and then later add one more and one more like a counter, for example,
to keep track of certain things, how many times they happen or how many times you want something to
occur.
And let's do an example of that.
Let counter equal zero.
If I wanted to add one to it instead of plus equals one, there's something called a urinary operator.
Urinary operators are operators where there's only one side.
This right here has two sides counter plus three right, the left and the right.
This has one side.
And this is just going to add one plus.
Plus, we'll add one to counter.
So now counter is one and we can do the same thing.
Let's do it one more time or three more times.
Who knows?
So we have counter set to four, if I can spell it, and we can now do the same, but decrements it
counter minus minus will subtract one.
So counter right now is four.
If I do counter minus minus, we end up with three.
Cool.
So I just wanted to show you those.
You'll see them all the time.
Plus equals minus equals star equals.
But then also the urinary operators.
Plus plus and minus minus.