Hey, welcome back.
Now that we've seen step one of this process where we select elements, we saw a bunch of different
methods that we can use to select elements once we have them.
Once we have selected them, we usually want to do something with them instead of just putting them
in variables for no reason or conflict logging them.
Typically we manipulate them in some way.
Manipulation is it's not exactly the best term because sometimes we are manipulating the elements.
We might be changing their styles, we might be inserting a new element inside of them, we might be
removing that element, but other times we're just accessing data.
And that's not I wouldn't call that manipulation.
We're just trying to figure out what is the contents of this div or what number did the user just click
on or what what information is in the form that is more accessing?
And we're also going to cover that in this section.
So manipulation is just the umbrella term.
The unfortunate thing about the DOM is when you're learning it, you take a look at any document or
any element that you select.
There are so many properties, so many methods, as we've already seen a couple of times.
It definitely can be overwhelming, but we're going to narrow it down to some of the most important
methods in properties you need to know.
And these are the ones that nine, more than nine times out of ten probably, I don't know, 48 times
out of 50, I guess I could reduce down.
Let's just say most of the time you end up using these methods.
These are the methods and properties that we use to style elements, to create new elements, to change
attributes, to add a class to an element or remove a class.
There are so many different things that we do this subset of methods and properties.
What do we have?
Like 18, maybe 20?
This subset is the majority of what you'll need to make most projects and to get by using the DOM.
So in this section we're going to just take these piece by piece.
We're going to start in this video by talking about accessing text from an element, how do we get the
contents of an element?
So we're going to focus on this corner here in our text and text content.
All right.
So I'm working with this same dummy web page.
It doesn't matter.
I'm just doing something simple.
But this applies to any any Web page you could open.
We could do it on MDM.
We could do it on Wikipedia.
On Facebook, although I just wouldn't want to show you my Facebook account.
But we could we open up the console or we run code from a script where we select an element.
So why don't we start there?
Let's select this h one.
So how do we select it?
Document dot and we have a bunch of options, but I'm going to do query selector.
There's only 1h1 and I want the first one anyway.
So we'll do this.
We'll save it to a variable const h one and the first property we'll see is called inner text.
So inner text is going to give me the text that is in between the tags right there.
So here's the opening edge one, here's the closing inner text.
Is this right there?
So that's how it behaves on a simple element, like an H one.
But what if we have content nested inside?
Let's see if we have a good example of this.
Scroll down.
We do have this ul if I were to run ul inner text, let's see what we get.
So I'm going to select the UL with my query selector.
On ULL there's only well there's multiple actually.
So we'll just take the first one because all the wells have allies inside and then we'll call this variable
UL.
So if I do ul inter text, here's what we get.
First thing, second thing, third thing.
So this was the UL that we selected.
You can see it highlighted when I type UL and my console and the text that was located inside of it
was nested.
It's not a direct child of the UL.
It's inside of an ally.
So we have carrots, we have peas, we have broccoli.
Or actually we have first thing, second thing and third thing.
They're not directly located in the UL their first inside of an ly, but when we use inner text on an
element, we get all of the text inside of it.
So we could also do this document body, which is a reference to the entire body.
We don't have to do query selector of body, although that should work.
I've never done that before, but I'm sure that does work.
Yeah.
But we have a shortcut which is just document body.
It's a property that's always on the document.
And if I do enter text on that, we get all of the text from my web page.
It doesn't matter how many elements deep it is, if it's buried or nested down, it extracts all the
text.
So this is the text from my web page.
Now reading inner text is great.
That's useful sometimes.
But also we can change elements, we can manipulate the text.
It's just another property on an object.
And if we change it, the browser is going to update to reflect that.
So we have our H one enter text.
If I want to change it, I can change it to how about I'm hungry?
Let's do double quotes.
I'm hungry.
And there we go, it updated.
Now, this change obviously is in the console.
It's not permanent.
If I were to refresh my page, it's gone.
I could add it to a script like I have over here, and then it would run each time and I would see it.
But it's kind of silly to update the inner text of an H one as soon as the page loads.
Why not just update the HTML?
But that's where events come in, where we can update something based off of an event, a user clicking
a hover.
For now, we're just learning the basics of changing elements.
So that's the basics of inner text.
If I were to do something like document, body or any element, let's do the ul ul dot inner text.
Remember that the UL has nested content inside, it has allies and this text is coming from the allies.
If I do ul inner text equals I am a big UL and I hit enter.
All of that stuff is gone.
So what we had originally was this we had a UL with three allies.
When I change inner text, even though the inner text we see is only this, we're not seeing those elements.
When I set inner text on something, it just puts the text right there.
So not a great idea to do that if you're actually trying to preserve the content you had before.
But we can use this when we're trying to update a heading or a caption or if we just know that there's
not content inside that we're going to lose.
Now, there's also a second property we can use to access the inner text or the text content of an element,
and that property is called text content.
So on the surface it seems exactly the same as inner text.
If we select the H one again, I'm going to scroll up, I refresh the page, by the way.
So we lost the change when it said I'm hungry.
But if I look at H one inner text, it's my web page, h one text content, which is the other property
we're about to see.
We get the same thing, so it seems like they both are identical.
I can set text content.
I'll change this to I am not hungry.
And it updates, same as in our text.
But now let's work with this paragraph here.
This paragraph has an idea of main and for some reason it's spaced really oddly.
Some of this stuff is on separate lines.
Let's say that I'm going to leave that I'll indent this here.
I'll add an extra return.
Let's save I'll format it oddly like this.
And I'm also going to add in a script tag.
Not that you really should put a script tag inside of a paragraph, but I'm going to to illustrate something.
I'll put a console.log here.
Hello, everyone.
And save.
So now we have our formatted HTML or our formatted text with some weird returns and indentation, and
then we have a script tag.
Let's refresh the page.
Let's select that paragraph.
Here's our console.log.
Hello, everyone.
So we'll do a document query selector of the ID of main.
We could also do get element by ID save this to a variable.
I'll call it p and let's look at P, enter text.
Okay.
So it's purely the text.
No formatting.
We don't get anything about that script.
It's just the text.
Now if we look at P text content.
Okay.
So it has the same text, but it also has that spacing.
It knows about the returns we had in there.
It knows about this script text.
So it doesn't include the script element or the tags, but the text in there is considered text.
So that's probably not ideal most of the time at least, and we end up getting it all with text content.
So that is a significant difference.
Also, if I had something that was hidden in this paragraph, a good example would be if I added a bold
tag maybe or a span or some other tag.
Let's do a bold tag around some of this content like that.
And then let's say for some reason I decide to do an inline style just to make it easier.
I'll say display none.
So we should not see this phrase here, whatever percentage.
Mm.
Autumn, autumn.
If I refresh, it's gone.
We don't see it showing up here.
But if I run those same lines, I select P, I look at inner text.
It's not here.
Now if I did the same thing with text content.
It's right here presented atom.
Same thing with our console.log.
So inner text is going to be aware of what is actually showing up on the page.
For example, our script text does not show up.
Nobody sees this in the browser window unless they open up the inspector or the dev tools versus with
text content.
It doesn't care at all.
It just gives us the inner text of that element from the actual HTML file.
It goes into this element and it just takes all the text, all the text it can find.
It cuts out those tags, cuts out the B tag, cuts out this.
And we get the text, including the script text.
So I almost always use inner text.
It's good to know though, that text content is faster.
Another one of those situations where it really doesn't matter.
But you know, I feel like I should say it.
It's such a tiny difference.
Most of the time it would be imperceptible, but the reason it's faster is because it doesn't have to
do any of this stuff where it calculates what's actually showing what's on the screen right now.
It just gives you everything.
It vomits it out.
So that's inner text and text content.
You can use both of them to access the text, but there are some differences, as we saw, and you can
use either to update the text within an element.
You just have to be careful.
If there's other stuff in there and you update it using either one, you're going to overwrite what
was there before.
All right.
So those are two new properties.
Enter text and text content.