Next up, we have another property that is kind of similar to inner text and text content.
It's called inner HTML, but it has a different name, obviously, and it has a different purpose.
So inner HTML is going to return or retrieve not only the text inside of an element, but also all other
tags inside of a given element.
So if I were to call form, if I select this form inner HTML, I would get all of these elements.
If I were to do form, enter text.
There is no inner text here, so let's try it out.
I'll select the form, I'll do a query selector document query selector of form.
There's only one form.
I'll get the first one, I'll save it to a variable called form and then form dot inner HTML.
All caps on the HTML portion.
Let's see what I get here.
I'm getting a string that contains all of the elements inside, so I get everything between those two
tags.
It could be text, it could be other tags.
It all just gets grouped into inner HTML.
If I were to try it on one more thing.
Let's select the first UL we find.
I'll do document query selector.
You will save that to a variable.
Just give it the name of UL.
Not very creative.
I do.
Ul inner text.
We saw this in the last video we get.
First thing, second thing, third thing.
And that's because that's the inner text.
It's skipping the actual tags.
Now if I do ul inner html, I get all of the content in there.
The li and the text.
The Li.
The text.
Li and the text.
All the attributes are there.
Everything that I wrote in the HTML is showing up and I can use inner html to update the insides of
an element the the insides to change the content in between the two tags if I wanted to.
So for the form which is right here, I could do this form in html equals and then just pass it in some
text if I wanted to.
And that entire form now only contains this text.
If I go to the Elements tab and I look at the form, that's it.
Everything that was there before is gone.
I kind of destroyed it, which is usually not what you want to do, but sometimes maybe it is.
And if we were just setting text, then I would probably use in text.
But we can also add HTML elements in.
The annoying part is that we have to make them a string inner text, inner HTML, text, content.
They all return strings.
So no objects are involved here except for the object that we're actually selecting.
I have my form.
That's an object, of course.
But if I do enter HTML again and I want to set it to contain some other element, I can pass in a string
and write HTML in there.
So this is fine for simple elements, but if you're doing something more complex, it can be kind of
annoying to type it all as a giant string.
And we'll see another way of adding elements later on in the same section.
But just to show that it works, let's do HTML equals.
What could we add inside the form?
How about a bold tag?
I am a bold tag.
Close it correctly.
We'll hit enter.
Now we have a bold tag in there.
So in our HTML allows us to pass in a string containing text containing HTML elements.
And what it will do is actually parse this string and look for those tags.
It's going through it and figuring out, okay, what is an element here?
What is just text?
And then it reflects those changes in the DOM.
And now if we look at form.
This is getting a bit ahead of ourselves.
But if we do a console that dear of form and if we look at its children, it has a new object.
As a child, it has a B object.
It's an element.
So it's not just about setting the text and the browser, just inserting that in between the the tags.
It's actually reading this and creating a bold object, a bold tag object, and that's what we see here.
So it does take more time because of that compared to inner text, if you're just setting text, but
if you need to add elements, you can do it this way.
But as I mentioned, it gets obnoxious, especially if you have attributes with quotation marks and
you've got to mix and match your quotes.
Now with template literal strings, it's not too bad, but still there are other ways of adding elements.
We're just not there yet.
Now the last thing about HTML versus inner text, let's select the H one.
So document query selector, I'm just going to stick to query selector for most of this because it's
our Swiss Army knife.
It's so versatile.
We'll save it to a variable called H one.
I now have h one.
We'll look at inner text, we'll look at inner HTML.
Great.
If I wanted to add something in to my web page, the first thing I'll show you that we haven't seen.
You can do this.
You can do plus equals.
If you don't want to completely override what's there, you want to keep my web page and for some reason
I also want to add is cool.
I'll put a space there because this string will just be added into what is already there.
And now we have my web page is cool.
Probably not that often that you would do it, but you can.
But what I want to show you here is that there is a difference between inner HTML and inner text when
you are setting them, when we retrieve them.
We've already seen the difference in our text does not give you the tags in or HTML does when you set
them.
It seems like you could use either.
If I want to add an element into this HTML tag or into this h one tag, let's say I want to I don't
know, plus equals a bold tag with a bunch of exclamation points.
I could do h one point in or html plus equals and then I'll write my bold tag and then some exclamation
points like that.
Close my quotes.
And those are I guess it's kind of hard to tell, but those are bolded.
They're part of a heading, but we can trust that they're bolded.
If we take a look at the H one, they are inside of a bold tag.
Now, if I instead do this with inner text.
I'll just add more exclamation points.
Sure.
What do you think is going to happen?
That's what happens.
So it doesn't ignore the tags, it just doesn't treat them as actual elements or tags for HTML.
It doesn't parse them.
It doesn't understand that they are bold tags.
Instead, it just takes this entire string and puts it in the element.
So we end up with the string of a bold tag.
So if you are trying to update HTML, you're trying to add an element with HTML, you need to use HTML
with inner text.
You can't actually create new elements.
You can't tell the browser.
I want to insert a bold tag or an image.
It will just insert the text that you pass in the literal string.
All right, so that's in our HTML.
Like I said, there are other ways of creating elements, so maybe not all that commonly used once you
see the other options, but it's important to cover already.