Next up, we'll talk about a couple of different properties that I'm just grouping together, their
properties that we can directly access on individual elements.
So let's start with a simple example.
When we have a form, if we want to retrieve the text in a form input or the values from a form, we
have an attribute on those elements called value.
So if I go to my form here, I have a couple of different inputs.
I'm also going to add an input with type equal to checkbox and let's do another input with type set
to range and we'll give it a min of 100 and a max of 500.
So we have a couple of different inputs.
We'll save.
Now let's select one of them or all of them.
Why don't we do all of them?
Sure.
So we'll do a refresh of the page first and then document query selector all this time.
Or we could have done get elements by tag name, but I'm going to do query selector all input and save
that to a variable const inputs.
And let's take a look at one of these inputs.
So I'll just print the whole thing out or return the value and open one up.
If we scroll down, there is a property down under V called Value and it's currently empty.
But if I fill in a bear name like Taco of the Bear and we do the same thing again, I'll have to rerun
this.
I'll look at inputs one more time.
Or actually, let's just do inputs zero dot value.
You'll see it's now Taco.
So value is how I can get the value out of this form.
Same thing with a password input.
If I do inputs of one value, yes, I do have access to that text in the password input.
Those dots are not there for real security purposes.
They're there to hide the password from other people, but it's not there to hide the password from
your code.
It needs to be sent to a in a request, usually to a server somewhere.
So that value has to remain.
So we have input one value.
We got the password value out of there.
Now what about a checkbox?
If I do inputs of two value, we get on and if I check it.
It's still on.
What's going on here?
So let's look at inputs of two.
How annoying.
If I specifically call one out, it does the HTML representation.
If I look at all inputs and I go to the index of two and we scroll down, you'll see we have a different
property called Checked.
So this is a different property we can use for checkboxes specifically.
So we get checked as false.
So I'll close that back up and we can do inputs to dot checked.
So this video is, like I said, kind of just a group of attributes that we can access.
So these are HTML attributes because I can change a value from HTML if I want there to be a value in
the form when it loads, I could say value equals what would be a good name for a bear?
Taco the bear, griz the bear.
How about just Buck Bubba?
I'll refresh the page and that value is in there.
And if I re select the inputs and I look at inputs of zero, not 90. value, it's set to Bubba and I
can change it to and this is a common thing we actually do not usually to change the input to be something
else like plus equals Bubba the bear probably wouldn't do something like this with code and change someone's
input, although it's possible.
Maybe you're doing some sort of fancy input where as a user types you're adding spacing in or you're
validating it.
I don't know.
But usually the way that we change the input value is to reset it to an empty string.
So if the user submitted the form and we captured the information with JavaScript by extracting the
values and then we do something with it, which we haven't talked about yet, and events and all this
stuff to come.
Then afterwards we might reset it to an empty string so it goes back to an empty input.
Think of a search bar.
You go into Reddit or something or I don't know if some website that has a single page search, if you
type something in, you hit enter, you see some new stuff load and your search bar usually empties
out.
Not all searches do that anyway.
Sometimes we can reset the input if we want to by setting its value to an empty string.
If we go back to this checkbox again, we saw that if we check it and we do inputs of two dot value.
It doesn't change.
But if we do inputs of two checked, we now get true.
If I uncheck it, we get false.
So that's how we can use JavaScript to read out the value from text inputs, password inputs, or read
out the checked state of a checkbox.
What about this slider?
This range goes from 100 to 500, I think.
And if we do inputs of three value, it's giving us 130.
If I go up, it's 437 right now, it's set so that the step of the range is one, I believe the default.
But if we give it a step of 50.
And refresh, run our code again, just select all the inputs and then we take a look at inputs.
Three point value.
It's 300 and I'm now stepping by 50 at a time.
So we do it one more time.
It's now 450.
Okay, so that is value and checked.
There's one other attribute that we have direct access to on each element, on each input element at
least, which is placeholder.
I can change placeholder text really not that common, but right now the placeholder of this password
input says password.
If I select that input which is in my list of inputs from query selector all it has index of nope index
of one.
If I do placeholder, I can retrieve the current placeholder text or I could change it to something
else.
Placeholder equals please enter password and there's my placeholder text.
It's been updated.
All right, so that's how we can work with inputs.
We also have a couple of other attributes that we can directly access off of elements.
Let's add an anchor tag in somewhere in my HTML.
It doesn't really matter where I'll put an anchor tag and give it an h ref of cars.com slash cute and
then some text in here.
Cats are adorable sometimes.
Refresh my page, let's select that anchor tag.
So I'll do a query selector of a need to add my document query selector.
Save that to a variable, call it a and let's look at a dot h ref.
There we go.
Notice.
Well, this is my fault.
I did a relative link.
I didn't actually add in w w w dot and a protocol.
So we end up with the file protocol because that's where I am viewing this file from.
But if instead I add in h to http colon slash slash WW cats dot com slash cute.
Run it again.
Select it.
Here we go.
Now it's a link to a website that may or may not exist.
I'm probably not going to click it and I can also change the link if I wanted to, to now be a http
colon, slash, slash, w-w-what google.com?
And if we look at that element, I'll just inspect it.
Where are you?
All the way down here.
We change that h ref and now goes to google.
And if I clicked it, it would take me to google.com, assuming I didn't misspell anything.
So that's another html attribute we have access to.
If you're not familiar with the term attribute, by the way, it's these things here where we have some
word equals something in quotes.
Usually it follows that pattern.
Class is an attribute.
ID is an attribute, source is an attribute alt on an image as an attribute.
And for some of these attributes, we have this access like directly on the object for value on an input
as we saw for h ref and on images we can access the source.
So if I wanted to change this image source to something else, let me get a new image.
I'll be right back.
I have a URL on my clipboard now and if I want to select this image and change it, I can easily change
the source.
There's a source attribute, so we'll select the image with good old document query selector of image.
That's the type of tag we want.
There's only one on the page, so we'll get the one and only one.
Save it to a variable.
And let's take a look at image source.
There's the URL that the image is currently displaying.
If I update it to this URL I have on my clipboard, there we go.
New image of a very cute little cat under a blanket.
So that's that's kind of it.
We have these different attributes that we can access directly through the DOM.
We'll see in the next video that we have some attributes that we can access that way and we have a different
mechanism or a different way of changing them and reading them in.
So that's coming up next.