Next up, we'll see two methods not properties, but methods called get attribute and set attribute.
And these methods do exactly what they sound like.
They allow us to access or change the value of attributes on elements.
So we've seen a couple shorthand or shortcut ways to access attributes.
Some special cases like value or placeholder or source or ref that are commonly used have their own
shortcut property, but there are other attributes that don't.
So we have these methods get attribute and set attribute, for example, on this range input right here,
if I select it const, I'll select using a query selector.
So I'll do const range equals, document dot, query selector.
And I don't want to just do input, I'm going to do input and then attribute type equals after use the
right quotes in here type equals range and I'll expand it a bit.
So give me the first input where it has the type attribute set to range and we have that range.
And if we look at it, where are you?
Right here.
We have a bunch of attributes.
We have the type attribute, we have men, we have Macs, we have step.
So if I want to know what the max value is for this range, I could do range dot and then the get attribute
method which takes the name of an attribute as a string and I'll type max and I get 500.
If I do min, I get 100.
I could also view the type attribute and get range.
So that's get attribute.
It's simple.
You pass it in the attribute you're looking for on the element that you're calling it on and it gives
you the value, assuming it has that attribute.
If I try and find an attribute that's not in there like lol, it just gives me null.
Now we can also use set attribute.
So range set attribute takes two arguments.
The thing we're trying to set, so I'll do min and then the value I want to give it.
Let's say the men is -500.
Okay.
Now, if we look in our HTML or in the Elements tab and we inspect that input, we should see that now
min is -500.
And if we play around with the range, let's go all the way down here and take a look at range value,
which we just saw.
It's now -350.
So we are successfully setting that attribute.
It's one that we don't really have a shortcut for.
We have a shortcut for value.
We had one for source on an image and a ref on an anchor tag.
But there are plenty of attributes you may need to change where you need to use set attribute.
So that's a couple of examples.
We also could change the entire type of the input.
I could do range, dot, set attribute and then do type, and then we could turn it into a radio button.
Sure.
Type equals radio.
And now we have a radio button there.
So we completely change the type of the input.
The variable is still called range, but it's no longer an actual range input.
So that's get attribute and set attribute.
There are plenty of other attributes we could use with this.
Most of the common ones have those short hands that we saw.
But if there's ever something you need to change, I mean, technically you could use set attribute
to change an ID.
So if there's ever an attribute that you need to update or that you need to access, these are your
go to methods get and set attribute relatively straightforward.