Next up, we'll see a group of properties that I'm struggling to come up with a name for.
They're all kind of, I guess you could say traversal or neighbor properties.
It's a way of accessing the parent or the children or the nearest sibling of a given element.
So it's this group right here, parent element, children, next sibling, previous sibling, they allow
you to access other elements based off of the current element that you're working with.
So this is actually surprisingly common.
You don't do it all the time, but there are situations where, especially when we get to events, when
a user might click somewhere and based off of that click, you'll have an element selected and you want
to then select some other element based off of this element.
If I was making a much a good example here, let's say I was making a checklist and I had checkboxes
in here, the click would occur on the checkbox and if I wanted to delete this entire lie, I would
need to access the parent of the checkbox.
Or if I wanted it.
For some reason I wanted to delete this entire form.
When I click on Submit, I would need to select from that button.
I would need to access the parent or there's plenty of other things we could do where we're accessing
the next sibling.
So these would be siblings here, so I'll just show you how they work.
Let's take a look at any given element.
Let's select something that has some siblings and some parents.
Let's go for this lie, the very first lie on the page.
So document dot or good friend query selector lie and save that to a variable.
We'll call it first lie.
Okay, so we have first lie and from there if we just inspect it console dear first lie you'll see that
we have some properties.
The first of which we'll see is called Parent Element Elm.
A.P. Here we go.
Parent Element is referencing a UL that parent you will we selected this lie right here.
The parent is that UL.
So this is a connection pointing upwards.
This is how we can find the parent from a given element.
I don't know why I just closed that.
I meant to just hide this, okay?
So I could access it by like parent.
I still have ally or it's called first lie isn't it.
First line dot parent elements and I get that ul and if I hover you can see the dev tools displays the
entire UL for me I also could do first like parent element dot parent element again.
And what do you think will see the parent of that UL is the body.
How about one more time?
But if I chain it on again, this time we get XHTML.
So we went from this li what was its parent this ul what is this ul nested inside of well, its parent
is the entire body and this body is nested inside of the HTML.
And if we tried one more time, we get nothing.
No, there is no parent of the HTML element.
Okay, so that's parent element.
You can use that to work backwards.
Back up the tree, find out a parent from a given element.
We also have the opposite.
We have children.
So instead of using the lie because our ally doesn't really have any children, as you can see here,
it's just text in there which actually will come back to in a moment.
We'll go select.
Hmm.
How about we select the UL?
I guess it's kind of boring, but we'll select the UL.
So const ul equals document dot query selector of ul.
We'll take the first one.
Okay.
So we have our UL right there.
I also could have just done first ll parent, but we have our UL.
I'll clear my console if I access UL children.
This is another array like object similar to what we get back from our selection methods and it contains
the children elements of this.
UL so here's the first one there in order of appearance in the DOM so li with the class of special,
then just a plain ly and another ly with the class of special.
So this is a way of accessing children, going the opposite direction, finding things that are nested
inside of a given element instead of what the given element is nested inside of.
So our allies don't really have children, but we could access one of them if we did.
UL children, if I want the first child I could do of zero and now I'm working with that lie and I could
do something to it, right?
I could access inner text.
Sure.
And we get first thing.
Now we also have a couple of different options we have next and previous siblings.
So what if we select the ally that we have?
It's called first lie right there.
The very first lie that.
Was from earlier.
We selected it before the UL if I accessed first like next.
Element sibling, we get the next sibling, which is second thing.
If I did one more next element sibling, we get this lie down here.
So siblings are on the same level.
They share a parent.
We also have previous sibling.
So if I were to save this to a variable, we'll call this concept third lie.
So third lie is this lie right here.
So you can see when I hover, I could go the other way.
Third, like previous element, sibling gives me this lie the one before it.
So now we have a way of not only doing parent to get the parent element.
We have children to get any children.
We have next element sibling and previous element sibling.
And with those different properties, we can access whatever we need from a given element.
We could work upwards, find multiple siblings away, we could find children, find parents.
Usually we don't need to do anything crazy because if we wanted to find within children, if we needed
to find something and there was hundreds of children, as we've already seen, we can actually call
query selector on an element instead of on the document.
So you can continue to search within something.
But if you just need the parent or the first child or the next sibling, you can use these nice properties.