We'll take a quick break from learning new properties and methods just to talk about how we can use
what we've already learned on multiple elements.
Everything we've been doing so far is one thing at a time.
We've been changing the inner HTML or the value of one input or one diff or whatever it is at a time.
But often we want to effect changes in multiple elements and we know how to select multiple elements.
We use query selector all, get elements by class name, get elements by tag name that gives us an array
like object.
So all we need to do is iterate over that object and then call whatever method or change whatever property
we want.
So why don't we start by changing the inner text of all allies on the page?
So we need to select all the allies, and I'm going to do this in a separate file because it takes a
couple of lines.
So I have a script as I've included it at the bottom of my HTML file and I'm going to select all the
lists.
So I need my document query selector all I want.
Liz So I'll pass in the string ally and then I'll save that to a variable.
But to go with const all Liz all these.
Okay, now we want to iterate over all else.
So for we could do a regular for loop for let i equals zero I less than all allies length I plus plus
and then we can access all allies of zero.
And we could start by just constantly logging all our lies of zero dot let's do in our text.
Okay.
Let's see what we get when I run this.
So I'll refresh the page.
Hmm.
No idea why I did zero.
It's supposed to be all allies of I.
Whatever that loop iteration is, we'll access that one and get the inner text.
And if we run it, there we go.
First thing.
Second thing.
Third thing.
Carrots, peas, broccoli.
So if I want to change them all, I can just set their inner text.
All allies of I dot inner text equals.
And then this is the hardest part always.
How about we are the champions?
I don't know why, but we'll just do it.
Okay.
What happens when I refresh the page?
Every single line now has been updated.
So this is the common pattern.
We select a group of things and we iterate over that array like object using a for loop.
Or we could easily do a for of loop, which I prefer for let ally of all allies.
We will.
What should we do?
How about ally dot in our HTML this time and let's pass in a string and we'll say we are.
And then a bold tag, the champions.
So now we're setting in HTML, which means that this will be treated as HTML.
It will be parsed and turned into an actual bold element on the page.
Let's see if it works.
There we go.
We are the champions on every single ally.
So we're overwriting the changes we did here.
But this also worked.
It's just annoying to have to deal with AI.
So why not use a four of loop so we can do things like this?
Obviously we can change styles once we see how to change styles, which we will see very shortly.
We can access attributes, we can set attributes, we could do all sorts of things, but the pattern
is the same.
You select and then loop and then do something versus what we've seen so far where we select one thing
and manipulate it directly without having to loop.
If you have multiple, you have to loop.
There's no easy shortcut to just impact all of them at once.
All right.
So that's it for this video.
Next, we'll move on to some other properties and methods.