Next up, a really important topic changing styles using JavaScript so we could select one element or
20 elements and potentially change their color, their background color, their font size.
We could hide them.
How do we do that?
How do we manipulate CSS properties using JavaScript and the DOM?
Well, there's a couple of ways I'm going to show you one in this video.
It's called the style property.
So every element that we select has a style property.
So why don't we select one?
How about this?
H one const h one equals document query selector.
H one.
In my CSS file that I have here, I've given all h1a color of purple and a font size of 60 pixels.
So if I look at h one dot style, I open this up, we get this massive object, but it looks like everything
is completely empty.
This is not telling me what the color is.
It's not telling me font size if I if I find color on here or I could just type it.
Where are you?
c0lo0, come on, here we go.
Empty string.
Why is that happening?
It seems like this should be a representation of the styles on the element.
But if I do h one style color as we just saw, nothing is there.
So this is the first really important thing to understand about the style property.
We can use the style property to change colors or styles.
We can change any of those properties and they will be affected on the page.
But if we're trying to use the style property to read existing properties, to read existing styles,
it won't work unless those styles are defined in line, which is not really a good idea.
We normally don't add inline styles.
If I go to my H one, I can style it in line.
I could say color is teal.
I don't know why I'm doing quotes again.
There we go.
Color is teal.
This is not normally what we would want to do.
We want to separate our styles from our HTML.
But if I do it this way and I refresh the page now, I select the H one again and I look at H one dot
style dot color.
It's now set to teal.
So the style property only contains styles that you have set inline, which normally will be pretty
much completely empty for every element that you look at.
But we can also change the color or any of these styles here.
Using the DOM using JavaScript I can now make this.
Is there a color called orchid?
Yes, there is a great color name.
We get this change, it actually changes it.
And if we look at what it does on our element, it now has the inline style color is orchid.
If I go select something else, like how about just this paragraph here?
So we'll do const p equals document query selector and then I'll just delete this.
We want the first paragraph.
So if I look at P, it's that paragraph right there.
If I do P dot style dot well let's do color again.
Color on this one will be white.
Okay.
So I have it highlighted so you can see it, but obviously it's not easily visible right now.
So why don't we change the background color and the way we do a background color in CSS is this background
dash color.
Now, this is another very important part of working with styles in the DOM in JavaScript, the property
names are camel cased, so there is no style background dash color.
It doesn't exist.
We'll get oh well I misspelled it, but this does not exist because in JavaScript this is not a valid
identifier.
You can't name a variable or add an object or a property to an object called B dash w that won't work.
Syntax Error.
So that is why all of the style properties in JavaScript are camel cased.
So I could do P style dot background color camel case.
It's set to an empty string because we haven't actually set an inline style.
All of the styles we have are coming from our stylesheet and I don't think we have a background color
anyway, but if I were to set it to black.
Now that change takes effect.
And if we look at the style attribute or the style property, we'll see that every single property name
is camel case if it's more than one word.
So any time you see animation delay or animation direction or anything like that in CSS, those would
be dashes in between kabob, case, animation, dash delay in JavaScript in the DOM, it's all camel
case.
It has to be, otherwise they wouldn't be valid names for properties.
Okay, so again, this is only inline properties that we can read out, but we can set any properties
we want.
But you have to remember that what you're doing is adding a property to the element itself, adding
CSS in line, and there's nothing really wrong with that.
But there's a better approach if you have a bunch of styles that you want to add.
If I wanted to add like ten different styles to one of these elements or to a bunch of elements with
this option using the style property, I have to do it one at a time.
P styled up background color equals black.
P style color equals white p style font size.
You can do that one camel cased equals and how about 40 pixels?
So that's three separate lines.
And if this was something I was doing frequently for some reason, probably not the style specifically,
but on a website we often have groups of styles that we want to apply to different elements and we keep
sort of a similar theme.
We would usually make a class, and that's what we'll get to in just a bit.
There's another alternative for styling.
So this is the style property.
It's useful.
It allows you to update styles one at a time.
Everything's camel case if needed, but it is not a good way to figure out what the current styles are
on an element.
Unless you happen to write all of your styles in line, it's not going to have the values you expect.
So there's another way we can get all of the actual styles, and that's what we'll see in the next video.
What I'll end up with here is just showing how we can use a loop and manipulate styles instead of a
loop as well.
So let's change these styles of all the lies on the page.
I'll come over to my file, my JavaScript file, select all the lies document, query, selector ally.
Actually I want query selector all.
We'll call this content all lies and then we can loop for let lie of all lies.
Why don't we set like style dot color to be some color?
Why don't we make a little array of colors actually?
So we'll do const colors equals and then red, orange, yellow, green, blue and purple.
How many allies do we actually have?
One, two, three, four.
We have six.
All right.
So we have seven colors here.
Yeah, no, six.
Okay.
I'm a moron.
We have six colors that works as long as we have six lives.
So if I want to access one of these colors and use it to change the corresponding ly using a for loop,
a four of loop is actually not going to help me much because I don't have the index.
I want to take the first lie out of the six and set it to be red.
The second lie set it to be orange.
So I would probably use a regular for loop here.
Or why don't we mix it up and use four each instead all at least for each, and then we'll write an
arrow function.
And remember in our arrow function we have two parameters that we can use.
Four for each we have the element and the index.
Why don't we just start by consult logging l and I see what we get.
Okay, so we're getting the lie and then the index here.
Now I can use that index to access the color.
So const color, we'll just call it.
Color equals colors of I.
And that should now give me a color based off of the index of the lie that we're working with.
So we get red, orange, yellow, green, blue and purple.
So I'm using a for reach just to mix it up.
And then in here we'll access the element which I think I'll rename to lie.
It's a better name for that parameter like style color equals this color.
Let's try running it.
There we go.
Red, orange, yellow, green, blue and purple.
So why did those styles win out?
Where if I refresh the page?
Well, I have to comment out this code before they already had a color, some of them based off of a
class.
And a class is relatively specific.
Right.
Why did these styles win out?
When I change the color, there was a conflict.
This is teal and I made it red.
Why did red win?
Remember, this is all inline styles and any time you do inline styles, it is extremely specific.
It's actually added to the element itself as we've seen like we have here, and that is going to win
out.
It's going to beat any class declaration you have for any class styles.
So that's why those styles end up applying.
All right.
So that's the style property.
Every element that we select, we can read existing inline styles, only using the style property,
but we can set any properties or any styles that we want as long as we use the correct camel case when
applicable, and it will actually add an inline style.
So it's not changing our stylesheet in any way.
It's just inserting an inline style declaration into the individual element.
All righty.