In this video, we'll see a different way of accessing style values.
So not to set a value, but to retrieve what the current value is for color or background color or display
position.
With all these different properties, we might want to access on an element we couldn't really do using
these style property.
As we saw.
For example, we take any of these allies, we select them.
I'll just do document query selector ly just to get the first one.
It has that class of special.
If I do style color, it's empty.
And we saw why that happens in the last video.
It happens because the style property only contains the inline styles.
It does not contain any calculated styles, any styles from a stylesheet, anything from a class, which
is what's going on here.
We have a class of special that is turning this little.
So if I want to get that calculated or computed value, we have a method called get computed style and
we pass in an element that we've selected.
So I'm going to have to select this fly and save it to a variable or pass this in to get computed style.
I'll call this Li and then get computed style of LI and I'll save this to a variable and this will return
to me an object called a CSS style declaration.
And if I open it up, what you'll see is a ton of stuff.
Keep scrolling down here.
We have key value pairs for all CSS properties.
Notice there are actual values here.
Most of them are just the default values in your browser.
So the default background color is down here, which is where are you?
Background background color are GBA 0000, which is just nothing.
The default background image is none.
The default background position zero zero.
Then here's one that we applied border one pixel solid teal which is coming from the stylesheet.
Here's the class special border one pixel solid teal.
So you can see that this object that we got from get computed styles, if we scroll all the way back
up, is actually going to contain all of the properties in CSS for a given element, all the possible
properties and all of their current values.
Now when I say current values, they could change.
So if we change something the easy way using the style object, which we could do, like style dot color
now equals pink.
Okay.
Now let's look at that style object that we got.
I'm going to clear my console.
It is not happy with the style object that I had printed out.
So we have our styles here that we got from get computed style.
If we do styles color.
We now have a different color.
This is the color I just said pink.
If I change the light style color is now equal to red.
And we do styles color again.
Now we have the RTB for red 255 red, zero green, zero blue.
So this object now that we got from get computed styles, I'm calling it Styles, will contain all of
the current updated styles.
And computed means that sometimes these styles may come from a stylesheet, sometimes they may come
from JavaScript, but we can also have things like a hover style on my H one.
If I add in a style based off of hover and I give it a color of purple and a font size of 80 pixels
instead of 60 pixels, if I refresh my page, I hover, it grows.
It's not actually turning purple.
Oh, I don't know why it did purple twice, but it doesn't matter because in my index I had a inline
style declaration.
And that's a perfect example of why inline style declarations suck.
They override everything.
So you can write a bunch of styles and they won't work.
So it should be purple now.
And instead of making it purple again when we hover, let's make it orange.
All right, so now I hover.
It goes orange and it gets bigger.
So what I could do to illustrate, get computed styles and the fact that it works on any sort of styles
that would be applied, let's figure out the computed color and font size when I hover.
Now, this is it's kind of tricky because in order to run that code from my console, I have to be typing
over here, although I guess I can move my my cursor over here as I do it.
So let's try it.
Let's select the H one, const H one equals document, query selector h one and then I'll run get computed
styles.
Let's make a variable called comp styles equals and then get computed style of that h one that we just
selected.
Okay.
So let's start by looking at camp styles dot color.
That's the purple color we have.
And if we look at font size, remember we have to use camel case.
It is 60 pixels.
So already this is much better than using the inline style property because we're able to actually get
a value for color and font size versus doing h one style color gives us an empty string.
H One style font size also gives us an empty string.
So now if I type my line, let's do comp styles dot color, but I'm not going to hit enter.
I'm going to hover first and then hit enter.
Take a look.
I hovered and we got a new computed style value and now it goes back to what it was before.
Same thing with font size.
It starts at nope, not that version.
This one starts at 60 pixels and if I run it again but first hover and hit enter.
Now it's 80 pixels, so it's kind of cool.
Computed styles is a great way to figure out what's actually going on on your page.
You can have a whole bunch of styles being applied to one element, but to know what is actually winning,
what is actually showing up in the DOM and taking effect, you can use get computed style.
All right, so that's pretty much it.
Get computed style returns a massive object containing every property that has been calculated in CSS.