Next up, we'll see a much better way to add multiple styles at once.
So if we go back to our code here, I'm going to make a couple of revisions.
I'm going to get rid of this hover style.
It's quite janky and we have all these lies.
Why don't we make a fake to do list?
So I'm going to just add in some content.
We'll do it maybe here before the form.
So I'll add in a UL and a couple of lies and the first thing I'll do is on the UL, I'll add an ID of
how about to dos?
And then I'll have a bunch of lies.
Each one will have a class of to do single to do not to dos, the UL will have to dos as the class and
then we'll just have some basic to dos.
I know it's not very exciting.
Let's go with mow the lawn and then a couple more things.
Maybe milk the cows and what's one more?
Feed the alpacas.
Alpacas.
And then let's also add in a checkbox next to each one of these.
So I think I'm going to make my I'm going to revise this.
I've changed my mind.
I'll fast forward.
I'll show you what I do.
Okay.
So I have three allies, each of the class of to do and I've added a button inside with just an X as
the text.
This is what we get.
Three different buttons, three different allies, and they all have a class of to do so.
Now I'm going to add some basic styles to my to do class I'll select to do and why don't we do font
size slightly increased so maybe 30 pixels.
Let's see how that looks.
Okay.
And I'll give them a color of olive and why don't we just start there?
So I have my three to dos here, each with a button.
Now, if I wanted to add some styles to mimic the crossing off of one of these to dos, I want to turn
it gray.
So change the color.
I want to add a line through effect, which is the text decoration property in case maybe I want to
shrink it down so it takes up less space.
Maybe change the opacity, different things that I could do if I want to do all of those at once to
mimic what happens when you click here or you click on a checkbox which doesn't exist right now with
what we know, it's totally possible we could do a query selector to grab the very first one.
Let's get that first to do, which is inside of the to dos ID and I'll just get extra specific.
We could just do this, but I'm going to get extra fancy so that we select the first to do class inside
of the to dos ID element.
I'll save that to a variable cost to do equals and then I can go to work applying one style at a time
to do style color equals and I'll change it to gray.
So e a let's see, is that working?
Okay, so it is gray now to give it text decoration, it's the same thing.
I just have to pay attention to camel casing and then the property name or the value is line through.
Well, refresh.
Is that working?
Yep.
We get our line through.
And why don't we also change the opacity to do style opacity equals and maybe 50%.
Is that going to work for us?
Okay.
So now it is extra see through.
I also could have just done an Reba color, but this is better because we have three properties and
as you can see, it's three separate lines, one per property.
And imagine we want to apply 20 different properties, radical changes to one of these elements.
This is not very ideal.
It's not good at all.
So what is the solution?
What's the best way of achieving this?
Using a class.
So we define a class in our CSS.
We could call it completed or finished or how about done?
And we'll set color to be gray.
We'll set text decoration to be line through, and we'll set opacity to be 50%.
So now we have this class that the element does not have, but we can selectively apply it.
So I'm going to comment out the individual lines.
And now let's apply that class to apply the class.
We've actually already seen one way of working with the class.
I think I have my to do over here.
Yeah.
So I selected it here.
I'm just accessing it in the console.
We can use get attribute class is an attribute so I can retrieve the current class and I get to do.
I could set attribute.
Like this set attribute class and then give it the class name I want to add or I want to use to set
the class.
And we called it done, right.
Done.
Yep.
So I can do this and it works.
Our styles are applied.
But if we look at what happened and you can see here the font size changed, that to do has lost the
to do class, it has the done class, which is what we wanted, but we completely overrode the to do
class.
So not ideal.
That's the downside of using set attribute.
Set attribute just takes this value here and automatically replaces the current class.
So I could do this to do space done to apply to classes and that works.
But that requires me to hard code in what I'm trying to achieve.
What are the classes?
If I have five different classes on one element and all I want to do is add the done class, this is
not the best approach.
So this brings us to a new property we haven't seen called Class List.
Now class list is an object representation.
It's called a DOM token list.
It kind of looks like an array, but it's not.
And it contains the classes that we have on this element.
And it's not just about containing the classes or allowing us to see them.
It also provides methods so that we can do things.
If we open this up, we have a ADD method, we have a contained method, we've got what else do we have
a toggle method.
That one's really useful and I can call these on the class list.
So let's cover up the left side of the screen and pretend we don't know if the To-Do currently has the
done class or not.
So we can still see it there.
It's gone.
We don't know if it has it or not, and I want to make sure that it does not have it.
I want to remove it.
The easiest way is to do class list, dot remove and then pass in the class name.
And if we scroll up, it's gone.
If I try and remove it again, no problem.
So this is already a nicer improvement using set attribute.
I can't just say remove this one part.
I have to say here is the entire new class string containing all the old classes I want and not containing
done.
But if I do it this way, I can just say get rid of done if it's there.
Or it could go the opposite.
I could do to do list dot add and it will add done.
And if it's there already, it's not going to keep adding it if we look.
It just has one done.
But perhaps the most useful part is the ability to toggle a class.
So if it's there already, then remove it.
If it's not there, add it.
And we have a method called toggle to do just that.
Toggle done.
So it's removed now.
It's added removed.
Added over and over and over.
Pretty good.
So this is useful.
If we were to rewrite this ourselves without class list and that method, it would be kind of annoying.
We would have to access to do that.
Get attribute class and then do maybe dot includes done.
And figure out if that's true or false.
So if it's false, then we want to add in done.
So we would do to do set attributes class and then we would take the current value.
So to do that, get attributes class and then we would add into that done.
This is quite janky.
So we're saying I want to set attribute, I want to set class to be the current value of it, plus the
string done.
And now we look at to do that, get attribute class.
That works.
And then if I wanted to toggle it again, I could do to do get attribute class that includes done now
it's true.
So I would want to remove done and use that attribute.
It's a nightmare to have to do it.
Well, nightmare is maybe an overstatement.
It's not great, but if we use toggle, it's super easy.
We don't have to care if it's there or not.
We just say Toggle it, flip it.
If it's there, remove it.
If it's not there, add it and notice that it does return true or false.
So if the class is currently not applied right now done is not applied.
If I toggle it and it adds it in, it returns true.
If the class is already there and I'm trying to toggle it again, it returns false when it removes that
class.
So to summarize the class list, it's a really, really nice property we have access to because we actually
apply and remove and toggle classes all the time.
We saw the downsides of applying styles one at a time.
It's annoying for one thing to have to type them on different lines.
We have to pay attention to camel casing and also our styles end up all in our JavaScript.
We're writing basically a stylesheet right here versus if we did it this way with a class, we keep
all of our styles together.
We write them one time, we put them in the actual CSS file.
So it has all of our CSS and we just pick a name for the class.
And then from our JavaScript we can selectively apply and remove and toggle that class so we can do
it all in a batch one line right here, and in our case it adds three different styles, but we could
have 100 styles in one class.
So this is generally the better approach to change styles using JavaScript unless you are just changing
one thing, you want to change the color.
It's a one off.
I don't know.
You just want to make something green or you want to change the font size.
You want to hide something one time, then go ahead and use the style property.
But if you're doing multiple styles at once or you plan on reusing this and styling multiple elements
the same way, create a class and add or remove it using the class list property and its methods.