Next up, we'll see how we can create elements from scratch and insert them or add them to the DOM so
we could create an image, give it a source and put it on.
I don't know the beginning of the page or put it inside of a div.
We could create 100 links with different URLs and insert them into the DOM.
So here's how we do it.
The first step is to make an element, and we have a method called create element.
So create element is actually really simple.
It's document, create, not attribute create element.
And you pass an a string of the type of element you would like.
So if we want to make a let's do ah2 element, we pass in H two and that's all we get.
It makes an empty element for us.
But as we've seen many times so far, this is not what it actually looks like.
This is only the HTML representation.
Let's save it to a variable.
We'll call this new H two and then let's do our console deer of new h two.
It's an object.
So we're making a new element of type H two.
And if we take a look at the element itself, we have let's see, we've got a HTML heading element.
That's the type of element it is.
And we have tag name set to H two.
And there's no text content.
There is no inner content or inner HTML, inner text.
They're both empty.
So if we want to put some content in, that's a separate step.
All we've done is make an element.
So we made an empty H two.
Then if we want to add into it, we could do new H two.
So let's just look at new h21 more time.
It's empty.
New age to enter text equals.
What should we put here?
I like animals.
Sure.
Oh, miss.
My quote.
Okay, so now if we look at New H two, here's the representation of it.
I can also continue to manipulate it.
I can add a class if I wanted to.
I would just do new to new h two dot class list is probably the easiest way to add.
And what classes do we even have?
Do we have any good ones we have to.
Do we have special?
Let's use the class of special.
Now we look at h two or nu h two, and that's what we got an h two attribute of class set to special
and the inner text of I like animals.
So how do we get it in the DOM?
How do we get it to show up?
Right now it's completely severed in its own little universe in the womb of the JavaScript console.
How do we get it into the real world, onto the page?
How do we deliver this element?
Okay, enough of that metaphor here.
What we need to do is select an element to append it to.
So we have some methods here.
The first one we'll see is called Append Child.
Where are you?
They put that on here.
There it is.
Append child.
So append child is a method that we call on a parent that we want to append an element into.
So if I wanted to append this H to into let's go to our HTML.
How about we put it in this section here?
I will select the section and then call append child on the section and pass in our new H to.
So we'll select that section document dot query selector of section.
Save that to a variable and then we'll call section append child and we pass it in our new H to.
This is the new element we've already made and we're now connecting it into the DOM by saying append
a child to the section and a child just means anything inside of this section.
We've already seen the children property.
When we append, it will go to the end of the children.
So it will append down here.
We should see it show up after broccoli.
And do we?
There it is.
I like animals.
If we look at our HTML in the elements tab, scroll down.
We have a section, the UL that was already there.
It's now joined by a new sibling this h two.
Let's do a couple more examples.
We also have the ability to make all sorts of different elements, so why don't we try making an image?
So I have an image URL I'll use here from Unsplash.
We'll make our new image.
So const new image equals document.
Dot create element.
And we pass in image.
And if I just do that and I run my code again.
Let's take a look at new image.
Same thing.
Console deer image.
New image.
We can see that.
It's also an object, of course, for making a new element, but it has a different type.
It's an HTML image element, so it behaves differently.
We don't have inner text.
We don't work with inner HTML because an image does not have an opening and closing tag, but it does
have a source.
So let's set the source.
New image source equals and I'll copy this URL I have.
You could put any URL there and now let's append it somewhere.
If we call a pen child again on the section, it will go inside of the section.
If we don't want to append it to the inside of the section, I just want it to go at the end of my body.
I guess it would go after the script, which maybe isn't ideal, but what I could do is use the body
and call a pen child on the body, or I could put it inside the form.
But let's do document, dot, body, dot, append, child, and then we pass in our image.
Documents bodyguard, a child of new image.
It's quite a large image.
Oh, boy.
Very large.
But there it is.
So we could also give it an inline style.
Say new image, dot style.
Dot width equals 200 pixels.
Refresh again.
Much smaller.
Much more manageable.
Maybe even a bit larger.
How about 300?
So this process is really common.
We make a new empty element of some type.
It's always going to start out empty.
And then we fill in the blanks when appropriate.
We fill in inner text if we need to.
We fill in source or ref or classes.
We add an attribute so we can do whatever we want.
So here's one more example.
I have a link for a YouTube video.
Let's make a new anchor tag.
So I'm going to copy my URL just so I can use it and we'll do content.
New link equals document dot create element of an anchor tag.
That's the type.
And then we'll set the inner text.
Not HTML, but inner text.
Let's go with Mr. Bubs video.
So that's the name of the video.
Wrong place for that period.
Mr. Period.
Bob's video click me and then we want to set the source.
Know the age ref sources for an image for a link and anchor tag.
We want h ref.
And then let's append it to the page somewhere.
How about we select the paragraph, maybe the first paragraph, and we'll add it inside the first paragraph.
So content first p equals document dot query selector p tag.
First P dot append child of new link.
Fingers crossed.
There.
We have a new link right here.
It was appended as a child of this existing paragraph.
If we click it, by the way, it does open up our YouTube video.
So that's the basics of creating elements.
You can create them of any different type.
You can fill them with content, enter text.
You can even use inner HTML if you wanted to.
You could even append other elements into each element so we could create an anchor tag and then create
a new empty span or a bold tag and append that to the new link and then take that in, append it to
first paragraph.
So we're not done with creating elements.
We'll actually get a little more practice.
We're going to build a little example, something slightly more complex.
And I'm also going to show you a few more methods where instead of appending at the end of something,
what if you want to insert at the beginning the first child of an element instead of the last?
So that's coming up next.
Oh, and if you've never seen this video, oh, Mr. Bubbs is quite the character here.
He's a very special dog.
He does not like not like love and attention or he has an odd way of showing it, but this is my favourite.
Okay, here we go.
Yeah, I got you.
I got this on camera anyway.
All right, back to Dom stuff.