Next up, we'll see a few other methods we can use to add new elements to the DOM.
We've seen a Penn child so far.
We'll see other options.
And we'll also talk about removing elements.
How do we delete something from the DOM as we saw in the very last video?
Append child takes a new element, but it's a method that we call on a parent.
So to add a new ally to this list, I need to select the list so I could do document query selector.
Take the first.
I think it's a UL query selector of UL.
I'll call this parent UL.
So I have that parent.
Well, I'll make a new lie concept.
New lie equals document create element of lie.
And then I will set its inner text just to be something like I am a new lie.
So we have that.
Now I need to make sure my quotes match.
When I do a pen child, it becomes the last element, the last child of the parent.
So parent ul append child of new ly.
That's what we get and that is useful sometimes.
You do want to append at the end the last child of an element.
But what if we wanted to put it at the beginning, make a new top to do?
Maybe these are ordered by priority or, you know, due date or something like that.
And I want my new to do to go up here or what if I want it to go in the middle?
We have a different method called insert before now insert before.
Sounds like the way that it would work is that we select a node and call insert before on it.
So if I wanted to insert before this ally, you might think I select that ly and then I call first ly
insert before new ly.
But that's not how it works.
We actually still have to select the parent and we have to select the element we want to insert before.
It's kind of annoying, not not knowing enough that you shouldn't use it, but it's just kind of cumbersome.
So if I want to make this ally that I have down here, I want it to go up top above, mow the lawn.
I need to first select mow the lawn so I'll make a variable called first ly equals document.
And what's the best way to select it?
I think it's the very first ly on the entire page.
Let me just double check over here.
We've got.
Yeah.
Or it's the first to do on the page.
We could do it that way.
If you want to get more specific the first ly with the class of to do and if we look at it there it
is.
So I have all the pieces I need.
I have my new ally that I've made right now.
It's down here, but I still have a reference to that.
So if I move it, it will move from down here.
Then we also have the first ly I want to insert before and I have the parent you will.
So here is how I would insert my ly at the top of the ul i call parent ul.
Dot and then insert before.
And then the annoying part is we have to say the new thing, we want to insert new lie and where I want
to insert it, where I want to insert it before I want to insert it before the first lie.
Okay.
So the way it structured again, we have to have the parent of what we're trying to insert into and
then we also have to select what we want to insert before and then what we are actually inserting.
And there we go.
It's now inserted as a child of parent.
Well, but it's also before first lie and if I wanted to move it right above feed the alpacas, I need
to select that one.
So I'll call that last ul Konst.
The last you will equals document query selector.
I'm going to do selector all of lie with the class of to do and then take the index of two, which is
the third 101.
Nope, it's the third one or it's a fourth one index of three because we inserted this so that should
give me.
No that did not give it to me.
Let's see last Uhl.
Actually, I was wrong here.
Index of three is only going to work if I actually had four elements with the class of two.
Do I forgot that this one up top does not have to do so.
We'll get rid of that and change it to index of two.
But I've already declared this variable, so I'm going to call this last to do.
So now I can insert I'll do parent ul dot insert before and then I want to insert the new ly before
the last to do.
And there we go.
It now is right before the last two do feed the alpacas.
We also have a completely different method that we could use called insert adjacent element.
And this one's a bit more complicated.
We passed in an element.
We have to have a target element, but then we also pass in a position and this is a string which might
seem odd, but we have four choices before begin, after begin, before end and after end.
So if you imagine that this is our target, we have a paragraph.
If we want to insert something before this paragraph, we would pass in before begin.
If we want to insert it after we use after end and then if we want to insert it as the first child of
the paragraph after begin and before end will be the last child.
So let's try this just one or two times.
We can use the same lie, I guess.
Or actually let's make a new element and we'll just be a bold tag.
Or how about an eye tag?
Document creates element of eye.
And we'll call this eye tag or I whatever.
It's not a great name, but that's fine.
And then we'll do I enter text equals I am italics.
So we have our eye tag.
Now let's select one of these elements.
How about the very first paragraph on our page?
So that will be document query selector p.
Save that to const first p.
Now I can call first p insert adjacent element and then I have to specify where.
So if I do before I begin.
And this method, I think, is kind of unpopular, mainly because you have to remember these strings
and a lot of the time you just want to insert something as the last child anyway, so you can use a
pen child and shortly I'll show you two other methods append and pretend.
But here we can pass in before begin and then our new AI element.
And if we take a look, it was inserted before the paragraph began.
So that's a way of inserting something before the paragraph.
And I personally think this is nicer, even if you have to remember before begin, it's better than
what we did earlier when we had to select the parent, insert before the target, and then the new element.
Let's try the same line, but we'll do after end.
Now it goes after the paragraph, after the paragraph ends.
And if we do after begin.
It goes into the paragraph element itself.
After the opening tag, the beginning tag.
It goes right there.
And then we have the final option before end, which we'll put it right here before the end of the paragraph.
One more time.
Before end.
For end.
And there it is.
So another option for inserting.
I did mention there are two other methods we can talk about called append and present.
These are newer.
They do not work in Internet Explorer, of course, and they're just a little bit simpler than append
child.
And also there is no pre pen child.
So Append is different from a pen child in that we can actually insert multiple elements at once.
So if I have this paragraph tag, let's see.
I have my eye still and I have my new ally, right?
Nope.
What do I.
New ly all caps or l capital i capital.
So we have two elements.
If I want to insert both of them into this paragraph, which we shouldn't really just put an ly in a
paragraph.
But if I wanted to I could use append.
So it looks like this.
The first paragraph that we already selected append and then we can pass in AI and new ly.
And now both of them have been appended inside that paragraph.
The italics tag was already there, so it kind of looks like nothing happened.
But it did happen, I promise.
And we also have pre penned, which is the same idea, except it will make things a first child.
So it still will be a child of the paragraph, but it will go to the beginning of the paragraph.
And there we go.
If we look, we've got am italics.
I am a new ly.
They're still inside the paragraph, but they are at the very beginning.
So append and pretend are nice.
They're short.
You don't have to do a pen child.
I mean, you just save a couple of letters, but with a pen child you cannot insert multiple.
If I did a pen child here, it's not going to be happy with me.
We get the one element inserted.
I am italics, but the ly was never added.
It just stayed where it was.
So append is cool because you can do that but it does not work in i e neither does pre penned woof.
So many different ways of adding elements.
Stick with the couple.
You don't have to master all of them.
A pen child is usually good enough.
If you have multiple you can do append.
Maybe you can do insert adjacent element.
You just have to remember the syntax you've got pre penned.
Next I'll show you some ways of removing elements.