All right, if you're still with me.
Thank you.
Congratulations.
We've covered a lot of methods.
We have two more methods in this video, and that's it for new stuff in this section.
We'll then do a quick little project where we get practice creating elements, removing elements, inserting
changing classes and styles and all of that stuff.
And then we'll move on to a new section on events in the DOM.
Now, events are really the main course of Dom stuff of these DOM sections.
Events are probably the most exciting, but also the missing piece that we need in order to actually
make useful applications and start to interact with our websites.
So two more methods and then a project, then events.
So the two methods are remove and remove child and they do what they sound like.
They remove and remove an element that you pass in.
They follow the pattern that we saw with Append Child where this was the the original way of doing it,
the older way of appending something as a child and it's supported in all browsers.
But there's a newer method append that does not work in Internet Explorer.
It's a little friendlier to use and you can pass in multiple elements.
Remove is similar.
So we have removed child which has been around much longer and then we have remove which does not work
in AII.
And if you go to the docs for remove child, it's actually mildly confusing.
On MDM, you scroll down to look at browser support compatibility unknown for E.
So I had a feeling this was a mistake.
Something is just wrong with with the data they have.
So on another website that I like called Can I use if you look at remove child for I it's been supported
in pretty much every version of I that they support on this website.
So I have no idea why MDM has a question mark there, but it is supported in IY.
So to use remove child we need to find the parent of what we're trying to remove and find the item that
we want to remove.
So why don't we remove?
Hmm, let's remove PS right here.
So that element is down at the very bottom.
We need to select that element which is in a UL and it has a class of special.
So we need to select the UL parent and the ally.
Let's get the parent first const UL equals document query selector and we have a couple of Uls on this
page.
What I'm going to do is select the one inside of a section.
Which should give us that one down there.
Let's see you.
Yep.
That one is at the bottom.
It's the only one contained inside of a section.
Now, if I want to get this one ally that has the class of special, I have a couple of options I could
just do document query selector, or I could search within the ul ul query selector for the class of
special.
And this is easy or easier because there's only one element with the class of special in that UL.
But if I instead did document that query selector, we have multiple other special classes or instances
of special on the page.
So it's, it's more work we would have to then say instead of a section, maybe that could get it.
But I like doing this version here where we search within the UL and ignore everything else.
All right, so I'm going to save that to a variable cost.
Remove me.
How about that?
Remove me equals UL query selector special.
So now we have that element.
Remove me and we have the parent ul I can call ul remove child and I want to remove the remove me element.
All right.
So the pattern is the parent and then remove child and then the child.
And this child needs to be a child of the parent.
So I couldn't select this ull and say that you'll remove child of this lie.
It wouldn't work.
Also, when we do remove a child, it does return the removed element so I can save it.
I'll just call it const deleted if you wanted to do something with it.
It's gone now.
Peace is gone.
And if we look at deleted, we do have a variable here that is an object.
It's the actual element that we were working with that we just removed.
It's just printing out as HTML.
Thanks to Chrome's lovely dev tools, which actually are lovely, except I hate this one feature.
And then we also have the remove method which works differently.
It does not need the parent node.
All we need to do is select the target, the thing we want to remove and then call remove on that node
on the actual item we want to remove.
So if I want to remove the H one, for example, I can select it const H one equals document query selector
of h one.
There's only one on the page and I can call h one dot remove.
I don't need the parent.
If I was doing this with remove child, I would have to say document up body dot remove child of h one.
But with remove it's easier.
We don't have to have the parent.
It just doesn't work in IY unfortunately.
H one remove parentheses and it's gone.
That's it.
And that's pretty much it for this video.
We can remove using the remove method that we just saw.
We've got removed.
Child You could do this in a loop, of course, if you had a bunch of things you wanted to remove,
and that's kind of it.
Now we've seen how to create elements, how to append them, pretend them, insert them before things,
insert adjacent to things and remove them.