All right, so let's try building something with what we've learned so far.
We still haven't talked about events and making things interactive, responding to input clicks, drops,
drags, all that stuff.
But we do have the ability to create elements, to manipulate existing elements, and we're going to
take advantage of that.
So I've included a starter file if you want to follow along so you can have the initial state.
What we're going to build is an NBA score table like what we have here, based off of whatever input
data we get, we could imagine it's coming from an API, but I've actually hardcoded some game data
where we have different games.
It's an array, we have an away team and a home team.
Each team has the team name or actually it's the city, not the whole team points and is winner.
And what I want to do is create a table like this dynamically, so not hardcoded in our HTML.
But imagine we had 100 different games or we had 100 different.
There's not 100 teams but a bunch of different teams.
We want to iterate over this data and create a table and we don't know how long it will be.
We don't know which cells or which which rows will be green versus red.
We don't know what the values will be.
So we'll create dynamic elements and append them to the page using the DOM.
So I live in the Bay Area, we'll be doing Warriors games and I have named this array Warriors games,
but this should work with whatever data you pass in and eventually we'll see.
We could connect something like this to an API and get data coming from an API somewhere at NBA Stats
or a Premier League or Laliga or whatever the sports league is.
We can get information and do something with it and make it visual, show something on the DOM.
So what we're going to do to start is ignore the table.
Tables are really annoying in HTML.
They're my least favorite things to create.
I mean, if you inspect the markup here, if you haven't made tables before, you can see just how dense
the stuff is to make a single table.
We've got so many different nested rows and TDs and tears and touches and t bodies and tables and table
headers.
It's just it's a little overwhelming to have to create all of those elements with JavaScript and append
them.
I think it would bog down the important stuff here.
So we're going to start with just a simple list.
Each game will be a list, it will have the score, it will have the home team.
So we'll start by making a simple list, something like this, where we'll have let's do it in our HTML
file, we'll have a ul in ly for each game and the home team will come second.
So the away team, let's say it's a Houston at Golden State, so we want to display it in the order
where we have a way team assign home team.
So that will be dynamic.
We also want to have the score, have the away team score and then the home team.
So let's say Houston won this game 100 to 94.
I want to bold this element here of the winning score.
So 100 beats 94.
So dynamically figure out which team won or which number is higher.
Give it a bold tag.
And if we look at this right now, it's not very impressive.
But then we also want to give a green or red color to this element, depending on which perspective
we're looking at it from.
And like I said, I live in the Bay Area, so we will be looking at this as Warriors fans.
So this element would be red.
It's a loss for Golden State, just like we have here.
So we have green on the games where Golden State won.
But if we went to the table, the corresponding table for the Houston Rockets, it's down here.
We have red for that very same game.
So different perspective, same data.
And we'll start with the perspective of Warriors or the Warriors already.
So I'm going to delete this.
I think I'm going to start by adding in a UL that I can append my data to.
We could also do this dynamically.
Maybe that's a better way of doing it.
Fine, we'll do it from our app.
JS We have our starter data, a simple array with a couple of objects.
Each object represents a game, a way team and home team, and then each of those team objects has team
points and is winner.
So why don't we start with something simple?
Let's get each team to print out or something like that.
As an ally on the page, the first thing I will do is make a new element.
So I'll make the container.
We can call this or maybe just parent ul parent equals document dot create elements of ul.
So that is where we will append a bunch of lies to.
And then what we want to do is iterate over all of these games so we can do that using a four of or
a four loop or four each.
But I'll do four let game of and I called my data warriors games.
No Warrior games, what did I call it, Warriors games.
All right.
So for each game, we want to extract home game or home team and away team.
They all have a home team and in a way, team.
So let's grab that from the object using our favorite D structuring const home team comma away team
equals game.
Game is each individual object or each element in the array called Warriors games and we could start
simple we'll console.log home team dot let's actually let's do a wait team so a way team dot team which
is the name of the team or the city actually or in the case of Golden State, it's not even a city.
There is no as far as I know, there's no Golden State City, a team team and then home team, dot team.
Let's run it.
And in our console.
There we go.
So we have Golden State at Houston, Golden State at Houston twice, and then Houston at Golden State,
Houston at Golden State and then after the first four games.
So this is the standard playoffs as far as I know in the NBA.
You have two games home or away and then you flip for two games and then you alternate.
So that's accurate.
We're printing out the correct way team and home team.
Now let's start by making an ly.
So we want an ly for each game if that's what we're going to do instead of a table, at least to begin
with.
So we'll make our new ly we'll call this game ly equals document dot create element ly.
All right, so we have that done next.
Let's go ahead and show some of this information.
Let's get the first part of the team names showing up.
So I'm going to have Golden State at Houston.
If Houston is the home team, Golden State is the away team.
So I want to take this format away team at home team and add that as the inner text on my ally.
We'll start there.
So game ly inner text equals and I'll do a template literal display the away team team and then at sun.
And then another dollar sign.
Curly braces for home team team.
So that should make me the ally and give me some inner text on the ly.
But nothing will show up because we're not appending it.
And what does it not like?
Line 97.
Oh, obviously not valid JavaScript there, so we won't see anything we need to append each ly to the
UL.
We've made our ul will append to that ul and we have a couple of choices we could do.
Append child.
We could also use the newer append method, but in this loop for each ly game ly I'm going to call ul
parent.
So this is the empty ul I've created.
I'm now appending one ly and then next time through we'll append a second ly and it will have some data
about the away team and the home team.
So ul parent dot append child I'll do a pen child just in case some of you are using internet explorer.
Even though I prefer append and we'll append the game ly now is this enough?
Will we see anything?
No, we will not, because the UL we created is still not associated with the page at all.
It exists in JavaScript.
It's an object.
It has a bunch of children, but we're never actually appending it to the page.
So if I just want it to show up in the body, we could append it to the body.
That's fine.
Or we could present it to the body to make it a little nicer.
I guess that's nothing wrong with that.
Put it above our script so I will select the body, which is easy.
Document dot body.
I don't need to use query selector, although I could query selector of body document body pre append.
If you are in e you can just do a pen child but pre pens ul parent.
Let's see what we get here.
Hey, there we go.
Golden State at Houston.
Houston at Golden State.
Blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
We now have what is this, seven.
Yes, seven lies appended to are ul appended to the body and none of that is there.
When the page loads, we're constructing it from scratch.
All right.
So next, let's work on the scores.
What we want to do is first we can just display the home team and the away team score.
I'll do the same format.
So a Wade team dot points, dash home team points, and I'll start by making it its own string.
So I'll just call this concept score line equals and we want to do this in a string template literal
just to make it easier.
We'll do a way team dot and then we have points.
And then I'll just do the dash and then home team dot points as well.
It's called points.
Yes, it is.
All right.
So we have a string now and we could console.log that string to see the scoreline each time through.
It won't be showing up on the actual page, but here we go.
That looks accurate.
So what we want to do next is get that in the lie as well.
And we have a bunch of different options for how we actually approach this.
I think what will probably be easiest is if we just make two strings and then set the inner text at
once with those two strings.
So I'll make a new variable here and I'll call this one const.
What do we want to call this team names maybe.
And then score line.
And then we can set game ly dot inner text or you could do text content equals.
And then I'll do another string template literal and add in my team names with a space and then again
with the score line.
So instead of doing these together in one line, it's kind of ugly to see all of those string template,
literal brackets and dollar signs.
So I'll break it up into two variables with names and then add those in.
Is it going to work?
All right.
Looks like it's working so we can double check the first game.
Golden State had 119, Houston had 106.
Let's double check up top 119 for Golden State and Houston 106 Golden State was the away team, Houston
was the home team and we were displaying it correctly.
Golden State away at Houston at home.
Next, we have a couple of choices.
Why don't we start by selecting the score that has won the winning score and bolding it?
Which do they do that?
No, they don't even do it.
On Wikipedia.
We're adding in functionality, so we'll show the winning score with a bold tag around it.
So we're going to have to calculate who won, and that part's pretty easy.
We'll just compare the two way team points and home team dot points.
Why don't we start by cleaning this up a tad?
We'll need access to a way team points in home, teams points for a couple different lines because we
need to calculate the winner and then display the points as well and figure out which class to apply.
So I'm going to do structure team and points out of each object.
So out of away team and out of home team.
Now this is kind of annoying because to use the structuring I would do team and points equals home team
and that works fine.
But now I have the exact same thing for away team and that means I'll have team and points and then
I'm creating another variable called team and points so we can use this in text we saw earlier with
D structuring if we want to, where we grab a particular value out of an object and we give it a new
name.
So why don't we call this one home team with an H and H points?
So H team and H points.
And then away team and away points.
Okay.
And then we'll use that instead of a way.
Team, team, we'll just do a team h team and then a points.
And age points and nothing should have changed.
If everything went well, we get the exact same output.
But now we have these variables I can re-use instead of having to access a way, team, team, a way,
team at points over and over.
Not a huge change.
And also the way my VTS code is formatting this, it makes it look like a lot more work than it actually
is.
It's only one line really.
So we're going to come down here now and compare the two points.
So we'll have a waypoint greater than home points, or we could do the other way around.
But if a waypoint is greater than home points, then we know that a way team has one, right?
So we'll do an if statement here.
If that's the case and if a waypoint does beat out home points, then what we want to do is on our score
line, we want a bold tag around a points and we can just add that like this, not right here, but
we can do it.
We can wrap a waypoints in a bold tag.
So the simplest way to do this is if a waypoints is greater than home points, we'll take score line
and just put it here on the same line, or we can do it on multiple lines.
It doesn't matter.
And we'll add the bold tag around the first part, the a waypoint right here.
So we'll put our bold tag, the closing bold tag, and then we could have an else.
We'll do the opposite const score line equals and we'll move the bold tag over here around h points.
And that should work.
We'll talk about refactoring this in the next video.
We'll see that we could move this to a function we don't have to declare can't scoreline.
We're not declaring it twice.
Only one of these ever runs, but we don't need to do it this way.
There are other options.
There's one problem with the way I've written this.
See if you can figure it out without running it.
It doesn't have to do with the actual data or the logic.
It has to do with scope.
We're using const and remember that constant but are both block scoped.
So if I define scoreline in here, it's scoped to this block so I can't use it down here.
So to fix that, we can't just say const scoreline like this and not define it and then update it.
And the reason for that is made very clear you cannot initialize a concept or you can't declare a concept
variable without a value const.
Hi, that doesn't work.
But with lit I can.
So that's what we'll do for now until we write this as a separate function.
So we'll say score line just exists.
It doesn't have a value.
Then if a waypoint is greater than home points, this is what scoreline should be, otherwise it should
be this and then we'll append it.
And right now we're doing inner text, which is not really going to work the way we want.
We end up with the tag just being rendered as text.
So we'll do enter html.
Try again.
Aha.
There we go.
So let's verify 119 is greater than 106.
That's correct.
It should be bolded.
127 bolded 126 awesome.
So that's working.
The next step is to add a background color.
So from the Warriors perspective, the first game should be green because the Warriors won, the next
game should be red because the Warriors lost, Houston won, and we'll do that for each one.
So what I'm going to do is create a class and my class I'll have to actually win where I'll set background
color to be.
We could just start with red.
I think I want an GBA color which will be full red, no green, no blue.
But I only want maybe like 0.3 on the Alpha Channel.
So a transparent red and it looks dark here, but it's because the background of my editor is dark.
If we actually saw that color, it's a transparent red.
So on a white background it looks sort of pinkish.
And then I'll duplicate this and make a loss class.
This one will be similar.
Oh why am I doing red for win?
That should be the other way around.
I want zero red.
I want 255 green and zero blue and then loss should be red.
So I have those two classes now.
We just need to decide which one to show which one to apply to the entire lie.
Now, to figure out if the Warriors want a game.
Because I'm doing this from the Warriors perspective, I want the Green Win class to be applied.
If whichever object the Warriors are, whichever one has Golden State rather than the Warriors, Golden
State is what we're looking for.
We'll check if it's winner is true, then we'll apply this class of win.
Otherwise we apply loss.
So to figure out which team is Golden State, we can do it in a sort of clunky way.
It's not that bad, but we'll check just one of the teams.
It doesn't matter.
Home team or away team team and check if it's Golden State.
So let's try it here.
Home team, which we already have that variable team that we extracted or the structured team equals
Golden State and I'll do this as a ternary question mark.
And if that's the case, then the variable we want, I'll call this warriors.
This will be a reference to the Warriors object here.
And we'll go with Warriors Equals Team Golden State.
If that's the case, then the Warriors object should be the home team object.
This entire home team.
Otherwise we'll set it to the away team.
And if I console that Log Warriors right now, we should get the Warriors information each time through,
whether it's away or home.
We should still see.
Golden State.
Great.
So now we've identified Golden State.
We have a reference to it.
Then we can simply access is winner.
So warriors dot is winner is going to be true or false.
Now, if it's true, then we'll apply the class of win.
Whoops.
That should be a question mark.
Otherwise we'll apply the class of loss.
And we could save this to a variable by concept, class, name, and then use that class name.
Or I could do it in a single line.
I want to apply my class to the game Ally.
So game like dot class list dot.
Add this entire expression, the ternary operator.
So we will either add win or loss as a class depending on warriors.
DOT is winner and the moment of truth will refresh.
Hey, check it out.
Okay.
So it seems to be working.
Golden State at Houston, we have Golden State one, so it's green here, Houston one.
So it's red and it's accurate the whole way through.
Notice, Golden State has four total wins out of seven.
Yes, they moved on.
Great job.
Okay, so this code we have right now is kind of gross.
Honestly, I'm not very happy with it.
And that's okay to get something out on the page, get something working.
But I definitely want to refactor this for two reasons.
One, we should break it up into different functions when applicable to make it just clean and easy
to understand.
But also, this is all tied specifically to Golden State right now.
What if I wanted to make a different table with the same data from the perspective of Houston and I
wanted to append it down below, I think it would be best to make our code team agnostic and we could
write a function called generate table or generate score chart or whatever.
This is where you pass an argument in of the team.
We pass Golden State in.
We get this.
If we pass Houston in, we would get the opposite as far as the colors.
So we could try that in the next video, we'll do the refactoring.
We'll make it a little bit nicer.