All right, so let's refactor this relatively ugly code.
And even if we're not making it easier to look at and understand, let's make it more reusable so I
can make two different tables or two different URLs for each team with a different perspective.
Or I could make this work with any data.
It doesn't have to be hard coded for warriors, and I don't want to have to just duplicate this code
to make another table or another UL with a bunch of allies that we're calling a table.
So the first thing I would do is just wrap it in a function.
Let's define a function.
I would probably call it like, hmm, make chart like that and then pass it in the data.
So I'm going to define my function.
I'll go with const make chart equals a function that accepts game data or games and then that will be
an arrow function.
It doesn't have to be, but that's fine.
And I'll start by just putting all of this code inside the function and the way I'll write my function
is I won't have it actually append the chart, it will make the chart, but then I can append it wherever
I want.
By calling it it will return the UL.
Let's get rid of this extra console.log.
So we're making this UL parent at the end will return ul parent and that will contain all of the allies,
all of the data.
And then I can simply append it or pretend at the end.
So I'll make my variable.
I'll call this chart one equals make chart and then document dot body dot pre penned chart one.
So I'm just moving it into a function.
Now, I could call this twice if I wanted to.
Assuming we don't have any errors, it looks like we do.
Data is not defined.
I need to pass in the actual name of this.
It's not called data.
It's called Warriors Games.
And then I do need to update my loop here.
The parameter is called games, so for game of games I don't want a hard code it to be this particular
data structure.
We want it to be whatever is passed in and there we go.
So now I could just make another table easily.
Just duplicate this code.
It will be identical, but I now am able to do it twice.
There we go.
All right.
So we've made our function slightly reusable, but now I want to break it up a little bit.
This is still kind of it's kind of a lot to do in here.
So what I would probably break it into is a function to determine the interior, the inner text, this
stuff right here.
And I'll call that get get content or get get text, get score line maybe equals function.
We'll figure out what it accepts in just a moment.
And I want to call it like this.
If I have my lie that I'm making right here, I want to call game ly dot.
Inner XHTML equals get score line.
And then I'll just pass it in the entire game.
So I'll move this content that is getting the D structuring home team and away way team variables.
This line that is making the team names the away team at home team.
I'll get the scoreline, the point stuff.
All of this right here.
Cut it out and move it over here and we're passing in the entire game.
Where are you?
Right here.
And I'm going to D structure from that.
I'll get the home team and the away team, which is what I did right here.
But I'll just pass the entire game and D structure it here inside of the parameter definition.
We need to make sure we return something.
And what I want to return is this line right here.
We'll walk through it in a moment.
Okay.
So we made this function called get score line.
We pass in the entire game.
It will extract or unpack home team in a way team and then further unpack each team.
A team H points eight points.
It creates the team names string, it creates the scoreline string and it returns both of them combined
into team names, score line into one string and that one string is returned from here.
And I'm setting game like inner HTML game lie represents each lie, each one of these.
So I just wrote a function to generate this for me.
And almost always, whenever we move stuff around and refactor into new functions, I'm sure we'll encounter
something.
Yep.
What is it now?
H team is not defined and the line that is causing me trouble right now is right here.
Warriors equals team will team is gone.
I moved it into this function.
So what I would probably do is to start just comment this logic out.
Let's make sure our last version worked.
Okay.
So we are getting the correct text on the inside of each lie.
Now I'll probably make a function called get winner or winning team or something like that.
The way that I want this to work, I should be able to pass in the team that I'm making the table for.
So Golden State, but I should also be able to do it for Houston instead.
But I'll start with Golden State, so I will accept a parameter called Target Team.
And then I want to check if for each game the winning team was Target team.
So if it was Golden State.
So this stuff that I have here, I'm probably going to move into a new function and I'll call that function.
Let's see, how would I want to call it?
Maybe is winner and then I could pass in game and target team.
Okay.
So that doesn't exist.
We'll define it.
Concept is winner equals game target team.
Aero function or just a regular function, and we'll check in that game.
We will do the same thing we have here.
So I'll just move this single line for now down here.
We'll replace Golden State with Target team and I think I'll structure the same way right here on game.
So we get home team and away team.
We're unpacking those values.
So we're passing one game in and we're passing in the string Golden State, for example.
And all I want to do is find where Golden State is, if it's a way or home and check if they are winner
if is winner is true.
So I have home team away team and target team.
I'll just check if home team dot.
Team equals Target team.
If that's the case, let's make this a variable just called team target and I'm going to return Target.
DOT is winner.
So this line is just to find the correct team, home team or away team.
So I could have done a way team team equals target team and then just set that to a way team.
Either way it works.
I'm just trying to identify Target which object actually has warriors as the team and then I'll return
that object's winner or is winner property.
And then here where I called it is winner.
I can use that now to decide the class and I could put it right here.
Just do it in one line.
We'll see how ugly it is or isn't.
So we'll call is winner for this one game with the target team.
Let's say it's Golden State.
If that returns true, we'll add win.
If it returns false, we'll add loss.
Is it going to work?
We probably have some other bug.
No, it seems like it worked.
So let's try switching it around this time instead of looking for Golden State.
Let's look for Houston.
Hey, it's working.
So we can see.
Houston lost the first one.
They won the second one and so on.
So we've now made this actually reusable and we can have a different target team each time.
So that's kind of all I wanted to do here.
We've got our function make chart.
It has two other functions.
Get scoreline is winner.
It doesn't have them, but it relies on them and we can call make chart multiple times.
It does not append anything itself.
It returns the the chart element that we then append on our own.
I could probably refactor this here.
I'm okay with it, but we could take advantage of is winner and just reuse that function.
There are more ways we could refactor this, but it's already been a significant chunk of time here,
so we're not going to go too crazy on this.
We have lots of projects coming up and you'll talk a lot about refactoring then.
So I think this is good enough.
The one thing I would do as we're displaying this is maybe add a title or two so we can see what's going
on.
Maybe in our index I'll just add two sections.
So the first one will have an H two that says Warriors or how about Golden State Warriors?
And this section will have an ID maybe of GS.
And then we'll have a second section with another age.
To this one will be Houston Rockets and the ID will be I guess I'll just do Houston Rockets GTS and
now I'll append my charts into here and I'll have a heading for them, which will make it a little bit
nicer to see what's what.
So over here I now can select those two elements.
So we'll call this concept Warriors section, maybe GTS section equals document, query selector or
document get element by ID.
Use the hash sign for GTS to get the ID of GTS and then I'll do Houston section equals document dat
query selector.
I don't want all I just want query selector of h.r.
So I have those two sections now I can make my two charts.
So we'll go with Golden State chart and Houston Rocket Chart and I'll change the target team to be Houston.
And then instead of document body pre penned, I'll do GTS section dot append child this chart, the
GTS chart that we made with the perspective of Golden State Warriors and then we'll do the Houston section
dot append child and we'll add in the HR chart and let's see if that works.
So we make two charts, one from each perspective, one looking at it from Golden State's point of view,
we append that to the Golden State section that I added.
Then we do the same thing for the Houston Rockets.
That perspective we pass in Houston and we use that and append that chart that we get back to our Houston
section.
And I added some h twos so that we have some text to look at and we know which chart is which and we're
good to go.
So that's it.
It's a lot of work, but we are dynamically creating these charts here.
They're not tables, it's just lies.
But we've got a couple of elements we're creating.
We've got bold tags, we've got Liz, we're adding classes.
We're changing the inner HTML.
We're using a ton of the stuff we've seen so far.