In the last video we talked about function scope, where if we declare a variable with any keyword,
whether it's lut, const or var within a given function, it is scoped to that function.
We don't have access to it outside that function.
Now we're going to see a different type of scope, which is called block scope, and it doesn't necessarily
have to do with functions, at least not directly.
But I did mention at the beginning of the section we would cover some function adjacent content.
And if you think back to one of the very first videos in the course when I introduced Let and Const
and also VAR, I said we would come back later on.
That's right.
Now to discuss one of the main distinctions between LUT and Const compared to VAR.
So this is it, block scope.
This is a very, very important concept around how variables work in JavaScript.
So let's start with a simple example.
Here's a conditional.
If true, it's always going to run.
Whatever code is in here, let's declare a variable called animal and set it equal to L.
If I console.log animal outside this block, what do you expect?
What will be printed out?
Let's try it.
Nothing we get an error.
Animal is not defined.
So what does this tell us?
It tells us that animal is scoped inside this conditional.
It is scoped to this block of code.
Blocks and JavaScript are denoted by curly braces.
Keep in mind, this is very different than an object literal, which is also curly braces.
This is an object.
This up here is a block.
So same thing.
If we had a while loop, if we had a four loop or a four of those are all blocks.
The code we write between the curly braces.
So this is not a function, but it appears that animal is still scoped to this block.
And if I console.log to animal here, of course it should work.
And it does.
We get eel and then animal is not defined.
So that's how it behaves.
And if I did change this to Const and I rerun it, we get the exact same output.
We have access to animal in the curly braces inside the conditional.
We do not have access to it out here.
Now if I duplicate this and I change this to instead use var, you can probably tell where I'm going
with this if I run it.
It works in both cases.
L is printed here in the block and outside the block.
So this tells us that Lutton can't have different scoping rules than Var.
Back in the day before let in cost, we only had var and var is scoped to functions what we covered
in the last video.
There is no block scope for var.
If we declare a variable using var in any block like a conditional a for loop a while loop, it is not
scoped to that block.
We have access to it outside and that could be problematic.
And that is different than how a lot of programming languages behave, which is why Lutton Const were
proposed, among other reasons.
So they also there's a distinction between const and lit.
That was one of the reasons they were added in to create constants in JavaScript, but also for scoping
reasons.
So why would this potentially be problematic?
What's wrong with having a variable declared in a block and having access to it afterwards?
There's a bunch of reasons, but let me illustrate a simple problem that used to come up occasionally
if we have a for loop using the var keyword.
So for var I equals zero I less than let's make an array called well, we'll just do animals, let animals
equal and then we'll have grizzly bear.
Let's do panda bear and spectacled bear spectacled bear and then we'll loop over this using a for loop.
I is less than animals at length I plus plus we'll console.log animals and let's also console.log I
so we get zero.
Oh well I didn't mean to cancel that log animals let's do animals of I instead of the whole array each
time we get zero grizzly bear, one panda bear, two spectacled bear.
But here's the thing.
Outside this loop, if I print I, it still exists and it's actually set to three because of the way
a four loop works, it starts at zero.
That's less than animal start length.
So we loop and we add one to IE and then it becomes one and then two and the last index in here is two.
So when I is two, we access the last element and then it's incremented to three.
The loop does not run again, but I doesn't cease to exist.
I is still here.
We have access to it and this could be problematic if you were relying on a variable called I, maybe
one you had defined somewhere else, like var I equals ten.
You might think that this I should remain as ten.
But if we print.
I down here, the only eye that we're getting is three from this loop.
So even though I had a different variable declared with var up top and it looks like at least sort of
upon first glance that I exist only in this loop because we use var it does not and that means that
we have access to it afterwards, which can have all sorts of unintended consequences.
It just makes it harder for you to know exactly where I stops.
It's not going to abide by these bounds if we use VAR because it's not block scoped.
Now, if I instead come down here and do this with let.
Let's see what happens now.
So the loop still works great.
But now when I console.log I at the bottom it's set to ten.
And that's because this I that we use let to declare is scoped to this block to the for loop so it doesn't
exist down here.
The only I that exists is this one here I used var but we could also use let.
And it works.
And if I did not have I declared up here, I try to print it out.
We get an error.
There is no I.
And the same holds true for Konst though.
You wouldn't use Konst in a for loop because it's being incremented.
That would break everything.
As you can see here, it will yell at me assignment to constant variable.
The first time it tries to add one, everything breaks, so I'll undo that change.
We'll go back to it.
The other thing that you can see right away, it tells you that these are not scoped the same way that
they exist in different scopes.
This I here and this I here is the fact that we don't get an error when we run this code.
Normally, if we have two variables in the same scope with a given name declared with lit or const,
let x equals ten.
If I try and make another x and set it equal to TW, we get an error.
Says Identifier X has already been declared.
In this case we're making a variable I with lit and then another I with lit on the very next line.
They exist in different scopes.
They are not conflicting once again compared to VAR, which is not block scoped.
This eye is the exact same eye down here, so they are in the same scope.
It starts as ten and then we are re declaring I as zero.
And you can do that with var in the same scope.
I can say var t equals one and then var t equals five, which I cannot do with an const.
I cannot use the same identifier twice.
So blocks also include things like while loops, conditionals.
As we saw, all of those rules apply for an const.
They are scoped to the block.
So now let's just write a function that also includes a block within it called double array, which
will double an array that is passed in.
So if we pass in the array of one, two, three, four or five, one, three, five, we should get
back two and then six and then ten.
Each element is doubled in a new array.
We're not updating the original, so I'm going to write a function that is expecting a R or some array
to be passed in.
We'll assume it's an array and then we'll loop over that array using a four let x of or let's call it
num num of array.
I'll make a variable in here called double.
Which is equal to numb times to.
And then up here I'll make a variable which will be an empty array and I will push double in for each
number.
So I'll start with one.
I'll double it, which I do.
Here I have a variable called double.
I will add that into a new empty array, which I'll call what should we call it?
I'll go with const because we're not going to change the reference.
We'll call this result.
It starts as an empty array and then result dot push double.
So what we have here is a function.
We have concert which is scoped to the entire function, which is why at the end I'm able to return
results because the result was defined in this function, not in a block.
Then we have double, which is scoped to this block.
We still have access to result.
So within a block we still have access to variables that were declared outside the block in this function.
So let's run this now.
We'll call double R on one, two and three.
So one, two, three, we get to four and six.
If I were to try and console.log, double and run the same line, it does not work.
If I instead use var for double.
It does work because VR does not cease to exist after this block.
Meaning the last time through the loop, which was on three double, is set to three times two, which
is six.
We have access to it down here, which is why we see six.
So this is just a quick example where we have different scopes going on.
We have const result, which is scope to the entire function because it's not inside of a block.
We have go back to let let double which is scoped to this block from a four of loop.
So down at the bottom we can still return results but we don't have access to double.
If we wanted for some reason to have access to double at the end, we could define it right here, let
double and we still have access to it here.
Double equals num times two.
If I run this code we still get two, four, six.
I don't know why you would want to access to double outside that block.
We're only using it to push a value in inside the loop.
But we, we do have access.
If you needed it, I can still access it even with let because I declared it in the function scope and
then I'm changing it within block scope.
But I'm going to undo that and go back to what we had earlier, where it only exists in the block.
So to sum this all up, let constant var are three ways of declaring a variable.
We've seen that there's a big difference between LUT and const because const cannot be reassigned.
It's a constant variable and both LUT and cons cannot be declared.
So we can't have what we've already seen.
Let X equals one, let x equals two.
We cannot re declare a new variable.
We can change it at any point, but I cannot re declare the same variable with the same name in the
same scope.
Var You can do whatever you want with it, but the very important difference that we covered here is
that on one side we have VAR which is not block scoped, on the other side we have LUT and const which
are block scoped.
So if you declare a variable with or const in a loop in a conditional in a for loop, in a wild loop,
those variables are scoped only to the confines of that block.
If they're not in a block, if they're defined in a function like we have here, we can access it within
that function.
It doesn't exist afterwards, which is what we saw in the last video.
And the same is true for var.
So Var was the only option a couple of years ago.
Function scoped now.
Lutton const are here.
BLOCK scoped.