Next up, I want to spend a little more time talking about this slide, not just this beautiful slide
with this stock photograph, but the content functions being objects.
And what that means, because we're going to prepare for the next video where we talk about using functions
within functions, accepting functions as arguments, returning functions as values.
But first, let's talk more about functions as objects.
So we saw that we could store a function in a variable.
We can also store functions in something like an array if we wanted to.
So let's see a quick example of that.
I'm going to define for different functions, just very simple ones and will be the first one.
It returns X plus Y and I'll mix up the different ways we declare them.
So we have a function statement now we'll do a function expression, so I'll do const subtract equals
function.
I'll leave it anonymous x and y and it returns x minus y and then I'll do multiply function, multiply,
multiply x, y, return x times y, and then one more is divide and I'll just duplicate this.
So we have divide and it returns X divided by Y.
So we have four functions.
Now I'm going to put them all in an array.
So I'll call this array operations for different operations.
And all I need to do is add, subtract, multiply and divide.
Now I have an array with four operations which are each a function.
So for functions stored in an array.
And if I wanted to execute any of them, let's say I want to call subtract.
That is index of 101.
So if I run my code over here, I can call operations square brackets one that gives me the function
that doesn't call it.
That's like me just typing, subtract, I'm not executing it, I'm just getting the value back, which
is an object.
It's a function which is an object.
But if I add my friends afterwards.
Right now I'm getting not a number because I haven't passed in any values.
So I'm going to pass in.
Let's go with 104.
And I get 96, 100 minus four X is 100, y is four.
If I wanted to call multiply index of two and I get 400 index of three.
Give me divide and index of zero gives me add.
Now this isn't very useful, putting them in an array to just call them manually one at a time.
It's a lot clearer if I just say add whatever 104, we can see what we're doing.
But the point that I'm trying to make here is that we can do things like loop over this array and call
each function so we don't have to.
Hard code it.
I could do a four of so four let let's call it funk of operations.
Funk is going to hold one of these functions as if it were a number or a string or any other value in
an array.
Because it is it's just any other value.
As far as JavaScript is concerned, it doesn't care.
And if I just write funk once again, that's not calling the function.
That's what I did right here.
I'm referencing it, I'm getting the value.
But to execute it, I need per ends.
So this variable will hold one of these functions each time through.
And by adding the prince, we'll call for different functions by the time this loop finishes running.
So let's just hard code in some numbers.
Let's do how about 30 and five?
And I'm not going to see a value.
I won't see anything happen because I'm not printing anything out.
It's all being returned.
I just ran it.
You don't see anything happen.
So let's store each result in a variable.
We'll call it result and then let's do a console.log result.
Okay, let's run it.
And there we go.
We ran four functions with this loop.
Maybe not something you would do, but I wanted to show you can we can treat functions as any other
value.
We can loop over them in an array.
We can even store them in objects.
So we have 35.
That was for ADD 30 plus five.
Then we have subtract 30 minus five.
We have multiply 30 times five and divide 30 divided by five.
So one more thing.
I'll just show that we can store them in an object.
We'll just go with a meaningless example for now.
This is a topic we will revisit quite a bit.
I'll make an object called thing and I'll set one property on it called Do something and it will be
equal to the value will be multiply.
So no quotes or anything.
Not the string multiply like this, but the function multiply.
I don't know why I'm saying multiply multiply.
So we're now storing a function as a value in this object.
And if I run my code and I look at thing.
We have a property called Do Something.
That's the key and the value is a function.
So I can call think dot, do something.
This doesn't execute it just like we saw earlier.
I'm simply getting the value.
I add the ends.
Now it's running, but it doesn't have any arguments.
So we'll do 50 and two.
It multiplies them and we get 100.
So I'm calling this function multiply, but it's part of an object.
I'm referencing the object, the property with the parent and it calls it.
Now, this might look kind of familiar where we have thing dot something and we put friends after it.
That's because we just wrote our very first method by adding a function to an object.
We're creating a method just like we have to uppercase.
Notice we're doing the exact same thing.
Some value dot to uppercase.
Or if we have an array.
Well, that's not a valid array.
If we have an array dot and then we call.
How about index of index of two?
It tells us that's an index one.
This is a function, but it's stored on the array.
We're going to come back to objects and how we add methods and putting functions and objects and all
that stuff in a separate section.
So that's not the main takeaway here.
That's a bigger topic.
But I wanted to show that functions are simply values in JavaScript.
We can store them in an array, we can call them dynamically put them in this func variable each time
through the loop.
Execute it.
It's just a placeholder name.
This will store the value of add or subtract or multiply or divide and actually execute it.
We can also put a function in an object.
So next we're going to see more of using functions within functions.
So passing functions as an argument to another function or returning a function which is actually a
very key part of JavaScript.
So let's get started.
That's next.