Next up, we're continuing along with more advanced function concepts.
We have this big word or a big phrase, higher order functions.
It simply refers to functions that operate on or with other functions.
So functions that either accept functions as arguments and use them or do something with them, or on
the other side of things, a function that returns another function.
So I'm going to show both of them.
We're going to start with the first example or the first type, a function that accepts a function as
an argument.
This is a really common pattern in JavaScript, and we'll see a bunch of examples and a bunch of built
in methods where we pass functions in as arguments, but we're going to start by defining our own.
So this is a very simple function called call twice and it accepts an argument that I'm calling func.
That's just the parameter name I've decided on.
It could be anything as long as it's a valid JavaScript identifier.
And then I'm executing that argument twice.
So if I have a function called laugh and I call twice the function, call twice and I pass in laugh,
it will call laugh two times.
So let me demonstrate this.
I'll define a function called call three times and we'll pass a function to it.
We can call it F just to make it different instead of func, and we'll execute F one time.
Two times.
Three times.
And then let's define some other function, whether it's laugh, scream, cry, let's go with cry and
it will console.log.
Boo hoo!
I'm so sad like that.
And now I can use it.
I can use call three times.
I mean, I can call CRI on my own just like this.
Of course, that should be review.
But I can also run call three times.
I'll expand this a bit and pass in cry.
Cry is a function.
I'm passing it into this function and then this function executes it three times in a row.
And there we go.
Boo hoo!
I'm so sad.
One time, two times.
Three times.
If we instead did it with a different function, how about instead of cry?
We do rage and we'll console.log.
I hate everything.
If we call three times and pass in rage.
Let's do another example.
This time we'll write a function.
Let's call it repeat or repeat end times, and we'll pass in a function and a number.
And then it will call that function and number of times.
So I'm going to define this function, repeat, end times and we'll pass in a function which I'll call
func, or we could call it action just to be different.
So you can see it truly does not matter.
It's just any parameter name that's valid.
It can store a function, it can store a string, it will store whatever we pass in JavaScript doesn't
care, and then we'll pass in a number which we'll call NUM.
What we're going to do is loop num times and each time through call or let EI is equal to let's go upwards.
So zero EI is less than num plus plus it doesn't matter.
We're just looping a number of times, num number of times and we'll call action each time in that loop.
Then to use this function, I'll reinstate cri and rage.
And now I can call something like repeat end times rage and I'll repeat it 13 times.
So I'm passing in the function rage.
It's called action in this function and we are looping 13 times each time through we're executing whatever
action was passed in what happens over here.
13 I hate everything.
Annoyingly chrome console condenses them.
You'll have to trust me.
It happened 13 times if we instead I'll come over here.
But if we instead change it to 11 times, we get 11 console logs.
If instead of rage I'm calling cry, we get 19.
Boo hoo.
I'm so sad.
Print it out in our console and for one more example, let's write a function called randomly pick or
randomly call or I don't know, we'll figure out a name.
It will accept two functions and it will randomly call one of them, but not both.
So I will comment this out.
We can leave it.
We'll just comment this line out.
We'll define our function, which I still haven't come up with a good name.
Let's go with pick one or call one.
Pick one is fine and we'll pass in function one and function two.
And then we need to write logic to randomly pick one of these values.
So the most common way of doing this is to pick a random number.
And if that number is, let's say the number is between zero and one, if it's less than 0.5, we'll
do one thing.
If it's greater than 0.5, we'll do another.
So let's pick a random number.
We'll go with rand equals math at random and we'll keep it as a decimal and then we'll just write some
logic.
If Rand is less than 0.5, we'll call function one and I'll expand this just to make it clearer.
Else.
If it's greater than 0.5, we'll call a function to.
And that's it.
Function one and function two will only call one of them, depending on what Rand is.
So if we console.log rand and then we try calling, pick one, which I'll just do it over here.
I'll call, pick one and pass in cry and rage.
It turns out that our random number was 0.9, 0.9, blah, blah blah.
So it ran rage.
I hate everything.
We'll try it again.
This time our random number was 0.38 and it ran cry.
So each time it picks one of them.
So there you have it.
Three examples of calling functions that are passed as arguments.
So a function call three times except another function as an argument, and we execute it three times
in the body of call three times.
Here's another one repeat end times.
It accepts an action and a number.
It loops number times or num times, let's say nine times, and it calls whatever this function is,
that number of times.
And then we also have pick one, which accepts two functions and a randomly decides which one to call.
None of these may seem that useful, but as you'll see very shortly, JavaScript comes with a ton of
built in methods, especially with arrays where we perform a function for every element in an array.
So that's coming up shortly.
But we still need to talk about the other type of higher order function.
We talked about functions that accept functions as arguments.
Next, we'll see functions that can return a function as the return value.