We saw double equals, which is going to check for equality of value, but it ignores type.
Triple equals cares both about value and type.
So it's three equal signs in a row, and again, it cares about the type and value.
It's not going to try and coerce the values to be of a common type.
So if we have something like two triple equals, the string two that's going to be false versus double
equals is true.
We also saw an example where we had zero double equals false.
That is true.
Triple equals is false, so it is stricter, hence the term or the name strict equality operator.
All of those examples that we saw with double equals that were kind of wonky, like undefined double
equals null, which is true if we do it with triple equals, they are not the same type.
So it doesn't matter, it's false.
But if we do something that definitely is true, three equals three or null triple equals null.
That's true.
And so on.
So triple equals is more precise or more specific.
It cares about type, and generally that's what you want.
If you were using double equals, you could get some weird behavior if you're trying to check if a certain
value is exactly false and instead the value was zero, this could lead to some unexpected decisions
or results.
So generally we stick to triple equals.
It's more specific.
It's more precise type usually matters.
If we had some variable called is logged in and it's set to false and we wanted to check is logged in
equal to false.
This works like we want to make sure nobody is logged in so we're checking is logged in set to false
but if somebody somehow set it to zero for example and we ran that line again is logged in double equals
false it still saying true but it's not actually false.
If we instead use triple equals, we avoid that entirely.
So in general, 99.99999% of the time what you want is triple equals.
And in this course we'll be using triple equals for everything.
It's really rare that you need double equals.
There are people who will say never ever use double equals.
I think it's a good rule of thumb if you're brand new to JavaScript.
I certainly haven't used it in the last year or so at least, but it is something you might see sometimes
in certain edge cases and scenarios.
I'm beating a dead horse here.
So just remember triple equals, not double.
And let's wrap up here by talking about non equality.
So just like we have two ways of checking if something is equal to another thing, we have two ways
of checking.
If two values are not equal, we have non equality, just the plain old non equality.
This is the analogue or the cousin of double equals.
And then we have strict non equality which is the cousin of triple equals.
So if we do something like one is not equal to two, we get true.
That makes sense.
One is not two.
If we keep using the one equal sign version, we could also do this.
One is not equal to one, but that gives us false because we're using a single equal sign which is like
the double equals.
It doesn't care about type.
So we end up with false because they're converted to the same type.
And it's essentially checking is one not equal to one, and that's false.
If we instead use this version where we have two equal signs, we end up with one strict non equality
string one.
And that is true.
So for the same reason that I said you should always use triple equals, you should almost always use
this version of non equality to equal signs.
So we've now covered all of the comparison operators we need to talk about.
We saw greater than less than and then also greater than or equal to less than or equal to.
And then in terms of the equality operators, just go with the bottom two here to check if things are
equal.
Use triple equals to check if things are not equal, use this version where we have one exclamation
point and two equal signs.
Those two circle them, remember them and ignore these two.
I need to show them to you, but ignore them.