We've got a quick but super important detour away from logic and conditionals and comparisons for just
a moment.
We need to talk about how we are going to run our code from here on out.
So far, we've been playing around in the console with little one liners, like one plus two or four
is less than or equal to eight.
It's nice we can get an answer evaluated immediately and we see the result visually.
We are not writing an entire script with a bunch of code and executing it when we're ready.
We're typing something immediately.
This is actually called a ripple read evaluate print loop.
That's what the JavaScript console is here.
It reads in whatever you type, it evaluates it, it prints it, and it loops meaning that I can do
it continuously.
If I hit enter right now this is not valid JavaScript.
So it throws an error.
But it reads in that code thinks this is code, it realizes it's not when it evaluates it or it's not
valid code, it prints an error and then it loops so I can do something else.
So that's great for playing around, for testing things out, but it's not so great for creating larger
scripts and larger applications where we actually want to have access to our code after the fact.
This code all goes away.
If I refresh the page, it's gone.
But also it's not that easy to write multiple lines of code and create larger scripts in the console.
So we're going to be writing our code in JavaScript files most of the time from here on out.
We'll try new things out.
We'll play around with new features in the console for a couple of minutes, but most of what we'll
do will be in a JavaScript file.
So we have a text editor.
I introduced this early on in the course I'm using vs code.
You can use any text editor you want.
You just need to make a dot JS file and unfortunately we can't simply open a JavaScript file in the
browser to run it.
We have to open an HTML file which has a script or it includes our JavaScript file.
The browser doesn't know how to handle just a plain JavaScript file.
It knows how to handle an HTML file that includes a JavaScript file.
So there's two steps.
Let's go ahead and try it out over in vs code.
I'm going to make a new file.
I'm working in a folder called code.
I'll make a new file.
You can either right click new file.
You can go file, new file or use a shortcut, which is what I usually do on a mac command.
N And I'll call this file app.
JS Or script.
JS It does not matter as long as you can reference it, so I'll go with script.
Actually, I changed my mind like app app.
JS And we'll put some code in here.
We saw this really early on in the course.
I'm just going to add an alert that says it's working.
So if we get it working correctly, we should see this pop up in the browser.
So that was the first step.
The next step is to create an HTML file and include a script.
So I'm going to go back to VS code.
I'll make a new file command n and I'll call this one something html.
A pretty standard generic name as indexed html.
You can call it code html website.
It doesn't matter as long as it ends in HTML.
And I'm going to put them in the same folder.
It just makes it easier when I'm including this JavaScript file.
So I'm going to put that there.
And if you're not super familiar with HTML, don't fret.
You don't have to type this entire structure from scratch.
If you're using vs code or a similar editor and VTS code, I can type exclamation point tab and it fills
all of this stuff out for me.
I get my standard boilerplate HTML, essentially the template, the thing we use every time or the code
we write every time in an HTML file.
I'll give this a title like my first JS script and then I'll save this.
Right now we're not including the script at all, so we need to include a script tag.
So I'm going to just use Autocomplete here type script or probably just SC, we'll give it to you.
And then we need to add a source attribute which corresponds to the path to our file.
So it's called JS there in the same folder.
So all I need to type here is app dot js.
Later on we'll talk about the placement of this script.
For now, you can put it anywhere in this HTML document.
It can go here, it can go at the bottom of the body.
It doesn't matter.
For now, because our script does not depend on any HTML.
We're not interacting with HTML.
We're not creating elements or deleting elements or having events or anything like that.
We're just simply printing some content so you can put it wherever you want.
If you're familiar with JavaScript already and with HTML and the problems that can arise from including
a script too soon, then go ahead and put it down at the bottom.
But it doesn't matter for now.
It will later.
All right.
So we have our script included.
Hopefully just make sure your name is matching whatever you name the file.
We'll save this and then I'm going to go to my browser.
Well, first, I'm going to open it in the browser.
So there's multiple ways of doing this.
You go to your HTML file, you right click, you can click open with you can just double click and it
opens up in your default browser, which for me is Chrome and we can see that it's working because my
alert came through.
It says it's working and that's it.
We don't see any content on the page.
We're not really worrying about that.
So for most of this early part of the course, we'll just be working in the console of our file that
we're opening up the HTML file.
So we've now successfully included a script.
It's working and this is a workflow.
We'll follow a lot if you're not very comfortable with it yet.
It takes some practice, but it's just one of those things you do often.
You could even make a template, a folder that you could just duplicate.
Any time you wanted to make a new script, you could also do this where you make a new script.
Here, we'll call this one app to JS and this one will say, Alert, I am a different script, we'll
save.
And then in my index I can just include app too.
Instead, I'll refresh my page and now I get script two.
I am a different script or app too, so you don't have to make a new HTML and JavaScript file.
Every single time you want a new script, you can just swap out which script you're including.
So then this brings me to one last important piece in the console.
We've been typing things like Let's go back to app.
JS We've been typing things like this four plus four or three equals equals three, and we see an answer
right away.
It's evaluated and printed back, but in regular JavaScript, in a script like we have here, this won't
show up, this won't print anything, it will be evaluated and JavaScript knows what the answer is and
what the result is.
But it doesn't show it to us.
It doesn't print it out.
So if we want something to be explicitly printed out, we have to use a method.
Another method.
It's not a string method, it's not a number method.
It has to do with something called the console.
The method is called console.log and all that it does is it prints something to the console.
So as I mentioned, when we write code like this, if I refresh my page, I make sure I'm including
app JS, not app too.
If I refresh, we don't see anything.
And if I open up the JavaScript console, you can see nothing is printed out.
I can also move this over.
Actually, since we don't really care about this HTML page, we just want the JavaScript.
I think what I would do instead is get rid of this right here and I'll just display the console next
to my editor.
So there is an HTML page open.
I'm just viewing the console and I put them together in one window.
But as you can see, nothing is showing up.
I refresh the page.
We don't see anything.
What if I instead use console.log?
Console.log.
And then we pass in three plus four or whatever we had before.
I'll save and refresh the page.
I now get seven.
Hallelujah.
It's working.
So this is the way that we actually view values, at least until we talk about HTML and displaying content
on a page.
For now we're just showing things in the console.
So console.log is a special really commonly used method, often used for debugging and trying to understand
what's going wrong somewhere.
Or when you're starting out just to print stuff so you can see while we're here, I'll just show you
a couple of flavors.
I'll just do one more flavor of console.log instead of logging something.
There's another method called console error and we can pass in some content.
It will be printed, but rather than print it nicely like this, I'll refresh the page.
It shows up like a JavaScript error.
So it's read.
We can exit away.
Maybe we can't.
Usually, I think you usually can.
But anyway, it just shows up differently.
Console again refers to the JavaScript console.
Log is going to print something out.
It will log it to you.
And the last thing is that we can pass in multiple things to console that log.
We could do three plus four comma.
Hello comma.
How about true?
And save.
I'll refresh my page on the left and let me make this a little clearer.
What it does is it prints them all to the console.
It separates them with a space.
So you could have as many things as you want passed in into console.log, and it will print them all
out, just separated by spaces.
So that's the detour.
We're going to go back to logic and conditionals and making decisions in our code now that we have a
place to actually write our code.
So the workflow makefile name it something dot js include it using a script tag in an HTML file.
Double click that HTML file to open it in the browser and then in the browser we'll be working in the
console for now.
So just open the console again and we will be using console.log to display values.
All right.