All right.
Now that we've seen how to run code from a file, we can start writing slightly longer, slightly more
complex scripts to add logic into our code to actually make decisions.
The key mechanism we use is something called a conditional statement.
Now, a conditional statement can have three different pieces in if an elseif and an else, and we'll
go through them in order.
And we're going to start with if so, if allows us to run certain code.
If a given condition is true, we spend a healthy amount of time talking about these different operators
and they all evaluate to true or false.
They all evaluate to a boolean.
Now we can use them inside of a conditional where we end up with either a true or a false.
And if that thing is true, if the condition is true, our code will run.
So let me show you the simplest example that we could do.
I'm working in an app JS file.
It's connected to my index HTML.
I have my index opened up over here.
I'm looking at the console.
Let's delete what I had in there.
I'll close down my sidebar.
The simplest possible conditional looks like this if something this isn't valid as it is right now,
but if some condition that becomes either true or false.
If it's true, run the code in here.
So let's do something like if one equals one console.log.
It's true.
We'll save.
I'll refresh my page and we end up with.
It's true.
This code runs.
If this becomes true, if you were to copy that and paste it here, we get true.
Now, if we did something like this, if one is not equal to one, we know that that is false.
It gives us false.
I'll refresh my page now and we don't see anything.
This code does not run.
So we've written our first simple piece of logic, our first decision that actually impacts which code
runs based off of this condition.
Now we'll learn how to write much more complex ones, but let's take a look at a couple of different
examples.
Here's one where I'm modeling a typical performance review you might have at a company where your manager
or your peers rate you on a certain scale.
And we're translating that numeric rating to feedback like, you're a superstar, you need improvement,
you meet expectations.
We could model that over here.
I'll just write a quick comment.
Example two We'll have a rating variable and set it equal to three, and we can simply check if rating
is equal to three, we'll console.log.
You are a superstar.
I don't know why it's all caps, but it works.
We'll refresh the page and we end up with You are a superstar.
We change rating to two.
We need improvement.
We don't get that printed out.
We could also do something like if rating is less than three instead of printing, you are a superstar.
We could print console.log.
How about we just go back to what we had?
You are not a superstar because only three is a superstar.
I'll refresh.
We don't see anything.
But if I change it to two, we get the slightly harsh feedback.
You are not a superstar in all caps, so I'm going to undo that and go back to what we had because we're
going to build on this example in just a bit.
So this is the first part of a conditional I mentioned.
There are two other things we can add on.
This is checking for a single condition and we can have multiple of these if we wanted to.
We actually already have two of them in a single file.
Both of them are being evaluated.
This one is false.
So that doesn't run.
This one is true.
So it does run.
But if we change rating, it may not run.
Here's one more example.
Nice and simple.
Let's say we have a number let numb and it's equal to 37.
Let's print out something if the number is even or let's go with something.
If the number is odd, how do we tell if a number is odd?
We go back to that modulo operator we saw early on the percent sign using the remainder.
So we divide by two and check the remainder using modulo.
And if two goes evenly into a number, that means it's an even number.
So the remainder would be zero.
So for an odd number, we'll just check if the remainder is not zero.
So let me show you that if num mod two is not equal to zero.
Console.log.
Odd number.
Let's see what we get when I refresh.
We should see odd number if I change it to 38, nothing.
All right.
So those are three simple examples of conditionals.
Very short ones, where we only have one piece, one condition.
And if this is not the case, we just keep moving on.
Whatever code comes after will be run.
Next we're going to see elseif, which we can chain on with our if.