All right.
So right now, the code works for these three ratings, specifically three, two and one.
But what if the rating is something else entirely?
Like zero would be an easy one or 23.
But what if it's also a or good something like that?
We're not accounting for it.
We won't print anything out at all.
It's just ignored and our code doesn't really display anything or doesn't display anything, period,
to the user.
To fix this, we can add in a third piece to our conditional.
We have if else if and we have else else is kind of like the otherwise part of the conditional.
It's the thing that runs.
If nothing else was true before it, then the code inside of else will be executed.
So you can see down here we don't specify a condition and set of parentheses like we do for if and else
if, because it just runs no matter what.
If nothing else ran first so we can add in and else down here just looks like this.
And in our situation, if rating is not three, two or one else will run.
If rating is three, two or one else will not run.
Just like if rating is three, nothing else runs.
If rating is two, nothing else runs after it and so on.
Else is the fallback.
It is the final piece of your conditional.
You don't have to have an else, but if you want to have one, you must have an if it doesn't make sense
to have an otherwise if there is no initial.
If so, we'll just cancel that log invalid rating.
We'll save, refresh the page and we end up with invalid rating.
If we have anything other than three to or one, we get invalid if we go back to two.
Oh, that's a string.
So that won't work because we're comparing with triple equals for exactly the number two.
But if we go back to the number two, it works just fine.
So often we do have an if and elseif or multiple else, ifs and else.
And by the way, I forgot to mention we can only have one else per if it doesn't make sense to have
more than one.
Otherwise we can have as many ifs as we want and we have one if at the beginning.
So sometimes we have all of them together, but often we'll just have a yes or no, a simple if and
an else.
So here's an example.
I have a high score variable and a user score.
So the idea is that we have a game or something where we have a high score, like an old arcade cabinet
where it stores the highest score ever on that cabinet and then the current user score.
And we could write a conditional that just checks if the user score is greater then we could even do
equal to.
I'm not sure what happens if you equal the high score on a game.
Do you then become the high score?
Let's let's say that's how it works.
So if user score is greater than or equal to the current high score, we will cancel that log.
Let's do a template literal.
Congrats you have the new high score of and then let's add it in and we'll show user score.
Then we could also update high score to now equal user score.
If what the user scored is higher than the current high score, then high scores should become that
score.
And then we can add in an else and we'll console.log.
Another template literal good game your score of and then user score with our dollar sign to interpolate.
It did not beat the high score of and then high score.
All right.
So if we run this right now, refresh, we get good game.
Your score of 1200 did not beat the high score of 1430.
If we change this to now be 1600.
Congrats.
You have the new high score of 1600.
So here we have a simple yes or no.
It's either this, and if it's not, then it's this.
There is no scenario where we won't have.
Well, I guess you could write code that breaks.
You could write something that causes an error.
But assuming that doesn't happen, one of these is going to run.
We don't have a bunch of else ifs.
We just have a simple if and an else.