The next thing to know about conditionals is that we can nest them inside of one another so we can have
multiple layers deep of conditionals where we're checking for a certain condition to be true and we
can nest them as much as we want, whether it's if and elses, we can throw an else ifs.
We just nest them inside the curly braces.
So let's try an example.
We'll go with this example I've been using in the slides of a password.
So let's say a user type, some password and we don't know what it is.
So that's going to be invalid.
I'm just going to make it undefined for now.
Let's say we don't know what it is.
We want to make sure the password is long enough so we would check if password length is let's say it's
greater than or equal to maybe six eight.
Not super strong.
It should be longer, but just to make our lives easier if it is greater than or equal to six, we'll
check something.
If it's not, we'll console that log.
Password must be longer.
Great.
But if it is greater than or equal to six, we're not done.
We also want to make sure there's no spaces in a password so we could check if password.
And the easiest way to check if there's a space anywhere in there, at least with what we know right
now, would be to do an index of the space character.
So that's not an empty string.
There's a space.
And remember, if it is found in the string password, we'll get an index like two or seven or 20 or
zero.
If it's not found, we'll get negative one.
So if we find negative one, that means there is a space.
So if password index of space is equal to negative one, that means there is no space.
We can then cancel that log.
Valid password.
And then otherwise we can cancel that log.
Password is long enough but cannot contain spaces.
So let's test it out.
Right now password is undefined.
Let's give it a value.
Password will be a hello kitty.
So that is long enough.
But if I refresh we see password is long enough but cannot contain spaces and there is at least one
space in there.
If I get rid of that refresh valid password.
Now, if I get rid of some of these characters, it's too short.
We get password must be longer.
So the main takeaway from this video should be that we can nest conditionals inside of other conditionals
we could add in another else if somewhere.
Although I don't really think I can't think of a good scenario, at least now with a password or an
else, if would make sense.
But we could continue to nest instead of else, instead of if.
But there is a point where it becomes a little bit difficult to read.
If your code is super nested and there are different solutions or strategies you can take to alleviate
that, we're about to start learning one of them at least where something like this could actually be
written as a single condition, because in order for a password to be valid, we need the length to
be greater than six and we want there to be no spaces.
That means it's valid.
What if we could just write a single conditional that said, if it's long enough and there aren't spaces,
it's valid.
That's what we'll see how to do next.
There's nothing wrong with nesting.
Sometimes you cannot get around it, but you just don't want to have like five levels of nested conditionals,
especially if they all have, if and else's.
It just can be a bit of a headache to understand.
So that's nesting.