Now that we've seen conditionals, we can talk about this kind of odd topic truthiness and falseness
or truth and false values.
All that this is is that every value in JavaScript has an inherent truthiness or falseness about it.
It doesn't mean it is truth or true or it is false.
There's only two values, true and false, that are actually true and false.
Those are the booleans, but every value has a truth or falseness to it.
Now, let me show you what I mean.
If we were to write a conditional like if let's make a variable called mystery.
Let's do, let's mystery equals five, and then we'll add a conditional of if mystery, just mystery,
not mystery equals anything.
Just if mystery will conceal that log truth.
And then else we can contact Logue Falsey.
I'm not sure if falsity is spelled like that or that it's not really the technical term.
But anyway, we are just checking this single condition if mystery, which is right now set to five.
If that is true, thi this would print.
If it's not true thi meaning it's falsely this would print.
Let's see what we get.
We get true thi.
So the number five is a truth e value.
In fact, every number that you could possibly choose except for zero is true.
You can see zero is false.
The only caveat to that is not a number which we've seen a couple of times that is also falsely.
So something like zero divided by zero is going to give us not a number.
I'm refreshing and we still see false.
Almost every single value in java script is true.
Thi except for these right here.
So the actual value of false of course is false.
Zero, as we just saw, is false empty string.
So there's no space in there.
It's just an empty string like this that is falsely null, undefined and not a number.
Everything else, excluding these, everything else, is truth.
Now, why does this matter?
Why should you really care?
It's not just a little piece of trivia to know.
Often you'll see people use this strategy if some variable do something, not mystery, but something
like this.
If, let's say current user or logged in user then console.log, something like you are logged in else
console.log.
Please log in.
Okay.
So something like this is pretty common.
Maybe not console logging, but displaying a certain page showing the sign in button versus the sign
out button.
We're just checking if a variable is toothy.
So if we define logged in user and it's set to I don't know.
Thomas One, two, three, we're going to see you are logged in.
But if it is not set to anything like undefined, please logged in, please log in or if it's set to
null, which would be another option.
Please log in.
Same thing if we had a string for somebody name username we could write if username and if that username
is still an empty string, then that code would not run.
If it was anything else in that string, it would run.
So this is just a small side topic, but you will see this pretty frequently checking for a value.
We're not checking to see if it's equal to something in particular.
We're seeing if it's true, which usually is a way of checking if something has content, if it exists,
if it's not null, undefined, zero, false, empty string or not a number, anything else will pass
this condition.