The next logical operator we have is or so or uses the pipe character which is located above the return
key, at least on every keyboard I've used.
You hold shift and for me it's on the backslash character.
So shift.
And then backslash gives you those pipes.
So those are not ones.
They're not L's.
They're not slashes.
They are pipes.
So you need two of them in a row and or is similar to and in that it takes two sides left and right,
but it works differently.
If either side is true, the entire thing is considered true.
So if we have true or false, only one of them needs to be true for the whole thing to be true.
So if both of them are true, that's fine.
It's not saying only one can be true.
It just needs one at a minimum to be true.
The left or the right.
And if that happens to be both of them, if it's one of them, it doesn't matter.
But in the event that neither side is true, so we have false or false, the entire thing is considered
false.
So again, this is not how you would usually use it.
Neither is this.
But this is slightly more complicated.
We're evaluating two expressions.
So is one equal or one not equal to one?
That would be false because one is equal to one.
So we have false.
Or ten equals ten.
That's true.
False or true is true.
Zero or undefined.
Now remember we talked about truthiness and false penis zero is considered false.
Undefined is false.
So we end up with false or false.
Neither side is true.
So the whole thing is false because logical.
Or then we have the one in the middle.
Ten divided by two equals five.
That is true or null which is false.
So true or false that evaluates to true.
So let's see an example where you would use this in practice.
Let's say we were, I don't know, running a community theater program and we're at the box office and
we're charging tickets for people who are adults, not children.
And we're defining children as people under the age of six.
And senior citizens also get in for free.
So if you are one of those categories, either under six years old or over 65, you get it for free.
Otherwise you don't.
You have to pay $10 we could use or so we would write something like this.
Let me close this down a bit.
Let age equals.
Let's go with 78.
If age is greater than let's go with the less than 1/1.
If age is less than six or age is greater than or equal to 65, at least in the US, I think 65 year
olds are considered seniors.
It depends on the place we'll console.log.
You get in for free and then we'll have our else.
You must pay.
So we have two things.
And if either one is true, you get in for free.
If age is under six, you're free.
If age is under 65 or greater than or equal to 65, you also get in for free.
Let's see what we get.
You get in for free.
If we change it to three years old.
You also get in for free.
But if you're 30, you have to pay.
So if we were to rewrite this without using the logical operator, it would be something like If age
is less than six, you get it for free.
And then we could also have an else.
If age is greater than or equal to 65, you get in for free, else you have to pay.
So when we use or we can combine multiple pieces into one line or one expression and again, one side
is all that is required in order to pass go in order for the expression to be true in our code to run.
We can also chain multiple orders together, just like we can with.
And let's do a quick example.
There are many, many colors out there in the world, but fans of mine or longtime students know the
best color of all time is, without a doubt, purple.
So let's write some code that checks to see if a color is purple or if it's a shade of purple like orchid
or violets.
We'll go with three to start.
So if it's one of those, we'll consider that log.
Congrats.
You picked purple or something like that.
So we need a variable.
We'll go with lit color equals something.
We'll fill it in if color is equal to purple or color is equal to.
Lilac or color is equal to violet or some other color.
Then we'll count that log.
Great choice.
We could keep changing these on and on and make a very long statement.
But as you can see here, color is empty string.
We don't get anything.
Let's set it to Violet.
Great choice.
So only one of these has to be true.
And in our case, violet color was equal to violet.
Even though these were false, this was true.
So we print great choice.
You can chain them together, although there is a much better way of checking one value.
Like if we had a color and we had ten valid options, we wanted to make sure it was one of those options.
You would not need to chain this ten times.
There are other tools you can use once we talk about arrays and some other built in methods that come
with JavaScript that would make your life easier.
But we're not there.
So we would write it like this.
We're still just focusing on or so we've seen and and or they are similar in that they take a left in
a right side.
We often use them in conditional statements inside the print, but they're very different in how they
behave when we have.
And both sides must be true in order to move on when we have or just one needs to be true.