Next up, the third and final logical operator.
We'll see for now, the not operator.
So unlike or or aunt where we have two characters, ampersand, ampersand or with or we have pipe pipe
with not we have a single character, one exclamation point, and it works a little differently.
We don't have a left and a right side like we did with or we have one side, we have the other same
thing with and not.
It's just going to operate on a single expression and it returns true if that expression is false.
So we put exclamation point in in front of some expression.
If that expression returns false, when you have the not in front of it, the whole thing is now true.
It kind of negates it.
So here's a couple of very simple examples we've seen NULL, which is a false value.
When you put an exclamation point in front of it, we end up with true.
Not?
No.
True.
Not zero.
Not empty string.
True.
Now, if we try it with a true value, like 45.
We get false now because 45 is truth.
So then not true is false.
Same thing with a string.
That is true thi.
And you can see where I'm going.
We can also use not to negate actual expressions that are not just a single value.
So something like zero equals zero is true.
It's true.
When we put the exclamation point than not in front, we get false or three less than or equal to four.
That is true.
The exclamation point gives us false.
The scenario is where you use this can vary greatly and it's hard to show all that useful of an example.
And I'll explain why in just a moment.
All of these operators and or not, along with the conditionals themselves, if elseif and else are
really flexible and there's often a ton of different ways of achieving the exact same logic or the same
outcome, but you can write it differently.
You can use nested things as we've seen you could use, and you can combine certain things with not
in order to make them work.
So let's take a look at an example we saw earlier.
We had the logged in user example where we were trying to check if a user was logged in or if this variable
had a value.
We wanted to do something, but now let's flip it and say that we want to check if there is not a logged
in user so that we can boot them off the web page.
They're in the wrong spot.
They shouldn't be here.
So if there isn't a logged in user, do something.
How would we do that with what we've seen so far without not we would do if logged in user.
And then else is where we would put our code.
The code down here would run when there is no logged in user, when it's undefined or null empty string.
But if we want to use not if we don't have an otherwise, we just want to check if there's not a user.
We could write this if not logged in user.
We'll console that log, get out of it and if I run it, we end up with Get out of here.
But if I change this to now have a value.
We don't get anything.
So we could have written this as we saw earlier with the regular if I put some code in here for when
the user is logged in and then in the else put this.
But if we don't have two situations, we just want to check if there's not a logged in user we could
use not.
So here's another very simple example.
Most of these, as you've already noticed, are quite silly and not they don't seem immediately useful.
But these pieces of logic that tools were learning, I promise they'd come into play all the time.
When you're creating real applications, we just don't have those tools yet, so we're kind of faking
it with logged in user or what we're going to do now, we'll do something like flavor.
Flavor will be grape.
So we are a online snow cone stand and we mail you snow cones pre-made using dry ice.
We only have two flavors.
We have grape and we have cherry.
So if a user orders something that is not grape and it's not cherry, we need to tell them You can't
do that.
So we have a couple of different ways of doing this.
We could check if flavor is not equal to grape.
And flavor is not equal to cherry.
We'll count that log.
We don't have that flavor.
So that's one way of doing it.
If I change this to watermelon, for example, refresh the page.
We don't have that flavor.
But if we wanted to write it another way, which is kind of what I'm getting at here, we have a lot
of options.
We could also say if flavor.
Equals grape or flavor equals cherry.
And then negate that entire thing with parents around it.
We would read this as if not flavor is grape or flavors cherry.
So this logic is basically the same thing we wrote up here, the same exact outcome, or it's true in
the same scenarios and false in the same scenarios.
But we've written it differently.
I definitely prefer well, I think I prefer this one.
It's easier, fewer operators, but this is totally valid.
And remember, the way it works is that we have or which is in parentheses.
So if one of these is true, the entire thing is true.
And that would mean flavor is grape or flavor is cherry.
So if flavor is grape, this becomes true.
This doesn't matter because it's an or so the whole thing becomes true like that.
And then we negate that.
So the whole thing becomes false.
And then this code would not run.
But if we had flavor was watermelon, for example.
This is false.
So this whole or becomes false and then we negate that false, which gives us true.
So let's make sure it works.
Comment this one out.
We'll console.log.
We only have grape and cherry refresh.
Right now we're using watermelon, is that right?
We only have grape and cherry.
I change it to grape.
No problem.
We don't get that console.log.
So it's not the most riveting example.
But I wanted to show that we can rewrite things two different ways.
I still prefer this one, but not gives us flexibility and sometimes it is actually useful.
But I just wanted to show we have flexibility.
All of this stuff can be rewritten multiple ways.
There's still further ways we could rewrite this.
We could nest instead, but I won't get into that for now.
So that is not the third logical operator and or.
And not.