All right.
I've got a question for you.
I have a simple expression.
I'm combining awe and and equality greater than.
I have a variable called X.
It's set to seven.
And my question is, what does this evaluate to?
And the reason I'm asking is that it has to do with operator precedence.
So this will be a very quick video, but it's very important when we're working with all operators,
as we've already seen with addition subtraction, multiplication, division, certain operators have
precedence over others.
For example, division happens before subtraction.
That also applies with logical operators and it applies with operators like this one here.
Greater than a logical guess would be to assume it goes from left to right.
So we would have x equals seven.
Well, that's true.
Then we have true or x equals three.
That's false.
So this whole thing, since we have the OR right there, this whole thing becomes true and then we have
true and x greater than ten.
Well, that's not the case.
Right, x is seven.
So that's false.
So then the whole thing becomes false.
That's what you might think the answer is.
But if we actually look and we paste it in, the answer is true.
And the reason for this is because the and operator takes precedence over or so.
This is going to run first and it's going to look for a left and a right.
And you can think of it as this right here.
So is x equal to three?
Nope.
So that's false.
X greater than ten?
Nope.
So the whole thing is false.
Only one part needed to be false.
So this is false or true, which is going to give us true, false or true.
We need one side to be true.
If we wanted the logic to actually work the way that we thought it did from left to right, we need
to use parentheses to group this.
We want this to run first, and if we run that, you'll see we get false because now we're checking
this first.
This thing evaluates to true and then this thing evaluates to false and the whole thing becomes false
rather than what we had here.
So the order does matter when we're working with these operators, especially the logical ones.
This is the rough order.
Well, this is the exact order.
Logical not is going to run first, then logical and then or it can be confusing to remember all of
this and keep track of it.
So if you ever have any doubt, put parentheses in there.
Parentheses will trump everything and it makes it clearer how things are supposed to run.
There's no shame in adding extra parens and if you go to MDM, this is kind of an interesting chart.
There is a table that shows the precedence of every single operator and you can see at the very top
the highest precedence is parentheses that always wins, that always runs first.
And as we scroll down, we can see we encounter logical not.
And that comes before logical and which is all the way down here and logical or so and before or and
not before both of those.
And this also explains why something like this works x less than three and X greater than one.
This is an operator and this is an operator.
These are going to run first.
So this on the left runs this on the right runs and then and does its thing.
So we know that because we've been using and for a while at this point and we've seen how it works.
But this chart explains that.
As you can see, if I scroll down greater than less, then all those operators come first before and
and or.
All right.
So that's it for this video.
I just wanted to make that clear.
There is an order and it can be confusing to remember.
So if you ever have any doubts, add in parens.
It also makes it clearer for anyone else who's reading it because not all developers happen to remember
that order off the top of their head either.