Next up, I'd like to introduce a different feature of JavaScript.
It has to do with decision making and logic.
It's called the switch statement.
It's not as commonly used as the typical conditional with if elseif and else.
But in certain scenarios it's really useful.
So let me show you what it looks like or why you would use it.
Imagine we have a variable with a number representing the day of the week.
So let's go with let day equals three.
If I wanted to translate a number going from 1 to 7 to Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday,
and so on.
Depending on where you are in the world, I think people use different start dates for the week.
I think outside of the U.S. and Canada, it's the week starts on Monday, which makes a lot more sense
than starting it on Sunday like we do in the U.S. So let's go with the international version.
Using a standard conditional, we would check if DE is equal to one and all.
Fast forward through this but we would console.log.
Sunday or no Monday.
Got to break that American habit.
We're going with international standard and then we would have else if de is two and I'll just type
this out quickly.
Okay, here we go.
It's quite long.
If day is one Monday to Tuesday and it's just a bunch of else ifs.
If I change the day to two, we get Tuesday.
If I change the day to seven, we get Sunday.
Let's also add in a fallback.
So if you didn't enter a number from 1 to 7, we'll console.log invalid day.
All right, so this is fine, but it's a lot of work and each time we're really just checking de against
one value over and over and over until we find a match or until we don't find a match in the else runs.
We can use a switch statement in a scenario like this where we're taking one value and we're just checking
it against multiple potential values.
So the syntax for switch is quite a bit different.
It looks like this switch and then the thing that we are checking.
So for us it would be de then we have our curly braces and then we have a bunch of cases.
So we would have case one meaning if DE is one.
And inside of that, we don't actually have to use curly braces.
We can console.log Monday and then we could have case to console.log Tuesday.
And let's just start with that.
So let's make a day to refresh the page and we get Tuesday, Tuesday.
As you can see here.
So I will flesh this out with the other days.
There we go.
So we have seven different cases when day is one due, this day is to do this three and so on.
I'll comment out the traditional conditional that we have up here.
There's a problem with our switch at the moment and you'll see it.
Day is set to two.
Let's see what we get when I refresh the page.
Oh, geez.
We got Tuesday, Wednesday, Thursday, Friday, Saturday, Sunday.
We got everything except Monday.
What if we change day to be?
Four.
Refresh the page now.
We get Thursday, Friday, Saturday, Sunday.
So that's kind of odd.
It's giving us every value after it matches.
So if cases four, it does this, it does this, it does this and this.
If case is one, it does all of them.
If Case is six or if day is six, we do this one and this one.
So the reason this happens, it's kind of annoying.
But what's happening here is that as soon as one of them matches in our case four.
So day is four.
This is true.
None of these other cases are tested and it's almost like it turns into this.
All of that code runs without checking for a case, so it's looking for the first match and then as
soon as it finds it, everything else runs.
And that seems like an odd choice.
And we'll talk about why that happens in a moment.
The way to fix this, if you only want one of these to run, is to add a break after each statement,
after each case.
So I'll make multiple cursors by holding option and clicking and then ad break after each one.
Now, if I refresh, I only get the correct day.
So if day is seven, I only get Sunday.
If day is one, I should only get Monday.
We still don't have our fallback.
So if we have something like nine, we had that else earlier.
We don't have an else.
The way we write the equivalent instead of else we write default and default will run at the end.
So we would have invalid day and now we get invalid day.
If we have seven, we get Sunday and it all works.
So this is odd, but this is still much easier to read.
It's a lot of lines, but it's much easier to read, in my opinion, than this.
We don't have to do all of these parents and the curly braces.
We don't have to check with triple equals over and over and over.
You can just look at this and pretty quickly understand what's going on.
If day is one, do this.
If day is four, do this.
As long as we have those breaks in there.
Now, why do we have those breaks?
I'm going to show you another example.
I'll comment this out for a moment.
So here's a second example.
We are taking an emoji.
It's just a text description of an emoji like Happy Face and printing out the corresponding colour or
the main colour.
So a happy face is yellow, a sad face is yellow, eggplant is purple, heart is red and lips are also
red.
So right now they're all going to run well.
Everything after we find a match.
So happy face gives us yellow, yellow, purple, red, red.
But if we add in our breaks, as we've seen, that fixes the problem.
But we do have some duplicated conflict logs.
We have multiple things that are red and we have multiple that are yellow.
We could rewrite this because of the way switch statements work, because of how they're structured.
We can combine certain cases and the way we do it looks like this.
Let's do happy face and sad face.
I'm just going to delete this entire thing here and put case sad face right here.
Case sad face right above happy face.
And I don't have any code coming after it.
So what happens here is that sad face could be a match.
Let's say it is.
This is true.
There's no break right here.
And because there's no break, it moves on and it runs this code and then it hits a break so we can
do the same thing for heart.
And lips will do case lips, and then we can remove what we had down below.
Right here.
So same thing.
If emoji is heart.
This is not true.
Not nope, this is true.
And then there's no code to run.
But there wasn't a break.
So then it just runs this code as we saw.
If you don't use a break after one of these cases, it's going to just run all the code that it sees.
So at this point, let's try it out.
We get yellow for sad face.
Let's do lips, we get red.
If we do heart, we should also get red.
We don't have a default on this one and that's fine.
Sometimes you don't, so that's pretty much it.
For switches, the syntax is definitely a little different.
But if you have one variable, one thing that you are checking against multiple values like we're doing
here, it's a nice and easy to understand way of writing that logic compared to doing a ton of else
ifs.
There's just a couple of gotchas, as you saw.
You need to make sure there's really just one you have to use break when it makes sense.
Sometimes it doesn't if you're trying to have multiple cases that correspond to the same piece of code
anyway, that switch.