All right.
Welcome back.
We've got a big section here.
It includes a couple of different topics by the end.
Our main goal is to make HTTP requests from JavaScript, from the client or from the browser.
So load data from an API send a request somewhere.
So very important stuff that you do all the time if you make single page apps.
And in the projects that we build later on, there's at least a couple of examples where we're working
with HTTP requests in the browser, but before we do that, we'll talk about promises and how we use
promises to manage asynchronous code and make our life easier.
But before we do that, we're going to talk about asynchronous code or async JavaScript, what it actually
means.
And in order to do that, we need to understand how JavaScript works behind the scenes.
At least we don't have to go crazy into detail, but we need to understand the basics.
So that's where we're going to start in this video.
We're going to talk about something called the call stack.
So the call stack is a tool or a feature of JavaScript.
It's also something you see in tons of other programming languages.
What it does is it helps JavaScript keep track of where it is in your code if you have multiple functions.
And some of those functions may call other functions, which often we have functions that call functions,
that call functions.
The call stack is the mechanism by which the JavaScript interpreter keeps track of its place.
It's how JavaScript knows which function is currently being run, which functions are not done yet,
what's waiting on results or return values?
You can kind of think of it as this diagram here.
If your script with a bunch of function calls is a massive book, the call stack is the bookmark or
your finger that you use to to figure out where you are to keep track of your current place.
And before we go into any more detail, let's talk about the stack part.
I think call in call stack makes some sense.
It has to do with function calls, which functions are being called, what is or what's been called,
what is waiting on a result to come back.
The stack part has to do with a data structure in computer science called a stack.
A stack is a very simple data structure.
All you need to know is that just like a stack of books on your your desk or a stack of plates on your
or in your sink, the last thing that you put in is going to be on top, and that will be the first
thing that you remove.
So the last thing that was added, the most recently placed item in our case, this apple on top will
be the first thing out.
You don't grab from the bottom of a stack of papers, you grab from the top the most recently added
thing to that stack.
And that's important because that's how the call stack works.
So we're going to walk through a simple example.
Here's what you need to know when a script has some number of function calls.
The very first function call that the JavaScript interpreter hits or reaches will be added to the call
stack.
That function will be carried out, and if there are any other function calls within that first function,
they will be added to the top of the call stack and that continues until one of those functions returns
a value, at which point it's removed from the stack, it's gone.
And then the function that came before it will hopefully finish.
Maybe there are some other function calls, in which case those are added to the top of the stack and
then removed or popped off as they complete.
I think this will become clear if we have an example.
So on the left I have a couple of different functions.
The first one is called is right triangle.
It accepts three different arguments A, B and C, three different numbers, and it should return true.
If A and B, if we square them and add them together, you get C squared, A squared plus B squared
equals C squared.
So if something is a right triangle, the third value here C would be the hypotenuse.
These two would be the other sides can't remember what they're called, but we have two sides on a triangle
and then the hypotenuse in a right triangle.
So nine would be three times three, 16 four times four and 25, five times five.
And that indeed would be a real right triangle.
Nine plus 16 does equal 25.
Okay, so is right triangle is not a function that just returns something immediately.
It needs to call other functions.
It's going to return if the square of a plus, the square of B is triple equals to the square of C,
so square of A needs to be called, and that in turn calls multiply x times x.
So we pass in three, multiply three times three, which is a different function, which returns two
values, the product of them.
So when the interpreter encounters the very first function, call is right triangle three, four, five.
It's added to the call stack, which is what I'm representing over here.
And we can't just get a value back immediately.
There are multiple function calls in here that happen first.
So square of a which is three in our case, square of three will be the first thing to be added to the
call stack, which is what this slide is.
A square of three does not return anything i.
It calls a different function.
Multiply three, comma three, which I'm showing here.
So then multiply is added to the stack.
So this function has not finished running.
This one has not finished.
This one doesn't call any other functions, so it returns three times three, which is nine.
And when it returns a value, it is removed from the stack.
The last thing in is the first thing out.
So then square of three now has a value back from Multiply, which was nine.
So it can return that value.
So it's popped off.
Now we end up with is right.
Triangle.
That's the current function that is being executed.
It's been waiting a while because those I mean a wireless relative, but it had to wait for two other
function calls to return.
So now you can kind of fill in the blank here.
The first part square of a square of three is nine.
We have a value, then it moves on.
All right.
Is there another function call?
Yep, there is square of four, which is B, so square of B, so square is added to the top of the call
stack.
And when I say top, it's not really a top and bottom situation, it's just a data structure.
Think of it kind of like an array, but much simpler.
But I'm just using top and bottom here to help explain visually what's going on.
Like a stack of books so square of four doesn't return a value right away.
At least it has to call multiply four, comma four.
So that's added to the top of the stack.
That does return a value x times y, four times four is 16 so that pops off the stack.
Then square of four now has a value for this.
It fills in that blank 16, which means that it's done because it returns 16 and then we fill in the
blank and is right triangle.
We now have this done, this done and then we have our triple equals square of C square of five.
So five is added to the call stack that doesn't return a value yet.
It has to figure out what multiply of five comma five is.
So that is the next function call added to the call stack that returns 25, which means that square
now has a value.
So both of those are popped off and then we end up with 25 here.
No more function calls now, just some simple math.
And actually the order here, it probably evaluates this first anyway, nine plus 16, it doesn't actually
matter here.
We're just talking about function calls, but we end up with nine plus 16 equals 25.
That is true.
So this function finally returns true, at least in this case and it is popped off the stack.
The call stack is empty, it returns true and we're done.
So that is a brief intro to the call stack.
In the next video, I'll show you an example of how you can actually see it using the DevTools, or
at least a representation of it with your own code.
And you can step through it step by step.
All right.
So let's do that next.