Okay.
So that was a brief intro to the call Steck.
Now I'd like to show you in the Chrome DevTools, you can actually take a look at the representation
of the call stack and step through it one call at a time.
So let's do it.
I have some simple code here, a function called make rant that I'm calling twice.
I'm passing in a string the rant text and then a place to append a new H one.
What it does is it makes a new empty h one.
Then it sets the inner text to the result of a function called get rant text.
Get rant text is going to call two different functions.
The first one is scream, which uppercase is it and add some exclamation points.
Then another function I call repeat.
Yes, there is a built in string repeat these days, but for this example I'm not using it.
I wanted a couple other functions on the stack, so then it calls repeat, which takes that scream,
the uppercase version of whatever we pass in.
So let's say we started with Go Away.
That's our phrase we pass in.
It's going to call scream, which will give us go away with three exclamation points.
And then if I call repeat, which I am here, get rant text repeats it eight times we end up with a
string that looks like this.
Whoops.
Eight of those.
Then we take that and create ah1 which we actually already created.
We add that as the inner text and append it to whatever element we pass in.
So it's just a dumb demo.
It's not something you probably would do, but this is what we end up with over here.
I have two h ones.
I hate mayonnaise.
Very true.
I hate mayonnaise so much.
Oh, my gosh.
I just.
I feel queasy, even just writing the word, let alone seeing it eight times here.
That's coming from Mac rant.
I just passed in the string and a place to append the new element.
And then here's the second one.
If you have to cough, please cover your mouth.
It's also being appended here.
Let's take a look at just one.
So it will make it a little easier when we step through the call stack.
So I'm going to open up the Chrome DevTools and go to the Sources tab and in the Sources tab.
I'll pretend that was closed.
If we open up this navigator on the left side for me, go to our file with the code.
So JJ's is the name of my file.
Whatever you named yours.
What we do is add in a breakpoint on the left.
I can actually click.
So if I click in here, I can make some changes and play around with them.
But if I click on the number to the left of one of those function calls, it will actually insert a
breakpoint.
It will pause execution of our code when it encounters this.
So all of this code will run first.
If I were to add in a console.log console.log.
Hello and refresh the page.
Well, I'm an idiot.
It goes away.
Of course.
I just said that if I do a console.log here.
Hello, this will run first before we encounter that breakpoint.
If I look at my console, we get.
Hello notice though I don't see anything over here.
It says, paused in debugger, and I have this little alert over here that says paused on Breakpoint.
So because I clicked there, it paused.
If I click and refresh, it doesn't pause anymore.
But if I click and I refresh the page, there we go.
Okay.
So let's see what we can do.
On the left side, we have a tab or a piece called Call Stack.
This is where we'll see a representation of the call stack.
And if we just walk through this first on our own, we'll zoom in a bit and can zoom in.
Okay, I'll close the sidebar.
Make rant is going to be called there's no function calls aside from make rant so far.
So make rant will be added to the call stack.
Then make rant itself calls document create element is a built in function or a method that won't appear
on the call stack really.
But our first function we defined is get rant text.
So get rant text is over here that calls scream.
So scream will run and return something.
Then we get to rant and that's returned.
We have text, then repeat is called with that value.
So repeat is going to run.
So let's just play around with it.
I'm going to click over here on this.
There's also a shortcut, but to make it easier for you to see when I'm actually advancing, I'll just
click.
So keep your eye here where it says Call Stack.
Okay.
So make rant was added to the call stack.
It's not done executing.
Otherwise it would be off and it can't be done.
It has to do some other stuff first.
So the first thing it did was evaluate this document, create element.
Then we get to this line.
Get rant text.
So you'll see.
Get rant text is now added to the call stack.
And if I look at any of these at any point, if I click at make click on make rant, you can see it's
kind of hard to show here, but this is the information, the values that are in current in the scope
of make rant.
So phrase is set to I hate mayonnaise.
That's the argument we passed in.
We also have element which is the body which I passed in down here and now this h one variable is this
h one element that we created with document create element.
So then instead of get rant text, we have a variable text, but it's not set to anything yet.
If I move forward again, we'll see.
Scream added to the top of the call stack.
There it is.
So make rant started, but it's not done.
It can't finish until get rant text comes back.
That can't finish until scream comes back.
We're in scream right now.
Scream just not call any other functions aside from returning string to uppercase.
So you'll see if I advanced again.
Scream is up top advanced and it's gone.
Scream has been removed.
It finished executing in a return to value which we now have here.
Text has value.
I hate mayonnaise, all uppercase with three exclamation points that came from Scream.
Then next line rant the variable let rant equals repeat of text.
This is text that variable.
So repeat this eight times.
So repeat is going to be added.
That's our next function.
You'll see it added to the stack.
There it is.
So get ready.
Text is still waiting.
Make rant is still waiting on get rant.
Text which is waiting on repeat.
So repeat is then going to loop.
I'll skip through this.
So we have results which is completely built at this point.
The loop is over.
We're now at return result.
So result is I hate mayonnaise.
Uppercase exclamation points repeated eight times in a single string that is returned.
So the contents of the function don't really matter.
In these examples, I just want you to pay attention to the call stack itself.
Watch when things are added and when they're removed.
So return results.
Repeat should be removed.
And there we go.
So now get rant.
Text has all those function calls.
It has returned values from them.
It's done and it's ready.
It's not done yet, but it's ready to return.
Rant So it waited first to get scream, then scream came back and it waited to get repeat, then repeat,
return to value.
So now it can return that value.
So it's going to return and get rant text will be removed.
There it goes.
Goodbye.
Now we're back in make rant.
The original function call that has been waiting patiently this whole time.
So you can kind of see where I was going with this.
Where are you?
This idea here of a finger in a book to keep track of where you are.
It's kind of the same idea, maybe.
I don't know if that's a good analogy or not, but it's kind of the same idea.
This function was originally added to the stack a while ago, but it couldn't finish until a bunch of
other function calls ran.
And this is a simple example.
Often you'll end up with some functions that have a whole bunch of function calls which call other functions.
And then recursion is a whole other issue, which we're not going to get into at this point.
But just know that this is a simple demo.
Most of the time your apps are going to have many more functions on the call stack at any given point,
or they could at least.
So make rant is now ready to append element that append child.
There is no return statement and make rant.
So there we go.
We get to the last line.
It's showing me this here.
So make rant will be removed from the call stack and because this element that append child h one ran
we now have the text showing up our new element on the screen.
So I'll step through it and it's gone.
It's completely off the call stack, which means that this function call here is done.
It finished.
That was the original starting point.
Now the interpreter has moved on to this line and there's nothing after it.
It's just done.
And there we go.
We made it through.
So that is how you can use the dev tools to step through step by step.
Each function call on the call stack and see what's going on.
And this can be useful if things are just behaving very oddly.
It's also a nice way if you had a breakpoint somewhere for you to just take a look at the values at
any given point, play around with the variables in there, see?
See what's going on, diagnose your problems.
But the main reason I brought it up here was just to make it clear how the call stack works.
This idea of the latest function call to be added to the stack, that function call will be the first
to be removed and you end up with this pile up of functions that are function calls that maybe are waiting
on a bunch of other function calls to finish, which themselves might be waiting in other function calls.
And eventually one of them has to finish and return something.
So that sort of a reverse cascade can happen.
The functions that were waiting will hopefully return, which continues all the way down to our original
function call, which was make rant.
So why are we talking about this?
Why do you need to know about it?
Well, it's going to help explain and help you understand how asynchronous code works in JavaScript,
which is what we're going to tackle right now.
Well, next video right after this.