Okay.
So we talked about the call stack.
Put that aside for just a moment.
Next, we need to address a fundamental characteristic of JavaScript as a language.
JavaScript is a single threaded language.
If you don't know what that means, don't worry.
All that it really means is that at any given point in our script, whatever script is being executed,
JavaScript is running one thing at a time.
It's it's not multitasking.
It does one thing.
There's a really good blog post.
I think it's on the Google, one of the official Google developer blogs talking about asynchronous JavaScript
that humans are multithreaded.
You know, if you can fold the laundry while watching TV or talking to your friend or whatever it is,
but humans are single threaded in one very specific case, according to this blog post, which is When
we sneeze, no one can do anything else except sneeze.
So when you're sneezing, that's the one thing you're focused on.
So back to JavaScript at any given point, one thing is being run at a time and this has a whole bunch
of implications.
But let me just demonstrate it first.
If we do something extremely simple, we console that log.
I happened first and then a different contact log.
I happen seconds.
And if we alert in the middle.
Alert.
Hi there.
And I run this code.
What will we see in our console when I refresh the page?
Well, let's refresh it.
There we go.
I get the alert.
We open up the console.
I won't even let me open it.
Well.
Well, let's try it one more time.
I'm going to refresh.
We get.
I happen first and then.
Hi there.
And it just stops.
This alert is blocking everything else from going on until the user finishes it or completes it, at
which point JavaScript moves on to the next line.
So that's as simple example, but here you can tell JavaScript is doing one thing when it's alerting,
it's not continuing to console.log.
Or if we had math after this or a different function call, it's not going to move on.
And that seems like it could be a severe limitation if we do things that take time, if we do things
that aren't immediate, we don't want to just have a user sit there waiting and have no other code running.
But as you've probably seen already, we have a way around this and we'll get to that in just a moment.
But here's a simple example of something that we do via JavaScript all the time.
We send a request from the browser.
We write some JavaScript code asking for, let's say, data from a movie API that takes time.
It goes sends a request to a server.
That server may or may not be online.
We may have a valid endpoint, we may not.
But even if everything goes great, it still takes time.
The server will respond to your request.
If we're looking for movies that match the query bat bat, it will search through its database, find
the relevant information, and then send a response back.
Bates Motel and Batman in this case again, this takes time.
It can be very slow.
So what happens to our application?
Does it just stop and nothing else happens?
Like what we had over here, where this alert potentially takes a long time for a user to finish, a
user may not notice it.
I mean, even if it's just a split second, your code is just doing nothing right now.
Is this what happens when we make a request, when we are fetching data from an API, when we're trying
to save data to an API, any time we do some sort of single page app functionality which usually involves
communicating with an API, communicating with a database or a server that takes time.
Is our app just going to sit there doing nothing?
And as a user, just going to sit there waiting for something to happen?
The answer is no.
How does that work and why not?
That's what we're going to answer in the next video.
JavaScript has a couple of tricks up its sleeve, or rather the browser has some tricks up its sleeve
to get around this single threaded ness of JavaScript.
So to summarize what we saw here in JavaScript at any given point, JavaScript itself is running at
most one line of code.
So it's not multitasking, it's not doing three things at once.
It's doing one thing at a time or nothing.
If it's not doing anything.
It's very important to understand that so that you can better understand the workaround we have, which
we're talking about right after this.