Okay.
So we establish that JavaScript is single threaded.
That means it's doing one thing at a time, like a human sneezing.
A human does one thing which is sneezing.
It's very, very difficult to also talk while you sneeze or eat.
Why you sneeze.
Although I guess I have been driving and sneeze and I continue to drive.
But I basically just prayed that I wouldn't crash because all I could do is sneeze.
So JavaScript does one thing at a time.
As we mentioned in the last video, a lot of the time we do things that take a lot of time.
That's a bad sentence.
Commonly, we do a lot of things that take time, whether it's getting data from a database or an API
or trying to save something or even just set a timer.
How how does something like a timer work in JavaScript?
So here's a simple example.
This is not exactly full code that would work.
I've made up a function called save to database, but imagine we're doing something like this, a user
type, something into a form it submits.
We want to grab value from the form, save it to a database, and that could take a couple of seconds.
It could take half a second.
It could go really fast.
It could take 10 seconds and fail.
Does this line just not run until this finishes?
Well, we have a workaround.
We've seen this a couple of times before.
We've actually seen it a lot for these processes, processes that take time.
We pass a callback function and those functions will be executed at the appropriate time after this
interval has passed in the case of a set timeout.
But this doesn't really answer the question of how does it work or why does it work?
We know that this does work.
Set time out for 3 seconds.
We'll wait 3 seconds before running this code, but how is JavaScript going to know?
How does it set a timer for 3 seconds if it can only do one thing at a time?
That is what we're going to talk about here.
If we go back to this example where we had our first console.log and then the alert blocked everything
else, JavaScript is fully focused on the alert until it's gone.
Then we move on to the next console.log.
Why?
If I replace this with a set timeout pass in some function where we console.log?
I happen?
Third and then an interval or a delay.
3 seconds, 3000 milliseconds.
Why does this work?
It seems like it shouldn't.
Like nothing different is really happening.
Except we're passing in some some function to be called later.
But based off of what I've told you, it seems like this should run.
Then JavaScript encounters this line which says Set a timer for 3 seconds.
That should just take up JavaScript full capacity to focus on anything.
It should just be setting a timer.
How can JavaScript keep track of 3 seconds and remember to do this or call this function while also
moving on to this console.log?
Remember that is printed out immediately and then 3 seconds later this is going to print out.
So if I have other code down here, I could have a whole bunch of other stuff that's all going to run.
Assuming that it doesn't take more than 3 seconds that will run before this doesn't seem like it should
be able to work.
It seems like JavaScript should have to focus entirely on keeping track of 3 seconds and knowing when
to actually execute this.
But we have a workaround.
The trick here is that the browser does the work.
JavaScript is not the same thing as your browser.
JavaScript is a language that is implemented in your browser, but the browser itself, like Chrome,
Safari, even Internet Explorer, are a good friend.
When I say good friend, I mean worst enemy.
Those browsers are written in usually C++, a different programming language, and the browser itself
is capable of doing certain tasks that JavaScript sucks at or things that take time they're handed off
to the browser.
So JavaScript says, Here is this thing I need you to do.
For me, the browser takes over and then when it's done it reminds JavaScript.
Okay, your turn again.
So this is a really key thing to understand.
JavaScript is not setting a timer or keeping track of how many seconds have gone by.
JavaScript is not sending a request to an API, the browser actually handles it.
And this is something that honestly, I went a long time without understanding about JavaScript and
it's not crucial to being able to make a request or use set timeout.
You've already done that in this course, but I think it helps a lot to understand why we use callbacks
and why we get to things like promises and async functions.
So browsers have a set of these APIs called just generally web APIs, and they can handle certain tasks
in the background, like making a request that takes time, set time out, which we saw here, that
takes time.
The browser is capable of doing those things in the background.
So JavaScript is going to encounter certain lines of code like this line.
JavaScript knows how to do that, then it gets to set timeout and it's going to pass it off to the browser
and say, Please remind me after 3 seconds has elapsed or Hey browser, you set this timer for me and
when you're done, give me this function back.
So that's why we pass a callback.
It just keeps plowing along.
It hands this off to the browser.
The browser is in charge of keeping time, and then it reminds JavaScript, Hey, here's that thing
I want you to do, or you wanted me to remind you of so JavaScript doesn't get hung up.
It's single thread isn't blocked by this set timeout because it's passed off to something entirely different.
It's passed off to the browser.
Then that callback function in the case of set timeout when it's time when 3 seconds has elapsed, the
browser is going to take that function, the one that just console.log something and put it on the call
stack.
So this is where the call stack comes back in.
So let's take a closer look with some diagrams here.
We have similar code, I think different text.
I print first, I print second.
So what I had.
Okay, I capitalized it here.
It doesn't matter.
So JavaScript is represented by this JavaScript logo.
It's going to encounter this line.
The interpreter sees this line.
It knows how to handle it.
Can't stop log.
I print first.
It runs that.
Then it gets to set.
Timeout.
Set.
Timeout is something that the browser will do for us or it will do for JavaScript.
So this is my personification a browser.
Can you set a timer for 3 seconds?
The browser says sure thing.
So remember this is separate from JavaScript.
This is the browser itself setting a timeout, keeping track of 3000 milliseconds.
So then JavaScript is free to continue on.
It doesn't have anything in its call stack that has to do with set timeout.
Instead it moves on to console.log.
I print second so it prints that out and there's a little time icon over here that signifies 3 seconds
have elapsed.
Now the browser says Time's Up JavaScript.
Make sure you run that callback now and it places the callback.
This function right here.
I use an arrow function in this example, I just use a regular function expression here.
It places that function back in the call stack.
So JavaScript knows, oh, I need to do this thing.
So JavaScript is not keep the time.
Same thing with making a request.
JavaScript does not make the request itself, the browser and its web APIs handle.
They manage all of that and they simply tell JavaScript.
They add to the call stack when it's appropriate.
Here's the next thing for you to do.
So JavaScript then now has a new function in the call stack and it executes it and it console.log.
I print after 3 seconds, so understanding this relationship will help a lot.
Once we get to promises and actually making requests, JavaScript can only do one thing at a time.
It's single threaded, but in special cases, when we are doing things like setting a timeout, requesting
data or adding an event listener to whatever it div in ly JavaScript isn't going to sit there and just
listen non-stop to see if something's been clicked that's handed off to the browser.
And the browser is in charge of deciding when to actually add a new callback or a function to the call
stack for JavaScript to execute.
Here's this really cool website I found that helps explain how this all works so you can type code over
here.
If you do play around with this, it's called loop.
It doesn't work well or it doesn't work at all if you use arrow functions or any of the newer JavaScript
syntax.
So just stick to some basic stuff.
But here's what it does.
It actually slows down or mimics the execution and what happens behind the scenes with JavaScript and
the handoff to Web APIs, which is what this box over here represents.
Here's the call stack, here's web APIs.
So JavaScript is going to encounter this line.
The Interpreter It can run this immediately and it will console that log.
Hi everyone.
Then it hit set timeout and you'll see visually that the web API takes over and you'll see visually
that the set timeout, the interval or the delay is being kept.
Track of over here for 7 seconds is what this one is set to.
And then another set timeout.
This one for 3 seconds will also be handled over here.
And in the meantime, JavaScript will move on.
If I add in, let's do at least one more console.log.
Console.log by for real everyone JavaScript moves on to this and then when the browser the web API is
over here decide or calculate that the time is is up 7 seconds or 3 seconds.
They add the callback here, not directly to the call stack, they add it to something called the callback
queue.
We don't have to get too far into the weeds here, but essentially this is a place where callbacks are
added and JavaScript will draw upon this queue.
It's a way of JavaScript to know, okay, what's something that I need to do next that is coming back
from the Web APIs.
So let's see what happens when I click Save and Run, I'll pause first thing call stack now has one
function call console.log.
Hi everyone.
Simple enough so it does that.
Now it gets to this set timeout function that is added to the call stack.
But JavaScript realizes, oh, this is one of those things I can hand off to the browser so it doesn't
take charge of this.
It hands it to web API.
The web API is.
There you go.
So it doesn't run the code.
It doesn't run the callback.
Oh, I just broke it.
Okay, let me pause again at the right moment.
There we go.
There's a timeout that is being kept track of over here and JavaScript moves on to the next line, which
is another set timeout.
So the same thing happens.
It's added to the call stack for a moment.
JavaScript then passes it off to the web APIs and says, okay, when that interval or that delay is
over, give me that callback back and I'll execute it at the right time.
So we resume JavaScript moves on to these two consort logs.
There's the first one, the second one they both run, and then the 3/2 timeout finished.
Now there's only one over here, the 7/2 one, the 3/2 one finished and it added the web API added that
callback here, which is supposed to console.log.
Oink, oink.
It added that to the callback queue, which JavaScript will now draw upon and you'll see that it.
Oh, did I now click resume.
There we go.
Those functions are then executed one at a time.
They both console.log and we're done.
So let's do it one more time.
Just quickly, I won't pause.
You can see the web APIs take control of those timers.
JavaScript moves on.
It has one thread, it keeps going and then it draws upon that callback queue.
When the web APIs have placed one of those functions in the callback queue, that relationship is very
important to understand.
So let's pause and now I'll have my console open so you can just see the whole thing as they get printed.
So we get hi everyone.
Then the next line which will be by everyone, then by for real everyone.
Then that first callback, the 3/2 one is added to the queue.
We get oink, oink and then the 7/2 interval or time out finishes so we get mu.
So I'll stop here.
Like I said, this is a very fundamental part of JavaScript.
This is why we use callbacks all the time.
This is how we get around the fact that JavaScript is not a multitasker.
It does one thing at a time.
So when we pass a function as an argument, as a callback function to things like set timeout, which
the web API is handle, those functions are not called right away.
JavaScript doesn't worry about it.
JavaScript just passes it off and continues on its merry way until the web API is at some point place
that function in the callback queue where JavaScript then draws upon and says, Oh, okay, you want
me to do this thing?
I guess it's time.
So it does not do the hard work of keeping track of time, it doesn't do the hard work of making a request.
And that's why we use callbacks so frequently for these asynchronous things, these these functions
that take time.
And I need to make that clear because now we're going to go more into async JS We'll talk about how
we make requests and that takes a lot of time.
And sometimes it sucks to write a ton of callbacks, which is where promises come in.
So this has been setting the stage.
I think it's very important to do.
I have taut promises and async functions without really going into detail of how this works.
But I think this will help.
I hope and please leave some feedback if you think I'm just confusing you or it's not really relevant
because you absolutely can learn this stuff without understanding what the web APIs are and the call
stack.
But I think it will help.
Maybe.
So let me know.
All right.
I'll be quiet.
And next, we'll move on to talking more about callbacks, some of the problems with having a bunch
of callbacks and how we can get around them with promises.