All right.
Welcome back.
So we saw why callbacks are so important in JavaScript.
We passed a callback in to certain functions that the browser takes over things like set timeout, set
interval.
Also, when we make requests different ways of making requests we haven't really covered yet.
The browser takes care of that and we pass in a callback.
But callbacks are not perfect.
They can get messy very quickly, which is what I want to show you here.
I'm going to show you a way of doing something with callbacks, and then we'll see how to refactor it
using promises.
So this is finally the ramp up to promises.
Let's write a simple function that will take a number of pixels and move our button over that number
of pixels, and it will do it after a delay.
So we could do like after a second, move it after another second, move it and so on.
So I'm going to start by selecting the button.
It's the only button on the page.
So const BTN equals document, query, selector button.
Then all we're going to do is change button style.
I'll do it with Transform this time.
I think a couple at some point in the course I did button that style that left in top, which is not
really the most performant way of changing position or moving an element around.
Transform is better.
And if you're curious why I have a YouTube video, you can check out on it.
It's called the only two CSS properties you Should Animate.
The short story is that when you transform something, it happens much later.
In the browser's rendering process, it's much easier for the browser to move something via transform
rather than changing left, which causes a render of a lot of different things anyway.
So I'm just going to do this.
We'll move it left to right.
So I'll just do translate X and pass in a number like 100 pixels and let's just make sure it's moving.
Okay.
So now I want to do this inside of a set timeout.
So it only happens after, let's say 1/2.
So set timeout and then I'll pass in a function.
Just do an arrow function here.
My duration will be 1000 milliseconds and I'll move this right there.
So now I refresh, it should start on the left and then 1/2 later it moves.
That works great.
Now, if I wanted to wait another second and then move again, maybe 200 pixels this time or some other
number, I would need to nest that function.
Call the set timeout inside of this set timeout.
Otherwise if I just have a second set timeout, I mean, I guess you could do this and just keep track
of the number of seconds, but this is not ideal.
We'll see an expanded version of what we're doing now or this wouldn't work.
But yes, technically, if you want this to run after 1/2 and this to run a second later, you could
do 2000 milliseconds, but we're not going to do that.
So in here we add another set timeout, same thing we add in our callback, our duration.
Let's do 1000 seconds or let's do 2000 milliseconds.
So 2 seconds and then this same line, I'll just duplicate it and I need to change what we're translating
it to.
Let's do 200 pixels.
So I'll refresh the second.
It moves another 2 seconds.
It should move again.
Cool.
And I could keep duplicating this.
I just have to keep nesting if I want to make sure that this is happening after this happens.
So we have our first set timeout for 1000 milliseconds.
It does this and then as soon as that happens, it sets another timeout for 2000 milliseconds.
And then again, let's just do 1000 for each of these.
Let's translate 300 pixels.
This isn't so bad because it's such a short thing that we're doing, but it is a lot of nesting.
To achieve this, let's go five levels deep.
Okay, so now I have five different set timeouts.
All of them.
1/2 long.
Let's go.
One, two, three, 400 pixels and 500 pixels.
Let's check it out.
It should move across the screen 100 pixels at a time, 1/2 at a time.
Okay.
So this is relatively readable.
It's not too bad.
It's kind of obnoxious to have to keep nesting them.
But that's not this is not as bad as it will get, let's put it that way.
So if I want to rewrite this as a function, I'm doing kind of the same thing every time.
If I want to make this a separate function, I could call.
What I need to do is first define my function and come up with a reasonable name.
Let's call this move left.
No, move right.
I would just move X because then we could pass in a negative number to go the other direction.
We'll do element the thing that is moving.
So our button an amount and then a delay.
And then we'll do a set timeout.
And then in here our function, we'll put the delay right here.
So that will be some number we passed in like 1000.
And then instead of buttons, that style that transform it will be element style, dot transform equals
and then a string.
I'll do a string template literal translate X and then I'll put in my amount that was passed in and
then follow it by pixels just like that.
So if I comment this out and I just call this one time, move X of button, let's go with 600 pixels.
So 600 and after 2 seconds.
Let's see if it works.
So 2 seconds go by.
Okay, it does move.
Now, here's the tricky part.
If I want to then replicate this behavior where we could have something happen after this or after the
delay immediately after we change the transform, I want another set timeout.
It doesn't really help me if I just manually set it here.
What we would do instead is pass in a callback, so we would write our function to accept a callback.
We could call it callback.
And then all we do is execute that callback function inside the set timeout.
After we do this, we call the callback same idea that we have here.
But now what we need to do is pass in a callback.
So we would pass in a function.
I'll do an arrow function.
Whoops.
Like this.
And we'll just call move x again button.
Let's go 100 pixels.
This time we'll replicate the same behavior.
So 1/2, another 200 pixels after 1/2.
Let's just see if that works.
We will run into an issue with what I have here because I haven't passed it in a callback so we could
do something simple like if callback
and let's see what happens.
It appears to work right.
So we did 100 pixels and then 200 pixels after a second and we could pass in yet another callback if
we want to continue to change chain these.
So move x button.
Let's go for 300 pixels 1/2 and let's actually do four or five levels button and then 400 pixels, 1000
milliseconds and one last one move x button.
500 pixels, 1000 milliseconds, no callback.
Here we go.
There we go.
Keep moving.
Awesome.
Okay, so we wrote a function here that accepts a callback and a delay.
It does something after that delay inside the set timeout.
That delay is variable right now.
They're all the same, and then it executes a callback.
If we pass one in and our callbacks are these arrow functions.
So this is one callback, this entire thing here, from here.
From this curly brace to this curly brace.
Nope.
This curly brace.
To this curly brace.
That is the callback for this first move x.
So this entire thing from this yellow curly brace down to here is the first callback for move x.
The first time we call move x.
That function, call those per ends go all the way down.
Right.
This is our initial function call and then we have our callback in there and then that itself calls
move x and then that has a massive callback.
All this nesting, it's still not that horrible because we're just doing one thing.
Each time you can look at it, it makes it clear you're doing this, then this, then this.
But here's where it's going to get trickier.
Let's rewrite our function so that we check if the element is going to go off the screen.
And if it does go off the screen, we can do something else, maybe reverse it or just console.log or
just stop.
We won't do anything.
And this is a really common pattern.
When we're working with asynchronous code, often we'll send, let's say, an HTTP request.
The term is request for a reason.
We're attempting something.
We're asking for a web page.
We may get some successful response or the server might be down.
We might have an invalid URL.
Your Internet might be down at home or on the computer.
So it's a request.
And that request, let's just say this was the name of a function to make a request whoops out of complete
there.
That request will accept two callbacks, a success callback and a failure callback so you can have two
different branches if the request works out.
Here's the code that runs.
If the request does not work, here is the code that runs the code to handle an error, for example.
So why don't we mimic that functionality here for move x instead of just moving no matter what?
Let's check if we are going to move off the screen and if that's the case, we won't do this.
We won't call the callback, we won't move further, we'll do something else.
We'll pass in a potential fallback or an error callback.
So I'm going to rewrite this here.
The logic to check if we're moving off the screen is not that important to what I'm showing you here.
But basically we want to get the width of the screen document up, body dot, client width and we'll
save this to a variable, let's call it const boundary, body boundary or something.
Then I'll show you a new method we haven't seen before.
There is something called get bounding client rect.
Let's test it out first in the browser.
So I have a button right here.
It's moved already.
I won't refresh the page if I call up that button variable and I call them zoom in here button get bounding
client rect which is a method for rectangle rect get rect.
Here we go.
It returns this object.
It's called a dom rect and dom rectangle and it tells us information about this element so we can see
it's width 225 pixels 0.875.
We can see its right let's see.
733 is that correct?
Let's try moving it further.
So let's do the same thing.
Why don't we on our last step, why don't we move 600 pixels over?
So instead of 400 we should be 600 or instead of 500, I mean, we'll go 600.
So currently it's at seven 33.875.
If we refresh and let it let it do its thing, just wait here.
Kill some time.
Let's see what we get now for the right.
The right is now 833.875.
And if we call move x again button, we'll move 800 pixels and let's 1/2 is fine.
No callback we wait 1/2.
Now let's look at our get bounding client rect right is 1033 and what is our entire width right now
of the body document dot body dot clients width not height but with 1132.
So we're close.
What we want to do is compare those to the right.
If we're going to the right, at least we're just worrying about moving to the right.
So we'll check if the right is greater than or equal to this boundary here, which we already have document
dot, body, client width, and that will change depending on the screen and if I have the console open.
So it's not just the dimensions of the screen itself.
We've seen this before.
Client width is going to update.
Okay.
So let's grab that variable, get bounding client rect and we want dot.
Right?
So let's save this const L right element.
Right.
And let's rewrite our function before we go any further so that we don't have to pass in this absolute
number.
For example, 100, then 200 and 304 hundred.
What if I could just say move 100 and then another 100, then another 100.
And this would put us at 300 pixels to the right of the initial position.
We would need to update this ever so slightly.
So I'll just comment that out for now, for amount.
We can keep that the same, but instead of just setting translate X to be that amount, we can calculate
the current transform or the current position on the screen and then add to that whatever amount is
passed in and use that to translate.
So the current amount, if we want to find that, is right here.
If we use get bounding client rect, we have the let's see left is 808.
And then we have a little bit of I believe it was margin or padding that added eight pixels.
It doesn't matter.
We're not going to be super precise.
I don't really care if this is going to be incredibly accurate.
I don't want to get too bogged down.
So let's use this left.
So whatever the left is, well then add another 100 or 200, whatever the amount is we're trying to
move.
I'll make a new variable.
I'll get the left and save that to a variable called Current Left.
Then here I'll just translate x to amount plus current left.
So now when I call this, I hopefully can just say move 100 pixels at a time.
It's easier.
You don't have to keep track of if you've moved 100, then you want to move 200.
If you want to move another 100, you have to add it together and do 300.
Now I can just say 100 every time or 200 every time or mix it up.
But I don't have to know how far we've already moved.
Okay, so translate x.
Let's just.
Let's see if it works.
Refresh the page.
It's working.
It's moving 100 pixels every time.
So now we can go back to checking if we've gone too far or if we're going to go too far.
We have our boundary.
We have the current right of the element.
And what we want to do is check if that right.
Plus, let's say we're moving 100 pixels, if another hundred pixels to the right is going to be too
far and we'll be off the screen, then we don't want to move.
So we could write a simple conditional if element, right?
Plus the amount we're trying to move is greater than the body boundary.
What do we want to do?
Why don't we start with just conflict logging done?
And I apparently cannot type greater than.
Oh.
Console.log.
Done.
Can't.
Go.
Oops, double quotes there.
Cannot go that far.
Else.
We need the else.
Otherwise, we'll just print this out and then run our code anyway.
So let's add an else.
We'll do the set time out down here.
Oh, boy.
Okay.
So we try and move 100 pixels every time.
And if it's too far, like if I do the last one and try and move 500 pixels, let's see.
We should move four times.
To three four.
Oh, well, I'm an idiot.
I moved the screen.
Let's try and move 1000 pixels.
That should be enough for it to trigger.
So, 100.
100.
And now we try and move.
1000.
Perfect.
Cannot go that far.
Let's try one more time.
And it doesn't move us any further.
That's it.
Okay, so that is working.
We now have this situation where we don't move anymore.
Otherwise we do the set time out and everything else and we call a callback.
Now let's go back to this idea of having a success and a failure callback so I could pass in.
Here's what I want you to do.
If we can keep moving.
If we can't move anymore.
For example, I could reset the position if we've gone all the way to the right.
Or I could just alert something the way that we would structure this.
And this is how a lot of older JavaScript libraries are actually written.
They have two callbacks you pass in, so your request or whatever you're doing, oh, my gosh, I don't
complete here.
Here we go.
And you pass in your success callback, which you wouldn't write like this, and then a fail callback.
So those are two functions as arguments.
So you would have your first function, do something and then your second function do something else.
So let's try it.
Let's rewrite this.
So we have our first callback.
Let's call this on success and on failure or on fail.
So down here, if we've made it to this point, that means we can keep moving.
So we'll call if on success, which I guess we can just assume our code.
Let's just assume that it will be passed in just to make our code simpler.
We'll do on success right there.
And on failure.
We'll be right in here.
So now we have two branching paths.
You try and move a certain number of pixels.
If that number is two too big of a gap to jump and you'll be off screen, this element will be off the
screen.
We'll call the on failure callback.
Otherwise, we'll actually do that movement after some delay that you pass in and then call your on
success callback.
So now we have to rewrite this whole thing to have two callbacks every time.
So I'm going to leave the original and I'll call Move X of our button.
Let's move 100 pixels the first time after 1/2, 1000 milliseconds.
This is our success callback.
If we're successful, we'll do something.
So I'll just write success.
Then we have to add our second callback here.
So a whole other function.
And this is if you cannot move, if this is too big of a jump to try and make, what do we want to do?
Why don't we start with a simple alert?
Cannot move further.
Okay.
And so then if we're successful, we'll do another move X this time.
Why don't we move 400 pixels after 1/2?
Here's our success callback.
We'll do something.
If success, I'll label these success and then we have to add a fail callback to this function call.
And already it's getting quite messy.
So this would be our fail for the second callback or for the second attempt.
And here's our fail for the very first move x.
So fail here we'll do the exact same alert cannot move further.
And if I say if it gets all formatted funky, but this is a lot to just follow and try and read with
your human eyes.
It's really not pretty.
And this is only two levels so far.
Just adding in that second callback really complicates things.
This is relatively easy to look at and understand this happens then after this callback will happen,
then this callback here when we have two callbacks at a time, we pass it in.
It's just clunky and ugly.
Okay, so move X button.
Let's see.
Here's our success.
Let's do one more move x.
So if we move 100 pixels, we're still good.
This calls or this is called, we try and move 400 pixels if we're still good.
This function is called otherwise this fail is called so move x this time let's do button something
very large like 700 pixels.
That should do it for us.
At least if I shrink my screen down and then after a second again, here's our success callback, we'll
just console.log.
Really, we still have screen left or something like that.
And then we pass in our failure callback here.
And this one will just alert, cannot move further.
Oh, boy.
I mean, look at this.
This is nasty to look at.
But let's just see if it works.
So we every single time we call Move X, we're now passing in two callbacks, the one to call if things
work and we can move the one to call.
If we can't move that far, we'll be moving off screen.
And then as soon as we start nesting them, it just grows into this absolute spaghetti mess.
So let's try it.
I'm going to refresh my page.
Okay.
So it actually did work.
But when I'm when I hit enter and close this alert, you'll see what it's kind of behaving oddly or
it might seem like it's behaving oddly.
This is because of our set timeout and what's happening.
If we go back, we're moving 100 pixels, then 400 and then 700 if we can.
But because this code is running right away, we're not doing it in the set timeout.
It seems like we're stopping too soon, but as you saw here, it stops or it appears to stop.
But I hit enter.
It still moves.
So that alert is actually coming from this move.
When we moved over here, we could fix this problem if we move our conditional into the set timeout
just to run through what's happening here, we're moving 100 pixels, but when we move 100 pixels,
we're starting by checking.
Can we continue to move?
All right.
We can.
So we don't run this and we set a timeout.
This timeout takes 1/2.
If we pass in 1000 milliseconds, it takes 1000 milliseconds for it to run and then call on success.
But as soon as that on success is called, this code runs immediately.
This is not part of the 1000 millisecond delay for the next time around.
It's happening at the very beginning of the function.
So we could rewrite this by moving this code into our set timeout.
This isn't necessarily the best way of designing this.
It might be better just a short circuit and just check as soon as possible if we can't move further.
But this will make it easier to see when it's working for us.
So now we're doing basically running the code at the exact same time.
We're checking if we can go and we're calling failure.
If we can't go, we're calling success if we can move and we're doing it all within the set timeout.
So now it moves, it moves again and then it says, okay, I can't keep going.
So we had the same outcome last time.
It just was alerting us before we had actually moved.
Okay, so this is looking great.
It works, right?
It's stopping when it should if I expand my screen all the way over here.
Let's see.
It now should be able to make that jump.
And now we get really we still have screen left, which is our success for our third move.
So you can see this is quite ugly and this is only three moves.
But we had here was five moves.
So why don't I take a second to recreate this?
I won't make you watch.
I'll just do it really quickly.
And through the magic of editing, it will be done.
There you go.
So I decided to change it to 300 pixel jumps, because I know some of you will have wider screens or
you won't have your console open like I have here.
So I wanted to make sure in most cases that this would hit the edge of the screen.
So I'm going 300, 300, 300, 300, 300, and then each time, if it fails, I have this failure callback.
It's just alerting.
Cannot move further, cannot move further, cannot move forever.
Oh my gosh.
Can't talk five times.
I have to rewrite that code.
I don't have an easy way of getting around this.
I have to pass it in that failure callback, even if I'm just doing basically the same thing every single
time.
And then on our last success, instead of continuing to move, I'm just alerting you have a wide screen,
so let's see what happens now.
We move one time, two times, three times four, and then it stops, cannot move further.
And if I close my console, I think we'll be able to make it to the end three, four, five.
And then the callback, which is you have a wide screen.
Oh, okay.
So this has been a ton.
I know this is an incredibly long, dense video.
I wanted to illustrate a situation where callbacks are useful.
We have to use callbacks with what we know so far in order to write a function like move X where we're
waiting for something to finish and then running some code.
We're using set timeout all over the place and our source as you see where you set timeout and in order
to to make our functions work the way we've written them, we have to pass callbacks so we have a on
success and on failure.
Remember, all of this stems from the fact that JavaScript does one thing at a time and the browser
is taking over.
When we call set timeout, the browser is keeping track of time and then it tells JavaScript, okay,
time's up, run this function.
And within this function we have some logic and then we tell JavaScript which one of these to run based
off of some conditional logic.
So this all stems from JavaScript, fundamental nature, the fact that it's single threaded and we have
these browser APIs, the web APIs that JavaScript works with to make a request, to set a timeout,
to set an interval, to add an event listener.
The browser takes care of that and then tells JavaScript, All right, here's a function, here's a
callback.
That's great, but it can get really messy when we start having different outcomes of success in a failure,
which happens a lot when we make requests.
This is a very simple example, but as you'll see shortly, when we make requests, real web HTTP requests,
we follow the same pattern.
We have some code to run when it when the request works, we have other code to run if the request fails.
And so if we structure our code like this on success, on failure, we have two callbacks.
Things get nested, ugly and very difficult to follow quickly.
I mean, look at how separated our code is.
Yes, part of it is the way that my code is formatting things.
But even if we don't have all this indentation, it's still really difficult to know.
If you want to change the failure callback for this first move x, you have to scroll down and just
make sure you're at the right level.
Right?
You have to.
Here's the first one.
Here's the second failure.
Third failure, it becomes hard to to really follow and understand.
So this is where promises come in.
Promises allow us to rewrite a function like this or this function here so that we don't have to do
all this crazy nesting.
It's so much, so much easier to read.
And that's what we're going to see in the next video.
So all of this has been set up for promises, but as long as it's been, this this video I know is probably
the longest video in the course a real slog.
I congratulate you if you made it here, and it will really help you understand why promises are worth
it.
Otherwise, if I just show you promises without showing you the struggle without promises, it doesn't
do promises justice.
So that's coming up next.