All righty.
So in the last video, we saw how using a bunch of callbacks and nesting things can get really out of
hand quickly.
This code is just long and difficult to understand when we're passing in to callbacks to each function
call here and they're all nested.
There's a term for this sort of a playfully loving term in JavaScript called callback hell.
And you can see another example of this here on the left.
Lots of nesting, lots of functions that are nested functions.
They're being passed as callbacks.
This is just not very fun to write, and it's especially annoying when it gets really long and super
far nested and indented, and it's just hard to follow.
So this is where promises come in.
Promises allow us to write asynchronous code that is much easier to read and understand.
It's usually shorter, but even if it's not actually shorter in terms of the number of characters,
it's much flatter.
Often it's not so nested.
So here is where we'll end up this code written or rewritten to use promises.
It looks like this a whole lot flatter, much easier to look at on your eyes, much easier to fix or
debug something if it goes wrong.
We don't have to figure out which callback we need to update.
We don't have to find the corresponding fail callback for this success.
Thankfully, you have this bracket matcher, which helps me, but it's really obnoxious.
So this is where we're going.
It will take a moment though, because we need to talk about the basics of promises.
When we work with promises, there's really two different things you need to understand.
The first is how you create a promise, how you could create a function that returns the promise.
And then the second is how you consume or interact with promises which we do all the time.
Even if we're not writing the promises ourselves, we might be making a request from a library or using
a library like Axios, which is something we'll see in just a bit.
It returns a lot of its functions, return promises.
So we need to understand how we work with those promises.
So we'll tackle both of those.
Creating promises from scratch and then also just working with promises that someone else made.
Okay.
So let's talk about the basics.
A promise is just an object.
It's a JavaScript object which represents the completion or failure of some eventual process, something
that can take time.
Usually it's something that takes time.
Otherwise you probably wouldn't need a promise.
So a promise is a way of promising a value that you may not have at the moment.
Think of a promise in the real world.
When I was a kid, I really wanted a dog.
I asked my dad.
He said, I promise we'll get you a dog if you get good grades.
I got good grades.
And well, he didn't follow through on the promise until he had new kids and then he got them a dog.
But other people's parents would probably follow through on those promises and actually follow through
and give them a dog if the kid's a dog.
So a promise is different than saying here is a dog right now.
It's just a guarantee or a supposed guarantee of an eventual value or a dog or whatever we're talking
about.
So when JavaScript promises are objects that represent an eventual either failure or success of some
task, that takes time.
You make a request.
If we use a library like Axios, which we will shortly, that returns a promise because that value,
if you're making an HTTP request, I can take time and that value may never come back.
It might be a failure or it might be successful and you might get some data back from an API, but it
takes time.
So the object that is returned in the meantime is a promise.
And what we do is we attach callbacks to that object so we don't pass it in to callbacks or a single
callback to a function.
And next, a whole bunch of things promises our objects that we can attach callbacks to instead.
This may not make sense at the moment, but why don't I start by showing you how it works and it should
click after a bit of practice.
So the way we make a new promise in JavaScript is like this new promise with a capital P.
I'll save this to a variable.
Let's go with this idea of my parents promising me a dog contest will get you a dog equals new promise.
And when we create a promise we pass in a function.
And this function has two parameters.
Always these two parameters we usually call resolve and reject.
And these are actually functions.
And at any point inside of this function here, this function that we pass into new promise, if we
call resolve, the promise will be resolved.
If we call reject, which is a function like this, the promise will be rejected.
Now, what does that mean for a promise to be resolved or rejected?
Well, why don't we just start with doing neither?
We just have our promise here.
New promise.
That's it.
And we're not doing anything in it.
Let's see what happens if I take a look at.
We'll get you a dog.
I'll refresh my page.
We'll get you a dog is a promise object and see that it has this one property called promise status.
Which is set to pending.
So the promise is it is a promise, but it has not been resolved or rejected.
It has not been fulfilled or it has not been broken.
If we were talking about this idea in the real world of a promise when someone promises you something,
we would say the status of that promise is pending until either they break the promise or they follow
through on it.
So if we don't reject or resolve a promise, its value or its status will be pending.
So the pending state of a promise is frequently what you will see initially when a promise is first
returned.
If we're making a request and that takes 10 seconds, which would be horrendously slow.
During those 10 seconds, we don't have a response.
We don't know if it's a failure or a success.
If the response went to the right URL, if a server was up, if your internet was working, so it would
be pending.
But if I immediately call reject, which is a function, if I just write reject here, it's not going
to work.
I need to execute this function.
Reject, refresh the page, take a look.
Uncut in promise.
We have an error that we didn't catch and our promise status is rejected.
And if I instead resolve like that refresh take a look at we'll get you a dog promise now has status
of resolved so still not very useful at this point but this is the most fundamental part of creating
a promise we call new promise we pass in a function.
And this function has two parameters resolve and reject.
You can name other things, but this is standard.
And when you call that first function, which should be called resolve, it resolves to promise, it
fulfills it, and the status is set to resolved.
And if we instead reject it, the status of that promise is rejected.
Okay, so now why don't we make something slightly more interesting?
We have.
We'll get you a dog.
Why don't we write a promise that is randomly resolved or rejected?
So that's pretty much the logic.
My dad used to decide if I was actually going to get a dog.
I'm pretty sure he just picked a random number and decided nope, there was no real rationale here,
so why don't we pick a random number?
We'll do rand equals math random.
And then if Rand is less than 0.5, we will let's do resolve, else we will reject.
So now this promise, every time I refresh the page, should be one of these states either immediately
resolved or immediately rejected, depending on that random number.
So this time it was resolved.
I try it again.
Resolved now it was rejected.
So this is the first part.
This is how we create a promise.
The next and also extremely important part is how we actually interact with the promise.
How do I run code if this promise was rejected versus run code if this promise was resolved, this is
where we meet our friend Dot then.
So every promise has a then method so we could call will get you a dog dot then and this dot then method
will run if our promise is resolved.
So I have my dot then and I'll pass in a callback.
This code will run when this promise is resolved and we'll console.log.
Yeah.
We got a dog.
So let's see if it works.
Okay.
So it was rejected.
This code did not run.
Refresh again this time.
If we take a look, it was resolved and our callback instead of Dot then was executed.
Let's try it again.
Rejected.
We don't see this code.
There's no yay!
We got a dog.
So we have another method we can use with every single promise we have then.
And another one called dot catch.
Well it's not called catch, it's called catch.
And we can just chain it on like this.
We could also do will get you a dog dot catch this code will run.
If the promise is rejected, we'll cancel that log.
How about sad face?
No dog.
So if the promise is randomly rejected, this will print out.
If it is randomly resolved, this prints out.
No dog.
It was rejected.
As you can see, status is rejected once again.
Rejected.
There we go.
Resolved.
All right.
So what we've seen so far may not seem that useful or revolutionary, but we've seen the two basic pieces
of working with and creating promises.
To make a promise we call new promise.
Every single time we pass in a function.
And that function has two parameters resolve and reject.
Within this function, we can then call resolve as a function to resolve the promise we call reject
as a function with parentheses to reject the promise.
And if we do neither, the promise will have a status of pending until it's either resolved or rejected.
So that's creating a promise.
Then we saw the dot then or the then method and the catch method.
Whatever we pass into then will automatically run when a given promise is resolved and whatever we pass
into catch the catch method will automatically run whenever a promise is rejected.
So these are two methods on a promise.
A promise is an object.
So this creates a new promise for us.
And then here we're using two existing methods on those promises or on this specific promise.
We'll get you a dog.
These are the basic building blocks of promises, and we're going to continue to build on these.
Remember, we will be refactoring some code.
That nasty callback hell we saw was that the last video?
Plus, we'll see how to make requests.
This will all start to make sense if you're if you're questioning it or if you're lost, it just doesn't
seem that useful.
This is not that great.
I totally recognize that.
But we have to start somewhere.
So next we'll continue on our Promises journey.