All right, so our current promise we'll get you a dog.
Promise is either resolved or rejected immediately.
There's nothing that takes time in this promise.
There's no real reason to use a promise.
We could just write a simple if else, and just generate a random number on its own and print out code
depending on if random is less than five.
Do this thing otherwise console.log.
No dog.
Pretty simple with what we've seen so far.
But now let's introduce some some delay so it takes longer.
What we'll do is just use a set timeout to simulate the number of years it took my dad to finally reject
his promise of getting me a dog.
So I will keep this here.
So we have a record of it, but I'll duplicate it.
And then in here, instead of just immediately resolving or rejecting, let's do a set timeout and our
set timeout will have a function and the delay will be 5 seconds.
And then in that function, the callback, I'll move my logic to pick a random number and then either
resolve or reject.
So now this promise takes 5 seconds before it's resolved or rejected.
Otherwise, those first 5 seconds it's pending, which we saw earlier.
So the then code or the dot catch code, whatever one of these runs, depending on if it was resolved
or rejected, it won't run for 5 seconds.
So let's try it out.
I refresh.
It takes 5 seconds.
Doo doo doo doo doo.
Come on.
There we go.
No dog.
If I refresh and I quickly take a look at we'll get you a dog.
It starts as pending for these 5 seconds.
It's pending now.
It's been rejected.
One more time it starts as pending.
Hopefully, this time it's resolved.
Nope.
Okay, one more time.
Come on.
Come on, resolve it.
Get me a dog.
Seriously.
Three in a row.
How about now?
It's pending.
What the heck?
Just resolve.
Oh, the joy if you.
Oh, my goodness.
How many of these are going to be in a row?
Just resolve.
Please.
Okay.
This is horrendous luck.
Oh, my.
Pending.
Oh.
Finally, I just hit the absolute jackpot of rejected promises.
How many was that?
Like eight?
Nine in a row.
Oh, what are the odds when I'm recording?
But we finally get it.
It starts as pending, and then it's resolved.
All right, so this is our first example of a promise that takes some time.
It takes 5 seconds.
It's kind of simulating, making a request and having to wait for that request to come back.
It's eventually resolved or rejected.
Yes, we're just hard coding a 5/2 delay for no reason.
But imagine that something has to happen over those 5 seconds.
Like we're animating something and we want to wait until the animation finishes, which will return
to.
That was the original impetus for promises.
In this section.
We were doing a whole bunch of nested callbacks and it was hideous when we were moving that button across
the screen.
So another thing that we frequently do is return a promise from a function.
Instead of just making one promise like we have here, we could instead just get rid of my variable.
Define a function we'll call this concept Make dog promise equals some function, and this function
will return a promise, this exact promise we already have, so we just right return.
So now I can call this function instead of we'll get you a dog I can do make dog promise dot then and
I can actually just chain this on like that.
I don't have to.
Well, if I call, make dog promise again.
And did duck catch, that would be two completely separate promises.
And they may not resolve.
They may not both resolve or both reject.
They could have different values.
But if we instead chain it like this, we get around that problem.
And it's also just shorter and cleaner.
You could save the variable or the result to a variable, you know, D equals make dog promise and then
do D then and D catch.
But this is just better.
There we go.
So let's test it out.
We'll wait 5 seconds.
Come on.
And there we go.
It was resolved.
So nothing major that we saw here except for the fact that one we can chain then and catch together
without having to create a variable or without having to reference the promise.
Again, I can just put a dot catch after it then, and only one or the other will run.
In this case, my promise is either resolved or rejected.
If it's resolved, this function runs here.
If it's rejected, this function runs here.
And then the second thing we saw was that we can make a function which returns a promise, which is
an extremely common pattern, rather than creating a promise from scratch and saving it to a variable.
Often we work with functions where we would call.
Once we get to Axios, Axios dot, get some URL, Reddit dot com, that will give us a promise and we
put a dot then in a dot catch after that.
So this function itself is not a promise.
We're executing a function which returns a promise just like we did here.
This returns a new promise.
It's either resolved or rejected eventually, but in the meantime, it's still an object.
It has a status of pending, and when it is either resolved or rejected, one of these will run.
So we have a lot more to cover.
So onwards we go.