The next thing to know about promises is that when you reject or resolve a promise, you can reject
or resolve it with a value and you'll have access to that value in your callback that you pass into
then or catch, which is really, really useful because most of the time we're not just waiting on some
resolve or reject that.
It happens arbitrarily like a random resolve or reject.
We want to know why was something rejected, for example, in the case of a HTTP request, why did this
fail?
And if it didn't fail, if it was resolved, what is the data that we got back?
That's the point of making a request, at least most of the time, is you're trying to get some information.
So we are going to make a fake request function here.
We'll call it const fake request and we'll pass in a URL.
So we'll call this like fake request, Reddit dot com or something.
Or actually let's just do relative URLs.
So slash dogs or slash log in and it's going to take some time.
So we know that it's going to return a promise because it takes some time.
So let's do return new promise.
And then we have our call back in here.
The I think it's called an execute or function executive function on the docks, at least it doesn't
really matter.
But we have our resolve parameter and our reject and then we'll do a set timeout.
And how long should this timeout take?
Let's say it takes 3 seconds to make a request, which is a pretty long time to make a request.
And then our callback that goes here for set timeout.
And what do we want to do in here?
Let's pick a random number and decide randomly if this request worked or not, and we'll resolve it
or reject sort of the same thing we've done before.
Math at random.
We'll save that to a variable cost rand and then we'll check if Rand.
We don't want it to fail half the time.
So let's say if Rand is less than 0.3, we will reject to start just like this.
And then else we will resolve.
So, so far, nothing new.
We've already seen how to do this.
If we call fake request, we don't even need to pass in a URL because we're not using it at the moment.
So fake request dot.
Let's just do a dot then a simple one and a dot catch.
We will console.log request worked and then in our catch we'll do a console.log request failed.
So this is kind of a recap of what we already know.
It's the same idea, a set time out faking something.
In the last video we were doing a dog promise.
But it was the same thing.
Except I think there's a 5050 chance now we have a 3070.
So if we run this, it should take 3 seconds and we'll see either request worked or request failed and
I won't keep going.
Hopefully we get a request.
One more chance to give it one more chance.
Yeah.
All right, well, you'll just have to trust me.
Request will fail at some point.
So this video is about how we can reject and resolve with a value.
We can pass information in to the resolve or reject calls.
So let's start with reject.
If we reject.
Why don't we pass in a status code?
So a typical HTTP response includes a status code.
You've probably seen 204 OC or definitely most likely at least seen 404 not found.
Why don't we just pass that through?
So reject and then let's pass an object in where status is set to 404.
So now instead of our catch, if something is rejected, our callback instead of catch will run.
We can add a parameter in now we could call it data or response and then we can look at resource status,
console.log, reg status.
And if this ever fails, let's do 1/2 just to make it easier.
Come on, it worked.
Okay, there we go.
For a four request failed.
So we have access to this data that we passed through.
Just a single variable or it's not even a variable, a single value.
We could pass more things like reject with this object.
And then I don't know what else would make sense in this context, but we could put whatever we want
in here.
We could also pass in two and then we just have a second parameter.
We could call it numb.
Now, as far as resolving with the value or multiple values, it's the same process.
Why don't we do something a bit more useful?
Like when we call fake request, we'll pass in a URL, how about slash users?
And then we'll use that URL to decide what to respond with.
We're pretending to be an HTTP request where mocking it out, we're adding the delay.
Why don't we start with a variable?
We'll call this.
What should we call this?
Maybe data or pages?
Sure.
It will be an object where we map a URL like slash users to some information.
And how about our users will be an array, an array of objects where we have an ID for each one.
Let's just say ID of one username is Bilbo and we'll just have to users in here to keep it simple id
of five username will be how about Esmeralda.
So whatever URL is passed in, we will use that URL parameter to access information out of pages.
Let's just add a second page in here.
This one will be slash about and it will just be a string of text.
This is the about page.
Okay.
So if you pass in slash users, what we'll do is take that URL and resolve with pages of URL.
Let's just call this data, consent data, and then we'll resolve with an object, maybe so that we
can include a status code of 200, which means okay.
And then we'll also include data and I'll just use a shorthand instead of data.
Call and data, we'll just add data.
So if we check it out, we pass in slash users.
Let's start with something easier.
How about slash about.
Then we'll go with response.
Maybe Rez again and we'll console.log.
Let's go with status code rez status and then duplicate that and do rez dot data.
Which is the second thing.
Right.
We have status and data that we resolve with and we'll go with data here.
Let's see what we get if it does resolve and it did.
Status Code 200 data.
This is the about page.
Now, instead of randomly resolving or rejecting, let's get rid of the random number and instead we'll
reject if the URL is invalid, if it's not contained within pages.
So we'll get rid of all this or almost all.
We'll just get rid of all of it.
And what we'll do here is check within the set timeout.
So we're still going to wait a full second or 3 seconds or whatever.
We'll check if the URL was in pages.
So if data, right.
We're just plugging this URL in.
If data we will resolve with this that we already have.
Else will reject.
With the object that has status set to 404, which means not found, which makes sense.
The URL you passed in was not found in our fake or fake application.
It has two end points right now.
Why don't we test this out now?
So if I do about we'll see if that one works.
It should still work.
I'll change it to users actually.
And then if we try another one this time fake request, it will do slash dogs, which does not exist
in our pages.
So if you are like dogs, this line should be undefined.
So this won't run and instead we'll reject.
Let's double check.
Cool.
So our first one worked, we got status code 200 from the then callback right here.
Red data were these two users and then the second request did not work.
We got 404 requests failed.
All righty.
So in this video, we saw that we can resolve and reject with data.
We can pass through some argument there.
In this case, it was an object in both resolving and rejecting scenarios.
And then instead of our then callback, we can add a parameter, give it whatever name we want, and
it will have that data.
It will be passed whatever the promise was resolved with.
And then same thing for Ketch, except when the promise is rejected, this function will run and this
parameter will have whatever value we passed.
All right, so we're almost done with the basics of promises.
We have one other really important topic to cover, which is chaining multiple promises.
What if we wanted to make another request after the first one?
We have a really nice way of doing it.
So that's coming up next.