All right.
So the last really critical part of promises is understanding, promise, chaining.
So I've updated the fake request function to now have a much more robust set of pages.
It's still pretty minimal, but we have a couple of different endpoints.
We can make a fake request to slash users, which would give us something like this where we have an
ID for each user and I could use that ID to make a second request to get more information about a user.
And this is actually a really common pattern where a website or some API is set up with some endpoint
that gives you a little bit of information about every user or every, I don't know, dog in the the
dog shelter or every post on a on the Reddit home page.
Then it gives you an idea that you can use to make a second follow up request using information from
the first so that you can get more detailed information like I have here.
So if we wanted to mock that, we would make a request to slash users, a fake request and get this
information back.
Then we could take this ID ID of one and make a request to slash users slash one.
But we want to do that after this one finishes, after we know for sure what that ID is, just like
we would in the real world.
So if you pretend for a moment that this is real, it's not just a fake object of pages where we're
just hard coding.
The data in those IDs could change.
There could be users that are deleted, so we would ask for all users and then make a request to user
slash one with what we know right now.
Here's how we would do it.
Fake request and then the URL.
Let's start with slash users.
Dot.
Then we have our callback, which gives us a response.
And then what we would do is take a look at response data.
That is the name that we use, right?
If we come down here, data and we want the ID right here, this ID of the first user.
So the array is what we get back that contains two items if we just console.log resource data.
Let's just pretend that we are on a journey with a real API.
Here's what we get back in array.
So if we want to take the first user, that would be console.log.
Data zero.
If we want that ID, we could save that to a variable.
Let's just make sure we're printing it out correctly after 1/2.
So let's save this to a variable.
We'll call it const ID.
So we have the piece of information we need to make our second request.
With what we've seen so far is it's going to Oh, I'm not printing anything.
Well, I'm an idiot.
Nothing will show up.
But with what we've seen so far, we would have to just make another call to fake request.
We have to do that.
Either way, we can't get around that.
But we would nest it in here because we need this to happen after this one finishes.
So logically it would go in the then if we put it down here, it's not going to happen afterwards.
We depend on this ID which we only have access to in this callback, the then callback, where the response
is passed through.
So I have to do it in here with what we've seen, I would call fake request again and we'll use a template
literal to do slash users slash and then dollar sign curly braces.
My ID I got from the previous request and I could do a second dot then same exact thing rez and then
we can console.log the response.
Let's see what we get.
So we should get a first.
Oh, actually we're not printing the very first time so we only see the second response that we get
back.
And it has more information about the user with ID of one and status of 200.
This all looks good if I wanted to make another request with that, if we look at the data we got back,
we have this top post ID so I now can send a request to another URL I've set up in my pages.
Object called slash, posts slash and then this id so I could then make another request, fake request
and it's dot data.
Dot.
What was it, top post ID Yes.
So this is a third request that is dependent upon the second request, which itself is dependent upon
the data.
We got back from the very first request, we got all users that gave us an ID we could use.
We use that to make a request using that ID.
Now we get this top post ID which we can use to make another request to post some ID.
So we'll do slash post.
Slash and we'll save this to a variable cost ID again.
Or how about post ID and then interpolate that with dollar sign curly braces post id one more dot,
then we'll get our response hopefully.
And then we'll do our console.log response.
Okay.
We'll try it.
Come on.
All right.
What do we get back?
Yes, we're getting our post information.
Ladies and gentlemen, may I introduce you to my pet pig Hamlet?
So this was some hypothetical post on our website by this user.
So what we have here doesn't.
Honestly, it doesn't look much better than what we saw in the whole callback hell section of this section
where we talked about nesting a whole bunch of things.
Also, we don't have catches right now.
So if I want to do that, it gets even messier.
If I want to catch, I would do catch pass in my callback and we'll just call this error and then console.log.
Oh, no.
And then we'll also just print the error.
So right now, we don't have a way of causing an error.
But if I mess up this request and I use a wrong or an invalid URL like that, it should catch it.
And it does we get Oh, no, here's our error.
It's a status code 400 or 404 in an object.
But if this one is valid and I instead mess this request up, this is a URL that doesn't exist in our
pages.
Let's see what happens.
It didn't work.
I mean, the promise was rejected, but we didn't catch it like we have here.
So this catch is only working for this fake request.
So I would need another catch for this then.
So we have a much, much nicer way of rewriting all of this.
What we're doing here is essentially the same thing we saw with callbacks where we just nest them and
nest them and nest them.
This fake request is dependent on the data from this one.
This third one is dependent on the second one, so it makes sense to nest them.
But we have a whole different way of structuring them.
What we can do instead, I'll just type this sort of in a shorthand up here.
If we do a dot then and in the callback, if the dot, then we return a promise we can call dot.
Then immediately after on the same level, I don't have to nest.
I can chain it and I can continue to chain as long as each callback for then returns a promise.
I won't nest my dot then so I won't have to do any nesting.
Instead I return a promise.
This dot then runs.
First it returns a promise.
This then will run if the second promise, the returned promise was resolved and so on.
So let me show you what that would look like.
We have our fake request then, and then we have this whole callback here.
We get the ID, then we have our second fake request here.
What I'm going to do is remove all of this right here.
And return this function call this returns a promise just like this did our function.
The first line says return new promise.
So this returns a promise.
We're putting the then on that promise, then inside this dot, then we return another promise.
And what I can do is put my next, then on the same level.
So here I am doing another dot, then getting the post ID from the response I can return this fake request
which returns a promise.
And I can move my.
Then outside.
So if you look at my code now, I should have saved the original where we were nesting things.
It was then and then inside that.
Then we essentially had another dot then and then another dot then and we didn't even bother with catches.
That was still a lot of nesting.
Now what we're seeing, if you take my word that this does work, is that we can write things in a much
more linear way.
So do this, then do this, then do this.
So this will only run if the first promise was resolved, meaning this ran, then that promise that
was returned.
The second promise was resolved meaning that this code runs in the dot, then callback, and this promise
is resolved which would trigger this callback.
So if any of those screw up at any point and this is a real magical part, we only need one catch.
So this sketch will run if any of these promises are rejected.
We have this promise.
We only need one catch.
It's like a catch all.
It's really, really nice.
So right now we do have an error here.
It won't work.
So let's just start with it actually working so users then users slash the ID, then post slash the
post ID.
Let's see what happens.
I'm going to console.log the data we get back each time.
So console.log says I'll do that here and you'll see them happening one after another, even though
they're not nested.
I'm doing it twice here.
Okay.
Moment of truth.
We get our first one, second, one, third one.
It's pretty cool, right?
We don't have to nest.
These take time, but we don't have to use a bunch of callbacks and continue to nest and get crazy with
that multi-level craziness.
Multi level craziness.
Yeah.
All we have to do is make sure we return a promise inside of this callback and then we can just add
another dot.
Then we could have as many levels as we want.
Remember, like I already said, this is only going to run this.
Then if this promise was resolved and this one is dependent on this promise being resolved, this one
is dependent on this one.
So it doesn't look like we have this crazy multi level dependency thing going on.
But that's the magic of promises.
We can rewrite our code in a much easier to read manner.
Right?
Do this, then do this, then do this, then do this.
If at any point something went wrong, do this.
So why don't we have something go wrong?
At the beginning, we'll use a URL that doesn't exist.
Oh, no.
So the catch ran that callback.
Now, let's have something go wrong here.
So we have our first promise that should be resolved.
There we go.
Then we get.
Oh, no.
And this code never ran right?
When we had an error with the very first one.
None of the other then ran.
It went straight to catch and it was done.
But now, if I have an error in this third request, we get the first two resolved.
Resolved, rejected.
Catch runs.
So hopefully you can see already, even though we're doing very fake stuff, it's a mocked request,
it's hardcoded, it's stupid.
I won't say stupid, it's useless in the real world.
It's useful in an educational context.
Even though all of that is true, it's still a good illustration of the benefits of using promises.
We can have multiple asynchronous actions that we want to happen one after another.
So not simultaneously, but one after another.
We change then as long as we return a promise.
Each time everything works and we only need one catch.
So what we're going to do next is revisit the early example that I use to illustrate callback hell,
where we were moving a button across the screen.
We'll rewrite it with promises, something slightly more useful instead of just an arbitrary fake request.
You'll see how much time.
Well, you'll see how much code it saves us and how many headaches it prevents.
It's so much easier to read.
So that's next.