Now that we're relatively comfortable with promises, let's try and refactor this little demo from earlier
where we had a button that was moving and eventually running out of room potentially and stopping.
So if we can't go further, if we can't go whatever, 200, 300 pixels, whatever the jump was, let's
see.
I think it was 300 pixels.
Yeah.
So if we can't go another 300 pixels, it stops and we achieve this by using a bunch of set timeouts
and then changing the transform property of the button.
But every time in that set timeout we would check, do we have room to move?
If we don't have room to move, we would call one callback that was passed in the on failure callback.
If we did have room to move, we called the on success callback, so we ended up passing two callbacks
in every time we call Move X and if we wanted the first one to complete the first move of 300 pixels
before the second one started, we have to use these callbacks with the way that we've set it up without
promises.
It's a bunch of nesting.
A bunch I mean, a whole bunch, as we saw.
Very, very painful.
So let's rewrite this using promises.
I'll comment this out so we don't get the original movement going on.
And I'll also duplicate this and comment it out, and then I guess I'll do it at the top here.
We're going to refactor, move x.
It's going to no longer accept an on success and success and on failure.
It's going to instead return a new promise.
Remember, this promise takes a function as its argument, resolve and reject, which are also two functions.
And then we can move this logic from before into our promise.
What is it called?
Execute or function?
Maybe I'm making that up.
I'm pretty sure that's what it's called.
But inside of this new promise function.
So instead of calling on failure, we would reject the promise.
If we can't move, we're calculating the end of the body.
How much?
How many pixels we have, let's say 900 pixels or something.
Or actually we can see it's telling me I'm at, what, 1225 pixels, then we're calculating the right
of the button and then the current left of the button, which we use if we are going to move and we
want to check if the right whatever, let's say 800 pixels plus the amount we're trying to move, 300
pixels, if that is greater than the boundary will reject meaning stop.
We're not going to continue otherwise.
Instead of on success, we'll call resolve.
So very similar code except we've wrapped it in a promise that we're returning and we're not using.
We're not passing in to callbacks every single time.
So now how would we use this?
It would look like this.
Move X of button, let's do 300 pixels and the delay of 1/2 dot then and we're not passing any value
in when we are rejecting or resolving.
We could possibly maybe when we reject we could include a reason.
We could include the maybe the current position of the element.
We could do something with it.
And then we've got our dot, then why don't we just cancel that log done moving and start there.
So I'm going to refresh the page.
It moves and we get done moving.
Okay, so if we wanted another move X after that first one like we had before we moved 300 pixels,
we move 300 pixels again 1/2 later, we don't have to nest it.
All we need to do is call move x again.
Move x button 300 pixels over 1/2, not 2 seconds.
And if I wanted another dot, then yes, you could do this, put it inside the existing dot, then callback,
or we just return this promise.
This gives us a promise now, which is what we saw in the last video.
We can change promises and I can put another then here and now I can console.log.
Done.
Done with both.
Okay.
So we do the first thing that takes some time when it finishes, when that 1/2 is over, the button
has moved, assuming it has room, which it showed we're only going 300 pixels, then we're going to
move x again, which will return a promise.
It may or may not be completed or resolved depending on if we have the correct number of pixels, the
correct space to keep moving.
And if we do this, then we'll run.
We don't have a catch yet, but this should be good because we're only moving 600 total and then we
get done with both.
So that only prints out after two move x functions are done.
Both promises have been resolved.
So now if we wanted to do like five of them, all we need to do is duplicate this a couple of times.
So now we're moving four times first 300 pixels.
It takes a second as soon as it's done, but not sooner as soon as it's done.
Then this runs and then as soon as that finishes and hopefully is resolved, this runs, then this runs.
We don't have a catch yet, so we may run out of space.
300.
Are we out of space now?
Yes, uncut.
So we had a rejected promise, but we didn't catch it.
And as we saw, all we need is one catch and we'll console.log.
Now let's do console.log.
Out of space cannot move.
And we should see one more time.
Here we go.
Outer space cannot move.
And if I instead changed it.
So we're trying to move.
Like, I don't know, 3000 pixels on the third move x.
We'll still have the same catch work.
It will catch that promise which is rejected.
We'll catch the error.
So let's try that.
First jump, second jump, third jump can't happen.
Outer space cannot move.
Now it's really cool is in situations like this where all we're doing in the end callback is returning
another promise.
We can shorten it up as we've seen with arrow functions.
If you do choose to use arrow functions, if you are returning something and it's the only expression,
the only line, you can use an implicit return.
So you could use parentheses.
We don't have to write the return keyword.
I can just do this right here, just like that, and we can chain them together.
So I'm just going to replace what I have with a couple of these.
Let's do five of them and keep our one catch.
So this only works to make it super concise and just nice and not a bunch of curly braces that only
works if there's only one expression and it should be returned implicitly.
So we don't right return, but it's being returned.
If you need some review on that, check out the arrow function section.
So let's check it out.
First move, second move, third, fourth.
And then we run out of space.
Awesome.
So I could change this to be at 100 pixels and do this a whole bunch.
Let's see when we run out of space.
One more time.
That's still I guess we're moving 300.
The very first time.
I didn't change that one.
And now we're out of space.
Pretty cool stuff, I think.
It's a really nice, nice way of shortening your code up and making it.
It's not even about shortening it.
It's making it just easier to follow if we compare.
This is a huge mess.
Not only is it nested, but we had to pass in two callbacks.
So we get this ugly like I don't know what to call this.
Like a triangle, a pyramid, mirror, image, the reflection.
There we go of all of these callbacks, even if they're doing the same thing, the failure callback
here, we just need a single catch and it does a trick.
So the last thing we could do is refactor this a bit so our sketch could actually know.
This callback could know where it was stopped, why we didn't keep moving to the right.
Basically, we know we're out of room, but we could print out you.
The button is currently at 500 pixels and you tried to move 300, but the body is X or who knows?
We could just make a little object when we reject that included, let's say, the body boundary and
I'll just use the shorthand here.
So body boundary will be the key and whatever it holds will be the value.
Let's also add in the element, right, and the amount.
So we'll have three different properties that we are passing through when we reject.
Then down here when we catch, we can just add in our object, we'll just call this, you can call it
error, but it's not really an error.
We'll call it data as a parameter and let's grab.
We could just structure actually if we want body boundary, we want a mount.
And what else was there?
LL Right, so we can console.log.
Something like body is let's do a template, literal string template literal body is body boundary.
P wide and then below that console.log, let's say element is at L right p x.
Comma and then we'll display the amount x is too large, so we reject with that information rather than
just blindly or always printing out outer space cannot move.
Let's see what happens when we finally hit that catch.
Oh, I forgot.
I did all these 100 pixel little tiny jumps.
Okay, here we go.
Body is 1354 pixels.
Element is at 1297.
100 pixels is too large because that would take us to 1397 and that's pretty much it.
So still a very simple example.
Not the most useful thing to do ever, but you can see what a massive difference is made.
I mean, we're doing, what, ten, 15 different calls to move X and they're happening one after another
and all of them are handled if something goes wrong, if they fail, we don't have room.
This catches all of them.
Compare that to this.
This is only five or so different move x calls if we wanted to replicate this.
I mean, I would I would be here forever.
We would have at least twice as much code as we have right now.
And it would be incredibly nested and hard to keep track of.
So that is a real value of promises.
It's not just about doing asynchronous things and being able to run some code afterwards.
It's also about being able to catch any time a promise is rejected, having a single catch, it makes
a huge difference.
We don't have to have ten or 20 different catches, one per each, then for each promise.
As long as we return a promise in the dot, then, which is what we're doing thanks to an implicit arrow
function return.
All right, so we're now moving on from our sort of playland promises where we're doing very, very
trivial, simple things.
And next, we'll move on to making real HTTP requests and use promises.
Those functions, those methods return promises.
So we'll get practice with all this fun stuff that we've seen so far.